<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
	"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:lang="en">
  <info>
    <title>Mirroring FreeBSD</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Jun</firstname>
	  <surname>Kuriyama</surname>
	</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>kuriyama@FreeBSD.org</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Valentino</firstname>
	  <surname>Vaschetto</surname>
	</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>logo@FreeBSD.org</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
	  <surname>Lang</surname>
	</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>dl@leo.org</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Ken</firstname>
	  <surname>Smith</surname>
	</personname>
	<affiliation>
	  <address>
	    <email>kensmith@FreeBSD.org</email>
	  </address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice xml:id="trademarks" role="trademarks">
      &tm-attrib.freebsd;
      &tm-attrib.general;
    </legalnotice>

    <pubdate>$FreeBSD$</pubdate>

    <releaseinfo>$FreeBSD$</releaseinfo>

    <abstract>
      <para>An in-progress article on how to mirror FreeBSD, aimed at
	hub administrators.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <note>
    <para>We are not accepting new mirrors at this time.</para>
  </note>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-contact">
    <title>Contact Information</title>

    <para>The Mirror System Coordinators can be reached through email
      at <email>mirror-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>.  There is also
      a &a.hubs;.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-requirements">
    <title>Requirements for FreeBSD Mirrors</title>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-diskspace">
      <title>Disk Space</title>

      <para>Disk space is one of the most important requirements.
	Depending on the set of releases, architectures, and degree of
	completeness you want to mirror, a huge amount of disk space
	may be consumed.  Also keep in mind that
	<emphasis>official</emphasis> mirrors are probably required to
	be complete.  The web pages should always be mirrored
	completely.  Also note that the numbers stated here are
	reflecting the current state (at
	&rel.current;-RELEASE/&rel1.current;-RELEASE).  Further
	development and releases will only increase the required
	amount.  Also make sure to keep some (ca. 10-20%) extra space
	around just to be sure.  Here are some approximate
	figures:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Full FTP Distribution: 1.4 TB</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>CTM deltas: 10 GB</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Web pages: 1GB</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The current disk usage of FTP Distribution can be found at
	<link
	  xlink:href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/dir.sizes">ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/dir.sizes</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-bandwidth">
      <title>Network Connection/Bandwidth</title>

      <para>Of course, you need to be connected to the Internet.  The
	required bandwidth depends on your intended use of the mirror.
	If you just want to mirror some parts of FreeBSD for local use
	at your site/intranet, the demand may be much smaller than if
	you want to make the files publicly available.  If you intend
	to become an official mirror, the bandwidth required will be
	even higher.  We can only give rough estimates here:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Local site, no public access: basically no minimum,
	    but &lt; 2 Mbps could make syncing too
	    slow.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Unofficial public site: 34 Mbps is probably a good
	    start.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Official site: &gt; 100 Mbps is recommended, and your
	    host should be connected as close as possible to your
	    border router.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-system">
      <title>System Requirements, CPU, RAM</title>

      <para>One thing this depends on the expected number of clients,
	which is determined by the server's policy.  It is also
	affected by the types of services you want to offer.  Plain
	FTP or HTTP services may not require a huge amount of
	resources.  Watch out if you provide rsync.  This can have a
	huge impact on CPU and memory requirements as it is considered
	a memory hog.  The following are just examples to give you a
	very rough hint.</para>

      <para>For a moderately visited site that offers
	<application>rsync</application>, you might consider a current
	CPU with around 800MHz - 1 GHz, and at least 512MB RAM. This
	is probably the minimum you want for an
	<emphasis>official</emphasis> site.</para>

      <para>For a frequently used site you definitely need more RAM
	(consider 2GB as a good start) and possibly more CPU, which
	could also mean that you need to go for a SMP system.</para>

      <para>You also want to consider a fast disk subsystem.
	Operations on the SVN repository require a fast disk subsystem
	(RAID is highly advised).  A SCSI controller that has a cache
	of its own can also speed up things since most of these
	services incur a large number of small modifications to the
	disk.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-services">
      <title>Services to Offer</title>

      <para>Every mirror site is required to have a set of core
	services available.  In addition to these required services,
	there are a number of optional services that server
	administrators may choose to offer.  This section explains
	which services you can provide and how to go about
	implementing them.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-serv-ftp">
	<title>FTP (required for FTP Fileset)</title>

	<para>This is one of the most basic services, and it is
	  required for each mirror offering public FTP distributions.
	  FTP access must be anonymous, and no upload/download ratios
	  are allowed (a ridiculous thing anyway).  Upload capability
	  is not required (and <emphasis>must</emphasis> never be
	  allowed for the FreeBSD file space).  Also the FreeBSD
	  archive should be available under the path
	  <filename>/pub/FreeBSD</filename>.</para>

	<para>There is a lot of software available which can be set up
	  to allow anonymous FTP (in alphabetical order).</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>/usr/libexec/ftpd</command>: FreeBSD's own
	      ftpd can be used.  Be sure to read &man.ftpd.8;.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/ncftpd</package>: A commercial package,
	      free for educational use.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/oftpd</package>: An ftpd designed with
	      security as a main focus.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/proftpd</package>: A modular and very
	      flexible ftpd.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/pure-ftpd</package>: Another ftpd
	      developed with security in mind.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/twoftpd</package>: As
	      above.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>ftp/vsftpd</package>: The <quote>very
		secure</quote> ftpd.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>FreeBSD's <application>ftpd</application>,
	  <application>proftpd</application> and maybe
	  <application>ncftpd</application> are among the most
	  commonly used FTPds.  The others do not have a large
	  userbase among mirror sites.  One thing to consider is that
	  you may need flexibility in limiting how many simultaneous
	  connections are allowed, thus limiting how much network
	  bandwidth and system resources are consumed.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-serv-rsync">
	<title>Rsync (optional for FTP Fileset)</title>

	<para><application>Rsync</application> is often offered for
	  access to the contents of the FTP area of FreeBSD, so other
	  mirror sites can use your system as their source.  The
	  protocol is different from FTP in many ways.  It is much
	  more bandwidth friendly, as only differences between files
	  are transferred instead of whole files when they change.
	  <application>Rsync</application> does require a significant
	  amount of memory for each instance.  The size depends on the
	  size of the synced module in terms of the number of
	  directories and files.  <application>Rsync</application> can
	  use <command>rsh</command> and <command>ssh</command> (now
	  default) as a transport, or use its own protocol for
	  stand-alone access (this is the preferred method for public
	  rsync servers).  Authentication, connection limits, and
	  other restrictions may be applied.  There is just one
	  software package available:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>net/rsync</package></para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-serv-http">
	<title>HTTP (required for Web Pages, Optional for FTP
	  Fileset)</title>

	<para>If you want to offer the FreeBSD web pages, you will
	  need to install a web server.  You may optionally offer the
	  FTP fileset via HTTP.  The choice of web server software is
	  left up to the mirror administrator.  Some of the most
	  popular choices are:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/apache24</package>:
	      <application>Apache</application> is still one of the
	      most widely deployed web servers on the Internet.  It is
	      used extensively by the FreeBSD Project.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/boa</package>:
	      <application>Boa</application> is a single-tasking HTTP
	      server.  Unlike traditional web servers, it does not
	      fork for each incoming connection, nor does it fork many
	      copies of itself to handle multiple connections.
	      Although, it should provide considerably great
	      performance for purely static content.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/cherokee</package>:
	      <application>>Cherokee</application> is a very fast,
	      flexible and easy to configure web server.  It supports
	      the widespread technologies nowadays: FastCGI, SCGI,
	      PHP, CGI, SSL/TLS encrypted connections, vhosts, users
	      authentication, on the fly encoding and load balancing.
	      It also generates <application>Apache</application>
	      compatible log files.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/lighttpd</package>:
	      <application>lighttpd</application> is a secure, fast,
	      compliant and very flexible web server which has been
	      optimized for high-performance environments.  It has a
	      very low memory footprint compared to other web servers
	      and takes care of cpu-load.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/nginx</package>:
	      <application>nginx</application> is a high performance
	      edge web server with a low memory footprint and key
	      features to build a modern and efficient web
	      infrastructure.  Features include a HTTP server, HTTP
	      and mail reverse proxy, caching, load balancing,
	      compression, request throttling, connection multiplexing
	      and reuse, SSL offload and HTTP media streaming.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><package>www/thttpd</package>: If you are going to
	      be serving a large amount of static content you may find
	      that using an application such as
	      <application>thttpd</application> is more efficient than
	      others.  It is also optimized for excellent performance
	      on FreeBSD.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-howto">
    <title>How to Mirror FreeBSD</title>

    <para>Ok, now you know the requirements and how to offer the
      services, but not how to get it.  :-) This section explains how
      to actually mirror the various parts of FreeBSD, what tools to
      use, and where to mirror from.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-ftp-rsync">
      <title>Mirroring the FTP Site</title>

      <para>The FTP area is the largest amount of data that needs to
	be mirrored.  It includes the <emphasis>distribution
	  sets</emphasis> required for network installation, the
	<emphasis>branches</emphasis> which are actually snapshots of
	checked-out source trees, the <emphasis>ISO Images</emphasis>
	to write CD-ROMs with the installation distribution, a live
	file system, and a snapshot of the ports tree.  All of course
	for various FreeBSD versions, and various
	architectures.</para>

      <para>The best way to mirror the FTP area is
	<application>rsync</application>.  You can install the port
	<package>net/rsync</package> and then use rsync to sync with
	your upstream host.  <application>rsync</application> is
	already mentioned in <xref linkend="mirror-serv-rsync"/>.
	Since <application>rsync</application> access is not required,
	your preferred upstream site may not allow it.  You may need
	to hunt around a little bit to find a site that allows
	<application>rsync</application> access.</para>

      <note>
	<para>Since the number of <application>rsync</application>
	  clients will have a significant impact on the server
	  machine, most admins impose limitations on their server.
	  For a mirror, you should ask the site maintainer you are
	  syncing from about their policy, and maybe an exception for
	  your host (since you are a mirror).</para>
      </note>

      <para>A command line to mirror FreeBSD might look like:</para>

      <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>rsync -vaHz --delete rsync://ftp4.de.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/ /pub/FreeBSD/</userinput></screen>

      <para>Consult the documentation for
	<application>rsync</application>, which is also available at
	<link
	  xlink:href="http://rsync.samba.org/">http://rsync.samba.org/</link>,
	about the various options to be used with rsync.  If you sync
	the whole module (unlike subdirectories), be aware that the
	module-directory (here "FreeBSD") will not be created, so you
	cannot omit the target directory.  Also you might want to set
	up a script framework that calls such a command via
	&man.cron.8;.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-www">
      <title>Mirroring the WWW Pages</title>

      <para>The FreeBSD website should only be mirrored via
	<application>rsync</application>.</para>

      <para>A command line to mirror the FreeBSD web site might look
	like:</para>

      <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>rsync -vaHz --delete rsync://bit0.us-west.freebsd.org/FreeBSD-www-data/ /usr/local/www/</userinput></screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-pkgs">
      <title>Mirroring Packages</title>

      <para>Due to very high requirements of bandwidth, storage and
	adminstration the &os; Project has decided not to allow public
	mirrors of packages.  For sites with lots of machines, it
	might be advantagous to run a caching HTTP proxy for the
	&man.pkg.8; process.  Alternatively specific packages and
	their dependencies can be fetched by running something like
	the following:</para>

      <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>pkg fetch -d -o <replaceable>/usr/local/mirror</replaceable> <replaceable>vim</replaceable></userinput></screen>

      <para>Once those packages have been fetched, the repository
	metadata must be generated by running:</para>

      <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>pkg repo <replaceable>/usr/local/mirror</replaceable></userinput></screen>

      <para>Once the packages have been fetched and the metadata for
	the repository has been generated, serve the packages up to
	the client machines via HTTP.  For additional information see
	the man pages for &man.pkg.8;, specifically the
	&man.pkg-repo.8; page.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-how-often">
      <title>How Often Should I Mirror?</title>

      <para>Every mirror should be updated at a minimum of once per
	day.  Certainly a script with locking to prevent multiple runs
	happening at the same time will be needed to run from
	&man.cron.8;.  Since nearly every admin does this in their own
	way, specific instructions cannot be provided.  It could work
	something like this:</para>

      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <para>Put the command to run your mirroring application in a
	    script.  Use of a plain <command>/bin/sh</command> script
	    is recommended.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Add some output redirections so diagnostic messages
	    are logged to a file.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Test if your script works.  Check the logs.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Use &man.crontab.1; to add the script to the
	    appropriate user's &man.crontab.5;.  This should be a
	    different user than what your FTP daemon runs as so that
	    if file permissions inside your FTP area are not
	    world-readable those files cannot be accessed by anonymous
	    FTP.  This is used to <quote>stage</quote> releases
	    &mdash; making sure all of the official mirror sites have
	    all of the necessary release files on release day.</para>
	</step>
      </procedure>

      <para>Here are some recommended schedules:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>FTP fileset: daily</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>WWW pages: daily</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-where">
    <title>Where to Mirror From</title>

    <para>This is an important issue.  So this section will spend some
      effort to explain the backgrounds.  We will say this several
      times: under no circumstances should you mirror from <systemitem
	class="fqdomainname">ftp.FreeBSD.org</systemitem>.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-where-organization">
      <title>A few Words About the Organization</title>

      <para>Mirrors are organized by country.  All official mirrors
	have a DNS entry of the form <systemitem
	  class="fqdomainname">ftpN.CC.FreeBSD.org</systemitem>.
	<emphasis>CC</emphasis> (i.e., country code) is the
	<emphasis>top level domain</emphasis> (TLD) of the country
	where this mirror is located.  <emphasis>N</emphasis> is a
	number, telling that the host would be the
	<emphasis>Nth</emphasis> mirror in that country.  (Same
	applies to <systemitem>wwwN.CC.FreeBSD.org</systemitem>, etc.)
	There are mirrors with no <emphasis>CC</emphasis> part.  These
	are the mirror sites that are very well connected and allow a
	large number of concurrent users.  <systemitem
	  class="fqdomainname">ftp.FreeBSD.org</systemitem> is
	actually two machines, one currently located in Denmark and
	the other in the United States.  It is
	<emphasis>NOT</emphasis> a master site and should never be
	used to mirror from.  Lots of online documentation leads
	<quote>interactive</quote>users to <systemitem
	  class="fqdomainname">ftp.FreeBSD.org</systemitem> so
	automated mirroring systems should find a different machine to
	mirror from.</para>

      <para>Additionally there exists a hierarchy of mirrors, which is
	described in terms of <emphasis>tiers</emphasis>.  The master
	sites are not referred to but can be described as
	<emphasis>Tier-0</emphasis>.  Mirrors that mirror from these
	sites can be considered <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis>, mirrors
	of <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis>-mirrors, are
	<emphasis>Tier-2</emphasis>, etc.  Official sites are
	encouraged to be of a low <emphasis>tier</emphasis>, but the
	lower the tier the higher the requirements in terms as
	described in <xref linkend="mirror-requirements"/>.  Also
	access to low-tier-mirrors may be restricted, and access to
	master sites is definitely restricted.  The
	<emphasis>tier</emphasis>-hierarchy is not reflected by DNS
	and generally not documented anywhere except for the master
	sites.  However, official mirrors with low numbers like 1-4,
	are usually <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis> (this is just a rough
	hint, and there is no rule).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-where-where">
      <title>Ok, but Where Should I get the Stuff Now?</title>

      <para>Under no circumstances should you mirror from <systemitem
	  class="fqdomainname">ftp.FreeBSD.org</systemitem>.  The
	short answer is: from the site that is closest to you in
	Internet terms, or gives you the fastest access.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-where-simple">
	<title>I Just Want to Mirror from Somewhere!</title>

	<para>If you have no special intentions or requirements, the
	  statement in <xref linkend="mirror-where-where"/> applies.
	  This means:</para>

	<procedure>
	  <step>
	    <para>Check for those which provide fastest access (number
	      of hops, round-trip-times) and offer the services you
	      intend to use (like
	      <application>rsync</application>).</para>
	  </step>

	  <step>
	    <para>Contact the administrators of your chosen site
	      stating your request, and asking about their terms and
	      policies.</para>
	  </step>

	  <step>
	    <para>Set up your mirror as described above.</para>
	  </step>
	</procedure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-where-official">
	<title>I am an Official Mirror, What is the Right Rite for
	  Me?</title>

	<para>In general the description in <xref
	    linkend="mirror-where-simple"/> still applies.  Of course
	  you may want to put some weight on the fact that your
	  upstream should be of a low tier.  There are some other
	  considerations about <emphasis>official</emphasis> mirrors
	  that are described in <xref
	    linkend="mirror-official"/>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="mirror-where-master">
	<title>I Want to Access the Master Sites!</title>

	<para>If you have good reasons and good prerequisites, you may
	  want and get access to one of the master sites.  Access to
	  these sites is generally restricted, and there are special
	  policies for access.  If you are already an
	  <emphasis>official</emphasis> mirror, this certainly helps
	  you getting access.  In any other case make sure your
	  country really needs another mirror.  If it already has
	  three or more, ask the <quote>zone administrator</quote>
	  (<email>hostmaster@CC.FreeBSD.org</email>) or &a.hubs;
	  first.</para>

	<para>Whoever helped you become, an
	  <emphasis>official</emphasis> should have helped you gain
	  access to an appropriate upstream host, either one of the
	  master sites or a suitable Tier-1 site.  If not, you can
	  send email to <email>mirror-admin@FreeBSD.org</email> to
	  request help with that.</para>

	<para>There is one master site for the FTP fileset.</para>

	<sect4 xml:id="mirror-where-master-ftp">
	  <title>ftp-master.FreeBSD.org</title>

	  <para>This is the master site for the FTP fileset.</para>

	  <para><systemitem>ftp-master.FreeBSD.org</systemitem>
	    provides <application>rsync</application> access, in
	    addition to FTP.  Refer to <xref
	      linkend="mirror-ftp-rsync"/>.</para>

	  <para>Mirrors are also encouraged to allow
	    <application>rsync</application> access for the FTP
	    contents, since they are
	    <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis>-mirrors.</para>
	</sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-official">
    <title>Official Mirrors</title>

    <para>Official mirrors are mirrors that</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>a) have a <systemitem>FreeBSD.org</systemitem> DNS entry
	  (usually a CNAME).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>b) are listed as an official mirror in the FreeBSD
	  documentation (like handbook).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>So far to distinguish official mirrors.  Official mirrors
      are not necessarily <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis>-mirrors.
      However you probably will not find a
      <emphasis>Tier-1</emphasis>-mirror, that is not also
      official.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-official-requirements">
      <title>Special Requirements for Official (tier-1)
	Mirrors</title>

      <para>It is not so easy to state requirements for all official
	mirrors, since the project is sort of tolerant here.  It is
	more easy to say, what <emphasis>official tier-1
	  mirrors</emphasis> are required to.  All other official
	mirrors can consider this a big
	<emphasis>should</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Tier-1 mirrors are required to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>carry the complete fileset</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>allow access to other mirror sites</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>provide <application>FTP</application> and
	    <application>rsync</application> access</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Furthermore, admins should be subscribed to the &a.hubs;.
	See <link
	  xlink:href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/eresources.html#ERESOURCES-MAIL">this
	  link</link> for details, how to subscribe.</para>

      <important>
	<para>It is <emphasis>very</emphasis> important for a hub
	  administrator, especially Tier-1 hub admins, to check the
	  <link xlink:href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/">release
	    schedule</link> for the next FreeBSD release.  This is
	  important because it will tell you when the next release is
	  scheduled to come out, and thus giving you time to prepare
	  for the big spike of traffic which follows it.</para>

	<para>It is also important that hub administrators try to keep
	  their mirrors as up-to-date as possible (again, even more
	  crucial for Tier-1 mirrors).  If Mirror1 does not update for
	  a while, lower tier mirrors will begin to mirror old data
	  from Mirror1 and thus begins a downward spiral... Keep your
	  mirrors up to date!</para>
      </important>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-official-become">
      <title>How to Become Official Then?</title>

      <!--
      <para>An interesting question, especially, since the state of
	being official comes with some benefits, like a much higher
	bill from your ISP as more people will be using your site.
	Also it may be a key requirement to get access to a master
	site.</para>

      <para>Before applying, please consider (again) if another
	official mirror is really needed for your region. Check first
	with your zone administrator
	(<email>hostmaster@CC.FreeBSD.org</email>) or, if that fails,
	ask on the &a.hubs;.</para>

      <para>Ok, here is how to do it:</para>

      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <para>Get the mirror running in first place (maybe not using
	    a master site, yet).</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para><ulink
	      url="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/eresources.html#ERESOURCES-MAIL">Subscribe</ulink>
	    to the &a.hubs;.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>If everything works so far, contact the DNS
	    administrator responsible for your region/country, and ask
	    for a DNS entry for your site. The admin should able to be
	    contacted via <email>hostmaster@CC.FreeBSD.org</email>,
	    where <emphasis>CC</emphasis> is your country code/TLD.
	    Your DNS entry will be as described in <xref
	      linkend="mirror-where-organization"/>.</para>

	  <para>If there is no subdomain set up for your country yet,
	    you should contact
	    <email>mirror-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>, or you can try
	    the &a.hubs; first.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Whoever helps you get an official name should send
	    email to <email>mirror-admin@FreeBSD.org</email> so your
	    site will be added to the mirror list in the <ulink
	      url="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook">FreeBSD
	      Handbook</ulink>.</para>
	</step>
      </procedure>

      <para>That is it.</para>
-->

      <para>We are not accepting any new mirrors at this time.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="mirror-statpages">
    <title>Some Statistics from Mirror Sites</title>

    <para>Here are links to the stat pages of your favorite mirrors
      (aka the only ones who feel like providing stats).</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="mirror-statpagesftp">
      <title>FTP Site Statistics</title>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>ftp.is.FreeBSD.org -
	    <email>hostmaster@is.FreeBSD.org</email> - <link
	      xlink:href="http://www.rhnet.is/status/draupnir/draupnir.html">
	      (Bandwidth)</link> <link
	      xlink:href="http://www.rhnet.is/status/ftp/ftp-notendur.html">(FTP
	      processes)</link> <link
	      xlink:href="http://www.rhnet.is/status/ftp/http-notendur.html">(HTTP
	      processes)</link></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>ftp2.ru.FreeBSD.org -
	    <email>mirror@macomnet.ru</email> - <link
	      xlink:href="http://mirror.macomnet.net/mrtg/mirror.macomnet.net_195.128.64.25.html">(Bandwidth)</link>
	    <link
	      xlink:href="http://mirror.macomnet.net/mrtg/mirror.macomnet.net_proc.html">(HTTP
	      and FTP users)</link></para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
