<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD GNOME Project: GNOME &gnomever; Upgrading FAQ">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.gnome">

  <h2>Contents</h2>
    <ol>
    <li> <a href="#q1">What is new in GNOME &gnomever;?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q2">How do I upgrade to GNOME &gnomever;?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q3">The upgrade failed; what do I do?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q4">List of known GNOME &gnomever; problems and their solutions</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q5">I have found a bug; whom should I alert?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q6">I want the fame and glory of the FreeBSD GNOME team!  What
      can I do to participate?</a></li>
    </ol>

  <h2>Full Text</h2>
    <ol>
<!-- Q1 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q1"></a>
      <p><b>What is new in GNOME &gnomever;?</b></p>
<!-- A1 -->
      <p>Although the canonical summary of new features can be found at
        <a
	href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/&gnomever;/">http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/&gnomever;/</a>,
	some of the most exciting new features of GNOME &gnomever; are:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Evolution MAPI support has been added to the FreeBSD port
	  to provide a richer experience for users of Microsoft Exchange
	  servers.</li>
	<li>Epiphany now uses WebKit as its HTML/JavaScript rendering
	  engine.</li>
	<li>Hal has been updated to fix some issues with volume
	  probing, and to support volume names (labels) that contain
	  spaces.</li>
	<li>A preview of the GNOME Shell environment has been added to
	  the ports tree (<tt>x11/gnome-shell</tt>).  This environment
	  is being slated to make its official appearance in GNOME 3.0.</li>
      </ul>

      </li>

<!-- Q2 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q2"></a>
      <p><b>How do I upgrade to GNOME &gnomever;?</b></p>
<!-- A2 -->
      <p>The answer is relatively simple:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>
	  <p>To build GNOME &gnomever;, you need to obtain the latest
	    ports tree skeleton.  This is most easily accomplished with
	    <tt>portsnap(8)</tt> or <a
	    href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/cvsup.html">CVSup</a>.  Simply obtain the latest ports tree, and you are
	    ready to go.  Then do the following:</p>
	  <pre>
# pkgdb -Ff
(resolve all moved or deleted ports)

# portupgrade -aW
	  </pre>

	    <p><b>NOTE:</b> it is recommended to run <b>portupgrade
	    -a</b> to make sure you get all the necessary ports.  The
	    -W option simply makes things a bit faster by not doing a
	    <tt>make clean</tt> after each port build.</p>

	  <p>If you are a <tt>portmaster(8)</tt> user, make sure you have
	    least 1.9 version. Then do the following:</p>

	  <pre>
# portmaster -a
	  </pre></li>

	</ol>
	</li>

<!-- Q3 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q3"></a>
      <p><b>The upgrade failed; what do I do?</b></p>
<!-- A3 -->
      <p>Unfortunately, this is not only possible, it is highly probable.  There are many possible
        valid GNOME configurations, and even more invalid starting points.  If the script fails,
	follow the instructions in the error message to let the FreeBSD GNOME team know about the
	failure.</p>

      <p>The majority of build failures will be dependency-related issues.  One simple way to resolve
        the problem is to remove the offending port, re-run <tt>portupgrade</tt> or <tt>portmaster</tt>, and then
	reinstall the port when the upgrade process is complete.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q4 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q4"></a>
      <p><b>List of GNOME &gnomever; problems and their solutions</b></p>
<!-- A4 -->
      <p>Although GNOME &gnomever; is certainly the best release to date (of course), there are
	    a couple regressions that slipped in, both in the GNOME code and in its implementation
		within FreeBSD.  Some of the more visible issues are:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><b>HAL</b> can not unmount and reset the da[0-9] devices
	  associated with USB disks when you manually detach them from
	  the system.  Manually removing a USB umass device while it
	  is mounted can result in a panic.  This is a known bug in FreeBSD.
	  See <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=kern/103258">kern/103258</a> and <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=kern/89102">kern/89102</a> for more details.</li>
	<li>Epiphany no longer saves passwords.  This should be fixed
	  in an upcoming release, but may get postponed until GNOME
	  2.30.</li>
	<li>Epiphany has problems rendering certain compressed web
	  sites (most notably <a
	  href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/</a>).
	  The page will appear as compressed binary garbage.  This is
	  being wored on, and should be fixed in an upcoming release of
	  libsoup.</li>
      </ul>
      </li>

<!-- Q5 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q5"></a>
      <p><b>I have found a bug; whom should I alert?</b></p>
<!-- A5 -->
      <p>Please read the FreeBSD GNOME Project's
        <a href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/bugging.html">documentation on reporting bugs</a>.
      </p>
      </li>

<!-- Q6 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q6"></a>
      <p><b>I want the fame and glory of being part of the FreeBSD GNOME team!
	    What can I do to participate?</b></p>
<!-- A6 -->
      <p>Please read our list of <a href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/volunteer.html">ways
        to get involved</a>!
      </p>
      </li>
    </ol>

</body>
</html>
