<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD GNOME Project: Hardware Abstraction Layer (HAL) FAQ">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.gnome">

  <em>"You're in luck, Dave.  Turns out I CAN let you do that."</em>

  <h2>Contents</h2>
    <ol>
    <li> <a href="#q1">How do I use hal on FreeBSD?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q2">How do I prevent hal from probing a
      device?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q3">How do I mount media using hal?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q4">How do I troubleshoot problems with
      hal?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q5">Does hal support Fuse file systems?</a></li>
    <li> <a href="#q6">Hal is interfering with my CD/DVD drive when I
      want to play a disc or burn something.  How can I stop this from
      happening?</a></li>
    </ol>

  <h2>Full Text</h2>
    <ol>
<!-- Q1 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q1"></a>
        <p><b>How do I use hal on FreeBSD?</b></p>
<!-- A1 -->
        <p>The only thing you need to do in order to use hal is to
	  start the HAL daemon, <tt>hald</tt>.  To do this, add the
	  following to <tt>/etc/rc.conf</tt>:</p>

	<pre>
dbus_enable="YES"
hald_enable="YES"
	</pre>

	<p><b>NOTE:</b> GNOME users can opt to add
	  <tt>gnome_enable="YES"</tt> to <tt>/etc/rc.conf</tt> instead
	  of the lines above.  This will start all GNOME-related
	  services including Avahi and GDM.</p>

	<p>Then you must either reboot, or run:</p>

	<pre>
# /usr/local/etc/rc.d/dbus start
# /usr/local/etc/rc.d/hald start
	</pre>

	<p>Once <tt>hald</tt> is running, hal-aware application will
	  automatically start to communicate with it over D-BUS.  To
	  confirm that hald is running correctly, execute
	  <tt>lshal</tt> from the command line.  This provides you
	  with a list of devices attached to the system.  <b>Note:</b>
	  <tt>lshal</tt> must be run from within a D-BUS enabled
	  session (e.g. GNOME or KDE).</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q2 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q2"></a>
	<p><b>How do I prevent hal from probing a device?</b></p>
<!-- A2 -->
	  <p>Sometimes, when hal probes a device, this can cause the
	    system to hang, panic, or otherwise behave badly.  By
	    using device information files (.fdi files), you can tell
	    hal to ignore such devices.  These files are in XML
	    format, and should be created under
	    <tt>/usr/local/share/hal/fdi/preprobe/20thirdparty</tt>.
	    For example, to tell hal to ignore USB uhci controller 0,
	    create a file
	    <tt>/usr/local/share/hal/fdi/preprobe/20thirdparty/10-ignore-uhci0.fdi</tt>
	    with the following contents:</p>

	  <pre>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;

&lt;deviceinfo version="0.2"&gt;
  &lt;device&gt;
    &lt;match key="freebsd.driver" string="uhci"&gt;
      &lt;match key="freebsd.unit" int="0"&gt;
        &lt;merge key="info.ignore" type="bool"&gt;true&lt;/merge&gt;
      &lt;/match&gt;
    &lt;/match&gt;
  &lt;/device&gt;
&lt;/deviceinfo&gt;
	  </pre>

	  <p>Using this same technique, you can also merge (or change)
	    other hal device properties.  Use the <tt>lshal</tt>
	    command to get a list of all available device properties.
	    You can also look at the system-provided .fdi files under
	    <tt>/usr/local/share/hal/fdi/preprobe/10osvendor</tt> for
	    more examples.</p>

	  <p>All .fdi files in this <tt>20thirdparty</tt> directory
	    are loaded in alphabetical order, so name your files
	    accordingly.  The convention is to start the files with a
	    number.  The lower the number, the earlier the file will
	    be loaded.</p>
	</li>

<!-- Q3 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q3"></a>
	<p><b>How do I mount media using hal?</b></p>
<!-- A3 -->
	<p>Understand that having hal alone does not mean media will
	  get automatically mounted. Hal simply serves as a broker for
	  requests to mount certain devices. Some other software needs
	  to make this request.  As of GNOME 2.22, this is Nautilus.
	  KDE and XFCE have their own components to mount hal
	  volumes.</p>

	<p><b>NOTE:</b> Volumes that you wish to manage using
	  hal should <em>NOT</em> be listed in <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>.
	  This is especially true for CD devices and floppy disk
	  devices.  If you try to dynamically mount a volume using hal
	  that is listed in <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> you will see the
	  following error:</p>

	<pre>
mount_cd9660: /dev/acd0: Operation not permitted
	</pre>

	<p>If you are a GNOME user be aware that prior to GNOME
	  2.22, <tt>gnome-volume-manager</tt> was responsible for
	  asking hal to mount volumes.  Since this responsibility
	  has moved to Nautilus, it is vital to change
	  <tt>gnome-volume-manager's</tt> configuration so that it
	  will no longer attempt to mount volumes.</p>

	<p><b>NOTE:</b> This step is only required if you are a
	  GNOME user that upgraded to 2.22 from a previous version
	  of GNOME.  If this is not the case, then skip to Step
	  1.</p>

	<p>From within your GNOME session, run the following
	  commands:</p>

	<pre>
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/automount_drives false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/automount_media false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/autobrowse false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/autoplay_cda false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/autoplay_dvd false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/autoplay_vcd false
% gconftool-2 -s --type bool /desktop/gnome/volume_manager/autoprinter false
	</pre>

	<p>Then restart GNOME.</p>

	<p><b>Step 1:</b> All users <em>MUST</em> have <tt>procfs</tt> mounted
	  on <tt>/proc</tt>.  Hal uses an application called PolicyKit
	  to authorize users to perform mount tasks, and PolicyKit
	  relies heavily on <tt>/proc</tt> entries.  If <tt>/proc</tt>
	  is not mounted, volume mounting will not work.  To mount
	  <tt>/proc</tt>, add the following to
	  <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>:</p>

	<pre>
proc           /proc       procfs  rw  0   0
	</pre>

	<p>Then run the following command:</p>

	<pre>
# mount /proc
	</pre>

	<p><b>Step 2:</b>  In order to mount volumes using hal, you
	  must be authorized. This authorization is carried out by
	  ConsoleKit and PolicyKit.  If you are a GNOME user, and you
	  use GDM to login to GNOME, then you do not need to make any
	  additional configuration changes in order to mount removable
	  media. If you are not a GNOME user, or you start GNOME
	  without using GDM, then you will need to edit
	  <tt>/usr/local/etc/PolicyKit/PolicyKit.conf</tt>, and add
	  the <tt>org.freedesktop.hal.storage.mount-removable</tt>
	  action to your username.  For example, if your username is
	  "marcus," you would add the following lines:</p>

	<pre>
&lt;match action="org.freedesktop.hal.storage.mount-removable"&gt;
  &lt;match user="marcus"&gt;
    &lt;return result="yes"/&gt;
  &lt;/match&gt;
&lt;/match&gt;
	</pre>

	<p><b>NOTE:</b> All config lines in this file <em>MUST</em> be
	  between the opening and closing <tt>&lt;config&gt;</tt>
	  tags:</p>

	<pre>
&lt;config version="0.1"&gt;
&lt;!-- New configuration lines go here. --&gt;
&lt;/config&gt;
	</pre>

	<p>If you use GDM to login to GNOME, GDM will add a ConsoleKit
	  record for the session.  If this session is active, then you
	  will be allowed to mount removable media without any
	  additional PolicyKit configuration.  You can confirm if
	  ConsoleKit is working correctly by running the command,
	  <tt>ck-list-sessions</tt>.  The <tt>active</tt> property must be
	  <tt>TRUE</tt> for auto-mounting to work.</p>

	<p>By default, PolicyKit allows root to do everything, and all
	  users in the "wheel" group are allowed to authenticate for
	  admin tasks with their own password.  To get a list of all
	  available actions, use the <tt>polkit-action(1)</tt>
	  command.  For more information on the directives available
	  for <tt>PolicyKit.conf</tt>, see the
	  <tt>PolicyKit.conf(5)</tt> man page.</p>

	<p><b>Step 3:</b> If you have fixed volumes you wish to mount,
	  you must also authorize yourself for the
	  <tt>org.freedesktop.hal.storage.mount-fixed</tt> action.
	  <b>Note:</b> This step is applicable to <em>ALL</em> users
	  including GNOME users using GDM. This is done just like the
	  removable action above.  For example, to allow user "marcus"
	  to mount fixed volumes, add the following to
	  <tt>PolicyKit.conf</tt>:</p>

	<pre>
&lt;match action="org.freedesktop.hal.storage.mount-fixed"&gt;
  &lt;match user="marcus"&gt;
    &lt;return result="yes"/&gt;
  &lt;/match&gt;
&lt;/match&gt;
	</pre>

	<p><b>Step 4:</b>  While not really part of hal volume
	  management, you may also be able to have volumes listed in
	  <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> automatically mounted.  In GNOME, for
	  example, Nautilus will mount volumes listed in
	  <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> provided the following conditions are
	  met:</p>

	<ol>
	  <li>The <tt>vfs.usermount</tt> sysctl is set to <tt>1</tt>.</li>
	  <li>The user requesting the mount owns the mount point.</li>
	  <li>The user requesting the mount is in the "operator"
	    group.</li>
	</ol>

	<p>For example, say you had the following listed in
	  <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>:</p>

	<pre>
/dev/ad0s1              /win/c          msdosfs rw,noauto       0
0
	</pre>

	<p>If you want Nautilus to mount this volume as the user
	  "marcus," do the following:</p>

	<pre>
# sysctl vfs.usermount="1"
# chown marcus /win/c
# pw group mod operator -m marcus
	</pre>

	<p>Then, when the user marcus logs into GNOME, <tt>/win/c</tt>
	  will be automatically mounted on the desktop.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q4 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q4"></a>
	<p><b>How do I troubleshoot problems with hal?</b></p>
<!-- A4 -->
	<p>If you run into problems with hal, you must first collect
	  the <a
	  href="https://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/bugging.html">general
	  troubleshooting information</a> required by the FreeBSD
	  GNOME Team.  You should also provide a detailed description
	  of the problem, and the output of <tt>lshal</tt> (assuming
	  <tt>hald</tt> is starting).  Remember, <tt>lshal</tt>
	  <em>MUST</em> be run under a D-BUS enabled session.  If you
	  cannot login to GNOME, KDE, or XFCE, run <tt>lshal</tt>
	  within <tt>dbus-launch</tt>:</p>

	<pre>
% dbus-launch lshal
	</pre>

	<p>You should also provide the verbose output from
	  <tt>hald</tt> when it is performing the problematic task.
	  To get this, first stop <tt>hald</tt>, then run it
	  manually:</p>

	<pre>
# /usr/local/etc/rc.d/hald stop
# /usr/local/sbin/hald --daemon="no" --verbose="yes"
	</pre>

	<p>Capture all of the output on the screen.</p>

	<p>If you are having problems with hal detecting volumes or
	  media, or having problems with mounting volumes through hal,
	  obtain the following additional information.  All of this
	  needs to be collected with the problem device attached to
	  the system.</p>

	<ol>
	  <li>Output of <tt>sysctl -b kern.geom.conftxt</tt></li>
	  <li>Contents of <tt>/etc/fstab</tt></li>
	  <li>Output of the <tt>mount</tt> command</li>
	  <li>Full <tt>dmesg</tt> output</li>
	  <li>If using GNOME, and a volume is not mounting properly,
	    include the output of <tt>gnome-mount --block --no-ui
	    --verbose --hal-udi &lt;Device UDI&gt;</tt> (&lt;Device
	    UDI&gt; is the Unique Device Identifier obtained from the
	    output of <tt>lshal</tt> for the device that is not
	    mounting properly)</li>
	</ol>

	<p>Additionally, if you are a GDM user, please provide the
	  output of <tt>ck-list-sessions</tt>.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q5 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q5"></a>
	<p><b>Does hal support Fuse file systems?</b></p>
<!-- A5 -->
	<p>Yes.  As of hal-0.5.11_10, Fuse file systems are supported.
	  See the installed
	  <tt>/usr/local/share/doc/hal-0.5.11/README.fuse</tt> file
	  for more details.</p>
      </li>

<!-- Q6 -->
      <li style="padding-bottom: 0.5em"><a name="q6"></a>
	<p><b>Hal is interfering with my CD/DVD drive when I want to play
	  a disc or burn something.  How can I stop this from
	  happening?</b></p>
<!-- A6 -->
	<p>Applications which are not hal-aware will not be able to
	  tell hald to stop polling CD/DVD drives when they begin to use
	  them.  Because of this, hald may cause these applications to
	  abort because two different processes are trying to use the
	  device at the same time.  Applications such as totem, k3b,
	  sound-juicer, etc. should not be affected as they are
	  hal-aware.  For other applications, you can start them using
	  the <tt>hal-lock</tt> command.  This command will try and
	  lock the device in question.  If successful, hald will stop
	  polling the device, and <tt>hal-lock</tt> will spawn the
	  desired application.  The arguments to <tt>hal-lock</tt> are
	  as follows:</p>

<pre>
% hal-lock --interface org.freedesktop.Hal.Device.Storage --udi UDI --run COMMAND
</pre>
        <p>You can use <tt>lshal</tt> to determine the proper
	  <tt>UDI</tt> value.  For example, to run <tt>abcde</tt> to
	  extract tracks from a CD:</p>

<pre>
% hal-lock --interface org.freedesktop.Hal.Device.Storage --udi /org/freedesktop/Hal/devices/storage_model_DVD__RW_DVD8801 --run abcde
</pre>

        <p>As soon as the application finishes, the lock will be
	  released.</p>
      </li>

    </ol>

</body>
</html>
