<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Commercial Gallery//EN"
                         "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/gallery.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/share/sgml/commercial.consult.xml,v 1.125 2010/12/22 08:06:39 jkois Exp $ -->

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/share/sgml/commercial.consult.xml,v 1.125 2010/12/22 08:06:39 jkois Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <categories>
    <category id="africa">Africa</category>
    <category id="asia">Asia</category>
    <category id="australia">Australia</category>
    <category id="europe">Europe</category>
    <category id="nzealand">New Zealand</category>
    <category id="namerica">North America</category>
    <category id="samerica">South America</category>
  </categories>

  <entry id="Aaronsen" category="namerica">
    <name>Aaronsen Group, Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.aaronsen.com/freebsd/</url>
    <description>
      Aaronsen Group, Ltd. advises on and implements a wide range of
      internetworking technologies, including remote access, wide area
      networks, international telecommunications, Intranetworking, web
      applications and local area services. Many of our custom web-enabled
      solutions are engineered using FreeBSD, Apache, mod_perl, and
      MySQL/Oracle. Please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@aaronsen.com">info@aaronsen.com</a>. Our web site
      is at <a href="http://www.aaronsen.com">http://www.aaronsen.com</a>
      and we can be reached via telephone at +1.412.391.6000.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Adimus" category="europe">
    <name>Adimus GmbH &amp; Co. KG</name>
    <url>http://www.adimus.de/</url>
    <description>
      Adimus GmbH &amp; Co. KG is a company based in Bochum, Germany. As a
      consulting partner we provide services in system administration for
      all flavors of Unix and Microsoft Windows, design and maintenance of
      LANs and WANs, IT security auditing and database management.
      Solutions for intra- and internet servers as well as our firewall
      toolkit are based on FreeBSD and third-party products from Compaq,
      Peacock, Cisco and Ascend. For more information please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@adimus.de">info@adimus.de</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.adimus.de/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Acadix" category="namerica">
    <name>Acadix, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.acadix.biz</url>
    <description>
      Acadix, LLC offers a full range of services for FreeBSD and other
      platforms, including system integration, file servers, WEB servers,
      and programming/porting.  Acadix provides on-site services to
      businesses, schools, and charitable organizations in the Milwaukee
      metro area.  Programming services are available to all locations in
      the U.S.  For more information, please <a
      href="http://acadix.biz">visit our website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Advance" category="namerica">
    <name>Advance Systems Group</name>
    <url>http://www.advansys.net/</url>
    <description>
      Advance Systems Group builds, administrates, and maintains
      Intranet/Internet networks using FreeBSD and other UNIX operating
      systems. ASG also provides a variety of other services including
      domain name hosting, web site construction, and software training.
      For more information, please phone us at +1.317.507.4229, e-mail <a
      href="mailto:sales@advansys.net">sales@advansys.net</a>, or <a
      href="http://www.advansys.net/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ateamsystems" category="namerica">
    <name>A-Team Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.ateamsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      A-Team Systems has over 15 years of experience helping clients
      leverage the power of &os; in combination with other open source
      software such as PHP, MySQL and Apache in a secure, customized
      and cohesive way.  We've been with &os; since version 1.0!  We
      can help you with your existing deployment or future plans:
      From encrypted backups to web and mail servers.  Visit our
      <a href="http://www.ateamsystems.com/">website</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ALE" category="europe">
    <name>ALE Software</name>
    <url>http://linux.wroclaw.pl/</url>
    <description>
      We offer IT consulting, systems integration and corporate information
      systems based on BSD software. For more information, email
      <a href="mailto:admin@linux.wroclaw.pl">admin@linux.wroclaw.pl</a> or
      visit our <a href="http://linux.wroclaw.pl">website</a>.  We operate
      mostly in Eastern Europe (Poland).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Adminia" category="europe">
    <name>Adminia Sistemas</name>
    <url>http://www.adminia.es/</url>
    <description>
      Adminia offers technological consulting and professional system
      administration services, specializing in free software and virtualized
      high-availability environments.  We have over 15 years experience in
      using and customizing FreeBSD systems in data processing centres,
      small and medium-sized businesses and universities.  We are located in
      Madrid, Spain.  Contact us for reliable and expert partnership via
      <a href="mailto:contacto@adminia.es">email</a> or visit our
      <a href="http://www.adminia.es">website</a>.   
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="anonbsd" category="samerica">
    <name>AnonBSD Inc.</name>
    <url>https://sites.google.com/site/anonbsd/</url>
    <description>
      We provide IT environment consulting.  Support in FreeBSD, OpenBSD,
      Linux (Debian, RedHat, SUSE, Gentoo, Slackware) and OpenSolaris.  High
      availability, virtualization, monitoring, security, deployment,
      network infrastructure.  We service in S&#227;o Paulo/SP and
      Campinas/SP in Brazil. Contact us via e-mail (<a
      href="mailto:ricardo.ichizo@gmail.com">ricardo.ichizo@gmail.com</a>) or
      by phone at +55 (19) 8202-1567.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="BITNETS" category="namerica">
    <name>BITNETS Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.bitnets.com</url>
    <description>
      BITNETS Inc. specializes in BIND, Apache, Postfix, Courier-IMAP and
      a variety of server components running on FreeBSD with emphasis on
      security and stability. Services include consulting on server
      evaluation, installation and configuration and FreeBSD-based managed
      secure e-mail hosting. We are located in St. Albert,
      serving the Edmonton area of Alberta, Canada. Call us toll-free in
      North America at 1-877-BITNETS for general enquiries or
      <a href="http://www.bitnets.com/contact">e-mail us</a>.
      Winners of the chamber of commerce InfoTech Award of Distinction.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="blappitconsulting" category="europe">
    <name>Blapp IT Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.blapp-it-consulting.ch/</url>
    <description>
      Located in Basel/Switzerland, Blapp-IT-Consulting provides
      consulting services related to complex mail routing and gateway
      solutions, SaaS, BSD Hosting, Internet servers and infrastructure,
      programming, FreeBSD and other BSD operating systems, security
      auditing/firewalls, system administration, etc.  For more
      information please visit our <a
      href="http://www.blapp-it-consulting.ch/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BMK" category="australia">
    <name>B.M.K. Industries</name>
    <url>http://www.bmk.com.au</url>
    <description>
      B.M.K. Industries is located in Melbourne Australia and specializes
      in setting up low cost routers and servers (Web, E-Mail, FTP, DNS and
      Secure Web Servers ) all using FreeBSD. Setting up Permanent Modem &amp;
      ISDN Internet Connections is also a specialty. <a
      href="http://www.bmk.com.au">Please visit our web page.</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bpa" category="europe">
    <name>Black Point Arts Internet Solutions GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.bpanet.de/</url>
    <description>
      Black Point Arts Internet Solutions GmbH is located in Germany
      (Frankfurt/Main).  We have experiences with FreeBSD, Linux and Windows
      Servers.  Our business activities include hosting/homing, programming
      and webdesign.  We develop solutions for your intra-, extra- and
      internet needs.  For more informations you can visit <a
      href="http://www.bpanet.de/">our website</a> or write an email to
      <a href="mailto:service@bpanet.de">service@bpanet.de</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BSDConsulting" category="europe">
    <name>BSD Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.bsdconsulting.no/</url>
    <description>
      BSD Consulting provides consulting services related to Internet
      servers/infrastructure, programming, FreeBSD &amp; BSD operating
      systems, security auditing/firewalls, system administration, etc.
      Based in Oslo, Norway.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="catpipe" category="europe">
    <name>catpipe Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.catpipe.net/</url>
    <description>
      catpipe Systems ApS provide managed services and support contracts
      for FreeBSD implemented on rackmountable servers preloaded with
      FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ChinaIS" category="asia">
    <name>China Internet Service</name>
    <url>http://www.1260.cn/</url>
    <description>
      China Internet Services <a href="http://www.1260.cn">www.1260.cn</a>
      is a China Internet Email and Webhosting provider offering UNIX
      shell accounts, web hosting, mailman and ezmlm, pop3, imap, webmail
      (squirrelmail), mysql, php, fastcgi and mod_perl hosting on FreeBSD
      servers in Nanjing. Phone: 0086-25-84527765.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Clue" category="namerica">
    <name>Clue Computing, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.clue.com/</url>
    <description>
      Clue Computing, Inc. has over 10 years of UNIX experience,
      specializing in system administration, networking, and security.
      Custom application development and testing available, including
      device drivers, kernel work, etc. We offer sales, assembly, and
      installation of FreeBSD systems for any application. For more
      information, email <a href="mailto:info@clue.com">info@clue.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Codeangels" category="europe">
    <name>Codeangels Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.codeangels.com</url>
    <description>
      Codeangels Solutions GmbH based in Switzerland, region Zuerich.
      Offers its customers a range of IT Security, Network and UNIX
      Services. We utilize and support FreeBSD in our services and
      solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CodeGen" category="namerica">
    <name>CodeGen Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.codegen.com/</url>
    <description>
      CodeGen, Inc. provide consulting and programming services,
      specializing in embedded systems. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:info@codegen.com">info@codegen.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ColoAdvisor" category="namerica">
    <name>ColoAdvisor</name>
    <url>http://www.coloadvisor.com/</url>
    <description>
      Located in New Jersey, ColoAdvisor finds the best fit hosting,
      colocation and cloud computing services based on technical,
      geographical and financial needs.  Contact us for an immediate
      site assessment and to begin the process.  Either via <a
      href="mailto:info@coloadvisor.com">email</a> or via phone
      (+1-877-732-4003, press 1 to speak to an advisor for a free
      consultation).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Collective" category="namerica">
    <name>Collective Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.colltech.com</url>
    <description>
      Collective Technologies is the recognized leader in systems
      management services for distributed enterprise computing
      environments. Collective Technologies highly skilled consultants
      combine technical expertise with solid business sense to develop
      world-class IT solutions. Collective Technologies specializes in
      keeping complex computer systems running reliably offering a full
      range of support services including UNIX, NT, Linux, FreeBSD, OpenBSD
      and NetBSD to address the needs of a client's systems management
      lifecycle. The company is headquartered in Austin, Texas, with 19
      offices nationwide. For more information, visit <a
      href="http://www.colltech.com">our website</a> or e-mail us at <a
      href="mailto:contact@colltech.com">contact@colltech.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoreSoftware" category="australia">
    <name>Core Software</name>
    <url>http://www.coresoftware.net.au</url>
    <description>
      Core Software is based in Perth, Western Australia. We are a
      consulting company specializing in OpenBSD, FreeBSD, Linux and
      Windows. We work with firewalls, Virtual Private Networks, Database
      Servers, Email and Web Servers, Security, WAN/LAN implementations,
      Multi OS networks. You can contact us <a
      href="http://www.coresoftware.net.au/contact.html">here</a> or visit
      our <a href="http://www.coresoftware.net.au">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DataPipe" category="namerica">
    <name>DataPipe</name>
    <url>http://www.datapipe.com/</url>
    <description>
      Built on a rock-solid network and immediate live customer support,
      DataPipe is a trusted hosting company providing secure managed
      solutions.  Our specialized teams of passionate professionals take
      a personal interest in each client's unique needs, enabling
      businesses to outsource with confidence.  With world-class
      facilities strategically located in the New York Metropolitan
      &amp; Silicon Valley areas, Hong Kong and London, UK, DataPipe
      offers custom FreeBSD solutions and expert FreeBSD support 24
      hours a day, 365 days a year.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DeLorentz" category="europe">
    <name>DeLorentz &amp; Partners</name>
    <url>http://www.delorentz.nl/</url>
    <description>
      DeLorentz &amp; Partners is a consulting firm based in Hilversum
      in the Netherlands. We offer various types of consulting and
      support on FreeBSD. Info at <a href="mailto:info@delorentz.nl">
      info@delorentz.nl</a> or phone us at Tel: +31 (0)35 - 624 44 66.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Dextra" category="samerica">
    <name>Dextra Solu&#231;&#245;es em Inform&#225;tica</name>
    <url>http://www.dextra.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      Dextra Solu&#231;&#245;es em Inform&#225;tica. Specialized
      consulting in TCP/IP networks, capacity and contingency planning,
      UNIX systems and network administration, system security and
      firewalls, VPNs implementation, Internet/Intranets projects. For more
      information, please phone us at +55.19.251.3644 (Brazil), e-mail <a
      href="mailto:staff@dextra.com.br">staff@dextra.com.br</a>, or <a
      href="http://www.dextra.com.br/">visit our web site</a> (in
      Portuguese).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DieWebmaster" category="europe">
    <name>Die Webmaster Gmbh</name>
    <url>http://www.diewebmaster.at</url>
    <description>
      Die Webmaster Gmbh - We are a consulting company from Linz, Austria
      and offer a wide range of FreeBSD based services: FreeBSD
      installation, integration, troubleshooting, maintenance, FreeBSD
      based hosting (for example jail servers), serverhousing, hardware
      selection, configuration and support. e-mail: <a
      href="mailto:info@diewebmaster.at">info@diewebmaster.at</a>
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="EscapeBox" category="europe">
    <name>EscapeBox</name>
    <url>http://www.escapebox.net/en/</url>
    <description>
      More than 20 years of IT experience on demand!  The EscapeBox
      Germany GmbH, founded in 2002, is a small but agile company that
      offers IT consulting services.  We can support our clients both
      from remote and on location, as desired.  So, if you are looking
      for capable freelancers for your projects, please do not hesitate
      to <a href="http://www.escapebox.net/en/contact.html">contact</a>
      us today!
    </description>
  </entry>  

  <entry id="EssenzConsulting" category="namerica">
    <name>Essenz Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.essenz.com</url>
    <description>
      Essenz Consulting is a web services and products provider. We offer
      custom built High-Performance Intel based <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/open.html">Workstations</a> and <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/server.html">Servers</a>. These systems
      are 100% FreeBSD compatible. Our systems feature Ultra2-LVD SCSI,
      high speed networking, Dual Pentium III and Dual Pentium III XEON
      processors, and many other fault tolerant and backup features. For
      more information contact <a
      href="mailto:sales@essenz.com">sales@essenz.com</a> or visit us at <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com">http://www.essenz.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TheFreeBSDMall" category="namerica">
    <name>The FreeBSD Mall</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsdmall.com/</url>
    <description>
      The FreeBSD Mall offers several different levels of support contracts
      for FreeBSD. Support is available on a per-incident basis, or as a
      convenient, extensible annual contract. Our highly trained technical
      support staff will handle your requests in a professional and
      efficient manner and will provide detailed responses to your needs by
      phone, fax, or email. The FreeBSD Mall staff has over 8 years of
      experience supporting FreeBSD.
  For more information, please see <a
      href="http://www.freebsdmall.com/support/">our support page</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FarNorthNetworks" category="australia">
    <name>Far North Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.networks.nq.nu/</url>
    <description>
      Far North Networks, Based in Innisfail, North Queensland (About 100Km
      South of Cairns). Focus is on business network support providing low
      cost file/print servers based on FreeBSD. We also specialize in
      setting up internet gateways/firewalls. For more information send us
      an email to <a
      href="mailto:info@networks.nq.nu">info@networks.nq.nu</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FrigateNetworks" category="namerica">
    <name>Frigate Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.frigate.com/</url>
    <description>
      frigate networks provides network troubleshooting, system
      administration, kernel development and ports of BSD software to
      commercial products such as routers and firewalls. Our Email, DNS,
      and WWW servers run FreeBSD. We also provide network management
      solutions based on HTTP and tcl. For more information please <a
      href="http://www.frigate.com/">visit our web site</a>, call us at
      +1.650.903.2266, or send email to <a
      href="mailto:info@frigate.com">info@frigate.com></a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FSCInternet" category="namerica">
    <name>FSC Internet</name>
    <url>http://www.fscinternet.com/</url>
    <description>
      FSC Internet is Canada's largest FreeBSD consulting firm. FSC's
      clients include numerous top-tier corporations (e.g. Mazda, Heinz),
      as well as mid-sized companies (e.g. the Vermont Telephone Company)
      and the public sector. FSC provides full consulting, implementation,
      support, and training services for all FreeBSD applications,
      including a special focus on security, high-performance Web
      applications, and Intranets. Please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@fscinternet.com">info@fscinternet.com</a> or call
      us at +1.416.921.4280 for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GNUnetworks" category="europe">
    <name>GNUnetworks</name>
    <url>http://www.gnun.net/</url>
    <description>
      GNUnetworks is a System's consultancy group focused on free
      software.  We provide FreeBSD and Linux servers for Internet /
      Intranet as well as embedded systems for firewalling and data
      processing.<br /><br />Phone: +34-937340794<br />web:
      <a href="http://www.gnun.net">http://www.gnun.net</a><br />
      mail: <a href="mailto:info@gnun.net">info@gnun.net</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GurixWebProfessionals" category="namerica">
    <name>Gurix Web Professionals</name>
    <url>http://www.gurix.com</url>
    <description>
      Gurix Web Professionals Web Development, design, and custom
      application programming using both open source and proprietary
      environments. Services also include private consulting, emergency
      response coordination and various IT solutions to maximize the
      effectiveness of your business.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HerrinSoftware" category="namerica">
    <name>Herrin Software Development</name>
    <url>http://www.hsdi.com/</url>
    <description>
      Herrin Software Development, Inc., creator of <em>Qddb</em>, provides
      custom software development, internet consulting, general computer
      consulting, and training services. For more information email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@hsdi.com">info@hsdi.com</a> or <a
      href="http://www.hsdi.com/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="hntsolutions" category="namerica">
    <name>HNT Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.hntsolutions.com</url>
    <description>
      HNT Solutions provides complete &os; support services and
      consulting.  Please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:unix@hntsolutions.com">unix@hntsolutions.com</a> or
      visit our <a
      href="http://www.hntsolutions.com/unixpractice">website</a>
      for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="GregLehey" category="australia">
    <name>Greg Lehey</name>
    <url>http://www.lemis.com/~grog/</url>
    <description>
      Greg Lehey has over 20 years industry experience in all system
      programming and systems administration disciplines, including device
      drivers, kernel debugging, compilers, libraries, performance
      analysis, and site planning. He is the author of <a
      href="http://www.lemis.com/vinum.html">
	The Vinum Volume Manager</a>, a virtual disk driver which includes
      software RAID, and also the books
      <a href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/port/">
	Porting UNIX Software</a> and <a
      href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/cfreebsd/">
	The Complete FreeBSD</a>. Contact him <a
      href="mailto:grog@FreeBSD.org">
	via Email</a>,
      or visit his <a href= "http://www.lemis.com/~grog">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IKTech" category="europe">
    <name>IKTech</name>
    <url>http://www.iktech.net</url>
    <description>
      IKTech Dipl.-Ing. Gernot Schmied is a high-end systems integrator and
      UNIX competence center located in Vienna, Austria. We especially
      focus on telecommunications, networking and security aspects for NPO,
      corporate and Service Provider/Carrier customers. We use selected
      commercial products as well as FreeBSD, OpenBSD, NetBSD, Linux and
      Solaris and are the premier competence center with regards to
      advanced routing gateways. For inquiries please contact <a
      href="mailto:office@iktech.net?subject=IKTech%20inquiry%20with%20rega
      rds%20to%20www.freebsd.org%20listing">office@iktech.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GlobalTechnopolis" category="asia">
    <name>Global Technopolis Corporation</name>
    <url>http://globaltechnopolis.com/</url>
    <description>
      Located in Tokyo, Japan, The Global Technopolis Corporation provides
      computing technology consulting services including strategy and
      implementation proposals, administration, maintenance, hosting,
      support, and training for <a
      href="http://globaltechnopolis.com/services/consulting/operating-systems-and-platforms/bsd/freebsd/index.html">FreeBSD</a>.
      Our engineers can assist your business to set up routers/gateways,
      web servers, applications servers, database servers, backup
      servers and so forth.  Professional project management and on-time
      delivery within budget is always our commitment to our clients.
      For further details, please visit our <a
      href="http://globaltechnopolis.com/">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Hypermetrica" category="europe">
    <name>Hypermetrica</name>
    <url>http://www.esliadmina.net</url>
    <description>
      IT-consulting company Hypermetrica provides IT consulting and
      professional system administration services.   We develop
      high-available environments, web and network services for small
      and medium-sized businesses based on FreeBSD and other UNIX
      operating systems.   Our office is located in Moscow, Russia.
      Contact us for consulting via <a
      href="mailto:info@hypermetrica.ru">email</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.esliadmina.net">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InformSystem" category="asia">
    <name>Inform System Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.inform.co.jp/</url>
    <description>
      Inform System Inc. is a FreeBSD/Internet/DataBase consulting company.
      Located in Osaka Japan, we offer a wide range of services to school
      and small businesses. For further details, please <a
      href="http://www.inform.co.jp/">visit our web site</a>, or send email
      to <a href="mailto:info@inform.co.jp">info@inform.co.jp</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="innominate" category="europe">
    <name>innominate AG</name>
    <url>http://innominate.de/</url>
    <description>
      innominate AGis a Linux, *BSD and Open Source service provider based
      in Berlin, Germany. Not only as consulting partner but also as system
      administrator, programmer, supporter and trainer we offer the full
      range of services with a heavy focus on Open Source products. Many of
      our tailor-made products are engineered using apache, Perl, Zope,
      MySQL and Oracle running on Linux and *BSD. For further information
      please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@innominate.de">info@innominate.de</a> or visit our
      <a href="http://innominate.de/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InterACT" category="europe">
    <name>InterACT</name>
    <url>http://www.interact.se</url>
    <description>
      InterACT is a Sweden based provider of Consultancy and Custom
      Development Services. Principal consultant <a
      href="mailto:cl@interact.se">Chris Lindbergh</a> has over 10 years
      system software development experience on BSD based platforms. Areas
      of expertise include Firewall and Networking System setup, custom
      development in C and C++, and supply of turnkey solutions. For
      further information, contact us by email at: <a
      href="mailto:info@interact.se">info@interact.se</a>, or phone Sweden
      on +46 (0)920-888 03
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ITSchulungen" category="europe">
    <name>IT-schulungen.com</name>
    <url>http://www.it-schulungen.com</url>
    <description>
      Located in Germany, IT-Schulungen.com is a portal for IT-Trainings
      (both individual workshops and public seminars) and offers
      training and consulting for different Open Source systems including <a
      href="http://www.it-schulungen.com/seminare/serversysteme/freebsd/index.html">FreeBSD</a>.
      For further information please call 01805 120 222 (from within
      Germany) or visit our <a
      href="http://www.it-schulungen.com">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ITSecurity" category="namerica">
    <name>It Security Services</name>
    <url>http://www.itsecuritymn.com</url>
    <description>
      IT Security Services is based in Minneapolis, Minnesota and serves
      the Twin Cities. We provide a complete line of security services,
      such as audits, secure servers, and new network installations with
      emphasis on security. We are highly skilled with FreeBSD, and can
      use it to run extremely fast and reliable servers using all popular
      services. You can reach us at <a href="mailto:
      info@itsecuritymn.com">info@itsecuritymn.com</a>, or our web site at
      <a href="http://www.itsecuritymn.com">http://www.itsecuritymn.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OKTS" category="namerica">
    <name>Okanagan Technology Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.okts.ca/</url>
    <description>
      Okanagan Technology Solutions specializes in open source
      technologies, in particular FreeBSD, Perl, Apache, and MySQL for
      clients in the beautiful Okanagan region of British Columbia.
      For more information, please visit our <a
      href="http://www.okts.ca">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LNC" category="namerica">
    <name>Linux Network Care</name>
    <url>http://www.linuxnetworkcare.com/</url>
    <description>
      Linux Network Care is based in Toronto, Ontario.  Our company is
      specialized in providing Linux and FreeBSD based solutions for
      small, medium and corporate sized businesses.  We provide
      ourselves on our delivery of dependable network solutions, world
      class server administration, tight server security and easy to
      understand Linux training.  We also provide desktop integration
      with Ubuntu Linux.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Lionra" category="europe">
    <name>Lionra Support Services Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.lionra.com/</url>
    <description>
      Lionra Support Services Ltd. provides IT solutions including
      tailored network infrastructure, custom-designed servers, remote
      administration and security audits.  We have over 10 years
      experience in the IT sector, specializing in *BSD, GNU/Linux
      &amp; Open Source software.  Further information about Lionra
      Support Services Ltd. and the services we offer can be found at
      <a href="http://www.lionra.com/">http://www.lionra.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Schweikhardt" category="europe">
    <name>Jens Schweikhardt</name>
    <url>http://www.schweikhardt.net/</url>
    <description>
      Jens Schweikhardt, located near <b>Stuttgart/Germany</b>, is a
      FreeBSD committer with 20 years of Unix experience who won several
      national and international programming contests. If you have a
      problem that can be solved using the Unix toolbox (preferably C,
      perl, shell) he is the one to make it happen. With his background in
      Unix Standardization he will make sure your investment runs portably
      and efficiently on all the Unices you care for. Contact him via <a
      href="mailto:schweikh@FreeBSD.org">schweikh@FreeBSD.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Stacey" category="europe">
    <name>Julian Stacey</name>
    <url>http://www.berklix.com/~jhs/cv/</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://berklix.com/">Net services &amp; systems
	engineering</a>, UNIX since 1978, Maintains a <a
	href="http://berklix.com/~jhs/consultants/">FreeBSD Commercial
	Consultants Index</a> (<b>sorted geographically &amp; by full
      &amp; part timers)</b>.  Be sure to visit his page!
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MediaCenter" category="europe">
    <name>MediaCenter</name>
    <url>http://www.umc.se/</url>
    <description>
      MediaCenter, Ume&#230;, Sweden. Located in northern Sweden we offer
      professional consulting and programming for secure inter/intranet
      solutions using FreeBSD and UNIX(-like) operating systems. We also
      work high performance database programming, primarily using
      PostgreSQL. For more information, please send email to <a
      href="mailto:info@umc.se">info@umc.se</a>, or visit our website (<a
      href="http://www.umc.se/">http://www.umc.se/</a>)
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MindStep" category="namerica">
    <name>MindStep Corp.</name>
    <url>http://www.mindstep.com/</url>
    <description>
      MindStep Corp. configure and maintain Intranet/Internet networks
      using FreeBSD and other Unix operating systems. MindStep also offers
      products and provides software development services customized to fit
      the needs of corporations of any size.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MidwestSystems" category="namerica">
    <name>Midwest Systems Solutions, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.midwestsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      Midwest Systems Solutions Inc. , based in Winnipeg Canada, provides
      hardware, software and consulting services including LAN, WAN, remote
      access, file and printer servers, Internet solutions and support and
      administration of FreeBSD and Linux systems. Midwest Systems
      specializes in Web, FTP, Internet Gateways, firewall solutions based
      on FreeBSD and Linux. Midwest Systems Solutions also offers both
      virtual and dedicated webhosting solutions. For more information,
      please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@midwestsystems.com">mailto:info@midwestsystems.com</a>
	or visit our website at <a
      href="http://www.midwestsystems.com/">www.midwestsystems.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Nesbitt" category="namerica">
    <name>Nesbitt &amp; Associates</name>
    <url>http://www.nesbitt.ca/</url>
    <description>
      Nesbitt &amp; Associates is based in Vancouver, Canada, but
      have worked with clients all over the world.  We specialize
      in open source technologies, in particular, FreeBSD, Perl,
      Apache, mod_perl and MySQL. For more information, please visit
      <a href="http://www.nesbitt.ca/">our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netgraft" category="namerica">
    <name>Netgraft Corp.</name>
    <url>http://netgraft.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netgraft Corp. is a technology consulting firm that specializes in
      open source technologies like Linux, FreeBSD, MySQL, Apache,
      Sendmail, BIND, etc. We're New York City based and can provide
      on-site support and customized business solutions based on these
      technologies.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netizen" category="australia">
    <name>Netizen</name>
    <url>http://netizen.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Netizen, based in Melbourne, Australia, provide Internet and Open
      Source consultancy services, including FreeBSD installation,
      configuration, support contracts, applications development,
      E-Commerce solutions, etc. See <a
      href="http://netizen.com.au/">http://netizen.com.au/</a> or email <a
      href="mailto:info@netizen.com.au">info@netizen.com.au</a> for more
      information.</description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NixSys" category="europe">
    <name>NixSys BVBA</name>
    <url>http://www.nixsys.be/</url>
    <description>
      NixSys specializes in the development, maintenance and deployment
      of Free and Open Source Software on any scale.  Remote and on-site
      systems administration, particularly in the areas of mail and dns,
      are also available.  <a href="mailto:philip@nixsys.be">Contact us</a>
      for more information and rates.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OmarSiddique" category="namerica">
    <name>Omar Siddique</name>
    <url>http://www.heedme.com/resume</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://www.heedme.com">Omar Siddique</a> is a Washington,
      D.C.  based consultant with broad experience in FreeBSD, Linux,
      Solaris.  His specialties include internet services, systems
      integration, system administration, and networking.  Contact him
      via <a href="mailto:omar@heedme.com">omar@heedme.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Omniscient" category="namerica">
    <name>Omniscient Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.omniscient.com/</url>
    <description>
      Omniscient Technologies is a Washington D.C. based consulting group
      with a broad array of experience in *BSD, Solaris, Linux and many
      other varieties of UNIX specializing in highly scalable systems,
      systems integration and network security. Custom application design
      also available. Contact via <a
      href="mailto:info@omniscient.com">info@omniscient.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenAssociates" category="namerica">
    <name>Open Source Associates, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.OpenSourceAssociates.com/</url>
    <description>
      Open Source Associates LLC is a St. Louis, Missouri based consulting
      firm specializing in the support of all things Open Source related
      with strong emphasis on FreeBSD, MySQL, Sendmail, BIND, and Apache.
      Open Source's highly skilled consultants are available for telephone
      support as well as support contracts and onsite consulting
      engagements anywhere in the United States. We have particular
      expertise in the design, implementation, and support of highly
      available clustered websites. We specialize in remote administration
      and management to keep complex systems running reliably. For more
      information email us at <a href="mailto:info@opensourceassociates.com"
      >info@opensourceassociates.com</a> or call toll-free 866-343-2589.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenSOS" category="asia">
    <name>OpenSOS SB</name>
    <url>http://www.opensos.net/</url>
    <description>
      OpenSOS SB is a company which provides consulting and professional
      services for FreeBSD based solutions based in Kuala Lumpur,
      Malaysia.  We also provide maintenance and support services
      in Malaysia.  We can operate at short notice in any region in
      Asia for a truly professional quick-to-service operational
      capability.  However we are willing to consider projects outside
      Malaysia.  We are specialized in FreeBSD, MacOSX and basically
      in all kinds of UNIX systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenWorld" category="namerica">
    <name>OpenWorld</name>
    <url>http://www.stdio.com/</url>
    <description>
      OpenWorld has been providing computer, network, and security
      consulting since 1994. Our clients? range from Fortune 500 companies
      to regional small businesses. Our engineers each have at least 10
      years of experience in Unix systems and networks. We provide full
      service consulting, implementation, installation, security, and
      support for FreeBSD, SUN Solaris, SCO Unixware, SCO OpenServer, SGI
      Irix, IBM AIX, Compaq Digital Unix, and Cisco IOS. Please email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@stdio.com">info@stdio.com</a> or call us at
      606-514-1800 for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Puryear" category="namerica">
    <name>Puryear Information Technology, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.puryear-it.com</url>
    <description>
      Puryear Information Technology, LLC provides open source application
      support, integration services, and technology management expertise to
      the Southeastern United States. Our company plays a pivotal role in
      the design and deployment of open source solutions--we have worked
      with companies to design and manage FreeBSD and Linux web farms;
      deployed open source-based clustering software to ensure high
      availability of critical network services; performed critical
      performance tuning and software integration for a popular spam filter
      appliance; and integrated Samba into Internet-accessible, VPN-based
      file services. Phone: +1-225-343-3056.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Pendulosoftware" category="samerica">
    <name>Pendulo Software</name>
    <url>http://www.pendulosoftware.com.ve</url>
    <description>
      Based in Caracas, Venezuela, Pendulo Software provides and
      specializes in support and consulting for FreeBSD and Linux
      solutions.  We offer onsite as well as offsite support, web
      development, design (2D and 3D), Multimedia, VPNs implementation,
      Virtualization, VoIP, high performance servers, Firewalls, custom
      application programming and many others services.  Our experience
      covers the most important branches of current IT industry, from
      routine of server management, security audits and updates, to high
      performance computing and mitigating attacks.  For more information
      about our services, please visit our multilanguage <a
      href="http://www.pendulosoftware.com.ve">website</a>, send an
      email to <a
      href="mailto:atencioncliente@pendulosoftware.com.ve">atencioncliente@pendulosoftware.com.ve</a>
      or <a
      href="mailto:infocorp@pendulosoftware.com.ve">infocorp@pendulosoftware.com.ve</a>
      or call us under +58 (212) 637-1074, +1 (407) 536-9895, or
      +1 (253) 642-6484.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PeterDufault" category="namerica">
    <name>Peter Dufault</name>
    <url>mailto:dufault@hda.com</url>
    <description>
      Peter Dufault, of HD Associates. Peter has over 15 years experience
      in medical device control, high performance simulation systems,
      digital closed-loop feedback systems, realtime UNIX-like systems, and
      UNIX device drivers. For more information, please send email to <a
      href= "mailto:dufault@hda.com">dufault@hda.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PHBSolutions" category="europe">
    <name>PHB Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.phbsolutions.com</url>
    <description>
      PHB Solutions, based in Belgium, provides *BSD installation,
      maintenance, support and consulting services (file servers, web
      servers, mail servers, database servers, routers). For more
      information, please contact <a
      href="mailto:philippe.bresoux@phbsolutions.com">philippe.bresoux@phbs
      olutions.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PhilBudne" category="namerica">
    <name>Phil Budne</name>
    <url>http://www.ultimate.com/phil/resume.html</url>
    <description>
      Phil Budne is a Boston area consultant who has worked professionally
      with BSD and other Unix systems since 1985. Services include
      development and porting of kernel extensions, device drivers, network
      protocol implementation, and applications, as well as network and
      system administration. For more information contact <a href=
      "mailto:phil+fbsd@ultimate.com">phil+fbsd@ultimate.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PineInternet" category="europe">
    <name>Pine Internet</name>
    <url>http://www.pine.nl/</url>
    <description>
      Pine Internet implements LAN, WAN and remote access solutions, offers
      Unix support and administration contracts and advises ISP's and other
      corporate customers concerning their network and server setup. Pine
      specializes in <a href="http://security.pine.nl/">Internet
      security</a>, performs security auditing services on demand, and
      offers firewall solutions based on FreeBSD. Other products we offer
      are webhosting, facility management and leased lines. Among the
      products we use are FreeBSD, Cisco routers, PHP, Apache, Perl,
      Solaris and MySQL. Pine has 8+ years of Unix and Internet experience.
      We feature some of the largest ISP's in the Netherlands as our
      customers. For more information, please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@pine.nl">info@pine.nl</a> or visit our website at
      <a href="http://www.pine.nl/">www.pine.nl</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PoulHenningKamp" category="europe">
    <name>Poul-Henning Kamp</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsd.org/~phk/</url>
    <description>
      Poul-Henning Kamp has over 12 years of experience in UNIX &amp; Networks,
      and is a former FreeBSD Core Team member. Poul developed <em>phkmalloc</em>,
      <em>tcl_nm</em>, <em>tcl_db</em>, <em>tcl_snmp</em> and more, and was
      the Release Engineer for several FreeBSD releases. Poul resides in
      Denmark, and can be reached via email at <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">phk@FreeBSD.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="psychsoftek" category="namerica">
    <name>Psychsoft Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.psychsoftek.com</url>
    <description>
      Psychsoft Consulting is an Industry recognized leading technology
      consulting firm based in Quincy, Massachusetts founded in 1987 with a
      highly educated, trained and experienced staff to help in all your IT
      needs. Psychsoft, Inc. personnel hold advanced degrees in various
      fields and have years of experience in IT implementation,
      troubleshooting, design and configuration. Areas of expertise include:
      Linux, Microsoft Windows, UNIX (including FreeBSD), TCP/IP, LAN, WAN,
      VPN, Network security, WIFI security, WIFI design, Database design,
      SQL, Web site design, Server design, System integration, Network
      printing and DSL/Broadband/T1 Internet access.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Questwork" category="asia">
    <name>Questwork Consulting Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.questwork.com/</url>
    <description>
      Questwork Consulting Limited is based in Hong Kong.  We provide
      consulting, web application development, hosting &amp; maintenance
      services on FreeBSD to our clients for more than 5 years.  For
      more information, please contact us by email at
      <a href="mailto:freebsd@questwork.com">freebsd@questwork.com</a>
      or visit our <a href="http://www.questwork.com/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RandDAssociates" category="europe">
    <name>R and D Associates, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.RnDAssociates.com/</url>
    <description>
      R &amp; D Associates, Inc. developed ServeTheWeb.com utilizing
      FreeBSD running Apache.  We employed consulting services from <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">Poul-Henning Kamp</a> to develop our
      Virtual Server solution (which is available in <a
      href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD</a> 4.0 and higher).
      R &amp; D Associates, Inc. is an application development firm
      specializing in client/server application development.  We use FreeBSD
      running Apache and utilizing PHP and MySQL (As well as NT with ASP and
      SQL/Access).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Secnetix" category="europe">
    <name>Secnetix GmbH and Co KG</name>
    <url>http://www.secnetix.de/</url>
    <description>
      Secnetix GmbH &amp; Co KG -- located in Munich, Germany -- has a
      strong focus on BSD systems and offers professional consulting
      services, ranging from basic administration, programming and
      security-related tasks to sophisticated projects involving design,
      implementation and maintenance of complex network setups. For more
      information, please <a href="http://www.secnetix.de/">visit our web
      site</a> or send a message to <a
      href="mailto:info@secnetix.de">info@secnetix.de</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SouthernGazer" category="australia">
    <name>Southern Gazer</name>
    <url>http://www.southerngazer.com</url>
    <description>
      Southern Gazer is a consulting company with 20 years PC technical
      support experience based in Sydney's idyllic Sutherland Shire. Our
      focus is helping businesses get their computers working right while
      spending as little as possible on IT. We're passionate supporters of
      Open Source products and can help the average business save money and
      gain reliability by using systems such as FreeBSD on their file
      servers, print servers, e-mail systems plus lots more. We also supply
      a complete range of Linux and BSD CD's at ultra low prices. Please
      drop by our <a href="http://www.southerngazer.com">website</a>, email
      us at <a
      href="mailto:info@southerngazer.com">info@southerngazer.com</a>, or
      call us on 02 9532 1217 to have a chat.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SteubenTech" category="namerica">
    <name>Steuben Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.steubentech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Steuben Technologies is a consulting company offering support,
      administration, custom software development, legacy systems
      support and solutions tailored to your unique business model on
      a wide range of platforms including FreeBSD, NetBSD and most
      commercial UNIX platforms and much more.  Please see our website
      or call us at (607)661-4431.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Synetec" category="europe">
    <name>Synetec</name>
    <url>http://www.synetec.pl/</url>
    <description>
      Synetec is an IT company located in Poland.  We are experienced in
      the installation and administration of &os;, Linux and Windows
      Server systems.  For more informations visit <a
	href="http://www.synetec.pl/">our website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Syntonet" category="europe">
    <name>Syntonet Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.syntonet.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      Syntonet Ltd is UK based provider of Consultancy and Custom
      Development Services. Principal consultant <a
      href="mailto:rob@syntonet.co.uk">Rob Pickering</a> has over 10 years
      system software development experience on BSD based platforms. Areas
      of expertise include firewall and networking system setup, custom
      development in C and C++, and supply of turnkey solutions. For
      further information, contact us by email at <a
      href="mailto:info@syntonet.co.uk">info@syntonet.co.uk</a>, call
      +44.870.166.4400 (Voice) or +44.870.166.4411 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SysCare" category="europe">
    <name>SysCare s. r. o.</name>
    <url>http://www.SysCare.sk/</url>
    <description>
      SysCare s. r. o. is a company based in Slovakia with the aim to
      provide highly professional solutions, including consultancy and
      outsourcing services for reasonable amount of money.  Our focus
      is on high-availability and high-performance solutions for web,
      database, DNS and email products built on &os;.  SysCare s. r. o.
      has been founded by Daniel Gerzo, who is being part of the official
      &os; development team.  For inquiries please send us an email to
      <a href="office@syscare.sk">office@syscare.sk</a>, or visit our
      <a href="http://www.SysCare.sk/">web site</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TecVD" category="europe">
    <name>TecVD</name>
    <url>http://www.tecvd.com/</url>
    <description>
      TecVD is located in Barcelona, Spain.  We are a company focused
      in system security and open source implementations (GNU/Linux,
      FreeBSD and OpenBSD) in heterogeneous infrastructure.  We also
      have security appliances, Tseg series, and network services
      appliances like Tcor series.  We can provide you with a complete
      enterprise solution tailored to your needs.  See our website or
      email us at <a href="mailto:tecvd@tecvd.com">tecvd@tecvd.com</a>
      for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TundraWare" category="namerica">
    <name>TundraWare Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tundraware.com/</url>
    <description>
      TundraWare Inc. provides FreeBSD related consultancy in all contexts,
      from Embedded to large Transaction Processing systems. We have
      extensive International experience and can provide services in
      network design, systems architecture, development, deployment and
      operations. Contact us via telephone on 847/827-1706, via email to <a
      href="mailto:info@tundraware.com"> info@tundraware.com</a> or write
      to us at TundraWare Inc., 817 Fairmont Court, Des Plaines, IL 60018,
      USA.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="UnixPorting" category="namerica">
    <name>UnixPorting</name>
    <url>http://www.UnixPorting.com/</url>
    <description>
      UnixPorting.com specializes in the porting of existing software to
      new operating systems or hardware. In addition to porting, we
      specialize in C and Perl programming, Unix system administration and
      security, and open source
      technologies (FreeBSD, Perl, Apache,
      mod_perl, MySQL, etc.). For more information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.UnixPorting.com/">our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AspenWorks" category="namerica">
    <name>AspenWorks, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.aspenworks.com/</url>
    <description>
      AspenWorks is an Aspen, Colorado based consulting company with offices
      in Portland, OR.  We specialize in network applications, and
      Wireless Broadband management for ISPs and WISPs.  AspenWorks has been
      in business since 1986.  Telephone:  970-925-3355
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Wave2" category="europe">
    <name>Wave2 Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.wave2.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      Wave2 Limited is an Open Source consultancy, based in the UK,
      providing custom solutions with an emphasis on FreeBSD.  Services
      include software development (Java, Perl, Python, VB),
      Heterogeneous Network / System Administration (FreeBSD, Linux,
      OSX, Solaris and Windows).  If you are looking for an Open Source
      solution, please contact me at <a href="mailto:info@wave2.org">
	info@wave2.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WilliamRichard" category="namerica">
    <name>William Richard &amp; Associates</name>
    <url>http://www.tdl.com/~wdr/consulting.html</url>
    <description>
      William Richard &amp; Associates offers FreeBSD, Internet, and e-commerce
      consulting, implementation, and support options for clients
      throughout the San Francisco Bay Area. Visit our website or <a
      href="mailto:wdr@tdl.com">e-mail us</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WorkgroupTechnology" category="namerica">
    <name>Workgroup Technology Partners, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.wgtech.com</url>
    <description>
      Workgroup Technology Partners, Inc.We sell and support Unix systems
      including Solaris, HP/UX, AIX, Linux and FreeBSD. For comments refer
      to <a href="http://www.wgtech.com">our site</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SecurityAudit" category="africa">
    <name>Security Audit and Control Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.sacs.co.za/</url>
    <description>
      Security Audit and Control Solutions (SACS) provides information
      security consultation and IT auditing services and offers
      professional FreeBSD support. SACS has developed a complete range of
      Technological Risk Management solutions using FreeBSD as an anchor
      for data analysis. Firewalls deployed using FreeBSD makes a cost
      effective solution in any organization and SACS can implement a
      secure FreeBSD firewall with caching engines, Network Address
      Translation (NAT) and proxies. For additional information please
      contact <a href="mailto:pearcem@sacs.co.za">Mervin Pearce</a> or
      visit <a href="http://www.sacs.co.za">http://www.sacs.co.za</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EDILtd" category="namerica">
    <name>EDI Ltd Consulting Engineers</name>
    <url>http://www.ediltd.com</url>
    <description>
      EDI Ltd Consulting Engineers. We provide consulting services for
      FreeBSD as well as local and wide area network design. Our
      diversified staff allows us to help you in all the areas your project
      requires, from cabling to encryption, network security audits,
      network design and network health studies. We have successfully
      completed several FreeBSD installations for mission critical
      operations, using it as a firewall, web server or mail server. If you
      would like to discuss your project with us, please contact us as
      (770) 956-7000, or <a
      href="mailto:info@ediltd.com">info@ediltd.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WhiteQueueConsulting" category="nzealand">
    <name>White Queue Consulting</name>
    <url>http://whitequeue.com/</url>
    <description>
      White Queue Consulting provides embedded FreeBSD kernel and
      userland development.  Our services include device driver
      development, kernel porting, software design and development in
      the kernel and userland.  We are able to work with clients in any
      location.  For further information contact us through our <a
      href="http://whitequeue.com/contact/">contact form</a> or visit
      the <a href="http://whitequeue.com/">White Queue website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="CrepidoSystems" category="europe">
    <name>Crepido Systems AB</name>
    <url>http://www.crepido.com</url>
    <description>
      Crepido Systems AB provides services for custom software development
      and system design under BSD and other Unixes. We have 10+ years
      experience in Unix programming and system design using Unix as
      building block.
	  Crepido System AB operates mainly in Sweden but
      requests outside Sweden are welcome.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MarkTinguely" category="namerica">
    <name>Mark Tinguely</name>
    <url>http://www.cs.ndsu.NoDak.edu/~tinguely/</url>
    <description>
      Mark Tinguely has provided Network and Unix solutions for over ten
      years. These solutions include work with Unix kernels and Unix
      applications, TCP/IP applications, Local Area Network protocol
      debugging, and BSD device drivers. Mark has authored BSD device
      drivers for 3 video capture boards, an Asynchronous Transfer Mode
      (ATM) network card, and a Watchdog card.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ITworksConsulting" category="australia">
    <name>ITworks Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.itworks.com.au</url>
    <description>
      ITworks Consulting is a privately owned information technology
      consultancy, situated in the central business district of
      Melbourne, Australia. The business consists of a specialized team
      of consultants who aim to provide information technology solutions
      to meet the needs of the business community. We provide a range of
      FreeBSD based web hosting, web database development and e-commerce
      services as well as professional FreeBSD consulting services and
      support contracts. For more information please visit our <a
      href="http://www.itworks.com.au">web site</a> or contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@itworks.com.au">info@itworks.com.au</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Raditex" category="europe">
    <name>Raditex AB</name>
    <url>http://raditex.nu/</url>
    <description>
      Raditex AB are a firm of consultants and also do education in Unix.
      We have long experience with all kinds of Unix systems not only
      FreeBSD or Linux. For more information phone us at +46 19 4501015
      or give us an email at <a
      href="mailto:gorhas@raditex.nu">gorhas@raditex.nu</a> or <a
      href="http://raditex.nu/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Mike_Meyer" category="namerica">
    <name>Mike_Meyer</name>
    <url>http://www.mired.org/home/mwm/</url>
    <description>
      Mike Meyer of Meyer Consulting has been providing Unix-based
      solutions since 1976, and web-based applications since 1992. These
      solutions range from chemical systems modeling to device drivers, and
      the web applications have ranged from community-building applications
      to web based software release systems. For more information, please
      contact <a href="mailto:mwm@mired.org">mwm@mired.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TheLinuxBox" category="namerica">
    <name>The Linux Box</name>
    <url>http://www.linuxbox.nu/</url>
    <description>
      The Linux Box, located in Ann Arbor, Michigan, provides consulting
      and training services for open source operating systems and products,
      including FreeBSD and Linux. For more information, contact <a
      href="mailto:info@linuxbox.nu">info@linuxbox.nu</a> or view our
      website at <a href="http://www.linuxbox.nu">www.linuxbox.nu</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LANCO" category="asia">
    <name>LANCO Global Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.lancoglobal.com/</url>
    <description>
      LANCO Global Systems (LGSL), based in India, Hyderabad, with offices
      in USA and UK, provides and specializes in <i>Application
      Development, Shell Scripting, PHP, C, C++ and Perl Programming,
      Networking Solutions, Unix device driver development, Web page
      Designing and Hosting, Web Server Solutions and configurations, ISP
      Services especially on Linux, FreeBSD and Solaris</i>. For more
      information, please email us at <a
      href="mailto:services@lancoglobal.com">services@lancoglobal.com</a>
      or call us at 0091-9849043975 or FAX us at 0091-040-3755413.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NS3G" category="namerica">
    <name>NS3G.COM</name>
    <url>http://www.ns3g.com/</url>
    <description>
      NS3G.COM, based out of Toronto, Ontario, Canada, offers a variety of
      services and products. We specialize in products that run under
      FreeBSD and other *NIX systems but also support other platforms.
      Solutions for firewalls, LAN's, WAN'S and web presence are just a few
      that we offer. Please visit us at <a
      href="http://www.ns3g.com/">www.ns3g.com</a> or contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@ns3g.com">info@ns3g.com</a> for more information or
      to get a quote.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Linast" category="europe">
    <name>Linast-Systemtechnik GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.linast.de</url>
    <description>
      Linast-Systemtechnik GmbH is located in Sankt Augustin, Germany (near
      Bonn/Cologne) and provides consulting, support and training for
      FreeBSD, Linux, MacOS X and other Unix Systems. For more information,
      please call +49.2241.209467, e-mail us at <a
      href="mailto:info@linast.de">info@linast.de</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.linast.de/">website</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Cybersource" category="australia">
    <name>Cybersource Pty. Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.cyber.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Cybersource is Australia's leading IT Professional Services Company
      in the areas of Unix/FreeBSD/Linux, TCP/IP Datanetworking and Open
      Platform application development using these technologies. With
      around 40 staff, are based in Melbourne and have been successfully
      providing IT Professional Services for 10 years.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NationalInformatics" category="namerica">
    <name>National Informatics Company</name>
    <url>http://www.nationalinformatics.com</url>
    <description>
      National Informatics Company provides research and development
      services for information technology. We work with FreeBSD to support
      or manage research projects for high performance computing,
      bioinformatics, enterprise software technologies and artificial
      intelligence. We also help companies make the transition from
      proprietary software products to Open Source products. Our phone
      number is (425) 740-0139.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Bilch" category="europe">
    <name>Bilch International Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.bilch.com/</url>
    <description>
      Bilch International Consulting, Hamburg is based in Germany. We are
      building fire walled servers and connect them to your ISDN, POTS, ATM
      or E1/T1 Line. BILCH Com is an ASP and application software
      developer. Please mail us at <a
      href="mailto:info@bilch.com">info@bilch.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ParcProductions" category="europe">
    <name>Parc Productions</name>
    <url>http://www.parcproductions.com/</url>
    <description>
      Parc Productions. Located in the Netherlands. Started in 1997. We
      deliver professional system engineering services for FreeBSD, OpenBSD
      and MacOS X. Our services include 24/7 support, consultancy,
      maintenance of both hardware and software, assembly and installation
      of hardware, remote and on-site support, development of scripts and
      software for the machines we maintain etcetera. Of course we deliver
      hosting facilities and space for your servers at low costs as well.
      Visit our websites at <a
      href="http://www.parcproductions.com/">www.parcproductions.com</a> or
      <a href="http://www.bsdengineering.com/">www.bsdengineering.com</a>.
      Please contact us by <a
      href="mailto:info@parcproductions.com">email</a> or by telephone:
      +31-204892456.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Worria" category="asia">
    <name>Worria Affordable Web Hosting</name>
    <url>http://worria.com/en/hosting.shtml</url>
    <description>
      Worria Affordable Web Hosting is a privately owned company in Hong
      Kong. We offer FreeBSD web hosting related consulting services, such
      as server administration and website management. For more details,
      please email <a href="mailto:sales@worria.com">our sales team</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ZYTRAX" category="namerica">
    <name>ZYTRAX, Inc</name>
    <url>http://www.zytrax.com/</url>
    <description>
      Zytrax, Inc. is based in Montreal, Canada and provides consulting,
      development, implementation, hosting and maintenance services
      specialising in the BSD platforms. Our skill base includes Apache,
      PHP, Ruby, DNS, Mail, LDAP, Samba, PostgeSQL/MySQL and embedded
      systems. Please email us at <a
      href="MAILTO:consulting@zytrax.com">consulting@zytrax.com</a>. We can
      be reached via telephone at +1.514.285.9088.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenTrend" category="namerica">
    <name>OpenTrend Solutions Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.opentrend.net</url>
    <description>
      OpenTrend Solutions Ltd provides consulting and facilities management
      services through Canada. We specialize in supporting FreeBSD, NetBSD,
      OpenBSD and Linux, and have specialist skills in system
      administration, security and network design &amp; management. We donate
      2% of gross profits to the support of open source software and have
      partnered with organisations in the United States and Australia to
      better support multi-national clients.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DaemonizedNetworking" category="namerica">
    <name>Daemonized Networking Services</name>
    <url>http://www.daemonized.com</url>
    <description>
      Daemonized Networking Services. Our staff have been supporting
      software and hardware development, brokerages, banks, hospitals,
      publishers, e-commerce, legal and medical research,
      telecommunications, and other environments since 1986, in the San
      Francisco Bay Area and Northern California. We build industrial
      strength web servers, running the latest release of Apache, OpenSSH,
      and OpenSSL, with all source, and firewall, based on FreeBSD, in less
      than one hour.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Linux4biz" category="asia">
    <name>Linux4biz</name>
    <url>http://www.linux4biz.net/</url>
    <description>
      Linux4biz is an independent provider of comprehensive Internet
      solutions, specialising in the Solaris, LINUX, FreeBSD, OpenBSD,
      NetBSD operating systems and Open Source Software. Linux4biz
      Consultants are able to advise on all aspects of implementing and
      administrating Unix/Linux servers, SAMBA solutions, E-mail servers,
      Mailing list servers, Web servers, DNS, Internet Security, Security
      Audits, Intrusion detection, Stress testing, Intranet setup, High
      Availability server solutions, Network solutions, Remote
      administration solutions. We also provide onsite as well as offsite
      support and consultancy. For more information about our services,
      please visit our website.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="INFOMATIK" category="samerica">
    <name>INFOMATIK</name>
    <url>http://info.matik.com.br</url>
    <description>
      INFOMATIK Tecnologia e Desenvolvimento - Brazilian Company is
      offering total site support for FreeBSD Servers. We have high
      performance solutions for Intranet and Internet. We are specialized
      in UNIX systems since 92. Please visit our Interactive Website or
      contact us per e-mail: <a
      href="mailto:info@matik.com.br">info@matik.com.br</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LOGIOS" category="europe">
    <name>LOGIOS</name>
    <url>http://www.logios.cz/</url>
    <description>
      LOGIOS NETWORK SYSTEMS, located in the Czech Republic, provides
      system maintenance, consulting and other services on various
      platforms, including FreeBSD and Linux. We also offer information
      security services, firewalls and IDS systems, system integration,
      software applications etc.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Xetpoint" category="europe">
    <name>Xetpoint</name>
    <url>http://www.xetpoint.fi/</url>
    <description>
      Xetpoint Oy is located in Pirkkala, Finland. We offer professional
      FreeBSD support, consulting, programming, maintenance and monitoring
      services. For more information, please visit our website.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RackmountNet" category="namerica">
    <name>RackmountNet</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmountnet.com</url>
    <description>
      RackmountNet is a One-stop shop for rackmount Linux, FreeBSD systems.
      Our products include Rackmount chassis, server rack cabinet,
      Rackmount LCD Monitor, and related accessories. For more information,
      contact <a
      href="mailto:sales@rackmountnet.com">sales@rackmountnet.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="siliconlandmark" category="namerica">
    <name>Silicon Landmark LLC</name>
    <url>http://siliconlandmark.com/</url>
    <description>
      Silicon Landmark's mission is to supply our customers with
      fully customized, scalable, turn-key Information Technology
      solutions at competitive prices. We specialize in designing
      package products that will meet and your business' needs
      and budget.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pythonbyte" category="namerica">
    <name>Python Byte Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.pythonbyte.com/</url>
    <description>
      Python Byte Solutions is an independent IT
      consulting company based in Southwestern Ontario, Canada.
      We provide services pertaining to software
      &amp; web development, hosting, support, installation,
      and training. We specialize in Python, Zope, Apache,
      MySQL, *BSD, and Linux. You can
      check out our web site or contact us directly at <a
      href='mailto:info@pythonbyte.com'>info@pythonbyte.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oscillation" category="europe">
    <name>os-cillation</name>
    <url>http://www.os-cillation.de</url>
    <description>
      os-cillation, located in Siegen/NRW, Germany.
      We offer a broad range in BSD-based software-development
      (C/C++/Java/HTML/PHP/Perl/SQL). Installation and
      support of FreeBSD based mail, web, firewall, database,
      news, dns and ftp servers. FreeBSD and Windows desktop
      integration. Also experienced with NetBSD, Solaris and Linux.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ForgottenTechnologies" category="asia">
    <name>Forgotten Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.forgotten.com.sg</url>
    <description>
      Forgotten Technologies, http://www.forgotten.com.sg
      is a Singapore-based company providing open source business
      solutions that include, but not limited to platforms such as
      Linux, FreeBSD and OpenBSD. Please email us at
      enquiries@forgotten.com.sg to find out more how we can help
      you in your business!
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WirewalkTechnologies" category="namerica">
    <name>Wirewalk Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.wirewalk.com/</url>
    <description>
      Wirewalk Technologies is a NYC based consulting company, with
      offices in London, Moscow and Rome. We provide consulting solutions
      for: FreeBSD, OpenBSD, Linux, Solaris, HPUX, AIX and Irix.
      Programming solutions in: C, C++, Java, Perl, Oracle, MySQl etc.
      Contact us: <a
      href="mailto:sales@wirewalk.com">sales at wirewalk.com</a>,
      646-827-9397.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="tunix" category="europe">
    <name>Tunix</name>
    <url>http://www.tunix.nl/</url>
    <description>
      For more than 10 years TUNIX - the only Dutch firewall
      developer - brings you a unique combination of
      security-services: high-level training on
      Internet-technology and tailor-made security solutions.
      TUNIX Security offers an end-to-end solution with a full
      range of services such as consultancy for developing a
      security-policy and design of a security-architecture,
      project-management, turn-key implementation of
      firewall-appliances, multi-level support and 24x7 management
      and monitoring. The security solutions are build on the TUNIX
      Firewall, a modular, FreeBSD based proxy-level firewall.
      For more information, please contact sales@tunix.nl
      or visit our website at www.firewall.nl.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="improware" category="europe">
    <name>ImproWare AG</name>
    <url>http://www.imp.ch/</url>
    <description>
      ImproWare AG focuses on Internet and Networking Services
      as well as System Integration and Consulting based on
      FreeBSD.
      We offer contract programming in all major programming languages
      with a focus on FreeBSD, userland and kernel.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="netmaniacs" category="europe">
    <name>NetManiacs</name>
    <url>http://www.netmaniacs.nl/</url>
    <description>
      NetManiacs is a dutch company based in Eindhoven.
      We provide consulting, (system administration) support,
      custom software and a broad range of (internet/business)
      server solutions.  For more information visit
      <a href="http://www.netmaniacs.nl">www.netmaniacs.nl</a>
      or contact us at <a href="mailto:info@netmaniacs.nl">
	info@netmaniacs.nl</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ArtisanComputerServicesLLC" category="namerica">
    <name>Artisan Computer Services LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.artisancomputer.com/</url>
    <description>
      Artisan Computer Services LLC is based in Tucson, Arizona.
      We provide system administration and configuration for web,
      mail, DNS, database, and streaming video servers using FreeBSD.
      We also do computer consulting on a variety of platforms
      (Mac OS X, Windows, *BSD, Linux), with an emphasis on integration
      and security.  You can reach us at
      <a href="mailto:info@artisancomputer.com">info@artisancomputer.com</a>,
      or our website,
      <a href="http://www.artisancomputer.com">www.artisancomputer.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BrainAllianceSolutions" category="europe">
    <name>Brain Alliance Solutions Oy / Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.brainalliance.com/</url>
    <description>
      Brain Alliance Solutions Oy / Ltd is located in Espoo, Finland.
      We offer professional FreeBSD installation, support, consulting
      and server solutions.  For more information, please visit our
      website at <a href="http://www.brainalliance.com">
        http://www.brainalliance.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TegtmeierInternetSolutions" category="europe">
    <name>Tegtmeier Internet Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.tegtmeier.de/</url>
    <description>
      Tegtmeier Internet Solutions is located in Hamburg / Germany.  We offer
      consulting, professional support and maintenance for *BSD and Linux systems
      and are developing individual solutions in C/Perl/PHP/SQL/HTML/shell, based
      on open source products.  We are focused on internet security, high
      availability and performance/optimization.  Visit our website at
      <a href="http://www.tegtmeier.de">http://www.tegtmeier.de</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenSourcery" category="europe">
    <name>Open Sourcery</name>
    <url>http://www.opensourcery.co.uk</url>
    <description>
      Open Sourcery is a UK based company providing support and consultancy
      for Free and Open Source Software.  We have <a
      href="http://www.opensourcery.co.uk/open-sourcery/our-experience/"
      title="Open Source support">experience</a> with a wide variety of
      Open Source software.  You can find out more and contact us at our
      <a href="http://www.opensourcery.co.uk"
      title="Open Source support">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Oxalide" category="europe">
    <name>Oxalide</name>
    <url>http://www.oxalide.com/</url>
    <description>
      Oxalide is a consultancy firm and solution provider.  Our fields of
      expertise include UNIX software system deployment such as secure mail
      systems (SMTP, POP, IMAP), advanced Web server configurations,
      high-availability firewalling, etc.  Our knowledge of FreeBSD, *BSD,
      Commercial Unix and Linux is thorough.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TechneticsConsultingPtyLtd" category="australia">
    <name>Technetics Consulting Pty. Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.technetics.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Technetics is located in Melbourne Australia.  We provide prompt IT services
      &amp; support, system maintenance, hard drive recovery services, consulting and
      other services on various platforms including FreeBSD, Linux and Unix.  We
      offer on site support within Melbourne Australia and world wide via remote
      login.  We also offer expert data recovery services for Unix based platforms.
      Call anytime ph. +61 3 9663 1899 or email us at <a
	href="mailto:info@technetics.com.au">info@technetics.com.au</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EnvescentLCC" category="namerica">
    <name>Envescent, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.envescent.com/</url>
    <description>
      Envescent is a leading provider of technology products and services
      focused on FreeBSD.  We offer consulting, pre-installed workstations
      and servers, compatible hardware, outsourced system and network
      administration and implementation, security auditing, technical support
      and much more.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="openMindShare" category="namerica">
    <name>openMindShare</name>
    <url>http://www.openmindshare.com/</url>
    <description>
      openMindShare draws on over a decade of expertise in diverse
      information technology fields.  We handle information technology
      infrastructure needs and we do it with FreeBSD.  We offer a myriad
      of services and solutions.  See our
      <a href="http://www.openmindshare.com/">web site</a> or
      <a href="mailto:info@openmindshare.com">e-mail</a>
      (info@openmindshare.com) for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RBJ-Consultants" category="europe">
    <name>RBJ-Consultants</name>
    <url></url>
    <description>
      Unix since 1990. Remote installation (Europe-webhosting,
      Brasil, USA) and local. We train, install, configure and
      admin FreeBSD, Linux (RedHat, Suse, Gentoo, Mandrake), Solaris.
      Inside network - MacOSX, Windows, etc (we support too).
      Contact: <a href="mailto:rbj@madeira.dyndns.org">Rui Bento</a>
      &lt;rbj@madeira.dyndns.org&gt;
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TechniSoft" category="africa">
    <name>TechniSoft</name>
    <url>http://www.technisoft.sn/</url>
    <description>
      Located in the Senegal (west Africa).  Started in 2001.  We deliver
      professional system engineering services for FreeBSD, OpenBSD and   
      Windows.  Our services include 24/7 support, consultancy, maintenance
      of both hardware and software, assembly and installation of hardware,
      remote and on-site support, development of scripts and software for
      the machines we maintain etc.  Of course we deliver hosting facilities
      and space for your servers at low costs as well.  Visit our websites at
      <a href="http://www.technisoft.sn/">http://www.technisoft.sn</a>.
      Please contact us by <a href="mailto:info@technisoft.sn">email</a>
      &lt;info@technisoft.sn&gt; or by telephone: +221 - 8559900.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sirius" category="europe">
    <name>Sirius</name>
    <url>http://www.siriusit.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      Sirius leads in the deployment, support and training of Open Source
      technology, including FreeBSD.  We support organisations across
      Europe in their pursuit of innovative, versatile and robust technology
      solutions without the financial burden of software licensing.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sectec" category="europe">
    <name>Sectec</name>
    <url>http://www.sectec.pl</url>
    <description>
      *BSD consultancy, installations and configurations.  Worked for
      government institutions as well as for large corporations.
      Intrusion Detection Systems, firewalls, nats, proxies,
      webservers, heavy load mail systems with GUI interface.  Security
      advisor experienced in firewalling.  Training.
      Telephone: +48 888 774 774, email: <a
	href="mailto:admin@bmtcordah.pl">admin@bmtcordah.pl</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sheridan" category="europe">
    <name>Sheridan Computers Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.sheridancomputers.co.uk</url>
    <description>
      We offer IT consulting, systems integration, corporate information
      systems and security solutions based on BSD software.  For more
      information, send us an <a
      href="mailto:info@sheridancomputers.co.uk">email</a> or visit our
      <a href="http://www.sheridancomputers.co.uk">website</a>. We
      operate in the United Kingdom.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="vocal" category="europe">
    <name>S.C. vocalNET S.R.L.</name>
    <url>http://www.vocal.ro</url>
    <description>
      Over 3 years experience with designing, installing  and
      maintaining (support and administration) security solutions
      (firewalls, IDS and VPN's) and voice solutions over *BSD platforms.
      We can secure services like mail, dns, web, ftp making them more
      secure and reliable.  For more information, please phone us at
      +40788401422 or +40217255117, e-mail:
      <a href="mailto:contact@vocal.ro">contact@vocal.ro</a>, or
      <a href="http://www.vocal.ro">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="opensourcexperts" category="europe">
    <name>Opensourcexperts</name>
    <url>http://www.opensourcexperts.com</url>
    <description>
      opensourcexperts.com hosts one the largest (free) directories <a
        href="http://www.opensourcexperts.com/Index/index_html">of
	companies who support Open Source</a>  software world-wide.
      If you provide support for FreeBSD list yourself in their <a
	href="http://www.opensourcexperts.com/Index/index_html/FreeBSD/index.html">
	FreeBSD index</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mseuss" category="europe">
    <name>Mseuss Unternehmensberatung</name>
    <url>http://www.msuess.de</url>
    <description>
      Msuess Unternehmensberatung is a consulting company based in
      Schwandorf (near Regensburg), Germany.  As a consulting / isv
      partner we are developing web-portals (using Python and ZOPE/Plone
      on FreeBSD) and developing individual solutions (Python, Tcl/tk,
      ADA) on FreeBSD.  We also provide ZOPE administration and
      consulting on FreeBSD and other *ix-like systems.  We are the
      main sponsor of the German <a href="http://www.freeunix.de/">
        ix-wiki</a>.  For more information please contact <a
       	href="mailto:freebsd@msuess.de">freebsd@msuess.de</a> or visit
      our <a href="http://www.msuess.de/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ceintec" category="europe">
    <name>Ceintec</name>
    <url>http://www.ceintec.com</url>
    <description>
      Ceintec provides FreeBSD and unix-like operating systems learning
      courses in Spain (Instructor-Led courses).  We also provide
      FreeBSD consulting and technical support for enterprises in Spain.
      For more information visit <a
	href="http://www.ceintec.com/empresas.html">
	http://www.ceintec.com/empresas.html</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="lori-sa" category="samerica">
    <name>Lori Design</name>
    <url>http://www.lori-sa.com</url>
    <description>
      Lori Design, based in San Jose, Costa Rica offers Web
      Development, design, and custom application programming using
      both open source and proprietary environments.  Services also
      include private consulting, emergency response coordination and
      various IT solutions to maximize the effectiveness of your
      business.  Lori Design is a proud w3c member in Costa Rica.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="wbpsystems" category="namerica">
    <name>WBP Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.wbpsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      WBP Systems has a wide range of experience in a number of
      disciplines.  <a href="http://bi.wbpsystems.com">Business
        Intelligence software</a> is created to increase the productivity of your
      business.  We specialize in CRM, ERP and SCM solutions.  Web
      portals and automation of certain business processes are also
      available.  The <a href="http://im.wbpsystems.com">Infrastructure
        Management</a> group is designed to manage, design and create
      integrated solutions for our customer's networks.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="UnitedWare" category="namerica">
    <name>UnitedWare, LLC</name>
    <url>http://united-ware.com/</url>
    <description>
      UnitedWare, LLC is a Cincinnati, Ohio based company that provides
      FreeBSD server setup and custom web and desktop applications.  We
      perform IT audits and solutions to identify and manage the
      information needs of any business.  To contact us visit our
      <a href="http://united-ware.com/">website</a> or give us a call at
      (513) 563-0897.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="Triona" category="europe">
    <name>Triona - Information und Technologie GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.triona.de</url>
    <description>
      Triona - Information und Technologie GmbH offers FreeBSD
      installation and administration services, individual software
      development, web-, application- and database-servers.  The company
      is based in Mainz, Germany.  For more information contact us via
      email <a href="mailto:bsd@triona.de">bsd@triona.de</a> or visit
      our web site.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ActivSupport" category="namerica">
    <name>ActivSupport, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.activsupport.com/</url>
    <description>
      ActivSupport is a network consulting firm located in the San
      Francisco Bay Area specializing in cross-platform environment
      support including FreeBSD.  ActivSupport also provides network
      security, and business continuity consulting.  Whether you are
      looking for a certified consultant or specific technical support
      solutions please contact us at 1-877.228.4863 for immediate
      assistance with your technical needs, or visit our <a
	href="http://www.activsupport.com/">web site</a> for more
      information about services we are providing.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TDI" category="namerica">
    <name>Tetrad Digital Integrity (TDI)</name>
    <url>http://www.tdisecurity.com/</url>
    <description>
      TDI is an information assurance company in the Washington, DC
      area and specializes in providing total security solutions in
      the private and public sectors.  TDI delivers an end-to-end
      solution to security problems occurring in the networks of
      private technology firms, the U.S. government and the military.
      TDI can provide consulting services for all aspects of FreeBSD
      secure enterprise deployment: desktop, server, infrastructure
      (router/firewall), etc.  Our website is at <a
	href="http://www.tdisecurity.com">http://www.tdisecurity.com</a>
      and we can be reached by email at <a
	href="mailto:freebsd@tdisecurity.com">freebsd@tdisecurity.com</a>
      , by phone at 202-337-5600 and by fax at 202-337-5601.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="heritage" category="europe">
    <name>Heritage Network Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.heritagenetworktechnologies.com/</url>
    <description>
      We are a privately owned Technology Consulting Company based in
      Baltimore area.  We provide support for Open Source Operating
      Systems and Software, as well as training for these.  We target
      small to medium enterprises as well as educational institutions.
      We can be reached at 301-807-0784 or by email at <a
	href="mailto:service@eissaf.net">service@eissaf.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="BSDPIE" category="europe">
    <name>BSD Professionals In Europe (BSDPIE)</name>
    <url>http://bsdpie.com/</url>
    <description>
      We are BSD based co-operating consultants offering Consultancy,
      Support, Development, Installation and Internet Services located
      in Munich, Germany.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FalconKnight" category="namerica">
    <name>Falcon Knight, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.falconknight.com/</url>
    <description>
      Falcon Knight, Inc. provides FreeBSD installation, configuration,
      and support from the simple to the advanced.  Falcon Knight
      performs large scale, load-balanced infrastructure planning and
      implementations, complete with application servers and clustered
      databases, all powered by FreeBSD.  If your environment simply has
      to be up 24x7 and you have high usage demands, call Falcon Knight
      now at 877-625-9000 or email <a
	href="mailto:info@falconknight.com">info@falconknight.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="venture37" category="europe">
    <name>Venture 37</name>
    <url>http://www.venture37.com/</url>
    <description>
      Our company provides Mail, Web and DNS hosting solutions based on
      OpenBSD &amp; FreeBSD as well as Technical Support and Management
      (on site or remote) for Microsoft Windows, OS X, Linux and
      BSD-like operating systems.  We also provide services such as
      connectivity &amp; colocation in datacentres at Brighton and
      London.  Check out our <a href="http://www.venture37.com/">
	web site</a> or contact us at <a
	href="mailto:info@venture37.com">info@venture37.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="opensistemas" category="europe">
    <name>Open Sistemas</name>
    <url>http://www.opensistemas.com</url>
    <description>
      We are a spanish company focused on providing business consulting
      and global solutions based on Open Source software and operating
      systems, like FreeBSD and GNU/Linux.  We offer customers and
      partners our high quality services, from integration to low level
      C/C++ developments, 24x7 support, and our own or third-party open
      technologies.  For more information contact us at <a
	href="mailto:info@opensistemas.com">info@opensistemas.com</a>
      , visit our <a href="http://www.opensistemas.com">web site</a> or
      contact us by phone at +34 91 445 39 36.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="ibermachines" category="europe">
    <name>Ibermachines Sistemas</name>
    <url>http://www.ibermachines.com</url>
    <description>
      Ibermachines is a spanish-based company offering open source
      software solutions to  small and medium size organizations.  We
      install, configure and maintain servers and workstations mainly
      running FreeBSD and GNU/Linux.  Also mail, web, intranet, fax,
      file and printing solutions are popular between our customers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="cts" category="europe">
    <name>CTS Consulting and Trade Service</name>
    <url>http://www.ctseuro.com</url>
    <description>
      CTS Consulting &amp; Trade Service is a full service Consultant
      and Supplier for pre-installed FreeBSD Servers.  We ship
      Firewalls, Internet Gateways, Mail Systems with virus protection,
      realtime http scanner, File and Print Servers.  Network planning
      and implementation of WANS with IPSEC tunneling, Samba and
      Hylafax installations.  Founded in 1985 with Unix and Mainframe
      experience since 1978.  We are based in Salzburg and Vienna,
      Austria and have customer references throughout Europe and
      Eastern Europe ranging from 5 to 60000 Users.  We are also
      shipping pre-installed Asterisk Telephone Systems and have best
      the references with it.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="jcr" category="samerica">
    <name>JCR Engenharia de Sistemas</name>
    <url>http://www.jcrengenharia.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      JCR Engenharia has more than 10 years experience in developing
      FreeBSD solutions, like firewalls, Internet Servers, cluster
      solutions and more.  We are located in Salvador, Brazil.
    </description> 
  </entry>

  <entry id="fortuitous" category="namerica">
    <name>Fortuitous Technologies</name>
    <url>http://fortuitous.com</url>
    <description>
      Fortuitous Technologies provides Capacity Planning, Performance
      Tuning, and consulting services for FreeBSD, Linux, and Unix
      systems worldwide. We cover Cluster, Grid, and Multi-tiered
      systems of all types.  Contact Fortuitous <a
	href="http://fortuitous.com/en/contact.html">here</a>  or by
      telephone at (512) 351-7783.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="netfence" category="europe">
    <name>NetFence</name>
    <url>http://www.netfence.it</url>
    <description>
      NetFence deploys and maintains Internet/intranet servers based on
      FreeBSD and other open source software (including Apache web
      server, Squid, Samba, Cyrus IMAP, PostgreSQL, OpenVPN and others).
      Network and client-side hardware/software/support is also offered,
      as well as custom programming and security coverage.  It is
      located in Bologna, Italy and can be reached at <a
	href="mailto:freebsd@netfence.it">freebsd@netfence.it</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="unixconsulting" category="europe">
    <name>Unix Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.unixconsulting.info</url>
    <description>
      Based in London, England, we are focused on BSD/Linux and Open
      Source consultancy and support.  Whether your business already
      runs Linux/FreeBSD/NetBSD/OpenBSD or you are considering the
      introduction of Open Source technology, <a
	href="http://www.unixconsulting.info/">Unix Consulting</a> can
      help you every step of the way.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="tc21" category="namerica">
    <name>Techno Centre Logiciels Libres (TC2L)</name>
    <url>http://www.tc2l.ca/</url>
    <description>
      TC2L is pioneers the IT industry by offering businesses and public
      institutions the first one-stop shop for services, open source
      software, and hardware to meet all IT needs.  Our approach is
      based on a unified network of technical and strategic high level
      partners for service throughout Quebec.  TC2L provides all the
      support you need for easy migration to FLOSS (including special
      attention to FreeBSD).  From planning and implementation to
      training and technical support, we provide comprehensive service.
      User support has always been TC2L's top priority.  As such, we
      have shared our expertise in FLOSS and computer problem solving
      abilities with the Government and large companies country-wide.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="flozer" category="europe">
    <name>Flozer</name>
    <url>http://www.flozer.com</url>
    <description>
      Spanish company focused on providing solutions and services based
      on FLOSS software and operating systems with FreeBSD, OpenBSD and
      GNU/Linux.  We offer customers and partners our solutions and
      services (consultance, development, migrations, virtualization,
      support). For more information contact us at <a
	href="mailto:contacto@flozer.com">contacto@flazer.com</a> or
      visit our <a href="http://www.flozer.com">web site </a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ironkeep" category="namerica">
    <name>Ironkeep Technologies L.L.C.</name>
    <url>http://www.ironkeep.net</url>
    <description>
      Ironkeep Technologies is a Traverse City based consulting firm,
      specializing in internet solutions, networks, vpns, software
      development, programming, web development, web design,
      application development, web hosting, consulting, and open
      source software including FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="nihonsoft" category="asia">
    <name>nihonsoft LLC.</name>
    <url>http://www.nihonsoft.com/</url>
    <description>
      We provide consulting in English and Japanese to help your
      business get started in Japan.  We especially like to help FOSS
      companies set up branches in Japan, and promote the use of FOSS
      systems such as Debian, Ubuntu, FreeBSD, OpenBSD and NetBSD
      throughout industries and schools in Japan.
    </description>  
  </entry>

  <entry id="techneticsdatarecovery" category="australia">
    <name>Technetics Data Recovery</name>
    <url>http://www.techneticsdata.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Technetics Data Recovery is one of the leading data recovery
      labs in Australia.  With many years of experience in the data recovery
      industry we are the experts you can rely on in the event of data loss.
    </description>  
  </entry>

  <entry id="ethon" category="europe">
    <name>Ethon Technologies GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.ethon.de</url>
    <description>
      Ethon Technologies GmbH -- located in Munich, Germany -- has a
      strong focus on BSD driven solutions.  We offer professional
      consulting services as well as BSD based telecommunication
      systems, ranging from basic PBX to telco solutions up to
      10.000.000 users. Feel free to contact us at
      <a href="mailto:info@ethon.de">info@ethon.de</a> or drop us a
      voicemail: +49.89.255456.0
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mosman" category="samerica">
    <name>Mosman Consultoria e Desenvolvimento</name>
    <url>http://www.mosman.com.br</url>
    <description>
      Mosman Consultoria e Desenvolvimento works at the development of
      a FreeBSD based ISP management solution called VirtexAdmin.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ish" category="australia">
    <name>Ish Pty. Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.ish.com.au</url>
    <description>
      Ish provides IT management, network security, FreeBSD and MacOS X
      system administration services in Sydney, Australia.  We have
      designed and implemented BSD-based computer systems for a wide variety
      of commercial customers, and we're available to provide troubleshooting
      and advice for system administrators.  As a developer of web sites, our
      Java/WebObjects-based services are all hosted on FreeBSD servers.  Please
      call us for a chat on +612 9550 5001,
      <a href="mailto:info@ish.com.au">e-mail us</a> or
      <a href="http://www.ish.com.au/products/unix">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="itinfusion" category="namerica">
    <name>IT Infusion Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.itinfusion.ca</url>
    <description>
      IT Infusion Inc. is a consulting firm based in Calgary, Alberta that has
      been serving clients in the US and Canada since 1998.  We have expertise
      in FreeBSD, Linux, thin client implementations, Windows integration,
      Enterprise e-mail systems, PHP/MySQL web development, and the deployment
      of a wide range of Open Source software solutions.  For more information,
      please <a href="http://www.itinfusion.ca">visit our website</a> or drop
      us an e-mail at
      <a href="mailto:casey@itinfusion.ca">casey@itinfusion.ca</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="zelites" category="europe">
    <name>Zelites</name>
    <url>http://www.zelites.org</url>
    <description>
      Zelites is a company based in Le Mans, France.  We offer many
      services: Support, installation, maintenance, administration,
      configuration of servers like firewall, VPN, IDS, web server, mail
      server, DNS or whatever you need.  Our services offerings include
      a high-level of security.  Our knowledge of *BSD (like FreeBSD,
      OpenBSD, NetBSD ..), Linux, MacOS and commercial Unix systems is
      wide and is your guaranty.  For more information, visit our
      <a href="http://www.zelites.org"
        title="Zelites, Prestataire FreeBSD">website</a>,
      <a href="mailto:info@zelites.org">mail us</a> or phone us at
      +33 (0) 2 43 46 94 24.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="hamburgnet" category="europe">
    <name>Hamburgnet</name>
    <url>http://www.hamburgnet.de</url>
    <description>
      Hamburgnet provides you with experience in FreeBSD and OpenBSD
      based projects.  From low-end webservers to high-end firewall
      and database clusters.  Storage, server, Unix, cluster &amp; consulting.
      You can visit our <a href="http://www.hamburgnet.de">website</a>,
      <a href="mailto:info@hamburgnet.de">mail us</a>, phone us at
      +49 (40) 73672322 or contact us via fax at +49 (40) 73672321.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="lifebiscuit" category="australia">
    <name>LifeBiscuit Technology</name>
    <url>http://lifebiscuit.com</url>
    <description>
      LifeBiscuit Technology is a Sydney based company providing technology
      consulting and outsourcing services for small businesses in
      Australia.  We provide support for open source environments:
      FreeBSD, Linux, OpenBSD and NetBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="osbty" category="australia">
    <name>OsBTI Pty. Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.osbti.com.au</url>
    <description>
      One of our specialities is the support, administration and
      installation of FreeBSD in SME Server Environments.  Through our team of
      technicians, we provide support both onsite and remotely to both
      Australia and small select international clients.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="tecno21" category="samerica">
    <name>Tecno21 - Openservices</name>
    <url>http://www.tecno21.com.br/FreeBSD/</url>
    <description>
      We provide setup and support for FreeBSD, OpenBSD and Linux.  We have 10+
      years experience with open source softwares on corporate and SMB
      customers.  We offer custom applications (C/C++/Java/C#),
      network infrastructure design, security, audit and smartcard solutions.
      Contact us via <a href="mailto:suporte@tecno21.com.br">e-mail</a> or
      by phone at +55 (11) 3825-2472.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="cybersecure" category="australia">
    <name>CyberSecure Pty Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.cybersecure.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      CyberSecure specialises in offsite data backup, managed firewalls and
      BSD consulting with an emphasis on quality and security.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pate" category="namerica">
    <name>Pate Consulting, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.pateconsulting.com/</url>
    <description>
      We specialize in providing solid open source solutions for businesses
      using OpenBSD, FreeBSD, and Linux. 6 years in business. 12 years of
      experience - MCSE, CCNA, RHCE certifications - Also MySQL, PostgreSQL.
      VPNs, firewalls, wireless, DNS, squidGuard, mail - even training with
      FreeBSD.  You can contact us via <a
	href="mailto:info@pateconsulting.com">e-mail</a>, call us at
      713.333.5468 or send us a fax at 713.333.5494.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="seciongmbh" category="europe">
    <name>secion GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.secion.de/</url>
    <description>
      secion GmbH is an IT service and consulting company located
      in Hamburg, Germany.  With our long-term experience in *BSD,
      Linux and Unix, as well as in-depth Windows knowledge, we
      deliver commercial-grade services in designing, implementing
      and administering server, client and network infrastructures.
      Our skills includes database-, web- and network/communication
      programming in large IT and Telco environments.  One of our main
      work areas is also designing and setting up larger IPSec VPNs,
      security systems, firewall concepts and communication systems.
      For more information call us at +49-40-389071-0 or visit our
      <a href="http://www.secion.de/">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="recoverdata" category="australia">
    <name>Recover Data</name>
    <url>http://www.recoverdata.com.au</url>
    <description>
      Recover Data supports hard drive repair for data recovery.  With
      over 10 years experience, our data recovery services are second to
      none. Specialising in recovering data for data recovery companies
      and RAID configurations.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="webangel" category="europe">
    <name>Webangel</name>
    <url>http://www.webangel.ie/</url>
    <description>
      Webangel is a company working with open-source operating system
      and software from the beginning.
      We offer
      <a href="http://www.webangel.ie/consultancy">consultancy</a>,
      <a href="http://www.webangel.ie/linux">support</a>,
      <a href="http://www.webangel.ie/webapp/webapps">development</a>,
      <a href="http://www.webangel.ie/opensource/ostraining">training</a>
      and remote administration services.
      You can reach us by <a href="mailto:office@webangel.ie">email</a>
      or phone: +353&nbsp;85&nbsp;157&nbsp;04&nbsp;61.
      We are based in Rathcoole, Co. Dublin Ireland.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="remsys" category="asia">
    <name>REMSYS</name>
    <url>http://www.remsys.net</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://www.remsys.net">REMSYS</a>, based in Chisinau,
      Moldova, provides and specializes in support and consulting for
      FreeBSD, BSDi, Linux and other Unix variants.  We are dedicated
      to offering solutions for desktop and server environments.  We
      can help installing, configuring, system administration (Exim,
      SMTP, Database, Webhosting, DNS, Apache Webstats etc.)  Our
      experience covers the most important branches of current IT
      industry, from routine of server management, security audits and
      updates, to high performance computing, mitigating attacks and
      recovering data from crashed file systems.  We offer you up to
      date solutions for remote systems management, keeping your
      network equipment up and operational 24 hours a day.  For more
      information please visit our
      <a href="http://www.remsys.net">web site</a> or contact us at
      <a href="mailto:info@remsys.net">info@remsys.net</a> or call us
      at +373 22 23-20-70, +373 79-40-63-09.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="collinssystems" category="namerica">
    <name>Collins Systems Solutions Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.csystems.ca</url>
    <description>
      Collins Systems Solutions Inc. is a Toronto, Ontario Canada
      based consulting firm specializing in the design, implementation,
      and support of all things UNIX including Solaris, FreeBSD,
      OpenBSD, all major Linux distributions, and Microsoft Windows
      operating environments.  Collins Systems has specialized skills
      in system administration, security, network design, system
      integration, network/server/application management and service
      monitoring.  Remote administration is the key to providing our
      customers all over the world with the most efficient and effective
      service. For more information, email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@csystems.ca">info@csystems.ca</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="firmbit" category="namerica">
    <name>FirmbIT</name>
    <url>http://www.firmbit.com/index.php</url>
    <description>
      FirmbIT is a high quality server management and security company
      providing friendly reliable support specializing in high security
      installations and scalable solutions with support for FreeBSD,
      OpenBSD, NetBSD, Redhat, Fedora, CentOS, Debian, Slackware, Gentoo,
      SuSe, Mandrake and Sun Solaris servers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="networkadvantage" category="namerica">
    <name>Network Advantage LLC</name>
    <url>http://net-vantage.com/</url>
    <description>
      We strive to bring the same technology advantages enjoyed by large
      organizations to small and medium-sized businesses, schools, and
      non-profits, at a realistic and practical cost.  FreeBSD running SAMBA,
      Apache, MySQL, PHP, sql-ledger, KDE, and many other applications is often
      the central ingredient of this solution.  Please email <a
	href="mailto:roy@net-vantage.com">us</a> for free initial consultation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="nullcube" category="australia">
    <name>Nullcube Pty Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.nullcube.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Nullcube provides services to organisations with exceptional
      security needs.  We use FreeBSD, OpenBSD and Linux to develop and
      support network architectures for security-sensitive environments,
      including firewalls, VPNs, proxies, and IDS / IPS solutions.  We
      also provide IT security auditing, penetration testing, risk
      management, and incident response services.
      Call +61&nbsp;1300&nbsp;767&nbsp;007 or send an email to <a
      href="mailto:info@nullcube.com">info@nullcube.com</a> for free
      initial consultation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="esystems" category="europe">
    <name>E-Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.e-systems.pl/</url>
    <description>
      We provide open source solutions for the small companies in Wroclaw,
      Poland.  We are specialized in servers (*BSD, Linux).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="giganetworking" category="namerica">
    <name>Giganetworking</name>
    <url>http://www.giganetworking.com</url>
    <description>
      Consulting in the areas of Internet security and data defense
      mainly with open source software. Particular knowledge of
      firewalls, internet applications, Mail, Proxy Servers, IDS and
      network administration.  Have developed a range of
      routers/appliances based on Linux/BSD.  For more questions please
      visit our <a href="http://www.giganetworking.com">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="eden-fx" category="asia">
    <name>EDEN-FX</name>
    <url>http://www.eden-fx.com</url>
    <description>
      EDEN-FX is a company which develops high class technology.  Founded
      in 1999, we are working with a team of highly qualified professionals
      specializing in hard and software engineering.  We have broad
      experience with the FreeBSD operating system.  EDEN-FX solutions
      manufactures firewalls, wireless engineering and develops network
      technologies.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="zero-penalty" category="namerica">
    <name>Zero Penalty</name>
    <url>http://zeropenalty.com/</url>
    <description>
      Located in the city of Toronto Canada, Zero Penalty is well positioned
      to service clients within Canada and abroad who require Technology
      Consulting services.  Though focused on technology infrastructure
      services, Zero Penalty offers a variety of products and services that
      include Telephony Services including VOIP Deployment and Management,
      Network Design, Build and Management, System Support, including Desktop
      Support, Hosting and Colocation.<br/>
      Offshore Services is one of our core strengths, including Infrastructure
      Management, Monitoring and Deployment.  Businesses that require offshore
      hosting and services will benefit from our expertise in working with
      international telecom providers, and our understanding of the
      international IT landscape.<br/>
      At Zero Penalty, we strive to make our clients comfortable with the
      choices they make, provide value, and quality products and services.
      Contact us today to start a relationship that will help your business
      strive in its IT requirements.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="osc" category="europe">
    <name>OSC Services</name>
    <url>http://www.orsec.fr/</url>
    <description>
      We proivde technical support and expertise, around opensource software
      technologies, security and network solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="osre" category="namerica">
    <name>Open Software Research and Education (OSRE)</name>
    <url>http://www.osre.org/</url>
    <description>
      Open Software Research and Education (OSRE) is a comprehensive entity
      providing open infrastructure design, development, deployment,
      maintenance and training.  We have extensive experience with FreeBSD
      and most other open source operating systems.  We are located in
      Longview, Texas and provide both on-site and remote support at
      affordable rates.  Please visit our <a
      href="http://www.osre.org">website</a> for more information or call us
      under 1.903.704.4310.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oullet" category="namerica">
    <name>Ouellet Consulting Inc.</name>
    <url>http://sirius.danosoft.com/oci/index.html</url>
    <description>
      OCI specialize in systems/networks design, implementation and security
      solutions, including solutions meeting HIPPA requirements.  We spec out,
      configure and support firewalls, proxy-arrays, servers, switches, mail
      systems, web servers, databases, etc.  We are familiar with and support
      most Windows and Unix/Linux systems including FreeBSD.  We offer remote
      administration services worldwide, on all supported platforms.  We plan
      and assist with Active Directory migrations.  For more information
      please contact us via <a href="mailto:info@danosoft.com">e-mail</a> or
      call us +1-850-510-6162.  Please see <a
	href="http://sirius.danosoft.com/oci/index.html">our website</a> for
      complete details on what we offer.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="wetinet" category="europe">
    <name>WeTi.NeT</name>
    <url>http://www.weti.net</url>
    <description>
      WeTi.NeT - Limberger HandelsgesmbH is a full service Consultant
      and Supplier for pre-installed FreeBSD Servers.  We ship Firewalls,
      Internet Gateways, Mail Systems with virus protection, realtime
      http scanner, File and Print Servers.  Network planning and
      implementation of WANS with IPSEC tunneling, Samba and Hylafax
      installations.  Founded in 1977 with Unix and Novell experience
      since more than 30 years. We are based in Bad Goisern and Salzburg,
      Austria and have customer references throughout Austria, Switzerland,
      the Netherlands and Germany ranging from 5 to 60000 Users. We are
      also shipping pre-installed Asterisk Telephone Systems and have best
      the references with it.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="handtake" category="europe">
    <name>HANDTAKE GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.handtake.de</url>
    <description>
      HANDTAKE GmbH is a service provider for Open Source solutions
      based in Munich. We provide a full range of services (consulting
      services, system administration, support, programming) for Linux,
      *BSD and other Open Source software.  For further information
      please contact
      <a href="mailto:freebsd@handtake.de">freebsd@handtake.de</a> or
      visit our website <a href="http://www.handtake.de">www.handtake.de</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mivitec" category="europe">
    <name>MIVITEC GmbH Niederlassung Muenchen</name>
    <url>http://www.mivitec.de</url>
    <description>
      "MIVITEC GmbH Niederlassung Muenchen" is a provides full redundant
      hosting infrastructure in 3 datacenters in Munich.  For our client
      we provide IT management, network security, Linux, BSD and MacOS X
      system administration services.  We have big experience of
      implementing high availability services, cluster systems and
      hosting infrastructures.  These services are provided for clients
      in our datacenters as well as in your company's datacenter, even
      in other cities in Germany and Austria.  For more information
      please call us at +49 89 420797870, send us an email:
      <a href="mailto:freebsd@mivitec.de">freebsd@mivitec.de</a> or
      visit our website <a href="http://www.mivitec.de">www.mivitec.de</a>.
      You are also invited to visit us in Munich, so that we can
      discuss your FreeBSD based projects.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="corbesero" category="namerica">
    <name>Stephen Corbesero</name>
    <url>mailto:corbesero@fast.net</url>
    <description>
      Stephen Corbesero has over 20 years of software and hardware computing
      experience in various flavors of Unix (FreeBSD since 2.2, SunOS, Solaris,
      ...), C and C++, Perl, databases, networking, etc.  He can provide system
      and network configuration and administration, some custom programming in
      the above languages, troubleshooting and repair.  He is located in
      Eastern Pennsylvania.  Please email <a
	href="mailto:corbesero@fast.net">him</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="hahnefeld" category="europe">
    <name>bj&ouml;rn hahnefeld IT</name>
    <url>http://www.hahnefeld.de</url>
    <description>
      We are a company for Software-Engineering and a Hosting- and
      Server-Solutions provider (Web-, Application-, Database-servers)
      for Germany, Austria and Switzerland.  We are experienced in the
      installation and administration of BSD and Linux systems.  Our
      software experience is with PHP, Perl and SQL and we speak English
      and German. We are located in Regensburg, Germany.  Please email
      <a href="mailto:info@hahnefeld.de">info@hahnefeld.de</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="paxym" category="namerica">
    <name>Paxym</name>
    <url>http://www.paxym.com</url>
    <description>
      Paxym's Highly Skilled team provides software development and
      consulting services in the areas of Kernels, Bootloaders for new
      CPUs &amp; Boards, Network Security Applications, Storage
      Appliances and Performance tuning of embedded SW and
      Network/Storage/Security Applications.  Paxym provides FreeBSD
      SMP for OCTEON (Multicore Mips64 CPU from Cavium Networks).  The
      port is extensively tested with OpenPosix, Apache WebBench,
      UnixBench, MySQL Sysbench, OHCP, Netperf, FreeNAS for stability
      and functional completeness.  Stable port based on FreeBSD 7.0 is
      targeted for Network, Security and Storage Applications.  Multiple
      cores, from 1-16 can be used in SMP mode.  Supports Dynamic &amp;
      Static Linking models, o32, n64 &amp; n32 ABI.  Root filesystem
      can be embedded in kernel memory or put on Compact-Flash/NFS.
      libthr for POSIX pthreads.  Paxym's team has had extensive
      experience with Multi-core Mips (Octeon), PPC and x86 CPUs.
      Working on these from Rom-Monitors, boot-loaders, Operating
      Systems, Network Stacks, Storage protocols, Device Drivers,
      Security Algorithms and Embedded Applications.  Paxym has been
      working closely on FreeBSD, Linux and proprietary OS environments.
      For more information, visit
      <a href="http://www.paxym.com">http://www.paxym.com/</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pontosi" category="europe">
    <name>PontoSI</name>
    <url>http://www.pontosi.pt</url>
    <description>
      PontoSI is portuguese company based in Vila Nova de Gaia.  We are
      specialized in FreeBSD and OpenBSD solutions and services.
      Please visit our website at http://www.pontosi.pt or contact us
      via email geral@pontosi.pt
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mejojose" category="asia">
    <name>Mejo Jose</name>
    <url>http://www.kannayath.com</url>
    <description>
      Open source technology consultant based in Dubai, UAE.  More
      information on the website -
      <a href="http://www.kannayath.com">www.kannayath.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="interfuture" category="europe">
    <name>Interfuture Systems Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.interfuture.co.uk</url>
    <description>
      Interfuture is an UK company offering a full range of UNIX
      consultancy, from desktop installation and support through to
      mission-critical server support and troubleshooting. One of our
      specialist areas and preferred operating systems is FreeBSD.
      Visit our website for more information:
      <a href="http://www.interfuture.co.uk/specialists/unix.php">http://www.interfuture.co.uk/specialists/unix.php</a>
      or call +44 203 002 2111.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="senseofsecurity" category="australia">
    <name>Sense of Security Pty Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.senseofsecurity.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Sense of Security is an Australian provider of Free BSD and Unix
      consulting services. We have a strong focus on building secure
      networks and systems, including firewalls, VPNs, web servers, etc.
      We are also experts at conducting security review, audit,
      penetration testing, and assessment services.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="opentech" category="europe">
    <name>Open Tech SmbA</name>
    <url>http://www.opentech.dk</url>
    <description>
      Open Tech SmbA is a Danish consultancy, that can help your business
      ensure and optimize production performance through a good practice
      of system and network administration of its information technology.
      Our office is located in Herlev, Copenhagen, Denmark.  We can be
      reached by phone at +45 43 62 22 88 and by electronic mail to
      <a href="mailto:opentech@opentech.dk">opentech@opentech.dk</a>.  Visit our
      website at <a href="http://www.opentech.dk">www.opentech.dk</a> and
      stay updated with announcements, technical procedures, system
      administration tasks, that we can do for you, contact details,
      business conditions and much more.  Open Tech SmbA is a legally
      approved and registered company in Denmark.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
