<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Commercial Gallery//EN"
                            "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/gallery.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/share/sgml/commercial.isp.xml,v 1.61 2010/10/23 19:19:59 jkois Exp $ -->

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/share/sgml/commercial.isp.xml,v 1.61 2010/10/23 19:19:59 jkois Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="astute">
    <name>Astute Hosting Incorporated</name>
    <url>http://www.astutehosting.com</url>
    <description>
      Astute Hosting provides advanced high-availability semi-managed
      dedicated hosting with all the flexibility of co-location but at
      a better price point than most unmanaged dedicated solutions.
      FreeBSD is our OS of choice, and what we run on our own servers and
      workstations.  Our bandwidth consists of 4 Tier 1's, and hundreds of
      peers across North America, Europe, and Asia.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ipglobal">
    <name>IP Global.net</name>
    <url>http://www.ipglobal.net/</url>
    <description>
      IP Global is the leading Texas Internet Service Provider offering
      data transport services to all major cities as well as hosting and
      colocation solutions to businesses and groups around the globe.
      We specialize in carrier grade transport circuits for Houston,
      Austin, Dallas / Fort Worth, and San Antonio ranging in
      connections from Fractional T1, Integrated T1,
      Full Unmetered T1 Service, and bundled T1's up to Burstable
      and Full T3 packages. IP Global also delivers Highspeed DSL
      and Local 56K Dialup Internet to the Houston area.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oberon">
    <name>Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.oberon.net/</url>
    <description>
      Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH is one of the biggest Internet
      Service Provider for japanese customers in Germany. We
      deliver services like WWW-housing, E-Mail gates, Highspeed
      DSL and PPP Dialup. With our Germany-wide dialin-infrastructure
      we try to satisfy all of our customers needs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bayhosting">
    <name>Bay Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.bayhosting.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      UK based FreeBSD hosting in secure, resilient facilities.
      Customised firewalls, managed servers, website hosting,
      e-mail hosting with virus/spam-scanning.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bewide">
    <name>Bewide Internet Service Provider</name>
    <url>http://www.bewide.com</url>
    <description>
      Bewide is an Internet Service Provider focussing on all forms
      of hosting, domain registration and development of internet
      applications.  We are a company demanding a high level of
      quality, using high quality hardware.  FreeBSD is the operating
      system of our choice, powering our systems with a high quality
      operating system, perfectly suited for our company.  For more
      information about Bewide, please visit our website <a
	href="http://www.bewide.com">http://www.bewide.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bpa">
    <name>Black Point Arts Internet Solutions GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.bpanet.de/</url>
    <description>
      We offer flexible solutions and serve our customers needs with
      compentent and fast support.  Our services include website hosting,
      virtual Servers (VPS) and server homing (e.g. managed
      servers)/colocation for all kinds of companies.  We are located in
      Germany.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bluegravity">
    <name>Blue Gravity</name>
    <url>http://www.bluegravity.com/index_bsd.php</url>
    <description>
      Providing FreeBSD based web/email/database hosting since 1997. Dedicated,
      Semi-Dedicated, co-located, and virtual hosting solutions to fit any
      needs. Unlike many hosts, we custom build servers in house with the highest
      quality hardware to reduce costs and pass those savings on to you.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bsdvm">
    <name>BSD Virtual Machines</name>
    <url>http://bsdvm.com</url>
    <description>
      Our company offers virtual private servers on the most stable in the world
      BSD platform.  This includes operating systems from BSD family such as
      FreeBSD, OpenBSD and NetBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bsdix">
    <name>BSDiX</name>
    <url>http://www.bsdix.com</url>
    <description>
      BSDiX is a hosting company specializing in FreeBSD hosting
      including shared hosting, VPS (Virtual Private Servers), fully
      managed dedicated servers, website hosting, e-mail hosting, dns
      hosting and other hosting services exclusively on FreeBSD.
      Our headquarters is in Oslo, Norway.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="dbi">
    <name>DBI Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.dbihosting.com</url>
    <description>
      DBI Hosting offers a cost effective <a
      href="http://www.dbihosting.com/bsdvps.html">BSD VPS</a> product
      based on the FreeBSD platform in a secure and stable environment.
      We guarantee our resources and our support team is second to none.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="emuadmin">
    <name>EmuAdmin</name>
    <url>http://www.emuadmin.com/</url>
    <description>
      Emuadmin is offering a full range of services supporting the FreeBSD
      operating system. Security, customized firewalls, full server management,
      custom programming, performance tuning, network management solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Exonetric">
    <name>Exonetric</name>
    <url>http://www.exonetric.com/</url>
    <description>
      Exonetric Consulting Ltd is a UK based specialist in FreeBSD hosting,
      offering both individual jails and managed or unmanaged systems on
      dedicated hardware.  In addition we provide BSD-aware colocation
      services in our London datacentre and are also able to offer
      assistance with capacity planning and recommendations for best-fit
      software components for larger systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="lf">
    <name>LF.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.LF.net/</url>
    <description>
      LF.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH is an Internet Service Provider and
      specialist in network integration services and solutions.
      Founded in 1992, with an assembled team of 25 specialists,
      LF.net is located in one of Germany's largest industrial regions
      in Baden-Wuerttemberg.  We deliver german-wide Highspeed DSL, 64K
      ISDN Dialup and leased line Internet access.  We also specialize
      in domain services, webserver hosting and housing, System
      integration services, network management, security and VPN
      solutions, virus and spam checking, screen design and
      programming as well as consulting and training.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="macomnet">
    <name>MAcomnet telecommunications company, Moscow, Russia</name>
    <url>http://www.macomnet.com/</url>
    <description>
      CJSC MAcomnet is one of the biggest Moscow telecommunication
      companies founded in 1991 by the Moscow Metropoliten and
      Andrew Corporation (USA).  Numerous customers do justice to
      MAcomnet service high quality and level, among them are large
      communications operators, Internet providers, telephone companies,
      banks, hotels, exhibition centers, embassies, well known trading
      companies, government organizations, institutions, industrial
      enterprises, scientific-research institutes, mass media.
      A lot of MAcomnet ISP servers are FreeBSD based.  MAcomnet
      hosts cvsup4.ru.FreeBSD.org and cvsup5.ru.FreeBSD.org cvsup
      mirrors.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="midlandcomputers">
    <name>Midland Computers</name>
    <url>http://www.midlandcomputers.com/</url>
    <description>
      Midland Computers is a UK based FreeBSD hosting provider.  We
      offer hosting solutions ranging from shared hosting to
      dedicated servers, all running FreeBSD and we run our own secure
      data center.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="hostpoint">
    <name>Hostpoint AG</name>
    <url>http://www.hostpoint.ch/</url>
    <description>
      With 55,000 customers and 100,000 domain names (status quo
      December 2007), Hostpoint is Switzerlands leading hosting
      provider.  Hostpoint offers website and application hosting
      services throughout Switzerland.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="improware">
    <name>ImproWare AG</name>
    <url>http://www.imp.ch/</url>
    <description>
      ImproWare AG focuses on Internet and Networking Services
      as well as System Integration and Consulting.
      ImproWare runs its own swiss-wide Multiservice-Backbones.
      It offers internet access via cable and leased lines.
      Serverhousing with 24/7 access to the server-room is
      also a service ImproWare offers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="iweb">
    <name>iWeb Technologies Inc.</name>
    <url>http://iweb.com/dedicated/server-deal/</url>
    <description>
      iWeb has been providing reliable and scalable Internet hosting
      infrastructure solutions with its shared web hosting, dedicated
      servers, managed hosting and colocation services for over a
      decade.  Power your valuable online web presence with an iWeb
      Dedicated Server running FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="gradwell">
    <name>gradwell dot com Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.gradwell.com/</url>
    <description>
      gradwell dot com Ltd is a UK Internet Email and Webhosting
      provider offering UNIX shell accounts, web hosting, mailman
      and ezmlm, pop3, imap, webmail (squirrelmail), mysql, php,
      fastcgi and mod_perl hosting on FreeBSD servers in London.
      Our site is <a href="http://www.gradwell.com/">
      http://www.gradwell.com</a>. Phone: 0870 787 9129.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="keyway">
    <name>Keyway Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.keyway.net/</url>
    <description>
      Keyway Internet Services has provided premium business
      and residential solutions since 1995.  Nationwide services
      include business-class hosting and dialup access.  Southern
      California services include T1, Fiber, DSL, and Wireless.
      We feature our own colocation facility in Ontario, CA, and
      are proud to feature FreeBSD as a recommended platform.
      All clients receive live no-hold support, and T1/Colocation
      clients receive 24/7/365 support.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="claryss">
    <name>Claryss Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.claryss.com/</url>
    <description>
      Claryss Networks provides secure and dependable technologies
      backed with years of experience.  Based in France, we provide
      shared and dedicated hosting, housing, consulting and
      outsourcing.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="easyspeedy">
    <name>EasySpeedy</name>
    <url>http://www.easyspeedy.com</url>
    <description>
      EasySpeedy provides dedicated servers with colocation benefits,
      and a flexible self-service environment.  We're dedicated to
      bringing our customers a wide range of automatically installed
      Linux and BSD-systems, all available at the click of a button.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="highspeedhostingsolutions">
    <name>Highspeedhostingsolutions.com</name>
    <url>http://www.highspeedhostingsolutions.com/</url>
    <description>
      Highspeedhostingsolutions.com offers high speed website hosting
      with free domain names, no data transfer charges, no setup fees
      and spam solutions.  Virtual Host accounts and Virtual Servers
      with FreeBSD as the operating system.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="eserver">
    <name>eServer.ru</name>
    <url>http://www.eServer.ru</url>
    <description>
      We provide high quality web-hosting and VIP-hosting services in
      Russia and CIS based only on FreeBSD systems customized for
      hosting needs, dedicated servers with support of all currently
      available FreeBSD distributions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="k2">
    <name>K2 Colocation</name>
    <url>http://www.k2colocation.com/</url>
    <description>
      K2 Colocation is a BSD friendly colocation company.  Our
      infrastructure resides on IBM xSeries servers running FreeBSD.
      We can provide colocation solutions for small, medium and
      enterprise level businesses.  We believe by focusing our efforts
      to the colocation arena we can better serve our customers.
     </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Quonix">
    <name>Quonix Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.quonix.net/products/dia.html</url>
    <description>
      Quonix Networks provides a variety of personal and enterprise
      hosting solutions powered by FreeBSD, including web, mail, secure
      shell hosting, dedicated servers and colocation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="velocity">
    <name>Velocity Servers</name>
    <url>http://velocity-servers.net/</url>
    <description>
      Velocity Servers provides game server hosting and webhosting on
      FreeBSD.  We can host any specific games that are designed to run
      on Linux.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LayeredTech">
    <name>Layered Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.layeredtech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Layered Technologies provides enterprise level, dedicated self
      managed hosting solutions to our clients at the best, very
      affordable prices.  The self-managed dedicated servers are hosted
      on tier-1 bandwidth.  FreeBSD is our no. 1 supported OS.  We have
      a local FreeBSD/CVSup mirror for customers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PantherTech">
    <name>PantherTech Media Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.panthertech.de/</url>
    <description>PantherTech offers low-cost CMS Hosting on FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MultaCom">
    <name>MultaCom Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.multacom.com/</url>
    <description>
      MultaCom Offers a full line of internet services including
      Colocation, Dedicated Servers, Web development, Bandwidth and IP
      services, Virtual Private Networks and Shared hosting based on
      FreeBSD and on site 24/7 FreeBSD System Engineers.  FreeBSD is
      widely used in our organization and our shared hosting is FreeBSD
      based.  We provide FreeBSD servers as dedicated and also install
      for free on servers we sell to others.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aplus">
    <name>Aplus.Net</name>
    <url>http://www.aplus.net/</url>
    <description>
      Aplus.Net is a facilities based provider located in San Diego, CA
      since 1995.  We provide Web Hosting, Dedicated Servers, Domain
      Names, Web Design, and E-Commerce solutions.  We offer to our
      customers the power and stability of the FreeBSD Operating System
      with our Web Hosting and Dedicated Servers.  Aplus.Net, everything
      for your online business.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IntegrityHost">
    <name>Integrity Host</name>
    <url>http://www.integrityhost.com</url>
    <description>
      Integrity Host provides shared hosting, VPS (Virtual Private
      Servers), and fully managed dedicated servers that run on
      multiple versions of FreeBSD.  cPanel and Fantastico are
      available and bandwidth allocation is generous.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="inetassociation">
    <name>Internet Engineering Association, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.inetassociation.com/</url>
    <description>
      Internet Engineering Association, LLC specializes in providing
      extremely secure, private and reliable Internet services.  Our
      complete website and email services provide clients a reliable,
      worry free environment.  Every server we use to provide service
      runs on FreeBSD.  Our technical infrastructure is housed within
      state-of-the-art Internet Data Center facilities located in
      Tokyo and San Francisco.  Our systems are designed to be extremely
      secure and reliable.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="associationkazar">
    <name>Association Kazar</name>
    <url>http://kazar.net</url>
    <description>
      Association Kazar, located in Paris, France, is a non-profit
      organization that provides for everybody the ability to host
      servers in our co-location, but also to use our co-location
      services for web, email, ftp, and databases.  We are online since
      1996, and use FreeBSD for almost everything.  We provide as well
      connectivity and many other services for people located in Paris.
      We host mailing lists for free if a member uses at least one of
      our services.  We are fans of FreeBSD and use it on
      intel/amd64/sparc64 machines.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Venigo">
    <name>Venigo Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.venigo.fr/</url>
    <description>
      Venigo Internet Services is a French based company, which provides
      hosting solutions like shared, dedicated, colocation hostings, and
      VPN solutions based on FreeBSD.  Venigo Internet Services is also
      able to provide management and support for variety of BSD &amp;
      Linux systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Seiretto">
    <name>Seiretto - UK FreeBSD Web Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.s4servers.com/</url>
    <description>
      Providing UK Dedicated servers and shared hosting 
      accounts on the bullet-proof FreeBSD operating system that we all 
      know and love.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SmartServ">
    <name>SmartServ Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.smart-serv.net/</url>
    <description>
      Based in Britsh Columbia, Canada, SmartServ Hosting offers a wide
      range of shared website hosting and shell hosting packages at an
      affordable price and rock solid stability.  Using FreeBSD servers,
      SmartServ offers a variety of unique features including your
      choice of PHP version, web serving software, and native IPv6
      presence.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HostDepartment">
    <name>Host Department</name>
    <url>http://www.hostdepartment.com/</url>
    <description>
      Host Department provides FreeBSD-based web hosting, reseller
      hosting, domain name registration, and free web hosting services
      for personal, small and medium enterprise businesses, government,
      and also non-profit organizations.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="negimaki">
    <name>Negimaki</name>
    <url>http://www.negimaki.com</url>
    <description>
      Negimaki uses FreeBSD in addition to providing training, support
      and web hosting for WordPress, gallery and PixelPost.  Free
      (open-source) personal publishing platforms.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NQhost">
    <name>NQhost</name>
    <url>http://nqhost.com/</url>
    <description>
      NQhost offers virtual private servers with guaranteed resources.
      Our <a href="http://nqhost.com/freebsd-vps.html">FreeBSD VPS</a>
      packages can be created in Germany or US-located data centers.
      We offer flexible tariff plans, configurations and friendly
      support.
     </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bsn">
    <name>BSn.Com</name>
    <url>http://bsn.com/</url>
    <description>
      BSn.Com is Munich, Germany based company providing ISP remote 
      hosting &amp; net services on FreeBSD (i386 &amp; Sparc
      architectures).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ServePath">
    <name>ServePath</name>
    <url>http://www.servepath.com/</url>
    <description>
      ServePath is a managed server hosting and data center provider
      located in San Francisco.  We deliver powerful, affordable FreeBSD
      dedicated server hosting, custom-built to meet your requirements.
      On the network side, all of our servers include full 100Mbps
      burstable connections to the Internet, with HSRP protected private
      VLANs.  All ServePath FreeBSD dedicated servers give you full root
      access, and you can choose from multiple FreeBSD release versions.
      Check our <a href="http://www.servepath.com/">web site</a>, or call
      us at 866-321-PATH.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HostingFreak">
    <name>HostingFreak.net, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.hostingfreak.net/</url>
    <description>
      HostingFreak is a company providing hosting services for
      everyone's needs.  Whether it might be a high content, or a
      private website, we are dedicated to a high level of reliability
      and performance.  Our company offers hosting services ranging from
      web-site hosting to self-managed dedicated servers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="berklix">
    <name>Berklix.Com</name>
    <url>http://berklix.com/</url>
    <description>
      English company in Munich, Germany.  Bilingual consultancy &amp;
      hosting.  Virtual &amp; physical domain hosting on diverse
      servers, and customer's own local &amp; ISP hosted servers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="M5Hosting">
    <name>M5 Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.m5hosting.com/</url>
    <description>
      We provide <a
	href="http://www.m5hosting.com/freebsd-dedicated-server.php">
	FreeBSD Dedicated Servers</a> as well as other dedicated servers
      with Unix-like operating systems.  All servers are customized to
      your specifications, including: disk partitions, OS version,
      package installation, number of IP Addresses, and more.  Our
      network emphasizes quality bandwidth rather than quantity.  We
      host the <a href="http://www.sdbug.org/">
	San Diego BSD Users Group</a> mailing list and web site.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="amdwebhost">
    <name>All My Data</name>
    <url>http://www.amdwebhost.com</url>
    <description>
      We offer several shared, reseller and shell hosting plans on
      FreeBSD platform that will meet and exceed all of your web
      presence needs from small personal family web sites to full blown
      online e-commerce solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bytecamp">
    <name>bytecamp GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.bytecamp.net/</url>
    <description>
      We run a homogenic FreeBSD environment in our own datacenter
      located in East Germany near Berlin since 2000.  Our developers
      contribute code to many open source projects.  bytecamp is the home
      for <a href="http://www.desktopbsd.net/">desktopbsd.net</a> and
      both biggest German BSD communities, <a
      href="http://www.bsdforen.de/">bsdforen.de</a> and <a
      href="http://www.bsdgroup.de/">bsdgroup.de</a>.  bytecamp offers
      professional hosting on a FreeBSD cluster, enterprise email solutions,
      domain name registration, dedicated and virtual servers.  We offer
      several shared, reseller and shell hosting plans on FreeBSD platform
      that will meet and exceed all of your web presence needs from small
      personal family web sites to full blown online e-commerce solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Liebscher">
    <name>Liebscher &amp; Partner</name>
    <url>http://www.freibergnet.de</url>
    <description>
      Liebscher &amp; Partner are now shipping the BSD <a
      href="http://www.freibergnet.de/fgnet/scan/sf=prod_group/se=Fanartikel/sf=category/se=BSD">
        Stuffed Daemon! <img alt="stuffed daemon" src="../gifs/plueschtier-tiny.jpg"/></a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ingate">
    <name>INGATE GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.ingate.de</url>
    <description>
      Located in Germany, INGATE GmbH provides managed and unmanaged
      dedicated servers with FreeBSD preinstalled.
    </description>
  </entry>
  
  <entry id="interouteger">
    <name>Interoute Deutschland GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.interoute-deutschland.de/</url>
    <description>
      Interoute Deutschland is located in Duesseldorf, Germany.  As full
      service provider we deliver a large range of services including
      leased lines, (S)DSL, virtual and dedicated hosting.  Using
      FreeBSD since years for internal purposes and customer solutions
      we are sure to meet your requirements.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oph">
    <name>OPH</name>
    <url>http://www.oph.net/</url>
    <description>
      OPH is a internet hosting provider located in Amsterdam.  We
      deliver powerful FreeBSD dedicated servers and custom-built
      servers to meet your requirements.  On the network side, all
      our servers include full 100Mbps / 1Gbps connections to the
      Internet.  For more informations, please check our
      <a href="http://www.oph.net">website</a>, or call us at
      +31 527 688768.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="fxservices">
    <name>F/X Services Managed Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.fx-services.com/</url>
    <description>
      We specialize in Internet Services and we have been doing so since
      1999.  We do this in a no-nonsense way: no long lists of
      tech-terms, just information that matters.  We are your partner if
      you are looking for: Colocating and/or managing dedicated server(s),
      Online backup / storage service, High quality webhosting for your
      site(s), Domain registration(s), Anti-Spam and Anti-Virus
      mailscanning services, Hosting of mailinglists, from low to high
      volume
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="elantech">
    <name>ElanTech, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.elantech.ru/</url>
    <description>
      We are providing wide range of IT services for small business
      companies in our region (Moscow, Russia).  Our main tasks - IT
      outsourcing and WEB developement.  As part of IT support and
      building networks for our customers we use the reliable and
      efficient OS - FreeBSD.  All our WEB developers use FreeBSD
      as comfortable development hosting platform.  Please, be free to
      <a href="http://www.elantech.ru/about/contacts.php">
	contact us</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sh3lls">
    <name>Sh3lls Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.sh3lls.net/</url>
    <description>
      Sh3lls Limited provides <a
      href="http://www.sh3lls.net/vps/freebsd_vps.html">FreeBSD based
      VPS</a> using the FreeBSD Jails Technology, as well as FreeBSD
      based unix shell accounts for IRC.  Our FreeBSD VPS and IRC
      shells are both highly DDOS protected and we have been in
      business since 2003.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="shockmedia">
    <name>Shockmedia</name>
    <url>http://www.shockmedia.nl</url>
    <description>
      Shock Media is a web- and serverhosting company located in the
      Netherlands.  We sell high quality hosting products with Service
      Level Agreements for affordable prices.  We install FreeBSD with
      or without webhosting control panel.  Feel free to contact us or
      to check out our website if you are interested in our hosting
      products.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="transip">
    <name>TransIP</name>
    <url>http://www.transip.nl</url>
    <description>
      Transip B.V. is a top 5 domain registrar in the Netherlands.
      TransIP uses FreeBSD exclusively on its own servers and offers
      virtual hosting and dedicated servers based on FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="gecadtech">
    <name>Gecad Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.axigen.com</url>
    <description>
      Gecad Technologies develops an innovative messaging solution
      available for Linux and BSD Platforms - AXIGEN Mail Server.
      This highly configurable MTA offers (E)SMTP, POP3, IMAP4 and
      Webmail SSL/TLS secured services.  It includes an integrated list
      server and connectors for Antivirus and Antispam applications.
      AXIGEN provides several administration tools, including an
      intuitive Web configuration interface, granting system
      administrators full control of the email traffic.  AXIGEN works
      on FreeBSD, NetBSD and OpenBSD.  For more information, please see
      <a href="http://www.axigen.com/">http://www.axigen.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="kionic">
    <name>Kionic.com Web Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.kionic.com</url>
    <description>
      We provide fast, reliable, and affordable web hosting and reseller
      hosting services backed by fast and friendly customer service.
      Our operating system of choice is FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="JohnCompanies">
    <name>JohnCompanies</name>
    <url>http://www.johncompanies.com</url>
    <description>
      JohnCompanies Collocation is a specialist in both dedicated and
      virtual FreeBSD servers.  Unlimited technical support comes
      directly from FreeBSD engineers with no complicated ticket
      system, impersonal auto responders and no first level techs
      reading from cue-cards.  Servers are housed in a state of the art,
      secure hosting facility with multi-homed tier 1 backbone
      connections.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="activeventure">
    <name>Active Venture Pte Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.active-venture.com</url>
    <description>
      Active-Venture.com strives to provide one of the most
      feature-packed and affordable web hosting services on the market.
      We offer an extensive range of FreeBSD-based virtual hosting
      plans to meet the needs of any webmaster for personal,
      professional, or ecommerce web hosting requirements.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="fastpcnet">
    <name>Fast PC Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.fastpcnet.net</url>
    <description>
      We offer colocation and managed services via our data center
      facilities.  We recommend FreeBSD to our colocation customers who
      want a stable and flexible platform.  We provide a pure colocation
      environment or dedicated managed hosting.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pairnetworks">
    <name>pair Networks, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.pair.com</url>
    <description>
       pair Networks, a global FreeBSD-based Web hosting and
       domain name registration company, headquartered in Pittsburgh, PA,
       hosts hundreds of thousands of Web sites for businesses,
       bloggers, artists, educational institutions and non-profit
       organizations from around the world.  pair Networks first went
       online in January 1996 and has experienced strong growth year
       after year.  All pair Networks' Web servers run the reliable
       FreeBSD operating system.  For more information <a
       href="http://www.pair.com/contact/">contact us</a> via e-mail
       or phone.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ppgnetsol">
    <name>PPG Network Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.ppgnetworksolutions.com</url>
    <description>
      PPG Network Solutions offers Web Hosting exclusively on FreeBSD.
      We have hosting packages for personal to medium sized businesses.
      All of our services are backed by administrators who's passion is
      to keep there sites up and running.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="crucialservers">
    <name>Crucial Servers LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.crucialservers.net</url>
    <description>
      Crucial Servers LLC uses FreeBSD to the fullest controlling our
      hosting network behind PC FreeBSD based routers that control
      ipv4 and ipv6 connectivity, traffic shapping and advanced
      firewall tactics all currently use FreeBSD.  All our public and
      private web servers all run FreeBSD 4.9 or higher and have
      uptimes over 400 days.  We are a FreeBSD friendly provider and
      offer Free consulting for colocation and server customers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="verio">
    <name>Verio</name>
    <url>http://www.verio.com/freebsd</url>
    <description>
      With our FreeBSD VPS v3 and MPS v2, we combine more that 10 years
      of virtualization and managed experience with the proven
      stability, performance, and security of the FreeBSD VPS 6.x
      operating system.  For over a decade the Verio name has stood for
      "true pricing" (with no hidden costs), FairShare resource
      management, bulletproof security, triple-data backups, easy
      application installations and upgrades, and industry-leading
      reliability. So multiply your possibilities with the Verio FreeBSD
      VPS and MPS and know that you're doing business with a strong
      provider!
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="infotime">
    <name>Infotime Internet</name>
    <url>http://www.infotime.net</url>
    <description>
      Infotime offers shared hosting, domain name registrations and dedicated
      servers.  We have been using FreeBSD for most of our services for
      the last 4 years.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="strategite">
    <name>Strategite</name>
    <url>http://www.strategite.fr</url>
    <description>
      Strategite is a company based in Paris, France.  We offer many
      services: Support, installation, maintenance, administration,
      configuration of servers like firewall, VPN, IDS, web server, mail
      server, DNS or whatever you need.  Our services offerings include
      a high-level of security using *BSD (like FreeBSD, OpenBSD, NetBSD),
      Linux, MacOS and commercial Unix systems is wide and is
      your guaranty.  For more information, visit our
      <a href="http://www.strategite.fr" title="Strategite">website</a>,
      <a href="mailto:a.lunot@strategite.fr">mail us</a> or phone us at
      +33 (0) 140 337 130.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="hamburgnet">
    <name>Hamburgnet</name>
    <url>http://www.hamburgnet.de</url>
    <description>
      Hamburgnet provides you with experience in FreeBSD and OpenBSD
      based projects.  From low-end webservers to high-end firewall
      and database clusters.  Storage, server, Unix, cluster &amp; consulting.
      You can visit our <a href="http://www.hamburgnet.de">website</a>,
      <a href="mailto:info@hamburgnet.de">mail us</a>, phone us at
      +49 (40) 73672322 or contact us via fax at +49 (40) 73672321.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="swishmail">
    <name>Swishmail</name>
    <url>http://www.swishmail.com/</url>
    <description>
      Swishmail, New York City based company, provides
      business <a href="http://www.swishmail.com/emailhosting1.php">email
      hosting</a> with virus/spam-scanning running on FreeBSD amd64 on HP
      AMD Dual Opteron 64 bit servers since 1999.  Swishmail is in the business
      of <a href="http://www.swishmail.com/emailhosting1.php">email
      hosting</a>, shell providing, <a
	href="http://www.swishmail.com/webhosting1.php">web hosting</a>,
      dedicated servers, and email accounting.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="reliableservers">
    <name>ReliableServers</name>
    <url>http://www.reliableservers.com/</url>
    <description>
      ReliableServers provides managed and unmanaged dedicated server hosting
      and colocation.  FreeBSD is our #1 installed OS, we even provide a local
      cvsup for all clients. Our datacenter is staffed around the clock to
      provide the best possible support.  Visit us at
      <a href="http://www.reliableservers.com/">www.ReliableServers.Com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mainlink">
    <name>Mainlink</name>
    <url>http://www.mainlink.de</url>
    <description>
      Mainlink is a Frankfurt/Germany based ISP offering root servers running
      FreeBSD and other *BSD flavours. Managing options, KVM-over-IP access,
      plain webspace, spam-protected email services etc. available. Foreign
      customers are welcome.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="mambobado">
    <name>Mambo Bado Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.mambobado.com</url>
    <description>
      Custom software development and software consulting services
      provider. Experienced at developing for and porting to BSD
      environments.  For more information please visit our
      <a href="http://www.mambobado.com">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id=" mindsalt">
    <name>MindSalt Timesheet and Expense</name>
    <url>http://www.mindsalt.com</url>
    <description>
      MindSalt Time &amp; Expense is a 100% Web-based application that allows
      you and your employees to access your timesheets and expenses from
      anywhere in the world through an intuitive, easy to use interface.
      All you need is an Internet connection to track time and expenses,
      monitor projects in real-time, and manage and approve timesheets and
      expense reports. The powerful reporting options in MindSalt 
      Time &amp; Expense supply the vital information that you need. Cost and
      billing, profitability, client billing, and project budgets are just
      a few of the types of information you will find in the flexible reports.
      With over 100 combinations of reports for Administrators, Managers, and
      Employees, you are sure to find the report you need. Start your free trial
      today.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="activedomain">
    <name>Active Domain</name>
    <url>http://www.active-domain.com</url>
    <description>
      Active-Domain.com has been providing domain name registration
      service since 2001.  We are utilizing FreeBSD exclusively on all
      our mail, web and DNS servers.  The stability and security of
      FreeBSD has enabled us to provide consistently DNS service for
      over hundred thousand domain names.  We fully recommend and
      support the development of FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sagonetworks">
    <name>Sago Networks</name>
    <url>http://sagonet.com</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://sagonet.com">Sago Networks</a> was founded as an
      alternative to the telephone and cable company monopolies and
      inefficient Internet companies.  Its mission is to be a one-stop
      shop for all of its customers' bandwidth and custom
      telecommunications needs.  The company also believes in providing
      a laser-like focus on customer service and, from its headquarters
      in the Tampa Bay area and satellite offices in Miami and Atlanta,
      has implemented multiple rapidly deployable, high-speed fiber and
      wireless networks and maintains one of the largest bandwidth
      datacenters in the country.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="colocrossing">
    <name>Colocrossing</name>
    <url>http://www.colocrossing.com</url>
    <description>
      Colocrossing provides FreeBSD powered colocation services in 6
      locations in the US.  From managed hosting to colocation, we are
      here for you.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="kuwaitnet">
    <name>KuwaitNET Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.kuwaitnet.net</url>
    <description>
      For the past 10 years, KuwaitNET has been providing
      <a href="http://www.kuwaitnet.net/en/hosting.php">web hosting</a>,
      <a href="http://www.kuwaitnet.net/en/server.php">managed dedicated
	servers</a>, <a href="http://www.kuwaitnet.net/en/services.php">
	domain registration</a>, IT consulting and IT project management
      services across the Middle East on our secured FreeBSD and Linux
      based infrastructure. As the only ICANN accredited registrar in
      Kuwait; we are the premiere source for Internet related services
      for customers from all industry verticals in the region.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="kwshell">
    <name>KwShell Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.kwshell.com</url>
    <description>
      KwShell Internet Services is an Arabic based company, which
      provides hosting solutions like shared and dedicated Servers.
      KwShell Internet Services is also able to provide management and
      support for a variety of BSD and Linux systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="rootbsd">
    <name>RootBSD</name>
    <url>http://www.rootbsd.net</url>
    <description>
      RootBSD is a hosting company specializing in virtual FreeBSD
      hosting and managed services.  The FreeBSD Virtual Private
      Servers allow users to modify the kernel, setup a firewall and
      many more options.  Each VPS includes root access and a web-based
      control panel for managing the virtual environment.  Technical
      support is handled in-house by FreeBSD experts who can diagnose
      problems and help you get up and running quickly.  RootBSD has
      donated services to FreeBSD developers to support the community.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ServerBeach">
    <name>ServerBeach</name>
    <url>http://www.serverbeach.com</url>
    <description>
      Founded in 2002, ServerBeach was launched to serve the market's
      thirst for self-managed servers equipped with powerful hardware,
      fast and reliable bandwidth, convenient automation tools, and
      first-class support - all at an affordable price.  Self-managed
      servers are not an afterthought at the Beach, it's our business.
      And we do whatever we can to satisfy the needs of our core
      customers, the "Geeks" - people like you.  People like us. In 2004,
      the picture improved even more when ServerBeach was acquired by
      PEER 1.  This allowed us to connect our data centers to the
      rock-solid, ultra-fast PEER 1 network with our 100% Uptime
      Guarantee.  ServerBeach is the only self-managed hosting company
      in the world that offers servers in three geographically diverse
      locations:  WEST COAST, CENTRAL US, and EAST COAST.  Now offering
      FreeBSD, Ubuntu, and other Linux Operating Systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SimpleRezo">
    <name>SimpleRezo</name>
    <url>http://www.simplerezo.com</url>
    <description>
      SimpleRezo, a French company, provides web hosting solutions based
      exclusively on FreeBSD and technologies (jails or dedicated
      server, Apache, PHP, Tomcat, MySQL, pgSQL...).  Other services
      include:  Network architecture consulting (fail-over, high
      availability), FreeBSD server administration or support (fileserver,
      firewalls, mailserver) and others more.  Please visit our <a
      href="http://www.simplerezo.com/nous-contacter.php">website</a>
      to get more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="webdrops">
    <name>Webdrops ICT</name>
    <url>http://www.webdrops.net</url>
    <description>
      FreeBSD hosting based in Italy since 2004.  We provide hosting on
      shared boxes, dedicated servers, co-location, gTLD and worldwide
      ccTLD registration and every DC service you may ask for.  We have
      rack space available in Milan IT, Dallas US and Amsterdam NL; We
      can provide simple or complex network infrastructure and supply
      Brand or custom hardware and network equipments.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sevenl">
    <name>SevenL Networks Inc.</name>
    <url>https://www.sevenl.net</url>
    <description>
      <a href="https://www.sevenl.net">SevenL Networks Inc.</a> providing
      <a href="https://www.sevenl.net/freebsd-dedicated-server">affordable
	FreeBSD dedicated server hosting</a>, VPS, managed web server
      offerings, colocation, data center space and other hosting services
      since 2003. SevenL currently hosts server infrastructure for Gentoo,
      Arch Linux, Linux Mint, CentOS, Startcom Linux and a number of open
      source software projects. SevenL Networks is located in Toronto,
      Canada.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="argentina">
    <name>Argentina.com</name>
    <url>http://www.argentina.com</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://www.argentina.com">Argentina.com</a> is an Argentina
      based Hosting and e-mail provider with FreeBSD infrastructure and
      Globalcrossing connectivity.  We offer FreeBSD-stable dedicated
      servers with great connectivity, Shared hosting on Plesk for FreeBSD,
      and Corporate FreeBSD based email hosting.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="skiltech">
    <name>SkilTech, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.skiltech.com</url>
    <description>
      SkilTech Web Design and Hosting, based in Elkton, MD, has been
      offering FreeBSD based hosting since 1998. Both shared and dedicated
      web hosting solutions are available, and unlike many larger firms,
      we can work with our customers to address their individual hosting
      needs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ermis">
    <name>Ermis | Domeinruimte</name>
    <url>http://www.ermis.nl</url>
    <description>
      Ermis | Domeinruimte has been hosting websites since 2004 on FreeBSD
      servers, but also offer anti-spam services, backup MX, handle domain
      name registrations and offer IT services to our corporate clients.
      We strive to bring the best service for the lowest price.  Since we
      are based in Rotterdam (the Netherlands) all our services are
      available primarily in Dutch, where possible but also offer services
      in English for our international clients.  We colocated our
      infrastructure in a climate neutral datacenter and our servers'
      energy consumption is remarkably low but retain performance.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
