<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE events PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Events//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/events.dtd">
<!--
     Events which might be interesting for FreeBSD users.

     Please sort the events by start date, with recent events earlier in the file.
-->

<events>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD$
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <event id="meetbsd-2007">
    <name>MeetBSD 2007</name>
    <url>http://2007.meetbsd.org/en/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>17</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>18</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="PL">Poland</country>
      <city>Warsaw</city>
      <site>Centrum Konferencyjno-Kongresowe PWSBiA</site>
    </location>
    <description>The fourth annual MeetBSD conference will be held in
      Poland to bring together BSD experts from around Europe.
      Several FreeBSD developers will be presenting on FreeBSD
      topics.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="linuxtageinessen-2007">
    <name>come2linux - LinuxTage in Essen</name>
    <url>http://www.come2linux.org/psp/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>10</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>11</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Essen</city>
      <site>Universit&auml;t Duisburg-Essen, Glas-Pavilion</site>
    </location>
    <description>Linuxtage in Essen is a two day event on Linux and
      Free Software in general. There will be workshops, talks, a
      theme park and room for various projects to present
      themselves. FreeBSD as well as nearly all other BSDs (OpenBSD,
      NetBSD, DesktopBSD, PC-BSD, MirBSD) will be present with a booth
      as well as several talks and installation workshops held by the
      new project www.BSDInstall.de.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="coscup-2007">
    <name>COSCUP 2007 - Conference for Open Source Coders, Users and Promoters</name>
    <url>http://coscup.org/2007/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>3</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>4</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="TW">Taiwan (ROC)</country>
      <city>Taipei</city>
      <site>Techonology Building 2F, National Science Council</site>
    </location>
    <description>COSCUP 2007 is a joint conference of ICOS (International
      Conference on Open Source), to make the open source carnival more
      exciting.  The mostly change of COSCUP in 2007 is, the conference is
      co-organized by all local communities in Taiwan, we hope to enlarge the
      participation of local communities during such kind of cooperation. Just
      like the spirit of COSCUP, in this conference, you can be both attendee
      and promoter, and also involve the operation of the conference.

      The major topics in COSCUP 2007 including web-based platform and embedded
      system due to the popularity of Web 2.0 and OLPC; the Chinese session,
      Lightning Talk and System session are the most interesting topics for
      years.  There will be some presentations and talks about FreeBSD.

      The program is attractive just like before, we invite not only big ones
      in the community but also developers of non-famous local OSS projects,
      to get more people involved and make OSS more brilliant in Taiwan.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="systems-2007">
    <name>Systems 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.systems-world.de/id/58547/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>23</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>27</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Munich</city>
      <site>Messe M&uuml;nchen</site>
    </location>
    <description>Systems is a four day IT fair with more than 50000
      visitors and 1200 exhibitors. FreeBSD will have a booth as well
      as the other majour BSDs and will try to repeat the great succes
      in 2006. There will be an Open Source conference with workshops,
      talks and a theme park for various projects.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="bsdcontr-2007">
    <name>BSDConTR 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.bsdcontr.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>19</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>20</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="TR">Turkey</country>
      <city>Istanbul</city>
      <site>Sultanahmet Campus Marmara University</site>
    </location>
    <description>BSDConTR is the first conference on BSD systems in
      Turkey.  The conference is organized in full cooperation with the
      EnderUNIX Software Development Team, which is largely known for its
      ongoing support for BSD systems in Turkey and its open source
      projects, and Marmara University.  Join the developers, users, BSD
      system admins and companies in Istanbul to share experiences and
      knowledge about BSD Systems.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="forum-software-libre">
    <name>I F&oacute;rum Software Livre</name>
    <url>http://www.softwarelivre.com.pt/index.php</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>12</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>13</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="PT">Portugal</country>
      <city>Lisbon</city>
      <site>Faculdade de Ci&ecirc;ncias da Universidade de Lisboa</site>
    </location>
    <description>I F&oacute;rum Software Livre is a two day conference on
      Free Software and Open Source, taking place in Lisbon. There
      will be some presentations and talks about
      FreeBSD.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="building-os-community-freebsd-ucbe-2007">
    <name>Course: Building and Running an Open Source Community</name>
    <url>http://www.unex.berkeley.edu/cat/course1557.html</url>

    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>3</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>10</month>
      <day>3</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="US">USA</country>
      <city>San Francisco</city>
      <site>UC Extension San Francisco: Room 216, South of Market Center</site>
    </location>

    <description>The BSD community started at UC Berkeley in the late
      1970's. Through the 1980's, the BSD software was developed and
      released from Berkeley. In 1992, Berkeley made its final
      release, 4.4BSD-Lite, an open-source version of BSD. Since that
      time, independent development has continued by the FreeBSD,
      NetBSD, OpenBSD, Darwin, and Dragonfly projects. This talk
      traces the history and structure of the BSD community from its
      start as a small group of paid staff at Berkeley up through the
      thousands of volunteer developers that make up the FreeBSD
      Project of today. It describes how the development structure set
      up at Berkeley was expanded to create a self-organizing project
      that supports an ever growing and changing group of developers
      around the world.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="kernel-internals-ucbe-2007">
    <name>Course: FreeBSD Kernel Internals</name>
    <url>http://www.unex.berkeley.edu/cat/course927.html</url>

    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>29</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>11</month>
      <day>3</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="US">USA</country>
      <city>Berkeley</city>
      <site>UC Extension Berkeley: Room 211, Golden Bear Building</site>
    </location>

    <description>This course will provide a firm background in the
      FreeBSD kernel. The course will cover basic kernel services,
      process structure, the FreeBSD jail facility for hosting virtual
      machines, scheduling, signal handling, and virtual and physical
      memory management. The kernel I/O structure will be described
      showing how I/O is multiplexed, special devices are handled,
      character processing is performed, and the buffer pool is
      managed. The implementation of the filesystem and its
      capabilities, including soft updates and snapshots, will be
      described. The filesystem interface will then be described to
      show how it can be used to support multiple filesystem types
      such as Sun Microsystem's Network File System (NFS). The course
      will also cover the FreeBSD socket-based network architecture,
      layering, and implementation. Socket communications primitives
      and internal layering will be discussed, with emphasis on the
      interfaces between layers; the TCP/IP implementation will be
      used as an example. A discussion of routing issues will be
      included. Other system-related topics include performance
      measurement, system tuning, and security issues. The
      presentations will emphasize code organization, data structure
      navigation, and algorithms. It will not cover machine-specific
      parts of the system, such as device drivers.

      Saturdays September 29, October 6 and 27, and
      November 3, 2007; 9:00AM to 5:30PM Sept. 29 to Nov. 3: Sat., 9
      am-5:30 pm (no meetings Oct. 13 and Oct. 20).</description>
  </event>

  <event id="bsd-narrative-history-ucbe-2007">
    <name>Course: A Narrative History of BSD</name>
    <url>http://www.unex.berkeley.edu/cat/course1556.html</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>26</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>26</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="US">USA</country>
      <city>San Francisco</city>
      <site>UC Extension San Francisco: Room 216, South of Market Center</site>
    </location>

    <description>Learn the history of the BSD (Berkeley Software
      Distributions) from one of its key developers, who brings the
      history to life, complete with anecdotes and footnotes to the
      historical narrative. The BSD community began at the UC Berkeley
      in the late 1970s. You'll hear about the triumphs and defeats of
      the project and its releases during its heyday in the 1980s. The
      Berkeley era concludes with the tumultuous lawsuit, ultimately
      settled in Berkeley's favor, which allowed the final release in
      1992 of 4.4BSD-Lite, an open-source version of BSD. The talk
      includes a brief commentary on the FreeBSD, NetBSD, OpenBSD,
      Darwin, and Dragonfly projects that took their genesis from the
      release of 4.4BSD-Lite.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="openexpo-2007">
    <name>OpenExpo 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.openexpo.ch/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>19</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>20</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="CH">Switzerland</country>
      <city>Zurich</city>
      <site>Event550 Hall</site>
    </location>
    <description>The goal of OpenExpo is the promotion of Open Source
      software in the business environment.  Among many others, there
      will be a FreeBSD booth.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="eurobsdcon-2007">
    <name>EuroBSDCon 2007</name>
    <url>http://2007.eurobsdcon.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>14</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>9</month>
      <day>15</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DK">Denmark</country>
      <city>Copenhagen</city>
      <site>Symbion Science Park</site>
    </location>
    <description>The sixth annual European BSD Conference.  It is
      oriented to developers and users of all BSD flavors, including
      FreeBSD of course.  A variety of full and half-day tutorials will
      precede the conference.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="froscon-2007">
    <name>FrOSCon 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.froscon.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>8</month>
      <day>25</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>8</month>
      <day>26</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Sankt Augustin</city>
      <site>Fachhochschule Bonn-Rhein-Sieg</site>
      <address>Grantham-Allee 20</address>
    </location>
    <description>FrOSCon is a two day conference on Free Software
      and Open Source, taking place in Sankt Augustin near the cities
      of Bonn and Cologne.  The conference revolves around a rich schedule
      of talks, highlighting current topics in Free Software and Open
      Source.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="cosin-2007">
    <name>CoSin 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.ccc.de/calendar/2007/cosin?language=en</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>7</month>
      <day>6</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>7</month>
      <day>8</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="CH">Switzerland</country>
      <city>Aargau</city>
      <site>Kulturzentrum Bremgarten (KuZeB)</site>
    </location>
    <description>CoSin is a three day conference on Open Source and
      various other topics taking place in the Kulturzentrum
      Bremgarten near Zurich.  There will be a FreeBSD booth as well
      as other BSDs.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="ltpact-2007">
    <name>LT Pact 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.ltpact.com</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>6</month>
      <day>20</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>6</month>
      <day>22</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="US">USA</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
      <city>Las Vegas</city>
    </location>
    <description>LT Pact is a two day web hosting conference in Las
      Vegas, Nevada being presented by Layered Technologies. The conference
      features talks and panels that focus on web hosting and technologies
      in use by large hosting companies. There will be a FreeBSD lab
      session during the conference and plenty of FreeBSD gear.
    </description>
  </event>

  <event id="linuxtag-2007">
    <name>LinuxTag 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.linuxtag.org/2007/en/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>5</month>
      <day>30</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>6</month>
      <day>2</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Berlin</city>
      <site>Messe Berlin</site>
    </location>
    <description>LinuxTag is Europe's largest event about Free Software,
      Linux and Open Source.  This year there will be the traditional
      FreeBSD booth and several BSD talks.
    </description>
  </event>

  <event id="bsdcan-2007">
    <name>BSDCan 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.bsdcan.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>5</month>
      <day>18</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>5</month>
      <day>19</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="CA">Canada</country>
      <city>Ottawa</city>
      <site>University of Ottawa</site>
    </location>
    <description>BSDCan is a developers conference with a strong focus
      on emerging technologies, research projects, and works in
      progress. It also features Userland infrastructure projects and
      invites contributions from both free software developers and those
      from commercial vendors.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="unix-linux-day-zweibruecken-2007">
    <name>Unix and Linux Day 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.unix-and-linux-day.de/index.html</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>5</month>
      <day>5</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>5</month>
      <day>5</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Zweibr&#252;cken</city>
      <site>FH Kaiserslautern, Site Zweibr&#252;cken</site>
    </location>
    <description>Among others, there will be a talk about FreeBSD by
      Alexander Leidinger.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="augsburger-linuxinfotag-2007">
    <name>Augsburger Linux-Infotag 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.luga.de/Aktionen/LIT-2007/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>24</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>24</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Augsburg</city>
      <site>FH Augsburg</site>
    </location>
    <description>The Augsburger Linux-Infotag offers two parallel tracks
      of talks to show the capabilities of free and open source software.
      There will be several talks about FreeBSD as well as a FreeBSD
      booth.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="asiabsdcon-2007">
    <name>AsiaBSDCon 2007</name>
    <url>http://2007.asiabsdcon.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>8</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>11</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="JP">Japan</country>
      <city>Tokyo</city>
      <site>University of Tokyo</site>
    </location>
    <description>AsiaBSDCon is a conference for users and developers on BSD
      based systems.  The conference is for anyone developing, deploying and
      using systems based on FreeBSD, NetBSD, OpenBSD, DragonFlyBSD, Darwin
      and MacOS X.  AsiaBSDCon is a technical conference and aims to collect
      the best technical papers and presentations available to ensure that
      the latest developments in our open source community are shared with
      the widest possible audience.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="linuxtage-chemnitz-2007">
    <name>Linuxtage Chemnitz 2007</name>
    <url>http://chemnitzer.linux-tage.de/2007/info/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>3</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>3</month>
      <day>4</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="DE">Germany</country>
      <city>Chemnitz</city>
      <site>Technical University Chemnitz</site>
    </location>
    <description>Linuxtage Chemnitz is a two day event on Linux and Free
      Software in general. There will be workshops, talks and room for various
      projects to present themselves. FreeBSD will be present with a booth as
      well as several talks.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="fosdem-2007">
    <name>FOSDEM 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.fosdem.org/2007/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>2</month>
      <day>24</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>2</month>
      <day>25</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="BE">Belgium</country>
      <city>Brussels</city>
      <site>Universite Libre de Bruxelles</site>
    </location>
    <description>A 2-day event to promote the widespread use of Free and
      Open Source software. Several BSD developers, including FreeBSD developers,
      will be present.</description>
  </event>

  <event id="scale-2007">
    <name>SCALE: Southern California Linux Expo 2007</name>
    <url>http://www.socallinuxexpo.org/</url>
    <startdate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>2</month>
      <day>10</day>
    </startdate>
    <enddate>
      <year>2007</year>
      <month>2</month>
      <day>11</day>
    </enddate>
    <location>
      <country code="US">USA</country>
      <state>California</state>
      <city>Los Angeles</city>
      <site>The Westin Los Angeles Airport</site>
    </location>
    <description>The fifth Southern California Linux Expo will have
      an <a href="http://www.socallinuxexpo.org/scale5x/exhibitions/freebsd.php">
      exhibition booth</a> on FreeBSD.  A computer will be available
      and CDROMs provided by <a href="http://www.freebsdmall.com/">FreeBSD Mall</a>
      will be handed out.</description>
  </event>
</events>
