<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Documentation Project">
]>
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>Overview</h2>

    <p>Getting to grips with a new and complex operating system is always a
      difficult task, no matter how pretty the GUI is. FreeBSD is no different
      in this respect.</p>

    <p>While there are a vast number of BSD Unix (and general &unix;) books
      available, FreeBSD has its own unique features, procedures and
      quirks.</p>

    <p>In addition, FreeBSD will be the first exposure to a Unix-like
      operating system for some of its users, so the availability of high
      quality, accurate documentation is paramount.</p>

    <p>The FreeBSD Documentation Project exists to help fill this gap. There
      are two ways in which this is undertaken:</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>Members of the Documentation Project write documentation and
	  submit it for inclusion in the <em>FreeBSD Documentation
	    Set</em>.</p></li>

      <li><p>Members of the Documentation Project discuss and arrange the
	  formatting and organization of the <em>FreeBSD Documentation
	    Set</em>.</p></li>
    </ol>

    <table class="tblbasic">
      <tbody>
      <tr>
	<td><h2 align="center">Current projects</h2>

	  <p>There are a number of projects currently <em>in progress</em> as
	    part of the documentation effort. Please take the time to look over
	    <a href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/DocIdeaList">the current list of projects</a>
	    and see if there is anything <b>you</b> can help
	    with.</p></td>
      </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>

    <h2><a href="who.html">Who we are, how to join</a></h2>

    <p>This page explains who makes up the Documentation Project, and how
      you can join.</p>

    <h2><a href="doc-set.html">The FreeBSD Documentation Set</a></h2>

    <p>This page outlines the components of the FreeBSD Documentation Set, and
      the sort of work that the Documentation Project does with them.</p>

    <h2><a href="submitting.html">Submitting Documentation</a></h2>

    <p>Submitting documentation is the best way to become a part of the
      project, and help make FreeBSD easier to use. This page explains the
      best way to submit documentation so that it gets looked at as soon as
      possible.</p>

    <h2><a href="translations.html">Translation</a></h2>
    <p>Translations of the FreeBSD documentation, Web pages,
      Handbook, Manual pages and FAQ.</p>

  </body>
</html>
