<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY url.articles "../doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles">
<!ENTITY url.books "../doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books">
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Documentation Project: Submitting documentation">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>I have written some documentation. How do I submit it?</h2>

    <p>First, thank you for taking the time to do this.</p>

    <p>You should make your documentation available for review. If you can,
      upload it to a website somewhere.</p>

    <p>Then post a message to the <tt>FreeBSD-doc</tt> mailing list, with a brief outline of
      the documentation and the pointer to its location, and solicit
      feedback.</p>

    <p>If, for some reason, you cannot put the documentation on
      a website somewhere you can send it directly to the <tt>FreeBSD-doc</tt> mailing list.
      If you do this, please only send plain-text documents.</p>

    <p>You may wish to cc: this request for comments to another appropriate
      mailing list. For example, something that relates to how to use Subversion to
      keep your source tree up to date would be of interest to the subscribers
      of the <tt>FreeBSD-stable</tt> mailing list.  Please only cc: at most
      one other mailing list.</p>

    <p>After people have looked over your documentation, and you have had
      the chance to incorporate any of their suggestions, you are ready
      to submit it.</p>

    <p>The correct way to do this is to open a Problem Report.  Instructions
      for doing this can be found at
      <a href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/support/bugreports.html">https://www.FreeBSD.org/support/bugreports.html</a>.</p>

    <p>You do this so that your submission can be tracked. When you submit a PR
      (Problem Report) it is assigned a unique number. One of the committers
      can then assign the PR to themselves, and liaise with you on committing
      the new documentation.
      For more information, see
      <a href="&url.articles;/problem-reports/">Writing FreeBSD Problem Reports</a>.</p>

    <p>Make sure the "Product" is set to "Documentation" and that the
      "Component" is set to either "Documentation" or "Website" as
      appropriate.  You should attach your files from earlier to the PR.
      Please also provide links to the mailing list posts where your changes
      were discussed, if appropriate.</p>

    <h2>I have made some changes to existing documentation, how do I submit
      them?</h2>

    <p>Again, thank you for taking the time to do this.</p>

    <p>First off, you need to produce a special file called a <i>diff</i>.
      This diff shows just the changes that you have made. This makes it easier
      for the person doing the committing to see what you have changed, and
      means you do not need to spend lots of time explaining what you have
      changed (although you should still explain why you think the change
      should be made).</p>

    <p>To make a 'diff', you should;</p>

    <ol>
      <li><p>Make a copy of the file you are going to change. If you are
	  changing <tt>foo.xml</tt>, do</p>

	<pre>
    % <b>cp foo.xml foo.xml.old</b>
	</pre></li>

      <li><p>Then, make your changes to foo.xml</p>

	<pre>
    % <b>vi foo.xml</b>
    ... tap tap tap ...

    ... test the changes, read them for typos and so on ...
	</pre></li>

      <li><p>Make the diff. The command to do this is</p>

	<pre>
    % <b>diff -u foo.xml.old foo.xml > foo.diff</b>
	</pre>

	<p>This looks at the difference between the two files, and writes them
	  to the file <tt>foo.diff</tt>.</p></li>
    </ol>

    <p>You can then send <tt>foo.diff</tt> back to the project.  Send a PR as
      described earlier, and attach the <tt>foo.diff</tt> file to the
      PR.</p>

    <h2>Further reading</h2>
    <ul>
      <li><a
        href="&url.books;/fdp-primer/index.html">Documentation
        Project Primer for New Contributors</a></li>
      <li><a href="docproj.html">&os; Documentation Project
        Home</a></li>
    </ul>
  </body>
</html>
