<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD 8.0-RELEASE Announcement">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.download">

<h2>
FreeBSD Project Announces Release of FreeBSD Version 8.0
</h2>

<h3>
Release includes enhanced virtualization support, NFSv4, and 802.11s D3.03
wireless mesh networking
</h3>

<p>
San Jose, CA (PRWEB) November 25, 2009 -- The FreeBSD Project has announced
the release of FreeBSD Version 8.0. This next major release branch of FreeBSD
delivers a large number of new technologies into the hands of an
ever-increasing number of users. Key release focuses include wireless
networking, virtualization, and storage technology.
</p>

<p>
802.11 wireless networking has been overhauled to add Virtual Access Points
(VAP) support, which allows multiple wireless networks to be hosted from a
single access point. Draft 802.11 mesh networking support allows
FreeBSD-based devices to dynamically link together to create a larger
wireless network. Also added are TDMA extensions to 802.11, targeted at
long-haul WiFi networks.
</p>

<p>
FreeBSD 8.0's network stack also offers multiprocessing optimizations: a
revised link layer subsystem, per-CPU flow cache, multiqueue transmit
support, and significant UDP and TCP protocol scalability improvements.
Zero-copy buffer extensions to BPF improve high volume packet capture
performance.
</p>

<p>
In FreeBSD 8.0, virtual machine administrators in FreeBSD's ground-breaking
lightweight "Jails" can now create their own nested jails. FreeBSD now
supports host and guest modes in VirtualBox, and can run as a 32-bit Xen
DomU guest.
</p>

<p>
The Network File System (NFS) implementation has been enhanced with GSSAPI
encryption, and also experimental NFSv4 client and server support. In
addition to ZFS moving from experimental to production status, FreeBSD 8.0
introduces GPT boot support.
</p>

<p>
Other notable updates in FreeBSD Version 8.0 include:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Experimental MIPS support based on a contribution from Juniper
  Networks.</li>
<li>Countless SMP scalability improvements significantly aid performance on
  16-core systems.</li>
<li>File system scalability improvements as a result of reimplemented VFS
  locking.</li>
<li>Improved exploit mitigation for buffer overflows and kernel NULL pointer
  vulnerabilities.</li>
<li>The extensible kernel security framework (MAC Framework) is now available
  out-of-the-box.</li>
<li>A ground-up rewrite of the USB stack improving performance, device
  support, and adding USB target mode.</li>
</ul>

<p>
"FreeBSD 8.0's wireless network stack is the industry leader, and makes
FreeBSD the platform of choice for a future generation of networking
products," said FreeBSD Core Team member Robert Watson. "Enterprise
consumers will appreciate 8.0's improved virtualization, storage, and
multiprocessor scalability."
</p>

<h3>
About The FreeBSD Project:
</h3>

<p>
FreeBSD is an advanced operating system for modern server, desktop, and
embedded computer platforms. FreeBSD's code base has undergone over thirty
years of continuous development, improvement, and optimization. It is
developed and maintained by a large team of individuals. FreeBSD provides
advanced networking, impressive security features, and world class
performance and is used by some of the world's busiest web sites and most
pervasive embedded networking and storage devices. The FreeBSD Project's web
site is at <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/">http://www.FreeBSD.org</a>
</p>

<h3>
About The FreeBSD Foundation
</h3>

<p>
The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization dedicated to
supporting the FreeBSD Project. The Foundation gratefully accepts donations
from individuals and businesses, using them to fund projects, which further
the development of the FreeBSD operating system. In addition, the Foundation
represents the FreeBSD Project in executing contracts, license agreements,
and other legal arrangements that require a recognized legal entity. The
FreeBSD Foundation is entirely supported by donations. More information about
the FreeBSD Foundation is available on the web at <a
href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/">http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/</a>.
</p>


  </body>
</html>
