<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--
     The FreeBSD Documentation Project

     $FreeBSD$
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="l10n">
    <title>Localization and Internationalization - L10N and I18N</title>

    <sect1 xml:id="l10n-programming">
      <title>Programming I18N Compliant Applications</title>
      <indexterm><primary>Qt</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>GTK</primary></indexterm>
      <para>To make your application more useful for speakers of other
	languages, we hope that you will program I18N compliant.  The GNU
	gcc compiler and GUI libraries like QT and GTK support I18N through
	special handling of strings.  Making a program I18N compliant is
	very easy.  It allows contributors to port your application to
	other languages quickly.  Refer to the library specific I18N
	documentation for more details.</para>

      <para>In contrast with common perception, I18N compliant code is
	easy to write.  Usually, it only involves wrapping your strings
	with library specific functions.  In addition, please be sure to
	allow for wide or multibyte character support.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>A Call to Unify the I18N Effort</title>

	<para>It has come to our attention that the individual I18N/L10N
	  efforts for each country has been repeating each others'
	  efforts.  Many of us have been reinventing the wheel repeatedly
	  and inefficiently.  We hope that the various major groups in
	  I18N could congregate into a group effort similar to the Core
	  Team's responsibility.</para>

	<para>Currently, we hope that, when you write or port I18N
	  programs, you would send it out to each country's related
	  FreeBSD mailing list for testing.  In the future, we hope to
	  create applications that work in all the languages
	  out-of-the-box without dirty hacks.</para>

	<para>The &a.i18n; has been established.  If you are an I18N/L10N
	  developer, please send your comments, ideas, questions, and
	  anything you deem related to it.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Perl and Python</title>
        <indexterm>
         <primary>Perl</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Python</primary>
        </indexterm>

	<para>Perl and Python have I18N and wide character handling
	  libraries.  Please use them for I18N compliance.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="posix-nls">
      <info><title>Localized Messages with POSIX.1 Native Language Support (NLS)</title>
	<authorgroup>
	  <author><personname><firstname>G&aacute;bor</firstname><surname>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</surname></personname><contrib>Contributed by </contrib></author>
	</authorgroup>
      </info>

      

      <para>Beyond the basic I18N functions, like supporting various input
	encodings or supporting national conventions, such as the different
	decimal	separators, at a higher level of I18N, it is possible to localize the
	messages written to the output by the various programs.  A common way of doing
	this is using the POSIX.1 NLS functions, which are provided as a part
	of the &os; base system.</para>

      <sect2 xml:id="nls-catalogs">
	<title>Organizing Localized Messages into Catalog Files</title>

	<para>POSIX.1 NLS is based on catalog files, which contain the
	  localized messages in the desired encoding.  The messages are
	  organized into sets and each message is identified by an integer
	  number in the containing set.  The catalog files are conventionally
	  named after the locale they contain localized messages for, followed
	  by the <literal>.msg</literal> extension.  For instance, the
	  Hungarian messages for ISO8859-2 encoding should be stored in a file
	  called <filename>hu_HU.ISO8859-2</filename>.</para>

	<para>These catalog files are common text files that contain the
	  numbered messages.  It is possible to write comments by starting
	  the line with a <literal>$</literal> sign.  Set boundaries are also separated by
	  special comments, where the keyword <literal>set</literal> must
	  directly follow the <literal>$</literal> sign.  The <literal>set</literal> keyword
	  is then followed by the set number.  For example:</para>

	<programlisting>$set 1</programlisting>

	<para>The actual message entries start with the message number and
	  followed by the localized message.  The well-known
	  modifiers from &man.printf.3; are accepted:</para>

	<programlisting>15 "File not found: %s\n"</programlisting>

	<para>The language catalog files have to be compiled into a binary
	  form before they can be opened from the program.  This conversion
	  is done with the &man.gencat.1; utility.  Its first argument is the
	  filename of the compiled catalog and its further arguments are the
	  input catalogs.  The localized messages can also be organized into
	  more catalog files and then all of them can be processed with
	  &man.gencat.1;.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="nls-using">
	<title>Using the Catalog Files from the Source Code</title>

	<para>Using the catalog files is simple.  To use
	  the related functions, <filename>nl_types.h</filename> must be included.  Before
	  using a catalog, it has to be opened with &man.catopen.3;.
	  The function takes two arguments.  The first parameter is the name of the
	  installed and compiled catalog.  Usually, the name of the
	  program is used, such as <application>grep</application>.
	  This name will be used when looking for the compiled
	  catalog file.  The &man.catopen.3; call looks for this file
	  in <filename>/usr/share/nls/<replaceable>locale</replaceable>/<replaceable>catname</replaceable></filename>
	  and in <filename>/usr/local/share/nls/<replaceable>locale</replaceable>/<replaceable>catname</replaceable></filename>,
	  where <literal>locale</literal> is the locale set and
	  <literal>catname</literal> is the catalog name being
	  discussed.  The second parameter is a constant, which can have
	  two values:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><literal>NL_CAT_LOCALE</literal>, which means that
	      the used catalog file will be based on
	      <envar>LC_MESSAGES</envar>.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><literal>0</literal>, which means that
	      <envar>LANG</envar> has to be used to open
	      the proper catalog.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>The &man.catopen.3; call returns a catalog identifier of
	  type <literal>nl_catd</literal>.  Please refer to the manual page for a list of possible returned error
	  codes.</para>

	<para>After opening a catalog &man.catgets.3; can be used to retrieve
	  a message.  The first parameter is the catalog identifier returned
	  by &man.catopen.3;, the second one is the number of the set, the
	  third one is the number of the messages, and the fourth one is a
	  fallback message, which will be returned if the requested message
	  cannot be retrieved from the catalog file.</para>

	<para>After using the catalog file, it must be closed by calling
	  &man.catclose.3;, which has one argument, the catalog id.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="nls-example">
	<title>A Practical Example</title>

	<para>The following example will demonstrate an easy solution on how to
	  use NLS catalogs in a flexible way.</para>

	<para>The below lines need to be put into a common header file of
	  the program, which is included into all source files where
	  localized messages are necessary:</para>

	<programlisting>
#ifdef WITHOUT_NLS
#define getstr(n)	 nlsstr[n]
#else
#include &lt;nl_types.h&gt;

extern nl_catd		 catalog;
#define getstr(n)	 catgets(catalog, 1, n, nlsstr[n])
#endif

extern char		*nlsstr[];</programlisting>

	<para>Next, put these lines into the global declaration part of the
	  main source file:</para>

	<programlisting>
#ifndef WITHOUT_NLS
#include &lt;nl_types.h&gt;
nl_catd	 catalog;
#endif

/*
 * Default messages to use when NLS is disabled or no catalog
 * is found.
 */
char    *nlsstr[] = {
        "",
/* 1*/  "some random message",
/* 2*/  "some other message"
};</programlisting>

	<para>Next come the real code snippets, which open, read, and
	  close the catalog:</para>

	<programlisting>
#ifndef WITHOUT_NLS
	catalog = catopen("myapp", NL_CAT_LOCALE);
#endif

...

printf(getstr(1));

...

#ifndef WITHOUT_NLS
	catclose(catalog);
#endif</programlisting>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Reducing Strings to Localize</title>

	  <para>There is a good way of reducing the strings that
	    need to be localized by using <application>libc</application>
	    error messages.  This is also useful to just avoid duplication
	    and provide consistent error messages for the common errors
	    that can be encountered by a great many of programs.</para>

	  <para>First, here is an example that does not use
	    <application>libc</application> error messages:</para>

	  <programlisting>
#include &lt;err.h&gt;
...
if (!S_ISDIR(st.st_mode))
	errx(1, "argument is not a directory");
	  </programlisting>

	  <para>This can be transformed to print an error message by
	    reading <varname>errno</varname> and printing an error message
	    accordingly:</para>

	  <programlisting>
#include &lt;err.h&gt;
#include &lt;errno.h&gt;
...
if (!S_ISDIR(st.st_mode)) {
	errno = ENOTDIR;
	err(1, NULL);
}
	  </programlisting>

	  <para>In this example, the custom string is eliminated, thus
	    translators will have less work when localizing the program
	    and users will see the usual <quote>Not a directory</quote>
	    error message when they encounter this error.  This message
	    will probably seem more familiar to them.  Please note that
	    it was necessary to include <filename>errno.h</filename> in order to directly
	    access <varname>errno</varname>.</para>

	  <para>It is worth to note that there are cases when
	    <varname>errno</varname> is set automatically by a preceding
	    call, so it is not necessary to set it explicitly:</para>

	  <programlisting>
#include &lt;err.h&gt;
...
if ((p = malloc(size)) == NULL)
	err(1, NULL);
	  </programlisting>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="nls-mk">
	<title>Making use of <filename>bsd.nls.mk</filename></title>

	<para>Using the catalog files requires few repeatable steps,
	  such as compiling the catalogs and installing them to the
	  proper location.  In order to simplify this process even
	  more, <filename>bsd.nls.mk</filename> introduces some macros.
	  It is not necessary to include <filename>bsd.nls.mk</filename>
	  explicitly, it is pulled in from the common Makefiles,
	  such as <filename>bsd.prog.mk</filename> or
	  <filename>bsd.lib.mk</filename>.</para>

	<para>Usually it is enough to define <varname>NLSNAME</varname>,
	  which should have the catalog name mentioned as the first
	  argument of &man.catopen.3; and list the catalog files in
	  <varname>NLS</varname> without their <literal>.msg</literal>
	  extension.  Here is an example, which makes it possible to
	  to disable NLS when used with the code examples before.
	  The <varname>WITHOUT_NLS</varname> &man.make.1; variable has
	  to be defined in order to build the program without NLS
	  support.</para>

	<programlisting>
.if !defined(WITHOUT_NLS)
NLS=	es_ES.ISO8859-1
NLS+=	hu_HU.ISO8859-2
NLS+=	pt_BR.ISO8859-1
.else
CFLAGS+=	-DWITHOUT_NLS
.endif</programlisting>

	<para>Conventionally, the catalog files are placed under the
	  <filename>nls</filename> subdirectory and
	  this is the default behavior of <filename>bsd.nls.mk</filename>.
	  It is possible, though to override the location of the
	  catalogs with the <varname>NLSSRCDIR</varname> &man.make.1;
	  variable.  The default name of the precompiled catalog files
	  also follow the naming convention mentioned before.  It can be
	  overridden by setting the <varname>NLSNAME</varname> variable.
	  There are other options to fine tune the processing of the catalog
	  files but usually it is not needed, thus they are not described
	  here.  For further information on <filename>bsd.nls.mk</filename>,
	  please refer to the file itself, it is short and easy to
	  understand.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
