<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rel '4.8-RELEASE'>
<!ENTITY title "Testing Guide for &rel;">
<!ENTITY email "qa">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.download">

<h3>Goals</h3>

<p>As part of our on-going effort to improve the release engineering
  process, we have identified several areas that need significant
  quality assurance testing during the release candidate phase.
  Below, we've listed the changes in &rel; that we feel merit
  the most attention due to their involving substantial changes to the
  system, or having arrived late in the development cycle leading up
  to the release.  In general, our goal in the QA process is to
  attempt to check a number of things:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The system has not regressed with respects to stability, correctness,
    interoperability, or performance of features present in prior
    releases.<br/><br/></li>

  <li>New features result in the desired improvement in stability,
    correctness, interoperability, or performance.</li>
</ul>

<p>To effectively determine this, it's desirable to test the system in
  a diverse set of environments, applying a wide set of workloads,
  forcing the system to operate both within and outside its normal
  specification.  Particular focus should often be placed on the
  continuing (or new) capability of the system to perform correctly
  when used in concert with systems from other vendors.</p>

<h3>Features to explore carefully:</h3>

<ul>

  <li><p><strong>OpenSSL</strong>.  OpenSSL was updated to 0.9.7a.
    Please test any SSL consumers on your system to make sure there
    have been no regressions in functionality.</p></li>

  <li><p><strong>IPFilter</strong> has recently been updated to
    version 3.4.31 and has not yet been thoroughly tested in
    -STABLE.</p></li>

  <li><p><strong>Firewire</strong></p></li>

  <li><p><strong>libc_r</strong> - A change has been made to fix
    libc_r in the case
    when a non-standard value of KVA_PAGES is used in the kernel.
    libc_r in general could use testing with real applications.</p></li>

  <li><p><strong>dlinfo()</strong> added - test your shared-library
    heavy ports to make sure there are no build problems.</p></li>

  <li><p><strong>ISC DHCP 3.0.1 RC11</strong> has recently been added
    to 4.8RC.  This
    version of the ISC DHCP client was used in 5.0-RELEASE, and should
    be well tested, but it was only recently made available to
    4.X-STABLE users so it has not received much testing to date in
    that environment.</p></li>

<!--  <li><p><strong>if_dc, if -->
</ul>

<p>The <a href="../../relnotes.html">release notes</a> will always be
  a good place to look for things to test.</p>

<h3>Known Issues</h3>
<ul>

  <li><p>Disks attached to a Mylex controller are not seen by
    sysinstall.  There is a problem because this module is loaded from
    the mfsroot floppy and the equivalent of a "camcontrol rescan" is
    not performed to discover disks after the module has loaded.
    Found by Julian.  Fixed by scottl Mar 28.</p></li>

  <li><p>GNOME2 does not work until the user manually runs 'fc-cache -f'.
    marcus@ has committed a fix to the port, murray@ has manually
    hacked some packages to test the proposed fixes, and kris@ will
    rebuild 150+ GNOME ports</p></li>
</ul>

</body>
</html>
