<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
	"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<!-- The FreeBSD Documentation Project -->
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:lang="en">
  <info>
    <title>Explaining BSD</title>

    <author><personname><firstname>Greg</firstname><surname>Lehey</surname></personname><affiliation>
	<address><email>grog@FreeBSD.org</email></address>
      </affiliation></author>

    <legalnotice xml:id="trademarks" role="trademarks">
      &tm-attrib.freebsd;
      &tm-attrib.amd;
      &tm-attrib.apple;
      &tm-attrib.intel;
      &tm-attrib.linux;
      &tm-attrib.opengroup;
      &tm-attrib.sparc;
      &tm-attrib.sun;
      &tm-attrib.unix;
      &tm-attrib.general;
    </legalnotice>

    <pubdate>$FreeBSD$</pubdate>

    <releaseinfo>$FreeBSD$</releaseinfo>

    <abstract>
      <para>In the open source world, the word <quote>Linux</quote> is
	almost synonymous with <quote>Operating System</quote>, but it
	is not the only open source &unix; operating system.</para>

      <para>So what is the secret?  Why is BSD not better known?  This
	white paper addresses these and other questions.</para>

      <para>Throughout this paper, differences between BSD and Linux
	will be noted <emphasis>like this</emphasis>.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <sect1 xml:id="what-is-bsd">
    <title>What is BSD?</title>

    <para>BSD stands for <quote>Berkeley Software
	Distribution</quote>.  It is the name of distributions of
      source code from the University of California, Berkeley, which
      were originally extensions to AT&amp;T's Research &unix;
      operating system.  Several open source operating system projects
      are based on a release of this source code known as 4.4BSD-Lite.
      In addition, they comprise a number of packages from other Open
      Source projects, including notably the GNU project.  The overall
      operating system comprises:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The BSD kernel, which handles process scheduling, memory
	  management, symmetric multi-processing (SMP), device
	  drivers, etc.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The C library, the base API for the system.</para>

	<para><emphasis>The BSD C library is based on code from
	    Berkeley, not the GNU project.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Utilities such as shells, file utilities, compilers and
	  linkers.</para>

	<para><emphasis>Some of the utilities are derived from the GNU
	    project, others are not.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The X Window system, which handles graphical
	  display.</para>

	<para>The X Window system used in most versions of BSD is
	  maintained by the <link xlink:href="http://www.X.org/">X.Org
	    project</link>.  &os; allows the user to choose from a
	  variety of desktop environments, such as
	  <application>Gnome</application>,
	  <application>KDE</application>, or
	  <application>Xfce</application>; and lightweight window
	  managers like <application>Openbox</application>,
	  <application>Fluxbox</application>, or
	  <application>Awesome</application>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Many other programs and utilities.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="what-a-real-unix">
    <title>What, a real &unix;?</title>

    <para>The BSD operating systems are not clones, but open source
      derivatives of AT&amp;T's Research &unix; operating system,
      which is also the ancestor of the modern &unix; System V.  This
      may surprise you.  How could that happen when AT&amp;T has never
      released its code as open source?</para>

    <para>It is true that AT&amp;T &unix; is not open source, and in a
      copyright sense BSD is very definitely <emphasis>not</emphasis>
      &unix;, but on the other hand, AT&amp;T has imported sources
      from other projects, noticeably the Computer Sciences Research
      Group (CSRG) of the University of California in Berkeley, CA.
      Starting in 1976, the CSRG started releasing tapes of their
      software, calling them <emphasis>Berkeley Software
	Distribution</emphasis> or <emphasis>BSD</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Initial BSD releases consisted mainly of user programs, but
      that changed dramatically when the CSRG landed a contract with
      the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) to upgrade
      the communications protocols on their network, ARPANET.  The new
      protocols were known as the <emphasis>Internet
	Protocols</emphasis>, later <emphasis>TCP/IP</emphasis> after
      the most important protocols.  The first widely distributed
      implementation was part of 4.2BSD, in 1982.</para>

    <para>In the course of the 1980s, a number of new workstation
      companies sprang up.  Many preferred to license &unix; rather
      than developing operating systems for themselves.  In
      particular, Sun Microsystems licensed &unix; and implemented a
      version of 4.2BSD, which they called &sunos;.  When AT&amp;T
      themselves were allowed to sell &unix; commercially, they
      started with a somewhat bare-bones implementation called System
      III, to be quickly followed by System V.  The System V code base
      did not include networking, so all implementations included
      additional software from the BSD, including the TCP/IP software,
      but also utilities such as the <emphasis>csh</emphasis> shell
      and the <emphasis>vi</emphasis> editor.  Collectively, these
      enhancements were known as the <emphasis>Berkeley
	Extensions</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The BSD tapes contained AT&amp;T source code and thus
      required a &unix; source license.  By 1990, the CSRG's funding
      was running out, and it faced closure.  Some members of the
      group decided to release the BSD code, which was Open Source,
      without the AT&amp;T proprietary code.  This finally happened
      with the <emphasis>Networking Tape 2</emphasis>, usually known
      as <emphasis>Net/2</emphasis>.  Net/2 was not a complete
      operating system: about 20% of the kernel code was missing.  One
      of the CSRG members, William F. Jolitz, wrote the remaining code
      and released it in early 1992 as <emphasis>386BSD</emphasis>.
      At the same time, another group of ex-CSRG members formed a
      commercial company called <link
	xlink:href="http://www.bsdi.com/">Berkeley Software Design
	Inc.</link> and released a beta version of an operating system
      called <link xlink:href="http://www.bsdi.com/">BSD/386</link>,
      which was based on the same sources.  The name of the operating
      system was later changed to BSD/OS.</para>

    <para>386BSD never became a stable operating system.  Instead, two
      other projects split off from it in 1993: <link
	xlink:href="http://www.NetBSD.org/">NetBSD</link> and <link
	xlink:href="&url.base;/index.html">FreeBSD</link>.  The two
      projects originally diverged due to differences in patience
      waiting for improvements to 386BSD: the NetBSD people started
      early in the year, and the first version of FreeBSD was not
      ready until the end of the year.  In the meantime, the code base
      had diverged sufficiently to make it difficult to merge.  In
      addition, the projects had different aims, as we will see below.
      In 1996, <link
	xlink:href="http://www.OpenBSD.org/">OpenBSD</link> split off
      from NetBSD, and in 2003, <link
	xlink:href="http://www.dragonflybsd.org/">DragonFlyBSD</link>
      split off from FreeBSD.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="why-is-bsd-not-better-known">
    <title>Why is BSD not better known?</title>

    <para>For a number of reasons, BSD is relatively unknown:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The BSD developers are often more interested in
	  polishing their code than marketing it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Much of Linux's popularity is due to factors external to
	  the Linux projects, such as the press, and to companies
	  formed to provide Linux services.  Until recently, the open
	  source BSDs had no such proponents.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>In 1992, AT&amp;T sued <link
	    xlink:href="http://www.bsdi.com/">BSDI</link>, the vendor
	  of BSD/386, alleging that the product contained
	  AT&amp;T-copyrighted code.  The case was settled out of
	  court in 1994, but the spectre of the litigation continues
	  to haunt people.  In March 2000 an article published on the
	  web claimed that the court case had been <quote>recently
	    settled</quote>.</para>

	<para>One detail that the lawsuit did clarify is the naming:
	  in the 1980s, BSD was known as <quote>BSD &unix;</quote>.
	  With the elimination of the last vestige of AT&amp;T code
	  from BSD, it also lost the right to the name &unix;.  Thus
	  you will see references in book titles to <quote>the 4.3BSD
	    &unix; operating system</quote> and <quote>the 4.4BSD
	    operating system</quote>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="comparing-bsd-and-linux">
    <title>Comparing BSD and Linux</title>

    <para>So what is really the difference between, say, Debian Linux
      and FreeBSD?  For the average user, the difference is
      surprisingly small: Both are &unix; like operating systems.
      Both are developed by non-commercial projects (this does not
      apply to many other Linux distributions, of course).  In the
      following section, we will look at BSD and compare it to Linux.
      The description applies most closely to FreeBSD, which accounts
      for an estimated 80% of the BSD installations, but the
      differences from NetBSD, OpenBSD and DragonFlyBSD are
      small.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Who owns BSD?</title>

      <para>No one person or corporation owns BSD. It is created and
	distributed by a community of highly technical and committed
	contributors all over the world.  Some of the components of
	BSD are Open Source projects in their own right and managed by
	different project maintainers.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How is BSD developed and updated?</title>

      <para>The BSD kernels are developed and updated following the
	Open Source development model.  Each project maintains a
	publicly accessible <emphasis>source tree</emphasis> which
	contains all source files for the project, including
	documentation and other incidental files.  Users can obtain a
	complete copy of any version.</para>

      <para>A large number of developers worldwide contribute to
	improvements to BSD.  They are divided into three
	kinds:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><firstterm>Contributors</firstterm> write code or
	    documentation.  They are not permitted to commit (add
	    code) directly to the source tree.  In order for their
	    code to be included in the system, it must be reviewed and
	    checked in by a registered developer, known as a
	    <emphasis>committer</emphasis>.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><firstterm>Committers</firstterm> are developers with
	    write access to the source tree.  In order to become a
	    committer, an individual must show ability in the area in
	    which they are active.</para>

	  <para>It is at the individual committer's discretion whether
	    they should obtain authority before committing changes to
	    the source tree.  In general, an experienced committer may
	    make changes which are obviously correct without obtaining
	    consensus.  For example, a documentation project committer
	    may correct typographical or grammatical errors without
	    review.  On the other hand, developers making far-reaching
	    or complicated changes are expected to submit their
	    changes for review before committing them.  In extreme
	    cases, a core team member with a function such as
	    Principal Architect may order that changes be removed from
	    the tree, a process known as <firstterm>backing
	      out</firstterm>.  All committers receive mail describing
	    each individual commit, so it is not possible to commit
	    secretly.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>The <firstterm>Core team</firstterm>.  FreeBSD and
	    NetBSD each have a core team which manages the project.
	    The core teams developed in the course of the projects,
	    and their role is not always well-defined.  It is not
	    necessary to be a developer in order to be a core team
	    member, though it is normal.  The rules for the core team
	    vary from one project to the other, but in general they
	    have more say in the direction of the project than
	    non-core team members have.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This arrangement differs from Linux in a number of
	ways:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>No one person controls the content of the system.  In
	    practice, this difference is overrated, since the
	    Principal Architect can require that code be backed out,
	    and even in the Linux project several people are permitted
	    to make changes.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>On the other hand, there <emphasis>is</emphasis> a
	    central repository, a single place where you can find the
	    entire operating system sources, including all older
	    versions.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>BSD projects maintain the entire <quote>Operating
	      System</quote>, not only the kernel.  This distinction
	    is only marginally useful: neither BSD nor Linux is useful
	    without applications.  The applications used under BSD are
	    frequently the same as the applications used under
	    Linux.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>As a result of the formalized maintenance of a single
	    SVN source tree, BSD development is clear, and it is
	    possible to access any version of the system by release
	    number or by date.  SVN also allows incremental updates to
	    the system: for example, the FreeBSD repository is updated
	    about 100 times a day.  Most of these changes are
	    small.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>BSD releases</title>

      <para>FreeBSD, NetBSD and OpenBSD provide the system in three
	different <quote>releases</quote>.  As with Linux, releases
	are assigned a number such as 1.4.1 or 3.5.  In addition, the
	version number has a suffix indicating its purpose:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The development version of the system is called
	    <firstterm>CURRENT</firstterm>.  FreeBSD assigns a number
	    to CURRENT, for example FreeBSD 5.0-CURRENT.  NetBSD uses
	    a slightly different naming scheme and appends a
	    single-letter suffix which indicates changes in the
	    internal interfaces, for example NetBSD 1.4.3G.  OpenBSD
	    does not assign a number (<quote>OpenBSD-current</quote>).
	    All new development on the system goes into this
	    branch.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>At regular intervals, between two and four times a
	    year, the projects bring out a
	    <firstterm>RELEASE</firstterm> version of the system,
	    which is available on CD-ROM and for free download from
	    FTP sites, for example OpenBSD 2.6-RELEASE or NetBSD
	    1.4-RELEASE.  The RELEASE version is intended for end
	    users and is the normal version of the system.  NetBSD
	    also provides <emphasis>patch releases</emphasis> with a
	    third digit, for example NetBSD 1.4.2.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>As bugs are found in a RELEASE version, they are
	    fixed, and the fixes are added to the SVN tree.  In
	    FreeBSD, the resultant version is called the
	    <firstterm>STABLE</firstterm> version, while in NetBSD and
	    OpenBSD it continues to be called the RELEASE version.
	    Smaller new features can also be added to this branch
	    after a period of test in the CURRENT branch.  Security
	    and other important bug fixes are also applied to all
	    supported RELEASE versions.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><emphasis>By contrast, Linux maintains two separate code
	  trees: the stable version and the development version.
	  Stable versions have an even minor version number, such as
	  2.0, 2.2 or 2.4.  Development versions have an odd minor
	  version number, such as 2.1, 2.3 or 2.5.  In each case, the
	  number is followed by a further number designating the exact
	  release.  In addition, each vendor adds their own userland
	  programs and utilities, so the name of the distribution is
	  also important.  Each distribution vendor also assigns
	  version numbers to the distribution, so a complete
	  description might be something like <quote>TurboLinux 6.0
	    with kernel 2.2.14</quote></emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What versions of BSD are available?</title>

      <para>In contrast to the numerous Linux distributions, there are
	only four major open source BSDs.  Each BSD project maintains
	its own source tree and its own kernel.  In practice, though,
	there appear to be fewer divergences between the userland code
	of the projects than there is in Linux.</para>

      <para>It is difficult to categorize the goals of each project:
	the differences are very subjective.  Basically,</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>&os; aims for high performance and ease of use by end
	    users, and is a favourite of web content providers.  It
	    runs on a <link xlink:href="&url.base;/platforms/">number
	      of platforms</link> and has significantly more users
	    than the other projects.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>NetBSD aims for maximum portability: <quote>of course
	      it runs NetBSD</quote>.  It runs on machines from
	    palmtops to large servers, and has even been used on NASA
	    space missions.  It is a particularly good choice for
	    running on old non-&intel; hardware.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>OpenBSD aims for security and code purity: it uses a
	    combination of the open source concept and rigorous code
	    reviews to create a system which is demonstrably correct,
	    making it the choice of security-conscious organizations
	    such as banks, stock exchanges and US Government
	    departments.  Like NetBSD, it runs on a number of
	    platforms.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>DragonFlyBSD aims for high performance and scalability
	    under everything from a single-node UP system to a
	    massively clustered system.  DragonFlyBSD has several
	    long-range technical goals, but focus lies on providing a
	    SMP-capable infrastructure that is easy to understand,
	    maintain and develop for.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>There are also two additional BSD &unix; operating systems
	which are not open source, BSD/OS and Apple's &macos;
	X:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>BSD/OS was the oldest of the 4.4BSD derivatives.  It
	    was not open source, though source code licenses were
	    available at relatively low cost.  It resembled FreeBSD in
	    many ways.  Two years after the acquisition of BSDi by
	    Wind River Systems, BSD/OS failed to survive as an
	    independent product.  Support and source code may still be
	    available from Wind River, but all new development is
	    focused on the VxWorks embedded operating system.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><link
	      xlink:href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/server/">&macos;
	      X</link> is the latest version of the operating system
	    for &apple;'s &mac; line.  The BSD core of this operating
	    system, <link
	      xlink:href="http://developer.apple.com/darwin/">Darwin</link>,
	    is available as a fully functional open source operating
	    system for x86 and PPC computers.  The Aqua/Quartz
	    graphics system and many other proprietary aspects of
	    &macos; X remain closed-source, however.  Several Darwin
	    developers are also FreeBSD committers, and
	    vice-versa.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How does the BSD license differ from the GNU Public
	license?</title>

      <para>Linux is available under the <link
	  xlink:href="http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU
	  General Public License</link> (GPL), which is designed to
	eliminate closed source software.  In particular, any
	derivative work of a product released under the GPL must also
	be supplied with source code if requested.  By contrast, the
	<link
	  xlink:href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.html">BSD
	  license</link> is less restrictive: binary-only
	distributions are allowed.  This is particularly attractive
	for embedded applications.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What else should I know?</title>

      <para>Since fewer applications are available for BSD than Linux,
	the BSD developers created a Linux compatibility package,
	which allows Linux programs to run under BSD.  The package
	includes both kernel modifications, in order to correctly
	perform Linux system calls, and Linux compatibility files such
	as the C library.  There is no noticeable difference in
	execution speed between a Linux application running on a Linux
	machine and a Linux application running on a BSD machine of
	the same speed.</para>

      <para>The <quote>all from one supplier</quote> nature of BSD
	means that upgrades are much easier to handle than is
	frequently the case with Linux.  BSD handles library version
	upgrades by providing compatibility modules for earlier
	library versions, so it is possible to run binaries which are
	several years old with no problems.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Which should I use, BSD or Linux?</title>

      <para>What does this all mean in practice?  Who should use BSD,
	who should use Linux?</para>

      <para>This is a very difficult question to answer.  Here are
	some guidelines:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><quote>If it ain't broke, don't fix it</quote>: If you
	    already use an open source operating system, and you are
	    happy with it, there is probably no good reason to
	    change.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>BSD systems, in particular FreeBSD, can have notably
	    higher performance than Linux.  But this is not across the
	    board.  In many cases, there is little or no difference in
	    performance.  In some cases, Linux may perform better than
	    FreeBSD.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>In general, BSD systems have a better reputation for
	    reliability, mainly as a result of the more mature code
	    base.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>BSD projects have a better reputation for the quality
	    and completeness of their documentation.  The various
	    documentation projects aim to provide actively updated
	    documentation, in many languages, and covering all aspects
	    of the system.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>The BSD license may be more attractive than the
	    GPL.</para> </listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>BSD can execute most Linux binaries, while Linux can
	    not execute BSD binaries.  Many BSD implementations can
	    also execute binaries from other &unix; like systems.  As
	    a result, BSD may present an easier migration route from
	    other systems than Linux would.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Who provides support, service, and training for
	BSD?</title>

      <para>BSDi / <link
	  xlink:href="http://www.freebsdmall.com">FreeBSD Mall,
	  Inc.</link> have been providing support contracts for
	FreeBSD for nearly a decade.</para>

      <para>In addition, each of the projects has a list of
	consultants for hire: <link
	  xlink:href="&url.base;/commercial/consult_bycat.html">FreeBSD</link>,
	<link
	  xlink:href="http://www.netbsd.org/gallery/consultants.html">NetBSD</link>,
	and <link
	  xlink:href="http://www.openbsd.org/support.html">OpenBSD</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
