<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/doc/share/sgml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Source code repositories">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

    <h2>CVS</h2>

    <p><a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/cgi/man.cgi?cvs">CVS</a> (the
      Concurrent Version System) is the tool we use for keeping our sources
      under control.  Every change (with accompanying log message explaining
      its purpose) from FreeBSD 2.0 to the present is stored here. It can be
      easily viewed from the web interface mentioned below.  To obtain a complete copy
      of the FreeBSD CVS repository or any of the development branches inside
      it, you may choose any one of following options:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/cvsup.html">CVSup</a> if you are looking
	for on-demand, low overhead access using a custom utility (written in
	Modula-3 no less).</li>

      <li><a name="anoncvs" href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/anoncvs.html">anoncvs</a>
	if you are looking for on-demand access that has higher overhead than
	cvsup (in terms of wall time and bytes transferred) but is easier to use
	for checking out small pieces of the tree and requires nothing more
	than the cvs tools already bundled with FreeBSD.</li>

      <li><a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/ctm.html">CTM</a> if you are looking for
	very low overhead, batch-mode access (basically, patches through
	email).</li>

      <li>The <a href="http://cvsweb.FreeBSD.org/">web interface</a>
	if you are looking to simply browse the repository in search of a
	specific change or file revision.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Mirrors of the CVS web interface are available in
      <a href="http://www.cz.FreeBSD.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">Czech republic</a>,
      <a href="http://www.dk.FreeBSD.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">Denmark</a>,
      <a href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">Japan</a>,
      <a href="http://cvsweb.FreeBSD.org/">USA/California</a>.
      </p>

    <h2>Subversion</h2>

    <p>In June 2008, development of the base system moved to a different
      version control system, <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>
      (SVN for short).  The <a href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base/">web
      interface</a> is available for browsing the repository.  All changes are
      also exported back to the CVS repository.</p>

    <p>In May 2012, the FreeBSD Documentation Project moved from CVS
      to Subversion.  Unlike the base system, the documentation SVN
      repository is not exported back to CVS.  There is a <a
	href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/doc/">web interface</a>
      available for browsing the contents of the FreeBSD Documentation
      Project SVN repository.</p>


</body>
</html>
