<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Source code repositories">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

    <h2>Subversion</h2>

    <p><a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>
      is the tool the &os;&nbsp;Project uses for keeping its sources
      under control.  Every change (with an accompanying log message
      explaining its purpose) is stored.  It can be
      easily viewed from the web interface mentioned below.</p>

    <p>In June 2008, development of the base system moved to a different
      version control system, <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>
      (SVN for short).  The <a href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base/">web
      interface</a> is available for browsing the repository.  All changes
      to the existing live branches (stable/9 and stable/8) are
      also exported back to the legacy CVS repository, however the
      CVS repositories are deprecated, and so existing users of them
      should move away from doing so.</p>

    <p>In May 2012, the FreeBSD Documentation Project moved from CVS
      to Subversion.  Unlike the base system, the documentation SVN
      repository is not exported back to CVS.  There is a <a
	href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/doc/">web interface</a>
      available for browsing the contents of the FreeBSD Documentation
      Project SVN repository.</p>

    <p>In July 2012, the FreeBSD Ports tree moved from CVS to
      Subversion.  There is a <a
      href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/ports/">web interface</a> for
      browsing the repository.  The Ports tree is also exported back
      to the legacy CVS repository.
      It will cease to be exported early 2013.</p>


    <h2>Legacy - CVS</h2>

    <p><a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/cgi/man.cgi?cvs">CVS</a> (the
      Concurrent Version System) was the tool that the
      &os;&nbsp;Project used to use to keep
      the sources under control.</p>

    <p>The old web interface can be accessed at <a
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">the cvsweb instance
      </a>.</p>

    <h2>Other options</h2>

    <p><a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/ctm.html">
      CTM</a> if you are looking for
      very low overhead, batch-mode access (basically, patches through
      email).</p>
</body>
</html>
