<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--
     The FreeBSD Documentation Project

     $FreeBSD$
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="policies">
  <info>
    <title>Source Tree Guidelines and Policies</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Poul-Henning</firstname>
	  <surname>Kamp</surname>
	</personname>
	<contrib>Contributed by </contrib>
      </author>
      <author>
	<personname>
	  <firstname>Giorgos</firstname>
	  <surname>Keramidas</surname>
	</personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </info>

  <para>This chapter documents various guidelines and policies in
    force for the FreeBSD source tree.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="policies-style">
    <title>Style Guidelines</title>

    <indexterm><primary>style</primary></indexterm>

    <para>Consistent coding style is extremely important, particularly
      with large projects like &os;.  Code should follow the &os;
      coding styles described in &man.style.9; and
      &man.style.Makefile.5;.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="policies-maintainer">
    <title><varname>MAINTAINER</varname> on Makefiles</title>

    <indexterm><primary>ports maintainer</primary></indexterm>

    <para>If a particular portion of the &os;
      <filename>src/</filename> distribution is being maintained by a
      person or group of persons, this is communicated through an
      entry in <filename>src/MAINTAINERS</filename>.  Maintainers of
      ports within the Ports Collection express their maintainership
      to the world by adding a <varname>MAINTAINER</varname> line to
      the <filename>Makefile</filename> of the port in
      question:</para>

    <programlisting><varname>MAINTAINER</varname>= <replaceable>email-addresses</replaceable></programlisting>

    <tip>
      <para>For other parts of the repository, or for sections not
	listed as having a maintainer, or when you are unsure who the
	active maintainer is, try looking at the recent commit history
	of the relevant parts of the source tree.  It is quite often
	the case that a maintainer is not explicitly named, but the
	people who are actively working in a part of the source tree
	for, say, the last couple of years are interested in reviewing
	changes.  Even if this is not specifically mentioned in the
	documentation or the source itself, asking for a review as a
	form of courtesy is a very reasonable thing to do.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>The role of the maintainer is as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>The maintainer owns and is responsible for that code.
	  This means that he or she is responsible for fixing bugs and
	  answering problem reports pertaining to that piece of the
	  code, and in the case of contributed software, for tracking
	  new versions, as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Changes to directories which have a maintainer defined
	  shall be sent to the maintainer for review before being
	  committed.  Only if the maintainer does not respond for an
	  unacceptable period of time, to several emails, will it be
	  acceptable to commit changes without review by the
	  maintainer.  However, it is suggested that you try to have
	  the changes reviewed by someone else if at all
	  possible.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>It is of course not acceptable to add a person or group
	  as maintainer unless they agree to assume this duty.  On the
	  other hand it does not have to be a committer and it can
	  easily be a group of people.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="policies-contributed">
    <info>
      <title>Contributed Software</title>

      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>Poul-Henning</firstname>
	    <surname>Kamp</surname>
	  </personname>
	  <contrib>Contributed by </contrib>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>David</firstname>
	    <surname>O'Brien</surname>
	  </personname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>Gavin</firstname>
	    <surname>Atkinson</surname>
	  </personname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
    </info>

    <indexterm><primary>contributed software</primary></indexterm>

    <para>Some parts of the FreeBSD distribution consist of software
      that is actively being maintained outside the FreeBSD project.
      For historical reasons, we call this
      <emphasis>contributed</emphasis> software.  Some examples are
      <application>sendmail</application>,
      <application>gcc</application> and
      <application>patch</application>.</para>

    <para>Over the last couple of years, various methods have been
      used in dealing with this type of software and all have some
      number of advantages and drawbacks.  No clear winner has
      emerged.</para>

    <para>Since this is the case, after some debate one of these
      methods has been selected as the <quote>official</quote> method
      and will be required for future imports of software of this
      kind.  Furthermore, it is strongly suggested that existing
      contributed software converge on this model over time, as it has
      significant advantages over the old method, including the
      ability to easily obtain diffs relative to the
      <quote>official</quote> versions of the source by everyone (even
      without direct repository access).  This will make it
      significantly easier to return changes to the primary developers
      of the contributed software.</para>

    <para>Ultimately, however, it comes down to the people actually
      doing the work.  If using this model is particularly unsuited to
      the package being dealt with, exceptions to these rules may be
      granted only with the approval of the core team and with the
      general consensus of the other developers.  The ability to
      maintain the package in the future will be a key issue in the
      decisions.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Because it makes it harder to import future versions
	minor, trivial and/or cosmetic changes are
	<emphasis>strongly discouraged</emphasis> on files that are
	still tracking the vendor branch.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2 xml:id="vendor-import-svn">
      <info>
	<title>Vendor Imports with SVN</title>

	<authorgroup>
	  <author>
	    <personname>
	      <firstname>Dag-Erling</firstname>
	      <surname>Sm&oslash;rgrav</surname>
	    </personname>
	    <contrib>Contributed by </contrib>
	  </author>
	</authorgroup>
      </info>

      <para>This section describes the vendor import procedure with
	<application>Subversion</application> in details.</para>

      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <title>Preparing the Tree</title>

	  <para>If this is your first import after the switch to
	    <acronym>SVN</acronym>, you will have to flatten and clean
	    up the vendor tree, and bootstrap merge history in the
	    main tree.  If not, you can safely omit this step.</para>

	  <para>During the conversion from <acronym>CVS</acronym> to
	    <acronym>SVN</acronym>, vendor branches were imported with
	    the same layout as the main tree.  For example, the
	    <application>foo</application> vendor sources ended up in
	    <filename>vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist/contrib/<replaceable>foo</replaceable></filename>,
	    but it is pointless and rather inconvenient.  What we
	    really want is to have the vendor source directly in
	    <filename>vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist</filename>,
	    like this:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>cd vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist/contrib/<replaceable>foo</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn move $(svn list) ../..</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>cd ../..</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn remove contrib</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn propdel -R svn:mergeinfo</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn commit</userinput></screen>

	  <para>Note that, the <literal>propdel</literal> bit is
	    necessary because starting with 1.5, Subversion will
	    automatically add <literal>svn:mergeinfo</literal> to any
	    directory you copy or move.  In this case, you will not
	    need this information, since you are not going to merge
	    anything from the tree you deleted.</para>

	  <note>
	    <para>You may want to flatten the tags as well.  The
	      procedure is exactly the same.  If you do this, put off
	      the commit until the end.</para>
	  </note>

	  <para>Check the <filename>dist</filename> tree and perform
	    any cleanup that is deemed to be necessary.  You may want
	    to disable keyword expansion, as it makes no sense on
	    unmodified vendor code.  In some cases, it can be even be
	    harmful.</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>svn propdel svn:keywords -R .</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn commit</userinput></screen>

	  <para>Bootstrapping of <literal>svn:mergeinfo</literal> on
	    the target directory (in the main tree) to the revision
	    that corresponds to the last change was made to the vendor
	    tree prior to importing new sources is also needed:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>cd head/contrib/<replaceable>foo</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn merge --record-only ^/vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist@<replaceable>12345678</replaceable> .</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn commit</userinput></screen>

	  <para>With some shells, the <literal>^</literal> in the
	    above command may need to be escaped with a
	    backslash.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <title>Importing New Sources</title>

	  <para>Prepare a full, clean tree of the vendor sources.
	    With <acronym>SVN</acronym>, we can keep a full
	    distribution in the vendor tree without bloating the main
	    tree.  Import everything but merge only what is
	    needed.</para>

	  <para>Note that you will need to add any files that were
	    added since the last vendor import, and remove any that
	    were removed.  To facilitate this, you should prepare
	    sorted lists of the contents of the vendor tree and of the
	    sources you are about to import:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>cd vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn list -R | grep -v '/$' | sort &gt; ../<replaceable>old</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>cd ../<replaceable>foo-9.9</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>find . -type f | cut -c 3- | sort &gt; ../<replaceable>new</replaceable></userinput></screen>

	  <para>With these two files, the following command will list
	    removed files (files only in
	    <filename><replaceable>old</replaceable></filename>):</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>comm -23 ../<replaceable>old</replaceable> ../<replaceable>new</replaceable></userinput></screen>

	  <para>While the command below will list added files (files
	    only in
	    <filename><replaceable>new</replaceable></filename>):</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>comm -13 ../<replaceable>old</replaceable> ../<replaceable>new</replaceable></userinput></screen>

	  <para>Let us put this together:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>cd vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/<replaceable>foo-9.9</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>tar cf - . | tar xf - -C ../dist</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>cd ../dist</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>comm -23 ../<replaceable>old</replaceable> ../<replaceable>new</replaceable> | xargs svn remove</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>comm -13 ../<replaceable>old</replaceable> ../<replaceable>new</replaceable> | xargs svn add</userinput></screen>

	  <warning>
	    <para>If there are new directories in the new
	      distribution, the last command will fail.  You will have
	      to add the directories, and run it again.  Conversely,
	      if any directories were removed, you will have to remove
	      them manually.</para>
	  </warning>

	  <para>Check properties on any new files:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>All text files
		should have <literal>svn:eol-style</literal> set to
		<literal>native</literal>.</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>All binary files should have
		<literal>svn:mime-type</literal> set to
		<literal>application/octet-stream</literal>, unless
		there is a more appropriate media type.</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>Executable files should have
		<literal>svn:executable</literal> set to
		<literal>*</literal>.</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>There should be no other properties on any file in
		the tree.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <note>
	    <para>You are ready to commit, but you should first check
	      the output of <command>svn stat</command> and
	      <command>svn diff</command> to make sure everything is
	      in order.</para>
	  </note>

	  <para>Once you have committed the new vendor release, you
	    should tag it for future reference.  The best and quickest
	    way is to do it directly in the repository:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>svn copy ^/vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist <replaceable>svn_base</replaceable>/vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/<replaceable>9.9</replaceable></userinput></screen>

	  <para>To get the new tag, you can update your working copy
	    of
	    <filename>vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable></filename>.</para>

	  <note>
	    <para>If you choose to do the copy in the checkout
	      instead, do not forget to remove the generated
	      <literal>svn:mergeinfo</literal> as described
	      above.</para>
	  </note>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <title>Merging to <emphasis>-HEAD</emphasis></title>

	  <para>After you have prepared your import, it is time to
	    merge.  Option <option>--accept=postpone</option> tells
	    <acronym>SVN</acronym> not to handle merge conflicts yet,
	    because they will be taken care of manually:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>cd head/contrib/<replaceable>foo</replaceable></userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn update</userinput>
&prompt.user; <userinput>svn merge --accept=postpone ^/vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist</userinput></screen>

	  <para>Resolve any conflicts, and make sure that any files
	    that were added or removed in the vendor tree have been
	    properly added or removed in the main tree.  It is always
	    a good idea to check differences against the vendor
	    branch:</para>

	  <screen>&prompt.user; <userinput>svn diff --no-diff-deleted --old=^/vendor/<replaceable>foo</replaceable>/dist --new=.</userinput></screen>

	  <para><option>--no-diff-deleted</option> tells
	    <acronym>SVN</acronym> not to check files that are in the
	    vendor tree but not in the main tree.</para>

	  <note>
	    <para>With <acronym>SVN</acronym>, there is no concept of
	      on or off the vendor branch.  If a file that previously
	      had local modifications no longer does, just remove any
	      left-over cruft, such as &os; version tags, so it no
	      longer shows up in diffs against the vendor tree.</para>
	  </note>

	  <para>If any changes are required for the world to build
	    with the new sources, make them now &mdash; and test until
	    you are satisfied that everything build and runs
	    correctly.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <title>Commit</title>

	  <para>Now, you are ready to commit.  Make sure you get
	    everything in one go.  Ideally, you would have done all
	    steps in a clean tree, in which case you can just commit
	    from the top of that tree.  That is the best way to avoid
	    surprises.  If you do it properly, the tree will move
	    atomically from a consistent state with the old code to a
	    consistent state with the new code.</para>
	</step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="policies-encumbered">
    <title>Encumbered Files</title>

    <para>It might occasionally be necessary to include an encumbered
      file in the FreeBSD source tree.  For example, if a device
      requires a small piece of binary code to be loaded to it before
      the device will operate, and we do not have the source to that
      code, then the binary file is said to be encumbered.  The
      following policies apply to including encumbered files in the
      FreeBSD source tree.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Any file which is interpreted or executed by the system
	  CPU(s) and not in source format is encumbered.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Any file with a license more restrictive than BSD or GNU
	  is encumbered.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>A file which contains downloadable binary data for use
	  by the hardware is not encumbered, unless (1) or (2) apply
	  to it.  It must be stored in an architecture neutral ASCII
	  format (file2c or uuencoding is recommended).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Any encumbered file requires specific approval from the
	  <link
	    xlink:href="&url.base;/administration.html#t-core">Core
	    Team</link> before it is added to the repository.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Encumbered files go in <filename>src/contrib</filename>
	  or <filename>src/sys/contrib</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The entire module should be kept together.  There is no
	  point in splitting it, unless there is code-sharing with
	  non-encumbered code.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Object files are named
	  <filename><replaceable>arch</replaceable>/<replaceable>filename</replaceable>.o.uu&gt;</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Kernel files:</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Should always be referenced in
	      <filename>conf/files.*</filename> (for build
	      simplicity).</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>Should always be in <filename>LINT</filename>, but
	      the <link
		xlink:href="&url.base;/administration.html#t-core">Core
		Team</link> decides per case if it should be commented
	      out or not.  The <link
		xlink:href="&url.base;/administration.html#t-core">Core
		Team</link> can, of course, change their minds later
	      on.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>The <firstterm>Release Engineer</firstterm>
	      decides whether or not it goes into the release.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>User-land files:</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The <link
		xlink:href="&url.base;/administration.html#t-core">Core
		team</link><indexterm><primary>core
		  team</primary></indexterm> decides if the code
	      should be part of <command>make world</command>.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>The <link
		xlink:href="&url.base;/administration.html#t-re">Release
		Engineering</link><indexterm><primary>release
		  engineering</primary></indexterm> decides if it goes
	      into the release.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="policies-shlib">
    <info>
      <title>Shared Libraries</title>

      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>Satoshi</firstname>
	    <surname>Asami</surname>
	  </personname>
	  <contrib>Contributed by </contrib>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>Peter</firstname>
	    <surname>Wemm</surname>
	  </personname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <personname>
	    <firstname>David</firstname>
	    <surname>O'Brien</surname>
	  </personname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
    </info>

    <para>If you are adding shared library support to a port or other
      piece of software that does not have one, the version numbers
      should follow these rules.  Generally, the resulting numbers
      will have nothing to do with the release version of the
      software.</para>

    <para>The three principles of shared library building are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Start from <literal>1.0</literal></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>If there is a change that is backwards compatible, bump
	  minor number (note that ELF systems ignore the minor
	  number)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>If there is an incompatible change, bump major
	  number</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For instance, added functions and bugfixes result in the
      minor version number being bumped, while deleted functions,
      changed function call syntax, etc. will force the major version
      number to change.</para>

    <para>Stick to version numbers of the form major.minor
      (<replaceable>x</replaceable>.<replaceable>y</replaceable>).
      Our a.out dynamic linker does not handle version numbers of the
      form
      <replaceable>x</replaceable>.<replaceable>y</replaceable>.<replaceable>z</replaceable>
      well.  Any version number after the <replaceable>y</replaceable>
      (i.e., the third digit) is totally ignored when comparing shared
      lib version numbers to decide which library to link with.  Given
      two shared libraries that differ only in the
      <quote>micro</quote> revision, <command>ld.so</command> will
      link with the higher one.  That is, if you link with
      <filename>libfoo.so.3.3.3</filename>, the linker only records
      <literal>3.3</literal> in the headers, and will link with
      anything starting with
      <replaceable>libfoo.so.3</replaceable>.<replaceable>(anything
	&gt;= 3)</replaceable>.<replaceable>(highest
	available)</replaceable>.</para>

    <note>
      <para><command>ld.so</command> will always use the highest
	<quote>minor</quote> revision.  For instance, it will use
	<filename>libc.so.2.2</filename> in preference to
	<filename>libc.so.2.0</filename>, even if the program was
	initially linked with <filename>libc.so.2.0</filename>.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In addition, our ELF dynamic linker does not handle minor
      version numbers at all.  However, one should still specify a
      major and minor version number as our
      <filename>Makefile</filename>s <quote>do the right thing</quote>
      based on the type of system.</para>

    <para>For non-port libraries, it is also our policy to change the
      shared library version number only once between releases.  In
      addition, it is our policy to change the major shared library
      version number only once between major OS releases (i.e., from
      6.0 to 7.0).  When you make a change to a system library that
      requires the version number to be bumped, check the
      <filename>Makefile</filename>'s commit logs.  It is the
      responsibility of the committer to ensure that the first such
      change since the release will result in the shared library
      version number in the <filename>Makefile</filename> to be
      updated, and any subsequent changes will not.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
