<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--
     The FreeBSD Documentation Project

     $FreeBSD$
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink=
  "http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="keeping-up">

  <title>Keeping Up</title>

  <para>The &os; Ports Collection is constantly changing.  Here is
    some information on how to keep up.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="freshports">
    <title>FreshPorts</title>

    <para>One of the easiest ways to learn about updates that have
      already been committed is by subscribing to <link
	xlink:href="http://www.FreshPorts.org/">FreshPorts</link>.
      Multiple ports can be monitored.  Maintainers are
      strongly encouraged to subscribe, because they will receive
      notification of not only their own changes, but also any changes
      that any other &os; committer has made.  (These are often
      necessary to keep up with changes in the underlying ports
      framework&mdash;although it would be most polite to receive an
      advance heads-up from those committing such changes, sometimes
      this is overlooked or impractical.  Also, in some
      cases, the changes are very minor in nature.  We expect everyone
      to use their best judgement in these cases.)</para>

    <para>To use FreshPorts, an account is required.  Those with
      registered email addresses at <literal>@FreeBSD.org</literal>
      will see the opt-in link on the right-hand side of the web
      pages.  Those who already have a FreshPorts account but are not
      using a <literal>@FreeBSD.org</literal> email address can change
      the email to <literal>@FreeBSD.org</literal>, subscribe, then
      change it back again.</para>

    <para>FreshPorts also has a sanity test feature which
      automatically tests each commit to the &os; ports tree.  If
      subscribed to this service, a committer will receive
      notifications of any errors which FreshPorts detects during
      sanity testing of their commits.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="svnweb">
    <title>The Web Interface to the Source Repository</title>

    <para>It is possible to browse the files in the source
      repository by using a web interface.  Changes that affect the
      entire port system are now documented in the <link
	xlink:href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/ports/head/CHANGES">CHANGES</link>
      file.  Changes that affect individual ports are now documented
      in the <link
	xlink:href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/ports/head/UPDATING">UPDATING</link>
      file.  However, the definitive answer to any question is
      undoubtedly to read the source code of <link
	xlink:href="http://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/ports/head/Mk/bsd.port.mk">bsd.port.mk</link>,
      and associated files.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="ports-mailing-list">
    <title>The &os; Ports Mailing List</title>

    <para>As a ports maintainer, consider subscribing to
      &a.ports;.  Important changes to the way ports work will be
      announced there, and then committed to
      <filename>CHANGES</filename>.</para>

    <para>If the volume of messages on this mailing list is too high,
      consider following &a.ports-announce; which contains only
      announcements.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="build-cluster">
    <title>The &os; Port Building Cluster</title>

    <para>One of the least-publicized strengths of &os; is that
      an entire cluster of machines is dedicated to continually
      building the Ports Collection, for each of the major OS releases
      and for each Tier-1 architecture.</para>

    <para>Individual ports are built unless they are specifically
      marked with <varname>IGNORE</varname>.  Ports that are marked
      with <varname>BROKEN</varname> will still be attempted, to see
      if the underlying problem has been resolved.  (This is done by
      passing <varname>TRYBROKEN</varname> to the port's
      <filename>Makefile</filename>.)</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="distfile-survey">
    <title>Portscout: the &os; Ports Distfile Scanner</title>

    <para>The build cluster is dedicated to building the latest
      release of each port with distfiles that have already been
      fetched.  However, as the Internet continually changes,
      distfiles can quickly go missing.  <link
	xlink:href="http://portscout.FreeBSD.org">Portscout</link>,
      the &os; Ports distfile scanner, attempts to query every
      download site for every port to find out if each distfile is
      still available.  <application>Portscout</application> can
      generate <acronym>HTML</acronym> reports and send emails about
      newly available ports to those who request them.  Unless not
      otherwise subscribed, maintainers are asked to check
      periodically for changes, either by hand or using the
      <acronym>RSS</acronym> feed.</para>

    <para><application>Portscout</application>'s first page gives
      the email address of the port maintainer, the number of ports
      the maintainer is responsible for, the number of those ports
      with new distfiles, and the percentage of those ports that are
      out-of-date.  The search function allows for searching by email
      address for a specific maintainer, and for selecting whether
      only out-of-date ports are shown.</para>

    <para>Upon clicking on a maintainer's email address, a list of
      all of their ports is displayed, along with port category,
      current version number, whether or not there is a new version,
      when the port was last updated, and finally when it was last
      checked.  A search function on this page allows the user to
      search for a specific port.</para>

    <para>Clicking on a port name in the list displays the <link
	xlink:href="http://freshports.org">FreshPorts</link> port
      information.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="portsmon">
    <title>The &os; Ports Monitoring System</title>

    <para>Another handy resource is the <link
	xlink:href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org">&os; Ports
	Monitoring System</link> (also known as
      <literal>portsmon</literal>).  This system comprises a database
      that processes information from several sources and allows it to
      be browsed via a web interface.  Currently, the ports Problem
      Reports (PRs), the error logs from the build cluster, and
      individual files from the ports collection are used.  In the
      future, this will be expanded to include the distfile survey, as
      well as other sources.</para>

    <para>To get started, use the <link
	xlink:href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/portoverview.py">Overview
	of One Port</link> search page to find all the information
      about a port.</para>

    <para>This is the only resource available that
      maps PR entries to portnames.  PR submitters do not
      always include the portname in their Synopsis, although we would
      prefer that they did.  So, <literal>portsmon</literal> is a
      good place to find out whether an existing
      port has any PRs filed against it, any build errors, or
      if a new port the porter is considering
      creating has already been submitted.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
