<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE news PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
News//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/news.dtd">
<!-- Simple schema for FreeBSD Project news.

     Divide time in to <year>, <month>, and <day> elements, each of which
     has a <name>.

     each <day> element contains one or more <event> elements.

     Each <event> contains an optional <title>, and then a <p>.  <p> elements
     can contain <a> anchors.

     Use the <title> element if the <p> content is lengthy.  When generating
     synopses of this information (e.g., for syndication using RDF files),
     the contents of <title> will be preferred over <p>.
-->
<news>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS"
  version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">$FreeBSD: www/en/gnome/news.xml,v 1.153 2010/11/20 15:22:27 kwm Exp $</cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <year>
    <name>2010</name>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>19</name>

        <event>
        <title>Announcing GNOME 2.32.1 for FreeBSD!</title>

        <p>Presenting GNOME 2.32.1 for FreeBSD. The offical release
          notes for this release can be found at
          <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.32/">
          http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.32/</a></p>

        <p>This will be the last release of the GNOME 2.x series, mainly a bugfix 
          and bridge release to the first release of the GNOME 3.x series.</p>

        <p>This release features commits by avl, marcus, mezz and myself.</p>

        <p>The FreeBSD GNOME Team would like to thank the following contributors 
          and testers for there help with this release:</p>

        <p>
        Zane C.B.
        <br />
        romain@
        <br />
        Olaf Seibert
        <br />
        DomiX
        <br />
        Bapt
        <br />
        jsa@
        <br />
        miwi@
        <br />
        Sergio de Almeida Lenzi
        <br />
        Maxim Samsonov
        <br />
        Kris Moore
        <br />
        </p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
        <title>Announcing GNOME 2.30.1. for FreeBSD!</title>

        <p>Presenting GNOME 2.30.1 for FreeBSD. The offical release
        notes for this release can be found at 
        <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.30/">
        http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.30/</a></p>

        <p>This release brings initial PackageKit support, Upower (replaces 
        power management part of hal), cuse4bsd integration with HAL and cheese,
        and a faster Evolution.</p>

        <p>Sadly GNOME 2.30.x will be the last release with FreeBSD 6.X support.
        This will also be the last of the 2.x releases. The next release will 
        be the highly-anticipated GNOME 3.0 which will bring with it a new UI 
        experience.</p>

        <p>Currently, there are a few bugs with GNOME 2.30 that may be of note 
        for our users. Be sure to consult the 2.30 upgrade FAQ at 
        <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq230.html">
        http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq230.html></a>
        for specific upgrading instructions, and the up-to-date list of known 
        issues.</p>

        <p>This release features commits by: avl, ahze, bland, marcus, mezz 
        and myself.</p>

        <p>The FreeBSD GNOME Team would like to thank Anders F Bjorklund for
        doing the initual packagekit porting.</p>

        <p>And the following contributors and testers for there help with this 
        release:</p>

        <p>
        Eric L. Chen
        <br />

        Vladimir Grebenschikov
        <br />

        Sergio de Almeida Lenzi
        <br />

        DomiX
        <br />

        walder
        <br />

        crsd
        <br />

        Kevin Oberman
        <br />

        Michal Varga
        <br />

        Pavel Plesov
        <br />

        Bapt
        <br />

        kevin
        <br />

        and Ion-Mihai Tetcu for running two exp-runs for us.
        <br />
        </p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

 <year>
    <name>2009</name>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
        <title>Announcing GNOME 2.28.1. for FreeBSD!</title>

        <p>Presenting GNOME 2.28.1 for FreeBSD. The official release
        notes for this release can be found at
        <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.28/">
        http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.28/</a>

        . Officially, this is mostly a polishing release in preparation
        for GNOME 3.0 due in about a year.</p>

        <p>On the FreeBSD front, though, a lot went into this release.
        Major thanks goes to kwm and avl who did a lot of the porting
        work for this release. In particular, kwm brought in Evolution
        MAPI support for better Microsoft Exchange integration. Avl
        made sure that the new gobject introspection repository ports
        were nicely compartmentalized so that large dependencies aren't
        brought in wholesale.</p>

        <p>But, every GNOME team member (ahze, avl, bland, kwm, mezz,
        and myself) contributed to this release.</p>

        <p>Other major improvements include an updated HAL with better
        volume probing code, ufsid integration, and support for volume
        names containing spaces (big thanks to J.R. Oldroyd); a new
        WebKit; updated AbiWord; an updated Gimp; and a preview of the
        new GNOME Shell project (thanks to Pawel Worach).</p>

        <p>The FreeBSD GNOME Team would like to that the following
        additional contributors to this release whose patches and
        testing really helped make it a success:</p>

    	<p>
        Andrius Morkunas
        <br />

        Dominique Goncalves
        <br />

        Eric L. Chen
        <br />

        J.R. Oldroyd
        <br />

        Joseph S. Atkinson
        <br />

        Li
        <br />

        Pawel Worach
        <br />

        Romain Tarti?re
        <br />

        Thomas Vogt
        <br />

        Yasuda Keisuke
        <br />

        Rui Paulo
        <br />

        Martin Wilke
        <br />

        (and an extra shout out to miwi and pav for the pointyhat runs)
        <br />
    	</p>

        <p>We would like to send this release out to Alexander Loginov
        (avl) in hopes that he feels better soon.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
          <title>Announcing GNOME 2.26.0 for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team is proud to announce the release of
          GNOME 2.26.0 for FreeBSD. The official release notes can be
          found at
          <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.26/">
          http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.26/</a>

          . On the FreeBSD front, we introduced a port of libxul 1.9 as
          an alternative for Firefox 2.0 as a Gecko provider. Almost
          all of the Gecko consumers can make use of this provider by
          setting:
          <br />

          WITH_GECKO=libxul
          <br />

          The GNOME 2.26 port was done by ahze, kwm, marcus, and mezz
          with contributions by Joseph S. Atkinson, Peter Wemm, Eric L.
          Chen, Martin Matuska, Craig Butler, and Pawel Worach.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>9</name>

        <event>
          <title>Announcing GNOME 2.24.2 for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team is proud to announce the release of
          GNOME 2.24.2 for FreeBSD. The official release notes can be
          found at
          <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.24/">
          http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.24/</a>

          . On the FreeBSD front, this release introduces Fuse support
          in HAL, adds multi-CPU support to libgtop, WebKit updates,
          and fixes some long-standing seahorse and gnome-keyring
          bugs.</p>

          <p>This release features commits by adamw, ahze, kwm, mezz,
          and myself. It would not have been possible without are
          contributors and testers: Alexander Loginov, Craig Butler,
          Dmitry Marakasov, Eric L. Chen, Joseph S. Atkinson, Kris
          Moore, Lapo Luchini, Nikos Ntarmos, Pawel Worach, Romain
          Tartiere, TAOKA Fumiyoshi, Romain Tartiere, Yasuda Keisuke,
          Zyl aZ, bf, Florent Thoumie, Peter Wemm, and pluknet.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2008</name>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>Announcing GNOME 2.22.0 for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team is proud to announce the release of
          GNOME 2.22.0 for FreeBSD. The official GNOME 2.22 release
          notes can be found at
          <a href="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.22/">
          http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.22/</a>

          . On the FreeBSD front, this release features an updated hal
          port with support for video4linux devices, DRM (Direct
          Rendering), and better support of removable media. Work is
          also underway to tie webkit more closely into GNOME. As part
          of the GNOME 2.22 upgrade, GStreamer received a rather large
          upgrade as well. Be sure to consult UPDATING on the proper
          steps to upgrade all of your GNOME ports.</p>

          <p>This release would not have been possible without the
          contributions and testing efforts of the following people:
          Pawel Worach, kan, edwin, Peter Ulrich Kruppa, J. W.
          Ballantine, Yasuda Keisuke, and Andriy Gapon.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2007</name>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>Announcing GNOME 2.20.1 for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>Presenting GNOME 2.20.1 and all related works for FreeBSD.
          The official GNOME 2.20 release notes can be found at
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.20/notes/en/">
          http://www.gnome.org/start/2.20/notes/en/</a>

          . Beyond that, this update includes the new GIMP 2.4
          (courtesy of ahze).</p>

          <p>The GNOME 2.20 update also includes a huge change in the
          FreeBSD GNOME hierarchy. We are now using the more standard
          DATADIR of ${PREFIX}/share rather than ${PREFIX}/share/gnome.
          The result is that fewer patches and hacks are needed to port
          GNOME components to FreeBSD. This will mean some user changes
          may be required, so be sure to read /usr/ports/UPDATING for
          more details.</p>

          <p>This release and the things we accomplished in it would
          not have been possible without mezz's crazy idea to collapse
          DATADIR, and his persistence to make it happen successfully.
          Ahze and pav also deserve thanks for their work on porting
          modules and testing the whole ball of wax on pointyhat
          (respectively).</p>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team would also like to thank our
          various testers and contributors:</p>

          <p>Yasuda Keisuke
          <br />

          Frank Jahnke
          <br />

          Pawel Worach
          <br />

          Brian Gruber
          <br />

          Franz Klammer
          <br />

          Yuri Pankov
          <br />

          Nick Barkas
          <br />

          Cristian KLEIN
          <br />

          Tony Maher
          <br />

          Scot Hetzel
          <br />

          Martin Matuska (mm)
          <br />

          Benoit Dejean
          <br />

          Martin Wilke (miwi)
          <br />

          (And anyone else I may have missed)</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>August</name>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.19.6 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Okay, okay, I have missed a few updates. But the FreeBSD
          GNOME team has not been slacking. We've been keeping up with
          the latest GNOME development releases including this
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2007-August/msg00000.html">
          latest one</a>

          . Checkout the ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          to see where GNOME 2.20 currently stands. Since 2.10 Beta 1
          is right around the corner, now is also the time to start
          putting together some killer FreeBSD GNOME screenshots. Send
          all submissions to
          <a href="mailto:freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org">
          freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>June</name>

      <day>
        <name>9</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.19.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The third release on the path to GNOME 2.20 is now
          available in both port and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">package</a>

          forms. There is one known build issue with
          gnome-system-monitor and FreeBSD &lt; 7-CURRENT that we hope
          to have worked out soon. Along with this release comes the
          GNOME 2.20 (and beyond!)
          <a href="http://live.gnome.org/RoadMap">roadmap</a>

          . This will prepare you for the exciting new features in
          store for our favorite Desktop Environment.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>31</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.18.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The next bug fix release for GNOME 2.18 has been
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2007-May/msg00004.html">
          released</a>

          and ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are available for FreeBSD. So the only question is, why
          haven't you upgraded yet?</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.19.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME forges ahead with the first release in the
          development train that will become GNOME 2.20. As always,
          FreeBSD is right there with them. Only we bring a twist. This
          time around, we are doing yet another bit of housekeeping,
          and dropping the "share/gnome" DATADIR. This means that the
          FreeBSD GNOME installation will be more like all the other
          GNOME distributions. The net gain is that porting new GNOME
          applications to FreeBSD should be much easier with fewer
          hacks and patches.</p>

          <p>At this point, the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">MarcusCom
          tree</a>

          is safe to use for most ports. There is still quite a few
          ports that still require conversion, and we will be working
          on those in the weeks to come. In particular, the Desktop and
          all gnome2 meta-ports are safe; and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          are available for the GNOME Desktop.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.18.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.18.1 has been
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2007-April/msg00008.html">
          released</a>

          and ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are available for everyone's faorite operating system. This
          release is a polishing of 2.18.0, so expect a more stable,
          nicer looking desktop experience. On top of that, some of our
          users have also submitted
          <a href="&base;/gnome/screenshots.html">screenshots</a>

          !</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>19</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.18 release for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>Presenting GNOME 2.18 for FreeBSD. GNOME 2.18 is a
          departure from recent GNOME releases in that it focuses more
          on stability and functionality than on new features. Not that
          it doesn't have its share of new and exciting items. Check
          out the
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.18/">official release
          notes</a>

          for all the goodies in this release.</p>

          <p>GNOME 2.18 for FreeBSD would not have been possible
          without the hard work of the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/contact.html">FreeBSD GNOME
          Team</a>

          and our intrepid band of testers including J. W. Ballantine,
          Pawel Worach, Yasuda Keisuke, Pascal Hofstee, miwi, Yoshihiro
          Ota, Vladimir Grebenschikov, Jukka A. Ukkonen, Phillip
          Neumann, Franz Klammer, and Neal Delmonico.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.92 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.18 is nigh! The 2.18 Release Candidate has been
          released, and both
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are now available for FreeBSD. We are
          <b>SO</b>

          close to a release, and yet we still don't have any
          screenshots. So please, if you are testing GNOME 2.17, send
          us your best screenshot. If you need ideas on what to
          highlight, check out
          <a
          href="http://live.gnome.org/TwoPointSeventeen/ReleaseNotes">
          the GNOME 2.18 release notes</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.91 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Where have we been?! While we haven't been updating the
          news page, we
          <b>have</b>

          been working on GNOME 2.17. We are pleased to announce that
          GNOME 2.17.91 (aka GNOME 2.18 Beta 2) is now
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">available</a>

          along with glorious
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          . We now request that all artistic people start submitting
          their GNOME 2.17 screenshots for our gallery.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>31</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.16.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.16.3 was
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2007-January/msg00111.html">
          released</a>

          and ports are available for FreeBSD. This is the final
          release in the GNOME 2.16 series. The GNOME authors and the
          FreeBSD GNOME Team have made sure that this release rocks
          like none other. Packages will be a bit delayed for 2.16.3 as
          marcus is currently traveling. Expect packages to start
          showing up in the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">FreeBSD GNOME
          Tinderbox</a>

          on February 8th.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2006</name>

    <month>
      <name>December</name>

      <day>
        <name>21</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.4 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.17.4 was
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2006-December/msg00005.html">
          released</a>

          just in time for Christmas. The one new module that is
          currently showing up in the FreeBSD port is
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/~jamiemcc/tracker/">Tracker</a>

          . As soon as the final set of new GNOME 2.18 modules is
          ratified, they will be added to the various meta-ports.
          Additionally, work has mostly been completed on a clean up of
          the FreeBSD libgtop backend. This means that applications
          like gnome-system-monitor will become much more accurate on
          FreeBSD. As always,
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are available to get you started with GNOME 2.17 testing.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The third installment on the road to 2.18 has been
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2006-December/msg00002.html">
          released</a>

          and we have cranked out the usual set of
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          . If you are one of the brave testers, please continue to
          provide your feedback and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/bugging.html">bug reports</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>FreeBSD backend committed to HAL git</title>

          <p>After seven months of development by Jean-Yves Lefort and
          Joe Marcus Clarke in MarcusCom CVS, the FreeBSD backend for
          <a href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software_2fhal">
          HAL</a>

          was finally
          <a
          href="http://gitweb.freedesktop.org/?p=hal.git;a=commit;h=76c310d0efb5d463f06291cb02100b3b3ce1da71">
          committed</a>

          upstream into the HAL git repository. This means that future
          releases of HAL will have FreeBSD support out-of-the-box.
          This is a major landmark in a project that started on April
          14, 2006 with the goal of bringing a better desktop
          experience to FreeBSD users.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>23</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.16.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.16 is maturing nicely with this
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2006-November/msg00062.html">
          second</a>

          bug fix and optimization installment. Additionally, thanks to
          our users, we have worked out quite a few bugs in the new HAL
          implementation. Don't just stand there! Upgrade already! Not
          a big fan of ports? Then try GNOME 2.16.2 from
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The follow-on release to GNOME 2.17.1 is a more complete
          development snapshot. More of the new GNOME 2.18 features are
          starting to show up. For instance, this release features two
          new games: glchess and gnome-sudoku.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">Ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are available for testing.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>22</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.17.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>No rest for the weary. No sooner had we gotten 2.16.1 into
          ports that 2.17.1 was released. Being a .1 release, this is
          still very rough, and only a few of the components have been
          updated for the new development release. However, we still
          encourage our local guinea pigs...er...users to
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">try this
          out</a>

          . Not up for compiling this all yourself? That's cool, we
          have
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          pre-built with debugging symbols.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.16.1 Unleashed!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.16.1 is now available for FreeBSD, and it is in
          the ports tree in time for FreeBSD 6.2 (no you are NOT
          dreaming)! This is a first. Usually the GNOME release cycle
          has conflicted with the FreeBSD release cycle. However,
          thanks to Kris and pointyhat, we were able to get the major
          patch tested. In addition to the core GNOME ports, almost 500
          ports were also touched to chase the GNOME move from X11BASE
          to LOCALBASE and fix build problems with the new freetype2.
          The bulk of the move was carried out by ahze, mezz, and pav,
          but it would not have been possible without cooperation from
          the FreeBSD KDE team who worked with us to make sure GNOME
          and KDE can still coexist happily. We would also like to send
          a shout out to kris and pointyhat for putting up with
          multiple test runs until we got something that was solid.</p>

          <p>Back to GNOME 2.16. This release brings a huge amount of
          new functionality to FreeBSD. Check out the standard
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.16/">release notes</a>

          to get the official spiel from the GNOME camp. But on top of
          what you will read there, jylefort and marcus have completed
          work on a port of HAL to FreeBSD. This will allow FreeBSD to
          take advantage of closer hardware interaction such as
          auto-mounting CD-ROMs, USB drives, and music players;
          auto-playing audio CDs; and managing laptop power
          consumption.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>September</name>

      <day>
        <name>17</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.16 available for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>Quite possibly the most functional GNOME release ever is
          now available for FreeBSD. GNOME 2.16 features HAL support
          for FreeBSD which allows FreeBSD users to take advantage of
          automatic volume mounting, advanced power management, and
          more. In addition, many performance improvements have gone
          into GNOME, and the eye candy has definitely been improved.
          Check out the full set of
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.16/">release notes</a>

          for all of the new goodies.</p>

          <p>Due to the fact that GNOME 2.16 will be the first GNOME
          release for FreeBSD to live in LOCALBASE, and because we are
          so close to the release of FreeBSD 6.2, GNOME 2.16 will not
          be committed to the ports tree until sometime in November
          most likely. In the meantime,
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are available from MarcusCom.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>August</name>

      <day>
        <name>2</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.14.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The last update (*sniff*) to GNOME 2.14 has been released
          with a fresh
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2006-August/msg00001.html">
          batch</a>

          of bug fixes and translation updates. The
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">package</a>

          build is just starting, but ports are ready. But if you want
          some real fun, check out
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">GNOME 2.15</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>July</name>

      <day>
        <name>27</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.15.90 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.16 Beta 1 has been released into its new home on
          FreeBSD: /usr/local (or LOCALBASE for l33t p0rters). The
          migration to LOCALBASE was quite smooth, but some ports still
          need adjustment. This latest development snapshot has an
          updated 2.16 module list (less Tomboy), and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          for all supported versions of FreeBSD are ready. So what are
          you waiting for!</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME is moving!</title>

          <p>...PREFIXes, that is. That's right, GNOME is leaving its
          home in X11BASE, and joining KDE (and a lot of other ports)
          in LOCALBASE. This is being done as part of an effort to
          collapse into one third-party package PREFIX as X11R6 is no
          longer as relevant as it used to be. All of the work is
          happening in the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">MarcusCom ports
          tree</a>

          , so expect GNOME 2.16 under /usr/local. The work is going
          extremely well, and we expect to be fully moved and unpacked
          in time for GNOME 2.16 Beta 1 (aka 2.15.90).</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.15.4 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>What happened to .1, .2, and .3? Well, GNOME 2.15 had a
          pretty rough start, especially for FreeBSD. However, we now
          have a working GNOME 2.15.4 along with
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          and a port of
          <a href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software_2fhal">
          HAL</a>

          ! There are still some nasty problems in this release, so be
          sure to checkout the official 2.15.4
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2006-July/msg00004.html">
          release notes</a>

          for workarounds.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>31</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.14.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.14.2 has been released, and all the updates have
          made it into the FreeBSD ports tree.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          are still being built. Be sure to read the 2.14.2
          <a href="http://gnomedesktop.org/node/2693">release
          announcement</a>

          for a list of all the fixes, translations, and other
          goodies.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.14.1 is now in the ports tree!</title>

          <p>Even though 5.5 and 6.1 have not been released, the ports
          freeze has been lifted, and GNOME 2.14 has been merged into
          the ports tree.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          built against the update ports tree will be available
          shortly. Be sure to check out the list of
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq214.html#q5">known
          issues</a>

          as well as the 2.14
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.14/notes/en/">release
          notes</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>Podcast interview with Joe Marcus Clarke</title>

          <p>In his latest
          <a href="http://bsdtalk.blogspot.com/">bsdtalk</a>

          podcast, Will Backman interviews Joe Marcus Clarke about the
          FreeBSD GNOME Project. The podcast is available at
          <a
          href="http://cisx1.uma.maine.edu/~wbackman/bsdtalk/bsdtalk032.mp3">
          http://cisx1.uma.maine.edu/~wbackman/bsdtalk/bsdtalk032.mp3</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.14.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>While we are still waiting for the releases of FreeBSD 5.5
          and 6.1, GNOME 2.14.1 has been released, an we are
          maintaining it in the ports module of the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">MarcusCom CVS
          repository</a>

          . Ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          are ready, and we have hammered out quite a few known issues
          for this release. Primarily, problems with GStreamer and OSS
          have been fixed as well as many crashes on amd64.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>16</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.14 has arrived!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.14 and FreeBSD: it's what your computer would
          want. Read the
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2006-March/msg00053.html">
          official release announcement</a>

          for all the new goodies, fixes, and most importantly,
          performance improvements. Instructions for upgrading can be
          found on our
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">development
          branch FAQ</a>

          . After 5.5 and 6.1 are released, we will put out the
          official announcement, and update the website with all new
          documentation; and of course, put GNOME 2.14 into the ports
          tree.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>1</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.13.92 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.14 Release Candidate is out, and ports and
          packages are
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ready</a>

          . It looks like GNOME 2.14.0 will be out on time on March
          15th. Now is the time to report any serious problems as well
          as submit GNOME 2.14 screenshots and splash screens.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.13.91 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Get your BETA 2 here! That's right, GNOME 2.14 Beta 2 has
          been released, and FreeBSD ports and packages are
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ready</a>

          . We are trying to document (and hopefully eliminate) any and
          all bugs (especially crashers). So if you find anything wrong
          in this release, please
          <a href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">report it</a>

          . We also need people to start sending in their FreeBSD GNOME
          2.14 splash screen entries. So down your favorite energy
          drink, and get to work.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>9</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.12.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The last release from the GNOME 2.12 branch is
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2006-February/msg00019.html">
          out</a>

          with FreeBSD ports right behind it. The next GNOME Desktop
          release will be 2.14.0 which is due out on March 13. GNOME
          2.12.3 is a bug fix and translation release.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.13.90 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>It's BETA time! GNOME 2.13.90 (aka GNOME 2.14 Beta 1) has
          been released along with a hot batch of FreeBSD ports. While
          still a beta, this release looks pretty solid. One of the
          biggest known issues is that the new GConf schema layout
          leaves behind a lot of leftover files (see
          <a href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=328623">
          #328623</a>

          for more details). This should be fixed by release time. We
          are entering crunch time, so please report any and all
          problems. Enjoy!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2005</name>

    <month>
      <name>December</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.13.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>If you are wondering what to get for that special GNOME
          user on your Christmas list, look no further. GNOME 2.13.3
          has been released, and ports and packages are
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ready</a>

          . Most of the kinks from GNOME 2.13.2 have been worked out
          (in particular, all games should be functional now).</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>1</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.12.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The latest stable GNOME release, 2.12.2, is now ready for
          your upgrading pleasure in both ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          formats. This is primarily a bug-fix release, but a few
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2005-November/msg00062.html">
          new features</a>

          made the cut.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>17</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.13.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The exciting new winter line of GNOME Desktops has been
          released, and ports are now available for FreeBSD. GNOME
          2.13.2 features three new proposed desktop modules: atomix,
          fast-user-switch-applet, and gnome-screensaver, along with
          Firefox 1.5 as the base for Epiphany and Yelp. Testers to
          their mark,
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">go!</a>
          </p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>5</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.12.1 merged into the ports tree</title>

          <p>Now that FreeBSD 6.0 is out the door, GNOME 2.12.1 has
          been merged into the FreeBSD ports tree. Check out the
          <a
          href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-gnome/2005-November/012608.html">
          official announcement</a>

          for more information.
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">
          Packages</a>

          built against the update ports tree will be available
          shortly. Be sure to use the
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/gnome_upgrade.sh">
          upgrade script</a>

          to handle the upgrade process!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.12.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Even though we are still waiting for 6.0 to be released,
          GNOME 2.12.1 has been released, and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          have been updated. At this point, most (if not all) of the
          FreeBSD-specific known issues have been resolved.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>September</name>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.12 has arrived!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.12 and FreeBSD, together at last. Read the
          <a
          href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-gnome/2005-September/012190.html">
          official unofficial release announcement</a>

          for instructions on upgrading. After 6.0 is released, we will
          put out the official announcement, and update the website
          with all new documentation.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>August</name>

      <day>
        <name>26</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.11.92 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.12 Release Candidate is
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2005-August/msg00003.html">
          out</a>

          ! Man were there a lot of problems to tackle in this one.
          Fortunately, everything should now be ironed out, and GNOME
          2.12 is shaping up to be a solid release. Please
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">test</a>

          our ports and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">packages</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.11.91 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.12 Beta 2 is
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/devel-announce-list/2005-August/msg00001.html">
          upon us</a>

          , and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          are now ready for FreeBSD.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          for amd64 and i386 are forthcoming. For this release, we have
          introduced a new feature that "normalizes" the shared library
          versions for many of the major GNOME 2 components. This means
          that future updates will most likely not see a shared library
          version bump which will help tremendously with upgrades. Test
          like there's no tomorrow!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>July</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.11.90 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>That's right, folks. GNOME 2.12 Beta 1 is now out, and
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">ports</a>

          have been updated for your testing pleasure. We also have a
          complete set of
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Desktop
          packages</a>

          available for i386 and amd64. Don't forget to checkout the
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/~davyd/gnome-2-12/">GNOME 2.12
          Preview Tour</a>

          so you can see what to expect from your shiny new
          desktop.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>19</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.11.5 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.11.5 has been officially released, and ports are
          available for FreeBSD.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          for i386 and amd64 are cooking as we speak. New modules for
          this release include evince and libgnomecups.
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">Test it</a>

          already!</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>7</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.10.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.10.2 has been released, and FreeBSD ports are now
          up-to-date. This is primarily a bug-fix release for GNOME
          2.10. All of the changes can be found in the
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2005-July/msg00019.html">
          official release announcement</a>

          .
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          for i386 and amd64 are forthcoming.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>June</name>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.11.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.11.3 has been released, and FreeBSD ports are
          ready with packages on the way! The FreeBSD GNOME team has
          been working like crazy to get this release out the door.
          Unfortunately, the GNOME project has not made any official
          release announcements, so this release only has one new
          module, gnomekeyringmanager. Get your copy now from our
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">development
          branch FAQ</a>

          .</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>FreeBSD GNOME to drop FreeBSD 4.X support</title>

          <p>Starting with GNOME 2.11, and continuing with the release
          of 2.12 and beyond, the FreeBSD GNOME team will no longer
          support the GNOME Desktop on FreeBSD 4.X. Some of lower-level
          components will be supported, however. FreeBSD 4.X lacks many
          of the features needed for a modern desktop, and there are
          now two stable 5.X releases with 6.0 around the corner. If
          you haven't done so already, now would be a good time to
          upgrade to 5.X or 6.0.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>18</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.10.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.10.1 has been released, and FreeBSD ports are
          already to go. This release is primarily a bug fix and
          performance improvement release, but some new features have
          been added. In particular, pkg-config got an overhaul to
          cleanup library linkage. This caused some unexpected build
          failure fallout, but work is underway to correct the
          problems. All of the changes in GNOME 2.10.1 can be found in
          the combined
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2005-April/msg00030.html">
          change log</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.10.0 is here!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.10.0 has been released, and merged into the
          FreeBSD ports tree. We even beat the 5.4-RELEASE ports
          freeze! This new release is jam-packed with
          <a
          href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.10/notes/rnwhatsnew.html">
          changes</a>

          , including some brand new
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq212.html#q1">goodies</a>

          now available on FreeBSD. Be sure to check out our
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq212.html">upgrade FAQ</a>

          prior to jumping in. For those that do not want to spend time
          compiling, packages for i386 are almost done building on our
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">Tinderbox</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>9</name>

        <event>
          <title>Splashscreen contest closed</title>

          <p>The search for the FreeBSD GNOME 2.10 splashscreen is
          over. Thanks to all the artists that submitted
          <a
          href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~adamw/images/gnome_splashes/">
          entries</a>

          . Our
          <a
          href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~adamw/images/gnome_splashes/franz_klammer-2.png">
          winning entry</a>

          was designed by Franz Klammer (based on the default GNOME
          2.10 splashscreen by Sami "alump" Viitanen), and is the
          default GNOME 2.10 splashscreen for FreeBSD. However, unlike
          previous release, all other entries have also been installed.
          You can use the deskutils/splashsetter port to choose the one
          you like best.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>22</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.8.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.8.3 has been released and the FreeBSD ports tree
          has been updated.
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">
          Packages for i386</a>

          are also freshly baked, and ready for your upgrade pleasure.
          All of the bugfixes, changes, and optimizations can be found
          in the
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2005-February/msg00071.html">
          release announcement</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.91 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.9.91 (aka GNOME 2.10 BETA 2) has been released,
          and
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          ports are available</a>

          for your favorite OS. This release features the final set of
          GNOME 2.10 modules. Please join us in heping to make this the
          best release since 2.8!</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>7</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.10 Splashscreen contest is open</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.10 is scheduled to be released on March 9, 2005,
          and we need talented artists to design a new FreeBSD GNOME
          splashscreen. The splashscreen should be in PNG format,
          feature both FreeBSD and GNOME, and work well with the
          scrolling application icons. The actual version of GNOME can
          be omitted if desired. Send all entries to
          <a href="mailto:gnome@FreeBSD.org">gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

          . The FreeBSD GNOME user base will decide the winner, and the
          artist will be credited in the GNOME 2.10 commit log.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>3</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.90 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.9.90 (aka 2.10 BETA 1) has been released, and
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          ports are available</a>

          for FreeBSD. For this first beta, we have updated the module
          list to what should be the final list for GNOME 2.10. Now
          would be a good time to join the testing effort, and be sure
          to
          <a href="mailto:gnome@FreeBSD.org">send in</a>

          some screenshots if you do.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.4 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.9.4 marks the first API/ABI frozen release of
          GNOME 2.9. GNOME 2.10 is still slated for release on March 9,
          so
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          test it already</a>

          ! GNOME 2.9.4 also marks the first "clean" desktop release in
          that it leaves no leftover files or directories are
          deinstall. Checkout the
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">
          packages</a>

          for yourself.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2004</name>

    <month>
      <name>December</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>Mozilla approves FreeBSD's thunderbird and firefox
          ports</title>

          <p>The
          <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/foundation/licensing.html">
          Mozilla License Team</a>

          has
          <a
          href="http://people.freebsd.org/~ahze/firefox_thunderbird-approved.txt">
          granted permission</a>

          to the FreeBSD Gnome Team for use of the
          <i>Firefox</i>

          and
          <i>Thunderbird</i>

          names, official icons, and use of the
          --enable-official-branding configure option.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>25</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>HO, HO, HO, Merry Christmas! GNOME 2.9.3 has been
          released, and ports are now
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">available</a>

          . This latest development release adds gnome-control-center,
          and should be quite usable.
          <a href="docs/faq2.html#q21">Packages</a>

          are also available for all supported i386 releases.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.8.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.8.2 has been released, and ports have been updated
          in the ports tree with
          <a href="docs/faq2.html#q21">Tinderbox packages</a>

          forthcoming. A merged
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2004-December/msg00026.html">
          ChangeLog</a>

          is also available.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.9.2 has been released (such as it is), and ports
          for FreeBSD are now
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">available</a>

          . Gnome-control-center and nautilus-media are still missing
          in action, but a lot of new modules including
          gnome-user-share, goobox, and totem-gstreamer have been
          added. If you like living on the edge, please help us with
          testing.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.9.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Although a bit late due to the 5.3 ports freeze, GNOME
          2.9.1 has been brought to FreeBSD. This first 2.10
          development release is not for the faint of heart. Due to
          changes in Nautilus, components such as gnome-control-center
          and nautilus-media will not work. However, if you have a
          strong constitution, please
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">join us</a>

          in testing GNOME 2.9.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>7</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.8 Release available for FreeBSD!</title>

          <p>After being delayed waiting for FreeBSD 5.3-Release, GNOME
          2.8 for FreeBSD is here! Be sure to use the gnome_upgrade.sh
          script to handle your upgrade, and check out
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/tinderbox/">the
          tinderbox</a>

          if you prefer packages. Visit
          <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/">the FreeBSD/GNOME
          webpage</a>

          for more information.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>Michael Johnson joins the FreeBSD GNOME team</title>

          <p>Michael Johnson has become the newest member of the
          FreeBSD GNOME team. He has shown an exceptional prowess for
          multimedia applications, but he will also be contributing to
          All Things GNOME.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>26</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.8.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Although a bit late with the news release, GNOME 2.8.1 was
          released on October 26th, and FreeBSD ports have been
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          available</a>

          since then. Packages are also up on the
          <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">
          Tinderbox</a>

          server. We are still holding off on the FreeBSD ports tree
          merge until after 5.3 is released.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>September</name>

      <day>
        <name>16</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.8.0 Released!</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.8.0 Desktop has been released, and the FreeBSD
          ports are ready to go. However, bad timing has struck once
          again, and GNOME 2.8 was released in the middle of the
          5.3-RELEASE ports freeze. Therefore, GNOME 2.8 ports will not
          make it into the FreeBSD ports tree until after 5.3 is
          released. The good news is, this will give the FreeBSD GNOME
          team more time to do quality assurance so to give you the
          best upgrade experience possible. If you just have to have
          the updates now, you can get the GNOME 2.8 ports from our
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">development CVS server</a>

          . Packages for i386 will also be available soon from the
          <a href="docs/faq2.html#q21">GNOME Tinderbox</a>

          .</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>BSD# Project Formation</title>

          <p>The BSD# Project has recently been formed on
          <a href="http://forge.novell.com">Novell Forge</a>

          and is devoted to porting and maintaining the Mono .NET
          framework from Ximian on FreeBSD. The Mono framework consists
          of not only the Mono runtime environment and compiler but the
          XSP webserver and Apache mod_mono for handling ASP.NET
          applications, the IKVM Java virtual machine for handling Java
          within the .NET framework, and numerous data providers to
          access common library functions in C# or integration with
          existing C libraries. The project is currently in it's early
          stages but has recently finished ports for all the latest
          Mono packages distributed by Ximian. There is still much more
          work to be done; from fixing threading issues in the runtime
          environment, to wider testing of XSP and IKVM, to further
          understanding the framework and how it all functions. Those
          interested in Mono and the BSD# Project are asked to visit
          the project's
          <a
          href="http://forge.novell.com/modules/xfmod/project/?bsd-sharp">
          homepage</a>

          and join the
          <a
          href="http://forge.novell.com/modules/xfmod/maillist/?group_id=1498">
          mailing lists</a>

          .</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>Mono .NET Framework Release 1.0.1</title>

          <p>The BSD# Project is pleased to announce that the entire
          Mono 1.0.1 .NET framework from Ximian has been ported for
          FreeBSD and is ready for use. In addition to an updated port
          of the Mono runtime, ports for all the latest library
          bindings, XSP and Apache mod_mono for ASP.NET, and the IKVM
          Java VM for .NET have been made. Please be aware that due to
          changes in the latest Mono release and recent changes to
          threading in the 5.X branch of FreeBSD, these packages only
          work on 5.3-BETA versions and above. These ports are not
          currently available in the standard FreeBSD ports tree at the
          moment as they require wider testing but the intent is for
          them to be there soon. Those interested in Mono may use
          mono-merge script available from the
          <a
          href="http://forge.novell.com/modules/xfmod/project/?bsd-sharp">
          BSD# Project</a>

          to merge the project's ports tree with their own.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>Koop Mast joins the FreeBSD GNOME Team</title>

          <p>Koop Mast became the newest member of the FreeBSD GNOME
          Team. He will focus mainly on Gstreamer. Please join us in
          welcoming Koop to the team!</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>1</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.7.92 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.7.92 (aka 2.8 Release Candidate 1) has been
          released, and the FreeBSD port is right there waiting. This
          release has fixed most of the major headaches from 2.7.4, and
          users that were looking for a good time to upgrade should
          consider this a good time. All the details on how to obtain
          this release can be found in our
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">Development Branch FAQ</a>

          . Packages for i386 will be available shortly.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>July</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.7.4 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.7.4 has been released just five short days after
          2.7.3, and the FreeBSD ports is ready to go. This latest
          release features a new desktop MIME system that is designed
          to integrate more closely with KDE. Unfortunately, not all of
          the GNOME applications have been converted over to it. All
          the details on how to obtain this release can be found in our

          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">Development Branch FAQ</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>19</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.7.3 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.7.3 has been released, and the FreeBSD port has
          been updated as well. This is the first development release
          to have the full proposed modules list included. New GNOME
          desktop modules that are available for FreeBSD include
          evolution, gnome-nettool, gnome-keyring-manager, and vino.
          Those that like to run with scissors can check our
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">Development Branch FAQ</a>

          for instructions on getting this release.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>June</name>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.6.2 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.6.2 has been released, and the FreeBSD port has
          been updated as well. This is another bug fix release in the
          GNOME 2.6 series. That said, a few new features did sneak in.
          Check out the
          <a
          href="http://lists.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2004-June/msg00067.html">
          release notes</a>

          for to see what's new.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.7.2 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.7.2 has been released, and the FreeBSD port has
          been updated right along with it. This is the second step on
          the road to GNOME 2.8. Note: this release still identifies
          itself as GNOME 2.7.1 in Help-&gt;About GNOME, but it really
          is 2.7.2. Those that solemnly swear to be up to no good can
          check our
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">Development Branch FAQ</a>

          for instructions on obtaining this release.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>3</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.7.1 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.7.1 has been released, and the FreeBSD port is
          available. This is a development release, and as such, should
          only be used by those willing to take risks. All of the
          details on getting this release, upgrading from GNOME 2.6,
          and debugging problems can be found on our
          <a href="docs/develfaq.html">Development Branch FAQ</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>1</name>

        <event>
          <title>Jeremy Messenger joins the FreeBSD GNOME Team</title>

          <p>
          <a href="mailto:mezz@FreeBSD.org">Jeremy Messenger</a>

          has finally agreed to take the FreeBSD commit bit that he
          earned a long time ago. Additionally, he is joining the ranks
          of the elite FreeBSD GNOME committers. Please join the
          FreeBSD GNOME team in welcoming Mezz to the Project!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.6 Release available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>After a delay stemming from GNOME server security
          compromises, GNOME 2.6 Release is available for FreeBSD!
          There are
          <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/faq26.html">
          instructions</a>

          for the upgrade process, and
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/tinderbox/">packages</a>

          for all supported versions of FreeBSD!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>17</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.6 Release Candidate 1 available for
          FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.6 Release Candidate 1 desktop has been
          released and just
          <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          cries out</a>

          for use. GNOME 2.6 is on schedule for final release on March
          24, so be sure to test this release thoroughly.
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/tinderbox/">Packages</a>

          for all supported versions of FreeBSD are also available.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>13</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.6 Beta 2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.6 Beta 2 desktop has been released and
          <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
          ports</a>

          are available. We are currently looking for volunteers to
          help with testing ports and packages installation as well as
          provide feedback on bugs, missing features, screenshots, and
          FAQ ideas. Please send any and all questions and comments to
          the
          <a href="mailto:freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD GNOME
          Team</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>8</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME package server now online</title>

          <p>A new package building
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/tinderbox/">server</a>

          for FreeBSD GNOME packages is online, and serving out GNOME 2
          desktop packages for both 2.4 and 2.5. Packages are available
          for all supported versions of FreeBSD. The server is still in
          its infancy, and a bit slow, but it's working constantly to
          provide the most up-to-date GNOME packages possible. As time
          goes on, other GNOME meta-ports will be added to the
          build.</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.6 Beta 1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.6 Beta 1 desktop is now available for FreeBSD.
          If you have been looking for a good time to switch away from
          GNOME 2.4, now is that time. Please test extra hard so we can
          work out all the bugs before the end of the month release
          date. All the details on upgrading to GNOME 2.6 Beta 1 can be
          found
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">here</a>

          . Note: the release identifies itself as 2.5.90, but it is,
          in fact, GNOME 2.6 Beta 1.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>18</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.5 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.5.5 desktop is now available for FreeBSD. It
          slipped in a scant four days after 2.5.4 to test weed out
          some more bugs before the first 2.6 beta release. The low
          down on obtaining this version and upgrading from GNOME 2.4
          can be found in the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">development
          FAQ</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.4 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The nameless GNOME 2.5.4 desktop is now available for
          FreeBSD. This latest development release is slated to be the
          last before the GNOME 2.6 beta cycle begins. Those interested
          in joining the testing effort should read the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">development
          FAQ</a>

          for details on obtaining GNOME 2.5 and upgrading from 2.4</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>5</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team is proud to announce the
          availability of GNOME 2.4.2 for FreeBSD. This is the next
          release in from the stable GNOME 2.4 branch. GNOME 2.4.2 is
          mainly a bugfix and translation release. The next major
          feature release will be GNOME 2.6 due out in late March.
          GNOME 2.4.2 is available in the FreeBSD ports tree.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>3</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.5.3 desktop, "That and a pair of testicles"
          release, is now available for FreeBSD. This releases fixes a
          lot of bugs in the previous release especially having to do
          with broken icons. Evolution users will be happy to find the
          Calendar and Contacts functionality also works now. For those
          wanting to ride the walrus, read the
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">FAQ</a>

          on how to get GNOME 2.5, merge it into your ports tree, and
          even upgrade from GNOME 2.4.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.2 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.5.2 desktop, "You want me to blow on your
          toes?" release, is now available for FreeBSD. To accompany
          this release, the FreeBSD GNOME team has setup an
          <a href="&base;/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">FAQ</a>

          on how to track the GNOME development branches. Please read
          that to familiarize yourself with what is involved. This
          release can be checked out from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Also be sure to download the ``marcusmerge'' script from
          the same URL to merge this tree into your main ports
          tree.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2003</name>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.5.1 desktop, "Hey, at least I'm housebroken"
          release, is now available for FreeBSD. This release is jammed
          packed with goodies including Evolution 1.5, gnome-network,
          gDesklets, and monkey-bubble. Those with iron constitutions,
          and a thirst for bug hunting should check out the ``ports''
          module from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . If you have not done so already, be sure to get the
          ``marcusmerge'' script from the above URL to aid in the
          upgrade. A man page for the script can also be found at the
          above URL.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4.1 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.4.1 desktop, the "Better late than never"
          release, is now available for FreeBSD. Due to the 5.2 ports
          freeze, GNOME 2.4.1 will not officially enter the FreeBSD
          ports tree until after 5.2 is released. However, it can be
          obtained from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          with the help of the ``marcusmerge'' script. For a complete
          list of what's changed, checkout the
          <a
          href="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-announce-list/2003-November/msg00095.html">
          release announcement</a>

          .</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.5.0 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.5.0 desktop, the "Obviously you're not a
          golfer" release, is now available for FreeBSD. FreeBSD GNOME
          junkies can check out this release from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Be sure to get the latest copy of the ``marcusmerge''
          script while you're there to help with the upgrade. Thanks to
          a few of our users, there is also a
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/marcusmerge.8.html">man
          page</a>

          to go with this script. NOTE: this is a developers release,
          and bugs will exist. If you're not into bug-hunting, you
          should probably steer clear until 2.6.0 is released.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>Pav Lucistnik joins the FreeBSD GNOME Team</title>

          <p>
          <a href="mailto:pav@FreeBSD.org">Pav Lucistnik</a>

          has been granted a commit bit, and has been added as the
          newest member of the FreeBSD GNOME team. Pav will be involved
          in all aspects of the FreeBSD GNOME project, and we're
          excited to have him aboard. Please join us all in welcoming
          Pav to the FreeBSD GNOME team!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME now builds on ia64</title>

          <p>Thanks to work by
          <a href="mailto:marcel@FreeBSD.org">Marcel Moolenaar</a>

          , the GNOME desktop now builds on ia64. There are runtime
          issues to be resolved, but this was expected. Most
          importantly, we have new ways to exercise FreeBSD/ia64 in
          general and KSE/ia64 in particular. Not to mention that we
          can proceed porting and building other GNOME ports. GNOME for
          FreeBSD now runs on i386, Alpha, Sparc64, and ia64.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>16</name>

        <event>
          <title>Adam Weinberger celebrates one year with the FreeBSD
          GNOME Project</title>

          <p>It's been one year since Adam Weinberger (aka adamw, aka
          lemniscate) signed his soul over to our project. Since then,
          project documentation readability is at an all-time high, we
          have more wacky GNOME games in the tree than ever before, and
          we're keeping up quicker with GNOME releases. Thanks,
          Adam!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>September</name>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4.0 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.4.0: "Temujin" has been released, and is now
          available for FreeBSD. Due to a timing conflict with the
          upcoming FreeBSD 4.9-RELEASE, GNOME 2.4 will not make it into
          the official ports tree until sometime in early October. In
          the meantime, you can get the ports from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Get the ``marcusmerge'' script to help you with the
          upgrade. If you already have this script, download it again
          as it has been updated. Thanks to all those who made this
          release possible.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4 Release Candidate 1 available for
          FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.4 Release Candidate 1 (aka "Kublai") desktop
          has been released and ported to FreeBSD. Those wanting to
          make GNOME 2.4 the best release ever should checkout the
          ``ports'' module per the instructions at the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Be sure to get the ``marcusmerge'' script as well to with
          the upgrade (even if you already have this script, download
          it again as it has been updated). Note, this release will
          identify itself as GNOME 2.3.90, but it is, in fact, GNOME
          2.4 Release Candidate 1.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>August</name>

      <day>
        <name>30</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4 Beta 2 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.4 Beta 2 (aka "Subotai") desktop has been
          released and ported to FreeBSD. This final beta is
          deep-frozen, meaning the final 2.4 will have very few, if
          any, source code changes from this release. The few, the
          brave, the testers should checkout the ``ports'' module per
          the instructions at the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Be sure to get the ``marcusmerge'' script as well to help
          with the upgrade. Note, this release will identify itself as
          2.3.7, but it is, in fact, GNOME 2.4 Beta 2.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>17</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.4 Beta 1 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.4 Beta 1 (aka "Jelme") desktop has been
          released, and ported to FreeBSD. For those of you chomping at
          the bit to test drive this baby, checkout the ``ports''
          module per the instructions at the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Be sure to get the ``marcusmerge'' script as well to help
          with the upgrade. Note, this release will identify itself as
          2.3.6, but it is, in fact, GNOME 2.4 Beta 1. For a list of
          what has changed between GNOME 2.2 and 2.4 checkout
          <a href="http://www.ilug-cal.org/GNOME_2_4.html">
          http://www.ilug-cal.org/GNOME_2_4.html</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>Alexander Nedotsukov joins the FreeBSD GNOME
          Team</title>

          <p>
          <a href="mailto:bland@FreeBSD.org">Alexander Nedotsukov</a>

          has been granted a commit bit, and has joined the FreeBSD
          GNOME team. Alexander will be working on general GNOME
          desktop porting and bug-busting as well as focusing on his
          ports of the GNOME 2 C++ bindings. Please join us in
          welcoming Alexander to the team!</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>3</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.3.5 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.3.5 desktop, the "Jebe" release, is now
          available for FreeBSD. Bleeding-edge GNOME fans can check out
          this release from the
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          MarcusCom CVS repository</a>

          . Be sure to get the ``marcusmerge'' script as well to help
          with the upgrade.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>July</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 1.4 Removed from FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 1.4 Desktop has been removed from FreeBSD. Users
          are encouraged to upgrade to GNOME 2.2 which offers many
          improvements over the older desktop. This follows the GNOME
          announcement that development on the 1.4 desktop had
          stopped.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.2.2 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.2.2 desktop has been released and ported to
          FreeBSD. GNOME 2.2.x is available in the main FreeBSD ports
          tree. Simply cvsup your ports, and upgrade. Packages may take
          a while, however. For details on what is new and what has
          been fixed, please see the GNOME 2.2.2
          <a
          href="http://www.gnomedesktop.org/article.php?sid=1213&amp;mode=thread&amp;order=0">
          change log</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>7</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.3.3 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.3.3, "The Four Hounds", has been released and
          ported to FreeBSD. Hearty adventurers should checkout the
          ``ports'' module per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          , and download the ``marcusmerge'' script to aid in the
          upgrade.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>22</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.3.2 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>On time, and featuring gnopernicus, the FreeBSD GNOME team
          presents the next GNOME 2.3 development snapshot, the "Little
          Hero" release. Testers should checkout the ``ports'' module
          per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          , and download the ``marcusmerge'' script to aid in the
          upgrade.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.3.1 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>It's a bit late, but here none the less. For those willing
          to live on the edge, the next installment of the GNOME 2.3
          development snapshot, code named "Daddy Walrus," has been
          ported. This snapshot lacks three ports found in the official
          GNOME distribution. They are gnopernicus, gnome-speech, and
          gnome-system-tools. The latter is missing because it does not
          fully work with FreeBSD, while the two former components rely
          on festival, which is broken on -CURRENT. To help out with
          the testing, checkout the ``ports'' module per the
          instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          . Be sure to download the ``marcusmerge'' script as well to
          aid in upgrading existing ports.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>13</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.3.0 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Calling all testers! The first of the GNOME 2.3
          development releases is now available. Code named "Mighty
          Atom," this release includes quite a few new proposed
          modules. The GNOME 2.3 snapshots will become the GNOME 2.4
          desktop on or around September 8. The full scoop can be found

          <a href="http://www.gnomedesktop.org/article.php?sid=1045">
          here</a>

          . Those wanting to test this release should checkout the
          ``ports'' module per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          . Be sure to download the ``marcusmerge'' script from the
          same page. This script will help you merge the GNOME
          development ports tree into your main ports tree. Send all
          questions to
          <a href="mailto:freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org">
          freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>4</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.2.1 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>Now that 4.8-RELEASE is out the door, the ports freeze has
          lifted, and GNOME 2.2.1 has been committed. GNOME 2.2.1 is a
          bugfix and performance release. However, it does boast "the
          best Nautilus ever." More details can be found at
          <a href="http://www.gnomedesktop.org/article.php?sid=986">
          http://www.gnomedesktop.org/article.php?sid=986</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>7</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.2 Desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.2 Desktop has been released, and ports are
          available for FreeBSD. Checkout the GNOME 2.2
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.2/notes/">release
          notes</a>

          for the full scoop on what has changed. A list of known
          issues with the FreeBSD port can be found
          <a href="docs/knownissues.html">here</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.2 Release Candidate 2 available for
          FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.91, "OUTATIME" release, is now available,
          and ports have been made for FreeBSD. This is the last
          release candidate before GNOME 2.2 is released on February 5.
          For those wanting to test this release, checkout the
          ``ports'' module per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          . A script is also provided at that site to help in merging
          this tree with the official FreeBSD ports tree.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>19</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME desktop 2.0.3 available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.0.3 desktop has been completed for FreeBSD
          after the long ports freeze to prepare for 5.0-RELEASE. This
          new release includes a variety of bugfixes over 2.0.2, as
          well as some polishing off of promised GNOME 2.0
          features.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME desktop 2.2 Release Candidate 1 available for
          FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.90 desktop, "1.21 Jigawatts" release, is
          available, and ports have been made. This is the first
          release candidate for GNOME 2.2, and is considered to be
          quite stable. People wanting to test this release should
          checkout the ``ports'' module per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>

  <year>
    <name>2002</name>

    <month>
      <name>December</name>

      <day>
        <name>22</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.5 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.5 desktop, "Enchantment Under the Sea"
          release, is available and ports have been made. Testers
          should checkout the ``ports'' module via anonymous CVS per
          the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.4 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.4 desktop, "We don't need... roads" release,
          is available and port have been made. For those wanting to
          participate in the testing, the ports are available via
          anonymous CVS from MarcusCom. Checkout the ``ports'' module
          per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>1</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.3 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.3 desktop, "Twin Pines" release, is
          available and ports have been made for it (including the
          GStreamer components!). For those wanting to test this next
          installment in the 2.1 developer series, ports are available
          via anonymous CVS from MarcusCom. Checkout the ``ports''
          module per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 to be the default GNOME in 5.0-RELEASE</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.0.2 will be the default GNOME desktop in the
          upcoming FreeBSD 5.0-RELEASE. The default desktop
          installation will come with both the Sawfish and Metacity
          window managers.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>November</name>

      <day>
        <name>24</name>

        <event>
          <title>FreeBSD GNOME news updates now available in RDF
          format</title>

          <p>The news updates from the FreeBSD GNOME Project can now be
          downloaded in RDF format. Simply point your RDF consumer at
          <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/news.rdf">
          http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/news.rdf</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.2 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.2 desktop, "Life Preserver" release, is
          available, and ports have been made for most of it. There are
          still some FreeBSD issues with the new GStreamer stuff, and
          some of the newer modules (such as system-tray) haven't yet
          been ported. For those wanting to test this latest
          development snapshot, ports are available via anonymous CVS
          from MarcusCom. Checkout the ``ports'' module per the
          instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>October</name>

      <day>
        <name>26</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.1 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.1 desktop, "Flux Capacitor" release, is
          available, and ports have been made for those wanting to test
          this next installment of the GNOME 2.2 development version.
          The ports are available via anonymous CVS from MarcusCom.
          Checkout the ``ports'' per the instructions at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>13</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.1.0 desktop available for FreeBSD</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2.1.0 desktop, "88MPH" release is available, and
          ports have been made for those wanting to test. The ports are
          available via CVS from MarcusCom. A cvsweb interface is
          available from
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi">
          http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi</a>

          . The module name is ``ports''. Instructions for checking out
          the ports is available at the cvsweb site.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>September</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.0.2 Final Released</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.0.2 development API and desktop has been released
          today (just in time for 4.7-RELEASE)! The ports tree is in
          sync with 2.0.2, and i386 -stable packages are available from

          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/">
          MarcusCom</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.0.2 RC1 Released</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.0.2 Release Candidate 1, "The Considerable Duck",
          is now available. The ports tree is already in sync with this
          release, as is the package distribution at
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/">
          MarcusCom</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>August</name>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.0.1 Officially Released!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2.0.1 was officially released today. More info can
          be found at
          <a href="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.0/">
          http://www.gnome.org/start/2.0/</a>

          . The ports collection is already in sync with 2.0.1, and
          2.0.1 packages are available for i386 -stable from
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/">
          http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>14</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 Packages Now Available!</title>

          <p>GNOME 2 packages for i386 FreeBSD-stable have been posted
          to
          <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/">
          http://www.marcuscom.com/downloads/packages/gnome/</a>

          . Both .tgz and .tbz packages have been posted. This includes
          everything needed to install GNOME 2 except for XFree86.
          These packages were built using XFree86 4.2.0 which is
          available in package format from a variety of locations.
          Please send email to
          <a href="mailto:freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org">
          freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

          if you have any problems.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 Desktop Updated to 2.0.1 Release Candidate
          1</title>

          <p>The GNOME 2 components have now been updated to the
          just-announced GNOME 2.0.1 Release Candidate 1: "Not
          Considered Harmful" release.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>June</name>

      <day>
        <name>30</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2.0 Officially Released</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team is proud to announce that GNOME 2.0
          Release has been ported to FreeBSD. This comes four days
          after the GNOME Project made their press release. Look for
          documentation updates to cover the new GNOME 2.0 desktop.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>15</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 components update to Release Candidate
          1</title>

          <p>GNOME 2 on FreeBSD is now up to the "Fever Pitch" RC1.
          This is supposedly going to be the final release candidate
          for GNOME 2, with a final release coming around June 21.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 components updated to the latest
          snapshot</title>

          <p>GNOME 2 components have been updated to the "Release
          formerly known as..." release snapshot. This brings a number
          of GNOME 2.0 components to 2.0.0. GNOME 2.0 release is
          imminent!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>May</name>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME 2 components updated to the latest
          snapshot</title>

          <p>GNOME 2 components have been upgraded to "Stay on target!"
          release snapshot. This brings a whole new round of bug fixes
          and GUI improvements to GNOME 2.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>21</name>

        <event>
          <title>Full port of GNOME2 beta 5 release is
          available</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD
          <a href="mailto:gnome@FreeBSD.org">GNOME Team</a>

          has finished porting of GNOME2 beta 5 release to FreeBSD. All
          existing ports were updated and many missed were added. The
          FreeBSD Ports Collection now contains all bits and pieces of
          the GNOME2 platform, both desktop and development ones.</p>

          <p>The team now works on improving quality of the port, by
          tracking down FreeBSD-specific problems and fixing them.
          Another goal is to provide set of pre-built GNOME2 binary
          packages on the official FreeBSD 4.6 release media along with
          GNOME 1.4 bits and pieces.</p>

          <p>We would encourage any help from our users in the form of
          problem reports, patches, suggestions etc.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>April</name>

      <day>
        <name>26</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME2 ports updated to GNOME2 beta4 release</title>

          <p>All components of GNOME2 Platform already ported to
          FreeBSD have been updated to the latest versions found in the
          official GNOME2 beta4 distribution.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>6</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME2 ports updated to GNOME2 beta3 release</title>

          <p>All components of GNOME2 Development Platform already
          ported to FreeBSD have been updated to the latest versions
          found in the official GNOME2 beta3 distribution.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>5</name>

        <event>
          <title>Joe Clarke now committer</title>

          <p>
          <a href="mailto:marcus@marcuscom.com">Joe Marcus Clarke</a>

          has been granted a FreeBSD commit bit (direct access to the
          cvs repository). His main focus as a committer will be
          FreeBSD GNOME, so that expect much faster problem resolution
          than ever. It is also expected that he would revive somewhat
          stalled GNOME2 porting effort. Welcome aboard, Joe!!!</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>March</name>

      <day>
        <name>12</name>

        <event>
          <title>Mozilla 0.9.9 is out</title>

          <p>Mozilla 0.9.9 is out bringing many bugfixes and new
          features and FreeBSD port was updated accordingly. Update is
          strongly recommended to all current users.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>11</name>

        <event>
          <title>GNOME2 ports updated to GNOME2 beta2 release</title>

          <p>All components of GNOME2 Development Platform already
          ported to FreeBSD have been updated to the latest versions
          found in the official GNOME2 beta2 distribution. Thanks to
          <a href="mailto:marcus@marcuscom.com">Joe Marcus Clarke</a>

          for his help.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>February</name>

      <day>
        <name>10</name>

        <event>
          <title>Work on porting GNOME2 platform to FreeBSD has
          begun</title>

          <p>The FreeBSD GNOME team started some initial work on
          getting GNOME2 bits and pieces running on FreeBSD. The work
          is expected to take quite some time, though some initial set
          of ports making up core of the GNOME2 platform would be
          committed to the FreeBSD ports repository as soon as
          possible.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>

    <month>
      <name>January</name>

      <day>
        <name>31</name>

        <event>
          <title>New FreeBSD GNOME site up and running</title>

          <p>Brand new FreeBSD GNOME site is up and running. Many
          thanks to all who make it possible, particularly
          <a href="mailto:marcus@marcuscom.com">Joe Marcus Clarke</a>

          and
          <a href="mailto:john_m_cooper@yahoo.com">John Merryweather
          Cooper</a>

          .</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>29</name>

        <event>
          <title>Ade is back!</title>

          <p>Famous
          <a href="mailto:ade@FreeBSD.org">Ade Lovett</a>

          , who was one of the main founders of the FreeBSD GNOME
          porting effort, but due to various reasons had left the
          FreeBSD GNOME team in June 2001 decided to re-join us. This
          is truly amazing news, because we still have many things to
          do, so that his help and huge experience in the field would
          be really useful.</p>
        </event>
      </day>

      <day>
        <name>28</name>

        <event>
          <title>Several core GNOME components updated</title>

          <p>Several core GNOME ports were updated to the latest
          versions (gnomelibs, gnomecore, glade etc.) Please follow
          usual
          <a href="docs/faq.html#q4">instructions</a>

          to update your system.</p>
        </event>
      </day>
    </month>
  </year>
</news>

