<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2017</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p><strong>This is a draft of the July&ndash;September 2017
      status report.  Please check back after it is finalized, and
      an announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
      list.</strong></p>

    <?ignore
    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between July and
      September 2017.  This is the third of four reports planned for
      2017.</p>

    <p>The third quarter of 2017 was another productive quarter for
      the &os; project and community. [...]</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from October
      to December 2017 is January 7, 2017.</p>
     ?>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>

    <p>Entries from the various official and semi-official teams,
      as found in the <a href="&enbase;/administration.html">Administration
	Page</a>.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>

    <p>Projects that span multiple categories, from the kernel and userspace
      to the Ports Collection or external projects.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>

    <p>Updates to kernel subsystems/features, driver support,
      filesystems, and more.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>

    <p>Updating platform-specific features and bringing in support
      for new hardware platforms.</p>.
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>

    <p>Changes affecting the base system and programs in it.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>

    <p>Changes affecting the Ports Collection, whether sweeping
      changes that touch most of the tree, or individual ports
      themselves.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>

    <p>Noteworthy changes in the documentation tree or new external
      books/documents.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>

    <p>Objects that defy categorization.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>third</name>

    <description>Third-Party Projects</description>

    <p>Many projects build upon &os; or incorporate components of
      &os; into their project.  As these projects may be of interest 
      to the broader &os; community, we sometimes include brief
      updates submitted by these projects in our quarterly report.
      The &os; project makes no representation as to the accuracy or
      veracity of any claims in these submissions.</p>
  </category>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os;&nbsp;Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/11.1R/announce.html">&os;&nbsp;11.1-RELEASE Announcement</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/10.4R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;10.4-RELEASE Schedule</url>
      <url href="https://download.FreeBSD.org/ftp/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os; Development Snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is responsible for setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project releases
	of &os;, announcing code freezes, and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team continued finalizing the
	11.1-RELEASE cycle, with the final release builds starting on
	July 21 and the official release announcement email sent on
	July 26.  Thank you to everyone who helped test 11.1-RELEASE,
	ensuring its quality and stability.&nbsp;[1]</p>

      <p>&os;&nbsp;11.1-RELEASE is the second release from the
	<tt>stable/11</tt> branch.</p>

      <p>Additionally, the &os; Release Engineering Team started the
	10.4-RELEASE cycle, with the code slush starting on July 28.
	With the final release build expected to start on September 29
	and the official announcement overlapping the end of the
	quarter, everything is on schedule as of this
	writing.&nbsp;[2]</p>

      <p>&os;&nbsp;10.4-RELEASE will be the fifth release from the
	<tt>stable/10</tt> branch, and is planned to be the final release
	of the 10.x series.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation&nbsp;[1]</sponsor>

    <partialsponsor>The &os; Foundation&nbsp;[2]</partialsponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat="arch">
    <title>AMD Zen (family 17h) support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	  <email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
	</name>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>This quarter, a bit of work was done to enhance platform
	support for AMD Zen (Ryzen, Threadripper, Epyc) processors:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The CPU topology detection code was enhanced to properly
	  detect Zen dies and CCXes.  This gives the scheduler more
	  locality information to make scheduling decisions.</li>

	<li>The x86 topology analysis was enhanced to report dies and
	  CCXes, in addition to the existing reporting on packages,
	  cores, and threads.  An example  of the new output is
	  &quot;FreeBSD/SMP: 1 package(s) x 2 groups x 2 cache groups
	  x 4 core(s) x 2 hardware threads&quot;.</li>

	<li>The amdsmn(4) driver for accessing SMN (System Management
	  Network) registers was added.</li>

	<li>CPU temperature monitoring support for Zen was added to
	  amdtemp(4).</li>

	<li>In cpufreq(4):
	  <ul>
	    <li>Added support for decoding Zen P-state info from MSRs
	      (mostly not necessary due to ACPI P-state information,
	      but potentially useful)</li>

	    <li>Work around the apparent Ryzen inability to achieve
	      the P1 state by not busying cores waiting to
	      transition.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>The intpm(4) smbus driver was fixed to attach to FCH
	  (Fusion Controller Hub).</li>

	<li>All MCA banks are now enabled and monitored on Zen
	  CPUs.</li>

	<li>Feature bit decoding was added for: CLZERO, SVM features,
	  RAS capabilities.</li>

	<li>SHA intrinsic support was added to the aesni(4) driver.
	  Ryzen is currently the only desktop processor to feature
	  these intrinsics.  Support is also present in Intel's
	  Goldmont line of low end SoCs.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Overall, Zen is now a very usable platform for x86
	workstations and servers.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>Dell EMC Isilon</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Add HWPMC support for new performance counters in
	Zen.</task>

      <task>Add support for the CCP (Crypto Co-Processor).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Updates to GDB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Baldwin</common>
	</name>
	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Luca</given>
	  <common>Pizzamiglio</common>
	</name>
	<email>pizzamig@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The port has been updated to GDB 8.0.</p>

      <p>Support for &os;/aarch64 userland binaries has been committed
	upstream.  These patches, along with support for debugging
	&os;/aarch64 kernels, have been committed to the port.</p>

      <p>Upstream patches adding improved support for &os;/arm userland
	binaries are currently in review.  &os; 12 has recently grown
	support for debugging VFP registers via <tt>ptrace()</tt> and
	core dumps as part of this work.  Support for &os;/arm kernels
	will be added to the port after the upstream patches are added
	to the port.</p>

       <p>Support for <tt>$_siginfo</tt> has been committed upstream.
	 This uses the recently added NT_LWPINFO note to extract
	 signal information from process cores.</p>

       <p>Hangs that occured when GDB's <tt>kill</tt> command was used
	 were fixed in &os; in r313992.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Figure out why the powerpc <tt>kgdb</tt> targets are not able to
	unwind the stack past the initial frame.</task>

      <task>Test support for sparc64 binaries and kernels.</task>

      <task>Add support for debugging powerpc vector registers.</task>

      <task>Implement <tt>info proc</tt> commands.</task>

      <task>Implement <tt>info os</tt> commands.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>Absolute &os;, 3rd Edition</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michael</given>
	  <common>Lucas</common>
	</name>
	<email>mwlucas@michaelwlucas.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://blather.michaelwlucas.com/archives/3020">Official Announcement</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The first draft of the third edition of <em>Absolute
	&os;</em> is finished.  It is 220,200 words, or roughly enough to
	stun a medium-sized ox.  It's on target to be in print before
	BSDCan 2018.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Stare at the wall blankly for a few days.</task>

      <task>Fix all the problems pointed out by dozens of community
	reviewers.</task>

      <task>Fix all the problems pointed out by John Baldwin, tech
	reviewer extraordinaire.</task>

      <task>Editing.  Copyediting.  Page layout.  Page editing.
	Re-editing.  Indexing.  Edits discovered by indexer.</task>

      <task>Pre-orders should open some time next year.</task>

      <task>Restrain myself from strangling people who ask when the
	fourth edition is coming.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Puppet</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Puppet Team</name>
	<email>puppet@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://puppetcommunity.slack.com/messages/C6CK0UGB1/">Puppetlab's &os; Slack Channel</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This summer has seen the creation of a puppet@ team to help
	maintain the ~30 Puppet-related ports in the &os; ports tree.
	These ports were previously maintained by various committers,
	and from time to time this introduced some delays when
	updating a port due to the need to wait for a maintainer's
	approval for a related change to a different port.</p>

      <p>Puppet 5 is now in the ports tree (as
	<tt>sysutils/puppet5</tt>).  The C++ version of Facter
	(<tt>sysutils/facter</tt>) got a lot of love and is now a
	drop-in replacement for the previous Ruby version of Facter
	(<tt>sysutils/rubygem-facter</tt>); it is the default facts
	source for the Puppet 5 port.</p>

      <p>Work continues on bringing in Puppetserver 5 to the ports
	tree, and on keeping all the ports up-to-date.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The <tt>pkgng</tt> package provider has some minor issues
	(it breaks things when no repos are configured, and is not
	working properly from the context of the MCollective package
	agent).</task>

      <task>The <tt>databases/puppetdb[345]</tt> and
	<tt>sysutils/puppetserver[45]</tt> ports rely on Clojure and
	Java, and download compiled jar files instead of building them
	from source.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Intel iWARP Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bartosz</given>
	  <common>Sobczak</common>
	</name>
	<email>bartosz.sobczak@intel.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D11378">iWARP for
      <tt>ixl</tt></url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>iWARP is a protocol suite that enables efficient movement
	of data across the network, building on Remote Direct Memory
	Access, Direct Data Placement, and Marker PDU Aligned Framing.
	It endeavors to avoid unnecessary (local) data copies and
	offload work from the main CPU to dedicated hardware.</p>

      <p>An initial commit adding iWARP support for the Intel X722
	family of network adapters is under review.  This is an
	important step towards introducing full iWARP support on
	systems equipped with Intel C620 Series Chipsets.  Currently,
	with the <tt>iw_ixl</tt> driver, only the kVerbs API is
	supported.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Additional testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Intel 10G <tt>iflib</tt> Driver Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Chris</given>
	  <common>Galazka</common>
	</name>
	<email>krzysztof.galazka@intel.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Piotr</given>
	  <common>Pietruszewski</common>
	</name>
	<email>piotr.pietruszewski@intel.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D11727"><tt>ixgbe</tt> <tt>iflib</tt> Conversion</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>ix</tt> and <tt>ixv</tt> network interface drivers
	support a variety of Intel network interfaces, with line
	speeds at 10 Gbit/second.</p>

      <p>This quarter, with the help of Matt Macy and Sean Bruno (among
	others), we've submitted a review in Phabricator for the
	conversion of the <tt>ixgbe</tt> driver to use the new (and evolving)
	<tt>iflib</tt> interface.</p>

      <p>Stay tuned for the conversion of the 40G driver
	(<tt>ixl</tt>) as it is currently being ported to use
	<tt>iflib</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Additional testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>FreeBSDDesktop</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Johannes</given>
	  <common>Dieterich</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmd@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Johnston</common>
	</name>
	<email>markj@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Matthew</given>
	  <common>Macy</common>
	</name>
	<email>mmacy@nextbsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop/">FreeBSDDesktop GitHub</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSDDesktop team is happy to announce the availability of
	<tt>graphics/drm-next-kmod</tt>. This port for &os; CURRENT
	(amd64) provides support for the <tt>amdgpu</tt>,
	<tt>i915</tt>, and <tt>radeon</tt> DRM
	modules using the <tt>linuxkpi</tt> compatibility framework.
	The port currently corresponds to DRM from Linux 4.9 and is in
	an experimental state. It works reliably for a lot of testers
	with modern GPU hardware (AMD HD7000 series/Tahiti to Polaris
	and Intel HD3000/Sandy Bridge to Skylake). Broader testing and
	reporting/fixing of bugs is appreciated.</p> </body>

    <help>
      <task>Resolve issues that cause <tt>radeonkms</tt> and
	<tt>amdgpu</tt> to fail with EFI boot (though there is a
	workaround available).</task>

      <task>Upgrade to Linux 4.10 and higher DRM versions.</task>

      <task>Get feedback from broader testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>OpenJFX 8</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Tobias</given>
	  <common>Kortkamp</common>
	</name>
	<email>tobik@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.openjdk.java.net/display/OpenJFX/Main">OpenJFX Wiki</url>
      <url href="https://www.freshports.org/java/openjfx8-devel"><tt>java/openjfx8-devel</tt></url>
      <url href="https://www.freshports.org/java/openjfx8-scenebuilder"><tt>java/openjfx8-scenebuilder</tt></url>
      <url href="https://github.com/asciidocfx/AsciidocFX">AsciidocFX</url>
    </links>

    <body>
	<p>OpenJFX is an open source, next generation client
	  application platform for desktop and embedded systems
	  based on JavaSE.  This quarter, the OpenJFX port was
	  reworked and has some significant improvements.</p>

	<p>More modules are being built.  With the new web module we
	  gain support for applications that have their own builtin
	  web browser like e.g.  AsciidocFX.  The new media module
	  allows JavaFX applications to playback audio and video
	  files.</p>

	<p>A port of the JavaFX scenebuilder, a RAD tool for
	  building JavaFX scenes, was added to the ports tree.</p>

	<p>The OpenGL Prism backend for GPU acceleration was enabled
	  by default.</p>

	<p>From a mainainer's and contributor's perspective, the
	  port was simplified by moving all &os;-local patches to
	  the ports tree and fetching the upstream sources directly
	  instead of using a separate repository for them.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Upstream some of the patches</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>René</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">About &os; Ports</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">Contributing to Ports</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/index.html">&os; Ports Monitoring</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team Website</url>
      <url href="https://twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/">&os; portmgr on Twitter (@freebsd_portmgr)</url>
      <url href="https://www.facebook.com/portmgr">&os; Ports Management Team on Facebook</url>
      <url href="https://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383">&os; Ports Management Team on Google+</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Ports Collection now features over 31,600 ports. There are currently
	2671 problem reports, of which 718 are unassigned. This quarter saw
	almost 5,900 commits from 175 committers. The number of open PRs grew
	compared to last quarter, and outpaced the number of changes.</p>

      <p>This quarter, we welcomed Zach Leslie (zleslie@), Luca Pizzamiglio
	(pizzamig@), Craig Leres (leres@), Adriaan de Groot (adridg@), and Dave
	Cottlehuber (dch@) as new committers. The commit bits of the following
	committers were taken in for safekeeping: alonso@ after 19 months of
	inactivity, rpaulo@ per his request, and ache@ after he passed away.
	Despite several tries and changing mentors, kami@ lacked interest in
	completing his mentorship, so his commit bit was also taken in for
	safekeeping.</p>

      <p>On the infrastructure side, two <tt>USES</tt> values were
	removed because they outlived their usefulness:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>execinfo</tt>: <tt>libexecinfo</tt> is now available in the
	  base system of all supported &os; versions</li>

	<li><tt>twisted</tt>: there is only one Twisted port left</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The default version of GCC was bumped from 5 to 6. Firefox was updated
	to version 56.0 and Chromium to version 61.0.3163.100. The version of
	<tt>pkg</tt> itself was updated to 1.10.1.</p>

      <p>During this quarter, antoine@ performed 28 exp-runs to test version
	updates of major ports, improving <tt>USE_GITHUB</tt> and
	<tt>SHEBANG_FILES</tt>, and API changes to the base system.
	This quarter, the foundations for ports &quot;flavors&quot; were
	committed, though more development and testing will be
	performed in the coming quarter before it goes live.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The PR load needs more attention, as the number of open PRs
	has started to increase again.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
