<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<!-- This file was generated with https://github.com/trasz/md2docbook -->
<!--
     Variables to replace:
     %%START%%     - report month start
     %%STOP%%      - report month end
     %%YEAR%%      - report year
     %%NUM%%       - report issue (first, second, third, fourth)
     %%STARTNEXT%% - report month start
     %%STOPNEXT%%  - report month end
     %%YEARNEXT%%  - next report due year (if different than %%YEAR%%)
     %%DUENEXT%%   - next report due date (i.e., June 6)
-->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>%%START%%-%%STOP%%</month>

    <year>%%YEAR%%</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>With &os; having gone all the way to 12, it is perhaps
      useful to take a look back at all the things that have been
      accomplished, in terms of many visible changes, as well as all
      the things that happen behind the scenes to ensure that &os;
      continues to offer an alternative in both design,
      implementation, and execution.</p>

    <p>The things you can look forward to reading about are too
      numerous to summarize, but cover just about everything from
      finalizing releases, administrative work, optimizations
      and depessimizations, features added and fixed, and many areas
      of improvement that might just surprise you a little.</p>

    <p>Please have a cup of coffee, tea, hot cocoa, or other beverage
      of choice, and enjoy this culmulative set of reports covering
      everything that's been done since October, 2017.</p>

    <p>&mdash;Daniel Ebdrup</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>

    <p>Entries from the various official and semi-official teams,
      as found in the <a href="&enbase;/administration.html">Administration
        Page</a>.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>

    <p>Projects that span multiple categories, from the kernel and userspace
      to the Ports Collection or external projects.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>

    <p>Updating platform-specific features and bringing in support
      for new hardware platforms.</p>.
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>

    <p>Changes affecting the Ports Collection, whether sweeping
      changes that touch most of the tree, or individual ports
      themselves.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>

    <p>Noteworthy changes in the documentation tree or new external
      books/documents.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>third</name>

    <description>Third-Party Projects</description>

    <p>Many projects build upon &os; or incorporate components of
      &os; into their project.  As these projects may be of interest
      to the broader &os; community, we sometimes include brief
      updates submitted by these projects in our quarterly report.
      The &os; project makes no representation as to the accuracy or
      veracity of any claims in these submissions.</p>
  </category>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/10.4R/announce.html">FreeBSD 10.4-RELEASE announcement</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/11.2R/announce.html">FreeBSD 11.2-RELEASE announcement</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/12.0R/schedule.html">FreeBSD 12.0-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="https://download.FreeBSD.org/ftp/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">FreeBSD development snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Release Engineering Team responsibilities
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>setting and publishing release schedules for official
	project releases of FreeBSD</li>

	<li>announcing code slushes, freezes, and thaws</li>

	<li>maintaining the respective branches for all supported
	releases</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	The FreeBSD Release Engineering Team, led by Marius
	Strobl,
	completed the 10.4-RELEASE in early October 2017. FreeBSD
	10.4-RELEASE was the
	fifth release from the <tt>stable/10</tt> branch, which
	built on the
	stability and reliability of 10.3-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD 11.2-RELEASE cycle started April 20, 2018 with
	the
	announcement of the code slush. The first stage progress
	was
	continued throughout the rest of the quarter with the code
	freeze,
	followed by three BETA builds, three RC builds, and the
	final release
	build was announced June 27, 2018.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Release Engineering Team started the
	12.0-RELEASE cycle
	August 10, 2018 with the announcement of the code slush.
	The code
	freeze followed on August 24, 2018. The tentative date for
	the <tt>stable/12</tt> branch was expected to be September 21,
	2018.</p>

      <p>
	Due to unforeseen circumstances with upstream code that
	was necessary
	to include in 12.0-RELEASE, the tentative release schedule
	needed
	to be adjusted several times. The API changes in the
	updated version
	of the upstream code required changes to be made for all
	base system
	utilities that linked with the upstream code. By the end
	of the
	2018Q3 quarter, the <tt>stable/12</tt> branch had not been
	created due to
	this delay.</p>

      <p>Throughout the remainder of 2018Q3, several development
	snapshots builds
	were released for the <tt>head</tt>, <tt>stable/11</tt>,
	and <tt>stable/10</tt> branches.</p>

      <p>Much of this work was sponsored by the FreeBSD Foundation.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>René Ladan</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">About FreeBSD Ports</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">Contributing to ports</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports monitoring</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team</url>
      <url href="https://twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/">FreeBSD portmgr (@freebsd_portmgr)</url>
      <url href="https://www.facebook.com/portmgr">FreeBSD Ports Management Team (Facebook)</url>
      <url href="https://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383">FreeBSD Ports Management Team (Google+)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the first quarter of 2018, the number of ports grew
	to almost 32,000.
	In 2018Q1, there were
	2,100 open PRs with fewer than 600 unassigned. There were
	7,900 commits from 169 committers. Compared to last
	quarter, the number
	of commits grew by 18% and the number of PRs dropped by
	25%. Those are
	some good numbers!</p>

      <p>During the 2018Q2 and 2018Q3 quarters, the number of ports
	grew to just under
	34,000. The number of open PR grew to almost 2,500 with
	fewer than 600
	of those unassigned. A total of 175 committers made almost
	14,200 commits.
	Compared to the first quarter, the number of commits
	dropped by 10% and
	the number of PRs grew by 19%.</p>

      <p>During the last three quarters, portmgr took twelve commit
	bits in for
	safekeeping: daichi@, deichen@, ian@, junovitch@, kevlo@,
	maho@, nemysis@,
	pawel@, rea@, tabthorpe@, vg@, and wxs@.</p>

      <p>Portmgr welcomed thirteen new committers in 2018Q2 and
	2018Q3:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Devin Teske (dteske@)</li>

	<li>Eric Turgeon (ericbsd@)</li>

	<li>Fernando Apesteguía (fernape@)</li>

	<li>Fukang Chen (loader@)</li>

	<li>Gleb Popov (arrowd@)</li>

	<li>Jesper Schmitz Mouridsen (jsm@)</li>

	<li>John Hixson (jhixson@)</li>

	<li>Kevin Bowling (kbowling@)</li>

	<li>Koichiro IWAO (meta@)</li>

	<li>Mateusz Piotrowski (0mp@)</li>

	<li>Matthias Fechner (mfechner@)</li>

	<li>Sergey Kozlov (skozlov@)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	The following committers returned after a hiatus:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Ion-Mihai Tetcu (itetcu@)</li>

	<li>Kevin Lo (kevlo@)</li>

	<li>Sean Chittenden (seanc@)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	During the last three quarters, Antoine Brodin (antoine@)
	ran no
	fewer than 113 exp-runs against the ports tree. These runs
	were
	executed to test updates, perform cleanups, and make
	improvements
	to the framework and the base system. Most of the runs
	were for
	port upgrades, but others include LLD progress, changes to
	the
	default port versions, improved support for armv6, armv7,
	and RISC-V
	architectures, removed old base system functionality, new
	USES, and
	better matching pkg-plist with Makefile options (DOCS and
	EXAMPLES).</p>

      <p>Five new USES values were introduced:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>apache: handle dependencies on the Apache web server and
	modules</li>

	<li>eigen: automatically depend on math/eigen2 or math/eigen3</li>

	<li>emacs: handle dependencies on the Emacs editor and
	modules.</li>

	<li>gl replaces the old USE_GL from bsd.port.mk</li>

	<li>qt-dist, qt:4 and qt:5 replace the old USE_QT from
	bsd.qt.mk</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	The EXTRA_PATCHES functionality has been extended to
	support
	directories, where it will automatically apply all
	patch-\* files to the port.</p>

      <p>Ports using USES=php:phpize, php:ext, php:zend, and
	php:pecl have
	been flavored and packages are now automatically built
	for all
	versions of PHP that are supported (5.6, 7.0, 7.1 or 7.2).</p>

      <p>2018Q3 had updates of major ports: pkg 1.10.5, Chromium
	65.0.3325.181, Firefox 59.0.2, Firefox-ESR 52.7.3, Ruby
	2.3.7/2.5.1
	and Qt5 5.9.4.
	The default version of PHP was changed from 5.6 to 7.1.
	The former
	version of PHP is no longer supported by the developers.
	The
	default versions of Samba and GCC are now respectively 4.7
	and 7. The
	Xorg ports have been reorganized and there have been
	changes to
	net/openntpd. Please review the UPDATING file for relevant
	details.</p>

      <p>Open tasks:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The number of commits dropped somewhat over the last three
	quarters,
	leaving more PRs unresolved. If possible, please pick up
	some PRs
	and improve everyone's experience.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Much of Core's focus for the past months has been on three
	items:</p>

      <p>1. Coordination between different groups to support the
	upcoming 12.0 release. The timing of the OpenSSL
	1.1.1 release posed challenges. The new OpenSSL
	version included API changes, so many components of
	the base system and ports required changes.
	Staying with the older OpenSSL in 12.0 was not a
	feasible option, because it would have meant
	backporting many changes to a version of OpenSSL
	that would be unmaintained by the upstream source.</p>

      <p>2. Discussions with the release engineering team and Scott
	Long about updating the FreeBSD release process.
	Topics for exploration include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>having more frequent point releases</li>

	<li>changing the support model</li>

	<li>revising and improving the tooling used to manage the tree
	and releases</li>

	<li>additional topics as they are discovered</li>
      </ul>

      <p>3. Gathering information to make decisions more
	data-driven. For example, we are planning
	developer and user surveys. If there are questions
	that you think should be added to the survey,
	please discuss them on freebsd-arch@. We are
	also exploring ways to collect automated hardware-usage data.
	This will help the project to understand the changing ways our
	software is used and to improve hardware support.</p>

      <p>Here are other noteworthy events (in chronological order)
	since the last quarterly report.</p>

      <p>2017 Q4</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Sean Eric Fagan's (sef@) commit bit was reactivated with a
	period of re-mentoring under Alexander Motin
	(mav@).</li>

	<li>The MIPS architecture was promoted to tier 2 status.</li>

	<li>Core approved changes to the Code of Conduct.</li>

	<li>All fortune data files, except freebsd-tips, were removed
	in r325828.</li>

	<li>Core approved the adoption of a policy requiring any
	license exceptions to be recorded alongside code.</li>

	<li>Gordon Tetlow (gordon@) became the new security officer.</li>

	<li>Core approved the use of SPDX tags.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>2018 Q1</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Jeb Cramer (jeb@) was awarded a src commit bit under the
	mentorship of Sean Bruno (sbruno@) and Eric Joyner
	(erj@).</li>

	<li>Members of the CoC Review Team were approved. The
	membership is to be reviewed once per year.</li>

	<li>A vendor commit bit was awarded to Slava Shwartsman
	(slavash@) of Mellanox Technologies under the
	mentorship of Konstantin Belousov (kib@) and Hans
	Petter Selasky (hselasky@).</li>

	<li>Walter Schwarzenfeld was awarded project membership.</li>

	<li>Brad Davis (brd@) was awarded a src commit bit under the
	mentorship of Allan Jude (allanjude@) with
	Baptiste Daroussin (bapt@) as co-mentor.</li>

	<li>Vincenzo Maffione (vmaffione@) was awarded a src commit
	bit under the mentorship of Hiroki Sato (hrs@).</li>

	<li>Ram Kishore Vegesna (ram@) was awarded a src commit bit
	under the mentorship of Kenneth D. Merry (ken@)
	and Alexander Motin (mav@).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>2018 Q2</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Tom Jones (thj@) was awarded a src commit bit under the
	mentorship of Jonathan T. Looney (jtl@).</li>

	<li>Matt Macy's (mmacy@) commit bit was restored under the
	mentorship of Sean Bruno (sbruno@).</li>

	<li>Breno Leitao (leitao@) was awarded a src commit bit under
	the mentorship of Justin Hibbits (jhibbits@) with
	Nathan Whitehorn (nwhitehorn@) as co-mentor.</li>

	<li>Leandro Lupori (luporl@) was awarded a src commit bit
	under the mentorship of Justin Hibbits (jhibbits@)
	with Nathan Whitehorn (nwhitehorn@) as co-mentor.</li>

	<li>The handover from the ninth to the tenth elected Core team
	took place. The tenth Core members are: Allan Jude
	(allanjude@), Benedict Reuschling (bcr@), Brooks
	Davis (brooks@), Hiroki Sato (hrs@), Warner Losh
	(imp@), Jeff Roberson (jeff@), John Baldwin
	(jhb@), Kris Moore (kmoore@), and Sean Chittenden
	(seanc@).</li>

	<li>Joseph Mingrone (jrm@) was appointed the Core secretary
	under mentorship of the retiring Core secretary,
	Matthew Seaman (matthew@).</li>

	<li>The new team liaisons were decided. portmgr: Sean, doceng:
	Hiroki, secteam: Brooks, re: John, clusteradm:
	Allan, CoC: Warner, Foundation: Benedict,
	bugmeister: John, CI: Sean.</li>

	<li>David Maxwell (dwm@) was awarded project membership.</li>

	<li>Daichi Goto's (daichi@) commit bit was reactivated with a
	period of re-mentoring under George Neville-Neil
	(gnn@).</li>

	<li>A vendor commit bit was awarded to Ben Widawsky
	(bwidawsk@) of Intel under the mentorship of Ed
	Maste (emaste@).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	2018 Q3</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Core decided to begin meeting twice per month in an
	attempt to catch up with many new agenda items.</li>

	<li>Li-Wen Hsu (lwhsu@) was awarded a src commit bit under the
	mentorship of Mark Johnston (markj@) with Ed Maste
	(emaste@) as co-mentor.</li>

	<li>Samy al Bahra was awarded project membership.</li>

	<li>George Neville-Neil (gnn@) was approved to begin
	co-mentoring Vincenzo Maffione (vmaffione@).</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Deb Goodkin</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit
	organization dedicated to supporting and promoting
	the FreeBSD Project and community worldwide.
	Funding comes from individual and corporate
	donations and is used to fund and manage software
	development projects, conferences and developer
	summits, and provide travel grants to FreeBSD
	contributors. The Foundation purchases and
	supports hardware to improve and maintain FreeBSD
	infrastructure and provides resources to improve
	security, quality assurance, and release
	engineering efforts; publishes marketing material
	to promote, educate, and advocate for the FreeBSD
	Project; facilitates collaboration between
	commercial vendors and FreeBSD developers; and
	finally, represents the FreeBSD Project in
	executing contracts, license agreements, and other
	legal arrangements that require a recognized legal
	entity.</p>

      <p>Here are some highlights of what the FreeBSD Foundation
	did to help FreeBSD last quarter:</p>

      <p>Partnerships and Commercial User Support</p>

      <p>As a 501(c)(3) non-profit, we don't directly support
	commercial users, but we do work with them to
	understand their needs and help facilitate
	collaboration with the community. Last quarter we
	met with a few key FreeBSD users and supporters,
	to discuss pain points, how they can contribute
	back to FreeBSD, and what technologies they would
	like to see supported, to support FreeBSD over
	more of their technologies and products.</p>

      <p>As many of you know, we formed a partnership with Intel
	around one and a half years ago. Since then the
	people we worked directly with left the company,
	but it moved us into a new relationship with their
	Open Source Technology Center (OTC).</p>

      <p>We are very encouraged that Intel has dedicated additional
	resources from the OTC to work on FreeBSD in
	addition to existing resources from the networking
	group and other technologies such as QuickAssist.
	Much of the work has been focused on security and
	OS mitigations but we're also focusing on other
	areas such as power management and persistent
	memory. In May and again in July we traveled to
	Intel's Hillsboro campus to meet with management
	and engineers from OTC and the networking team. We
	presented an overview of the project and
	Foundation and also discussed key markets and
	vendors who use FreeBSD in their products or
	services and their future requirements.</p>

      <p>Intel was also interested in learning more about who
	contributes to FreeBSD. Along those lines we've
	done some work with OTC to create scripts and
	organizational mappings to answer that question.
	Note that we do need developers
	to help us update and maintain the organizational
	mappings as we understand that developers do tend
	to move around and contractors are often working
	on behalf of multiple organizations.</p>

      <p>Fundraising Efforts</p>

      <p>Our work is 100% funded by your donations. As of September
	30, we raised $328,482. Our 2018 fundraising goal
	is $1,250,000 and we are continuing to work hard to
	meet and exceed this goal! Please consider making
	a donation to help us continue and increase our
	support for FreeBSD: <a
	href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/donate/">https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/donate/</a>.</p>

      <p>We also have a new Partnership Program, to provide more
	benefits for our larger commercial donors. Find
	out more information at <a
	href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/FreeBSD-foundation-partnership-program/">https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/FreeBSD-foundation-partnership-program/</a>
	and share with your companies!</p>

      <p>OS Improvements</p>

      <p>The Foundation improves the FreeBSD operating system by
	employing technical staff to maintain and improve
	critical kernel subsystems, add features and
	functionality, and fix problems. This also
	includes funding separate project grants like the
	arm64 port, porting the blacklistd access control
	daemon, and the integration of VIMAGE support, to
	make sure that FreeBSD remains a viable solution
	for research, education, computing, products and
	more.</p>

      <p>We kicked off or continued the following projects last
	quarter:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>OpenZFS RAID-Z Expansion project</li>

	<li>Headless mode out-of-the-box for embedded ARM boards like
	the Beaglebone Black</li>

	<li>Performance and scalability improvements</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Having software developers on staff has allowed us to jump
	in and work directly on projects to improve
	FreeBSD such as:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>ZFS improvements</li>

	<li>New Intel server support</li>

	<li>kqueue(2) updates</li>

	<li>64-bit inode support</li>

	<li>Stack guard</li>

	<li>Kernel Undefined Behavior Sanitizer</li>

	<li>Toolchain projects</li>

	<li>i915 driver investigation</li>

	<li>NVDIMM support in acpiconf(8)</li>

	<li>Continuous integration dashboard (web page and physical
	hardware)</li>

	<li>FAT filesystem support in makefs(8)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Continuous Integration and Quality Assurance</p>

      <p>The Foundation provides a full-time staff member who is
	working on improving our automated testing,
	continuous integration, and overall quality
	assurance efforts.</p>

      <p>Foundation employee Li-Wen Hsu set up new CI servers to
	speed up amd64 build and test jobs, to reduce the
	latency between changes being committed and
	results being available. Li-Wen also set up a
	staging / development server in order to test
	changes to the CI system itself without affecting
	production results. We have also started a small
	hardware test lab, currently connected to the
	staging server, that tests the full boot and test
	cycle on physical hardware. In the near future
	additional hardware devices will be added, and
	this will migrate to the production CI server.</p>

      <p>Release Engineering</p>

      <p>The Foundation provides a full-time staff member to lead
	the release engineering efforts. This has provided
	timely and reliable releases over the last five
	years.</p>

      <p>Foundation employee Glen Barber continued leading the
	efforts on the upcoming 12.0-RELEASE. For details
	surrounding the work involved and progress thus
	far on 12.0-RELEASE, please see the FreeBSD
	Release Engineering Team section of this quarterly
	status report.</p>

      <p>Supporting FreeBSD Infrastructure</p>

      <p>The Foundation provides hardware and support to improve
	the FreeBSD infrastructure. Last quarter, we
	continued supporting FreeBSD hardware located
	around the world.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD Advocacy and Education</p>

      <p>A large part of our efforts are dedicated to advocating
	for the Project. This includes promoting work
	being done by others with FreeBSD; producing
	advocacy literature to teach people about FreeBSD
	and help make the path to starting using FreeBSD
	or contributing to the Project easier; and
	attending and getting other FreeBSD contributors
	to volunteer to run FreeBSD events, staff FreeBSD
	tables, and give FreeBSD presentations.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation sponsors many conferences, events,
	and summits around the globe. These events can be
	BSD-related, open source, or technology events
	geared towards underrepresented groups. We support
	the FreeBSD-focused events to help provide a venue
	for sharing knowledge, to work together on
	projects, and to facilitate collaboration between
	developers and commercial users. This all helps
	provide a healthy ecosystem. We support the
	non-FreeBSD events to promote and raise awareness
	of FreeBSD, to increase the use of FreeBSD in
	different applications, and to recruit more
	contributors to the Project.</p>

      <p>Check out some of the advocacy and education work we did
	last quarter:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Organized and ran the Essen FreeBSD Hackathon in Essen,
	Germany</li>

	<li>Participated in the FreeBSD Developer Summit BSDCam, in
	Cambridge, England</li>

	<li>Represented FreeBSD at the ARM Partner Meeting</li>

	<li>Presented and taught about FreeBSD at SdNOG 5 in Khartoum,
	Sudan</li>

	<li>Exhibited and gave a talk at OSCON 2018 in Portland, OR</li>

	<li>Exhibited at the 2018 Grace Hopper Celebration and
	sponsored as a Silver Non-Profit Sponsor</li>

	<li>Exhibited at COCON 2018 in Taipei, Taiwan</li>

	<li>Sponsored and gave presentations and tutorials at
	EuroBSDCon in Bucharest, Romania</li>

	<li>Organized and ran the Bucharest FreeBSD Developer Summit</li>

	<li>Sponsored the 2018 USENIX Security Symposium in Baltimore,
	MD as an Industry Partner</li>

	<li>Provided FreeBSD advocacy material</li>

	<li>Sponsored the 2018 USENIX Annual Technical Conference in
	Boston, MA as an Industry Partner</li>

	<li>Sponsored the OpenZFS Developer Summit as a Silver Sponsor</li>

	<li>Presented and taught about FreeBSD at SANOG32 in Dhaka,
	Bangladesh</li>

	<li>Sponsored the SNIA Storage Developer Conference 2018 as an
	Association Partner</li>

	<li>Provided 11 travel grants to FreeBSD contributors to
	attend many of the above events.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	We continued producing FreeBSD advocacy material to help
	people promote FreeBSD around the world.</p>

      <p>Read more about our conference adventures in the
	conference recaps and trip reports in our monthly
	newsletters: <a
	href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/</a></p>

      <p>We help educate the world about FreeBSD by publishing the
	professionally produced FreeBSD Journal. Last
	quarter we published the July/August issue that
	you can find at <a
	href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/journal/">https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/journal/</a>.</p>

      <p>You can find out more about events we attended and
	upcoming events at <a
	href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/news-and-events/">https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/news-and-events/</a>.</p>

      <p>Legal/FreeBSD IP</p>

      <p>The Foundation owns the FreeBSD trademarks, and it is our
	responsibility to protect them. We also provide
	legal support for the core team to investigate
	questions that arise.</p>

      <p>Go to <a
	href="http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org">http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org</a>
	to find out how we support FreeBSD and how we can
	help you!</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Continuous Integration</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Jenkins Admin</name>
	<email>jenkins-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Li-Wen Hsu</name>
	<email>lwhsu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://ci.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD Jenkins Instance</url>
      <url href="https://artifact.ci.FreeBSD.org/">FreeBSD CI artifact archive</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Jenkins">FreeBSD Jenkins wiki</url>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-testing">freebsd-testing Mailing List</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ci">freebsd-ci Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD CI team maintains continuous integration tasks
	for FreeBSD. The CI
	system regularly checks the changes committed to the
	project's Subversion
	repository can be successfully built, and performs various
	tests and analysis
	with the build results. The CI team also maintains the
	archive of the artifact
	built by the CI system, for the further testing and
	debugging needs.</p>

      <p>Starting from June 2018, the project is sponsored by the
	FreeBSD Foundation in
	hardware and staff. For more details of the sponsored
	projects, please refer
	to:</p>

      <p><a
	href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/freebsd-foundation-update-september-2018/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/freebsd-foundation-update-september-2018/</a></p>

      <p>In addition to that, we also helped checking regressions
	for OpenSSL 1.1.1
	update and test continuously for 12-STABLE branch.</p>

      <p>We had meetings and working groups at two developer
	summits during 2018Q3:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><a
	href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DevSummit/201808/Testing">BSDCam
	2018</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DevSummit/201809">EuroBSDCon
	2018</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Work in progress:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fixing the failing test cases and builds</li>

	<li><a
	href="https://ci.FreeBSD.org/job/FreeBSD-head-amd64-dtrace_test/lastCompletedBuild/testReport/">DTrace
	test</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://ci.FreeBSD.org/job/FreeBSD-head-amd64-test_zfs/lastCompletedBuild/testReport/">ZFS
	test</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://ci.FreeBSD.org/job/FreeBSD-head-amd64-gcc/">GCC
	build</a></li>

	<li>Adding drm ports building test against -CURRENT</li>

	<li>Adding tests for selected project branches, e.g.:
	clang700-import</li>

	<li>Adding new hardware to the embedded testbed</li>

	<li>Implementing automatic tests on bare metal hardware</li>

	<li>Planning running ztest and network stack tests</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>4G/4G address space split for i386</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Most 32-bit FreeBSD architectures, including i386, started
	to suffer
	from the rapid growth of the size of software during the
	past decade.
	When a 32-bit address space is enough space for a given
	task, 32-bit
	mode still has an intrinsic advantage over 64-bit mode,
	due to less
	memory traffic and more economical use of caches. It has
	grown
	harder to provide the self-hosting i386 system build due
	to the
	increase in size of the build tools.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD i386 kernel, prior to the 12.0-RELEASE
	version, split
	the 4GB address space of the platform into 3GB (minus 4MB)
	accessible
	to userspace accesses and 1GB for kernel accesses.
	Neither kernel nor userspace could access a full 4GB
	address space.
	Programs that require very large virtual address spaces,
	such as
	clang when compiling or lld when linking, could run out of
	address
	space: 3GB of address space was insufficient for their
	operation.
	The kernel also had trouble fitting into the traditional
	1GB
	limitation of address space with the modern sizing for
	network
	buffers, ZFS and other KVA-hungry in-kernel subsystems.</p>

      <p>In FreeBSD 12, the i386 architecture has been changed to
	provide
	dedicated separate address spaces for userspace and
	kernel, giving
	each mode full access to 4GB (minus 8MB) of usable address
	space.
	The userspace on the i386 architecture now has access to
	the same
	amount of address space as the compat32 subsystem in the
	amd64
	architecture kernel. The increase in kernel address space
	enables
	further growth and maintainability of the i386
	architecture.</p>

      <p>The split 4GB/4GB user/kernel implementation uses two page
	directory
	entries (PDEs) shared between modes: one for mapping the
	page table,
	another for the mode switching trampoline and other
	required system
	tables. The required system tables, which must always be
	mapped,
	regardless of kernel or user mode, includes such things as
	the
	GDT/IDT/TSS entries. Significant changes were made to the
	locore
	code. The page table creation portion of the code was
	completely
	rewritten from assembly to C, improving readability and
	maintainability
	of the code.</p>

      <p>Because the user address space is no longer shared with
	the kernel,
	the copyout(9) functions were rewritten to make a
	transient mapping
	of userspace pages for the duration of any needed
	accesses. The initial
	implementation used the vm_fault_quick_hold_pages()
	framework, but
	this was later optimized by temporarily switching to user
	mode
	mappings from a trampoline, and then using hand-written
	assembler
	routines to perform a faster small block copy operation.</p>

      <p>Future plans for the ongoing maintenance of i386 include
	making the i386 pmap
	capable of runtime selection of the PAE or non-PAE page
	table format
	and supporting NX (no execute) mappings for regular i386
	kernel.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeBSD/DTrace</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>George Neville-Neil</name>
	<email>gnn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Domagoj Stolfa</name>
	<email>domagoj.stolfa@cl.cam.ac.uk</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>DTrace is a whole-system debugging tool in FreeBSD and is
	one of the
	actively supported projects during the past year.</p>

      <p>A research prototype of a distributed version of DTrace
	and a version
	of DTrace that can trace bhyve virtual machines from the
	host FreeBSD
	system are currently under development at the University
	of Cambridge
	as a part of the CADETS project. Recent developments
	include the
	creation of dlog, an in-kernel DTrace consumer which is
	able to
	publish to Kafka, and improvements to early boot and
	shutdown tracing.
	On the virtualisation front,
	improvements were made in the ability to dereference and
	follow
	pointers inside guests from the host in the probe context
	by
	implementing a nested page table walk inside DTrace for
	Intel
	architectures. The CADETS project has started formalizing
	DTrace in HOL4 which enables automated test generation,
	high assurance
	of DTrace implementations in terms of adherence to the
	specification
	and exploration of all allowable behaviors for a given D
	script. Currently, the formal model contains most of DIF
	instructions
	and a code generator for them, providing the ability to
	run DIF
	programs specified using the model using FreeBSD's DTrace
	implementation.</p>

      <p>As a result of all of this, a number of changes were
	upstreamed to the
	FreeBSD auditing subsystem and new variables such as
	<tt>jid</tt> and
	<tt>jailname</tt> were added to DTrace which can be
	accessed from D scripts.</p>

      <p>OpenDTrace Specification 1.0 has been published which
	covers the
	internal workings of DTrace in general, and its adaptation
	to various
	operating systems in particular. This work was sponsored
	by
	AFRL/DARPA through the CADETS project.</p>

      <p>Ruslan Bukin (br@) has added C-compressed ISA extension
	support to the
	RISC-V FBT provider as a part of the ECATS project.</p>

      <p>Mark Johnston (markj@) has done some work to fix
	interactions between
	FBT and ifuncs. ifuncs are a toolchain feature which allow
	programmers
	to select a function's implementation at boot-time, rather
	than at
	compile-time. For instance, on amd64, memcpy() is an ifunc
	and may be
	implemented by either memcpy_erms() or memcpy_std(). FBT
	created
	probes for the implementation functions, but we needed
	some extra
	support to ensure that fbt::memcpy:entry continues to work
	as
	expected. Similar work is needed for the PID provider, but
	is still
	pending.</p>

      <p>Microsoft showed a <a
	href="https://youtu.be/tG8R5SQGPck?t=891">working
	demo of DTrace</a>,
	which was ported from FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>Added to FreeBSD base in 11.2, dwatch is a new DTrace
	tool, developed
	by Devin Teske (dteske@), for automating complex queries
	for data and
	surgically tapping the kernel. In base there are 85
	profiles for
	interpreting domain-specific data with another 17
	available from ports
	making a total of over 100 different pipelines from which
	you can
	extract data in multiple formats. dwatch also simplifies
	observation
	of over 100,000 probe points available in FreeBSD, making
	it easy to
	find any process, thread, or jail triggering any probe.
	On top of all
	that, dwatch profiles can leverage higher-level languages
	such as
	python, perl, sh, and many more.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ACPI NVDIMM driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>NVDIMM is a technology which provides non-volatile memory
	with
	access characteristics similar to regular DRAM, which is
	the
	technology that implements the normal memory address space
	of a host.
	There are ACPI and UEFI specifications that define
	platform independent
	ways to detect and enumerate the presence of NVDIMMs.
	These
	specifications allow the retrieval of most of the data
	needed to
	allow proper application use of the NVDIMM storage.</p>

      <p>A new FreeBSD driver parses the ACPI NFIT table which
	lists NVDIMMs,
	their operational characteristics, and the physical
	address space
	where the NVDIMM memory is accessible. The driver presents
	each
	address region as two devices: One device allows userspace
	to
	open(2) a devfs node, which can be read/written/mapped
	from the
	application. This mapping is zero-copy. The second device
	is a
	geom disk(9), which makes it possible to use NVDIMM for
	the backing
	storage for a normal FreeBSD filesystem, such as UFS, ZFS,
	or msdosfs.
	Note that buffer cache/mapping of files from a traditional
	filesystem
	created over NVDIMM causes an unneeded double-buffering.</p>

      <p>Empirically, on typical modern hardware, NVDIMM regions
	are located
	far from the regular DRAM backed memory in the address
	space, and
	have attributes that are not compatible with regular DRAM
	memory.
	This makes it unfeasible to extend the kernel's direct map
	to provide
	the kernel mappings for the NVDIMM regions.
	A new pmap KPI was designed, pmap_large_map(9),
	which allows efficient mapping of very large physical
	regions into
	the KVA. The new code has some optimizations to the cache
	flushing
	operations over the mapped regions, which is needed to
	efficiently
	support bio flushes from a filesystems using the NVDIMM
	storage.
	The NVDIMM driver is the first user of the new KPI,
	but the new KPI might also be useful for the NTB driver.</p>

      <p>
	TODO:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Intel is currently working on extending the driver to
	support
	UEFI namespaces.</li>

	<li>A DAX-capable filesystem is needed, which solves the issue
	of
	double-buffering. Our tmpfs already provides VM facilities
	which
	allows it to avoid double-buffering for mmap, which can be
	reused
	there.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>SMAP</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for SMAP (Supervisor-Mode Access Prevention), has
	been added
	to the amd64 kernel. The SMAP feature makes any access
	from the
	supervisor mode to the pages accessible to user mode cause
	a fault,
	unless the %eflags.AC bit is set at the time of the
	access.</p>

      <p>The SMAP implementation uses the ifunc framework to avoid
	checking
	for the SMAP capability of hardware on each call to
	copyout(9) and
	other functions.</p>

      <p>In the amd64 architecture, FreeBSD has a common address
	space between
	the kernel space and user space. Enabling SMAP virtually
	splits
	the shared address space into two disjoint address spaces,
	which
	have different access criteria. This splitting of the
	address space
	provides a relatively low-overhead way of catching direct
	accesses
	from kernel to usermode, when not using the copyout(9)
	family of
	functions. The copyout(9) family of functions are
	permitted direct
	access to user space. Any direct access from kernel mode
	to user
	address space that isn't performed through the copyout(9)
	family
	of functions indicates a potential programming error.</p>

      <p>It is interesting that very few bugs were found in the
	FreeBSD
	kernel after the SMAP feature was enabled. One issue that
	was
	identified existed in the pci(9) user driver. Enabling the
	SMAP
	feature identified at least two ports, VBox and acpi_call,
	which
	appeared to access userspace in an unsafe manner.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Large scale package building</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Mateusz Guzik</name>
	<email>mjg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Building packages on a 128-thread machine with poudriere
	exhibits some
	bottlenecks.</p>

      <p>See the October FreeBSD Foundation Newsletter for a short
	write-up:
	<a
	href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/freebsd-foundation-update-october-2018/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/freebsd-foundation-update-october-2018/</a></p>

      <p>One encountered problem stems from process handling.</p>

      <p>The standard process life cycle on UNIX-like systems looks
	like this:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>a process is created with fork(2)</li>

	<li>it can do regular work or execve(2) a new binary</li>

	<li>it exits, becoming a zombie</li>

	<li>the parent collects the exit code and removes the zombie</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	There are other variations (e.g. vfork(2) can be used
	instead of
	fork).</p>

      <p>When you type 'ls' into your shell, it will typically
	vfork a new process
	which will then execve /bin/ls.</p>

      <p>All this is guarded with several global kernel locks, but
	the granularity
	can be significantly improved.</p>

      <p>A different problem stems from pipes.</p>

      <p>Pipes are used all the time, e.g. "du -s | sort -n"
	creates a pipe whose
	one endpoint is standard output for du and another is
	standard input for sort.</p>

      <p>By default the pipe can hold up to 16KB before it gets
	filled up.</p>

      <p>The kernel dedicates part of its virtual address space to
	hold pipe buffers
	and allocates/deallocates physical pages as pipes get
	created/destroyed.
	This induces TLB invalidation requests to other CPUs,
	which causes an
	unnecessary slowdown.</p>

      <p>An easy way out is to cache a certain number of buffers.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>String functions on the amd64 architecture</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Mateusz Guzik</name>
	<email>mjg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Functions like memset, memmove and memcpy are very
	frequently used by virtually
	all programs. They can be optimized in various ways, but
	FreeBSD uses very
	rudimentary implementations using rep movsq/stosq. rep
	prefix has high startup
	latency which is overly expensive when dealing with small
	sizes.</p>

      <p>Short term goal of this project is to implement faster
	variants for the kernel
	and import them into libc. The main speed up comes from
	not using rep for small
	sizes (&lt; 256) and from aligning target buffers to 16
	bytes when rep is used.
	On top of that runtime detection of the Enhanced REP
	MOVSB/STOSB extention can
	be used to only use rep movsb/stosb.</p>

      <p>Mid term goal extends userspace. SIMD extensions can be
	used to make these functions
	faster. They can't easily be used in the kernel: SIMD
	registers are not saved on
	transitions user&lt;-&gt;kernel for performance reasons.
	Thus any use would have to
	take care of saving these registers, which can consume any
	advantage from using them in
	the first place. This is not a concern for userspace code.</p>

      <p>There is a BSD-licensed implementation in bionic:
	<a
	href="https://android.googlesource.com/platform/bionic/+/master/libc/arch-x86_64/string/">https://android.googlesource.com/platform/bionic/+/master/libc/arch-x86_64/string/</a></p>

      <p>which with some modifications can be used in libc later
	on.</p>

      <p>See the Intel Optimization Manual for reference:
	<a
	href="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/manuals/64-ia-32-architectures-optimization-manual.pdf">https://www.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/manuals/64-ia-32-architectures-optimization-manual.pdf</a></p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>32-bit compatibility and other ABI cleanups</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Brooks Davis</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>As part of maintaining an external ABI (application binary
	interface)
	compatibility layer, I've been improving FreeBSD
	infrastructure,
	primarily the 32-bit compatibility layer. One of FreeBSD's
	strengths is
	that we can easily support many ABIs. This includes
	support for a.out
	format executables (vs the standard ELF), support for i386
	on amd64, the
	Linux emulation layer, etc.</p>

      <p>This infrastructure has existed for decades and not every
	design
	decision has stood the test of time. Support has also been
	incomplete
	in a number of areas (e.g. network management under 32-bit
	emulation).</p>

      <p>Committed improvements include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Improved <tt>ioctl</tt> and <tt>sysctl</tt> support to
	allow <tt>ifconfig</tt> and
	<tt>netstat</tt> to work in 32-bit compat mode.</li>
	<li>Migration from a model of translating <tt>ioctl</tt>
	commands and data
	structures at the kernel boundary to translating where the
	commands
	are processed. This is a correctness improvement (`ioctl`
	commands
	do not have meaning outside the specific file descriptor
	in question)
	and improves code reusability (my out-of-tree work will
	soon include
	a 64-bit compatibility layer.)</li>
	<li>Simplifications of the generic ELF process execution path
	by Ed
	Maste, John Baldwin, and myself. A number of
	simplifications including
	minor speedups have been committed.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Portions of this work were developed by SRI International
	and the
	University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory (Department of
	Computer
	Science and Technology) under DARPA/AFRL contract
	FA8750-10-C-0237
	("CTSRD"), as part of the DARPA CRASH research programme
	and under DARPA
	contract HR0011-18-C-0016 ("ECATS"), as part of the DARPA
	SSITH research
	programme.</p>

      <p>Work in progress includes cleanups to the APIs used by the
	kernel when
	creating processes and continued <tt>ioctl</tt>
	improvements. Work is also
	underway to generate the 32-bit system call list from the
	"default"
	list.</p>

      <p>The remaining <tt>ioctl</tt> commands handled in
	<a
	href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base/head/sys/compat/freebsd32/freebsd32_ioctl.c?view=log">sys/compat/freebsd32/freebsd32_ioctl.c</a>
	need to be migrated to the point of implementation. Help
	with the latter
	would be appreciated.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Save/Restore/Migration support in bhyve</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Elena Mihailescu</name>
	<email>elenamihailescu22@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Darius Mihai</name>
	<email>dariusmihaim@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Sergiu Weisz</name>
	<email>sergiu121@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mihai Carabas</name>
	<email>mihai@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/tree/projects/bhyve_migration">Github repository for the save/restore and migration features</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Save-and-Restore-a-virtual-machine-using-bhyve">Github wiki - How to Save and Restore a bhyve guest</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Virtual-Machine-Migration-using-bhyve">Github wiki - How to Migrate a bhyve guest</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Suspend-Resume-test-matrix">Github wiki - Suspend/resume test matrix</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Save/Restore feature is a facility to suspend and
	resume guest
	virtual images that has been added to the FreeBSD/amd64's
	hypervisor,
	bhyve. The bhyvectl tool is used to save the guest virtual
	machine
	into three files:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>a file for the guest memory</li>

	<li>a file for state of each device / CPU state</li>

	<li>a file that has metadata that is used in the restore
	process</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	To suspend a bhyve guest, the bhyvectl tool must be run
	with the <tt>--suspend
	&lt;state_file_name&gt;</tt>
	option followed by the guest name.</p>

      <p>To restore a bhyve guest from a checkpoint, one simply has
	to add the <tt>-r</tt> option
	followed by the main state file (the same file that was
	given to the <tt>--suspend</tt>
	option for bhyvectl) when starting the VM.</p>

      <p>The Migration feature uses the Save/Restore implementation
	to migrate a bhyve guest
	from one FreeBSD host to another FreeBSD host. To migrate
	a bhyve guest,
	one needs to start an empty guest on the destination host
	from a shared guest
	image using the bhyve tool with the <tt>-R</tt> option
	followed by the source host
	IP and the port to listen to migration request. On the
	source host, the
	migration is started by executing the bhyvectl command
	with the <tt>--migrate</tt>
	option, followed by the destination host IP and the port
	to send to the messages.</p>

      <p>New features added:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Create the socket connection between source and
	destination hosts</li>

	<li>Migrate the guest state via sockets</li>

	<li>Separate the suspend/resume/migration code from the
	bhyverun.c and bhyvectl.c and added two new files
	for them: migration.c and migration.h</li>

	<li>Added save/restore state for xhci</li>

	<li>Added save/restore state for fbuf</li>

	<li>Fix vhpet restore state issues (timers related)</li>

	<li>Add partially support for suspending and resuming a Linux
	guest</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Future tasks:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Check if live migration can be implemented using the
	FreeBSD's Copy-on-Write mechanism</li>

	<li>Add live migration support by using EPT (Intel)</li>

	<li>Add live migration support by using NPT (AMD)</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for nvme</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for virtio-console</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for virtio-scsi</li>

	<li>Fix restore timers issues</li>

	<li>Fix suspending bhyve - threads issues</li>

	<li>Fix suspending bhyve - mutexes issues</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for Windows guests</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Matthew Grooms
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      iXsystems
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Building FreeBSD on non-FreeBSD hosts</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Alex Richardson</name>
	<email>arichardson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BuildingOnNonFreeBSD">Wiki</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/arichardson/freebsd/tree/crossbuild-aug2018">GitHub project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Currently FreeBSD can only be built on a FreeBSD host.
	However, most free
	CI tools only allow building on Linux or macOS and
	therefore can not be used
	for building the FreeBSD base system. It is sometimes
	useful to
	cross-build FreeBSD for a remote machine or an emulator
	even if the build
	machine is not running FreeBSD.
	The goal of this project is to allow building FreeBSD on
	both Linux and macOS hosts
	and in the future it may be extended to allow compiling on
	a Windows host.
	This work originates from the CHERI project and was
	motivated by multiple cases of
	people wanting to try out CheriBSD but not being able to
	compile it since they did
	not have a FreeBSD system available for compiling.
	Once completed this project will also allow developers to
	contribute to FreeBSD
	even if they don't have access to a FreeBSD build system.</p>

      <p>The current set of patches for this project can be found
	on
	<a
	href="https://github.com/arichardson/freebsd/tree/crossbuild-aug2018">GitHub</a>.
	With the current prototype it is possible to compile both
	world and kernel for
	architectures that use the clang compiler and for MIPS64,
	which uses gcc. However, some options such as
	LOCALES are
	not supported yet and require further changes before the
	bootstrap tools can be built
	on Linux/macOS.</p>

      <p>Some changes required for building on non-FreeBSD have
	already been merged to
	HEAD but there are still a rather large number of changes
	that need review.</p>

      <p>If you are interested in getting this into HEAD and would
	like to help, please
	try the current prototype and report any issues to
	arichardson@FreeBSD.org.
	If you can help with reviewing the changes please contact
	arichardson@FreeBSD.org
	to be added to any pending Phabricator reviews.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ENA FreeBSD Driver Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Michał Krawczyk</name>
	<email>mk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/amzn/amzn-drivers/blob/master/kernel/fbsd/ena/README">ENA README</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ENA (Elastic Network Adapter) is the smart NIC which is
	used in the virtualised
	environment of Amazon Web Services (AWS). It supports
	multiple queues and can handle up to 25 Gb/s,
	depending on the instance type on which it is
	used.</p>

      <p>Since last report, ENA versions v0.8.0 and v0.8.1 have
	been released, which introduced
	many bug fixes, new features, optimization, stability and
	error recovery
	improvements. The last is especially important on the AWS,
	where the instances
	have to be reliable as they may be running very sensitive
	functions and the
	down time of the VM should be reduced to minimum.</p>

      <p>The v0.8.0 and v0.8.1 release patches included:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Upgrade of the HAL to version v1.1.4.3</li>

	<li>Improvement to the reset routine - the driver is now
	triggering reset from
	more fault points and is passing the reset reason to the
	device, which can
	perform the reset adequately to the encountered error.</li>

	<li>Device statistics (like global Tx and Rx counters) are no
	longer read directly from the device.
	The only exception is Rx drops, which are still read using
	the AENQ
	descriptor.</li>

	<li>The RX Out Of Order completion feature was added, which
	enabled to cleanup the
	RX descriptors out of order by keeping trace of all free
	descriptors.</li>

	<li>RX ring is now being monitored, to prevent the ring from
	stalling.</li>

	<li>Error handling paths were reworked and fixed.</li>

	<li>Driver was covered with branch prediction statements, to
	make the most
	of this CPU feature in the hot paths.</li>

	<li>Fix handling of the DF flag in the IP packets.</li>

	<li>Add dynamic logging and reduce number of messages being
	printed by the driver.</li>

	<li>MTU configuration now is being verified using the device
	capabilities instead
	of a constant value.</li>

	<li>Do not pass packet header length hint to the device,
	because for the chained
	mbufs it may be problematic to determine header length, if
	the header is split
	into multiple segments.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Amazon.com Inc.
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeBSD Graphics Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Graphics Team</name>
	<email>x11@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Niclas Zeising</name>
	<email>zeising@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop">Project GitHub page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD X11/Graphics team is responsible for the lower
	levels of the FreeBSD
	graphics stack. This includes graphics drivers, graphics
	libraries such as the
	MESA OpenGL implementation, the X.org xserver with related
	libraries and
	applications, and Wayland with related libraries and
	applications.</p>

      <p>There have been a lot of changes since the last report.
	The most important one
	is the change of driver distribution and updates. On
	FreeBSD 11.2 and later
	modern graphics drivers using the Linux KPI subsystem are
	found in ports. These
	give much improved support for Intel and AMD graphics
	hardware, however, they
	are currently only available for amd64.</p>

      <p>The legacy drivers available in the FreeBSD base system
	are also available in
	the ports tree, since they cause issues with the new
	drivers. They will remain
	in tree for 11.2 and 12, but work is on-going to have them
	removed for 13,
	except for arm.</p>

      <p>The easiest way to install the new drivers is to install
	graphics/drm-kmod which
	will install the correct driver depending on your
	architecture and FreeBSD
	version.</p>

      <p>There have been changes to the ports as well. Most notably
	is the changed
	handling of OpenGL dependencies, which has moved to USES
	instead of being
	handled directly in bsd.port.mk. Other big infrastructure
	changes is the move
	from individual \*proto packages to xorgproto, and turning
	that into a build
	time dependency. Many thanks to portmgr for help with
	exp-runs for these
	changes.</p>

      <p>There have been updates to applications and libraries as
	needed.</p>

      <p>On the project management side, there is ongoing work to
	set up a more efficient
	way of working, including bi-weekly conference calls to
	discuss the current
	works in progress. Notes from these conference calls will
	be posted on the
	mailing list.</p>

      <p>Looking forward, the current major work in progress is to
	update the graphics
	driver to be on par with Linux 4.17. The code is merged,
	but patching and bug
	fixing is ongoing.</p>

      <p>There is also work to port the VMware guest graphics
	driver, vmwgfx, to FreeBSD
	and to the Linux KPI, to get better graphics support in
	VMware.</p>

      <p>Lastly, on the driver side is to get the new graphics
	drivers to work on i386 as
	well. Experimental support for this exists in the code
	repository, but is not
	yet merged to the FreeBSD ports tree.</p>

      <p>In userland, the biggest things happening is the update of
	the input stack,
	including libinput and supporting libraries.</p>

      <p>Work is also ongoing on updating MESA libraries.</p>

      <p>On the project management side, the most important tasks
	is to continue to work
	on the team, and how we work internally.</p>

      <p>We are also working on setting up a list of requirements
	for testing, so that we
	can be reasonably assured that updates won't cause
	regressions.</p>

      <p>People who are interested in helping out can find us on
	the x11@FreeBSD.org
	mailing list, or on our Gitter chat: <a
	href="https://gitter.im/FreeBSDDesktop/Lobby">https://gitter.im/FreeBSDDesktop/Lobby</a>.
	We
	are also available in #freebsd-xorg on EFNet.</p>

      <p>We also have a team area on GitHub where our work
	repositories can be found:
	<a
	href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop">https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop</a></p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ifuncs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Ed Maste</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mark Johnston</name>
	<email>markj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mateusz Guzik</name>
	<email>mjg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>An ifunc is a special construct in an ELF object, which
	allows for
	the selection of the implementation for the given symbol
	at runtime,
	when the ELF module gets the final relocations applied.
	The selection
	of which code to use is governed by the small piece of
	user provided
	code, attached to the symbol, the so called resolver
	function.
	Ifuncs provide a convenient way to select between
	different
	machine-specific implementations of the parts of the code,
	without
	the ugliness and unsafety of the alternative approach,
	which is
	runtime patching.</p>

      <p>Ifuncs require support both from the static linker ld(1),
	and from the
	runtime linker for the corresponding execution
	environment. On
	FreeBSD, with the switch from the ancient GPLv2 licensed
	BFD-based
	ld(1) to either in-tree LLD or external modern BFD ld, the
	use of
	ifuncs become possible. Runtime linkers for ifunc support
	exists for
	the following environments:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>i386, amd64, and arm64 kernels</li>

	<li>usermode dynamic linker ld-elf.so.1 on i386 and amd64</li>

	<li>static binaries startup code for i386 and amd64</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	The use of ifuncs were previously applied for optimization
	of the
	following areas of the amd64 kernel:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>context switching code, instead of huge number of runtime
	checks
	(PTI vs non-PTI, PCID or not, is INVPCID instruction
	supported for
	PCID) now uses set of mode-specific routines, see
	pmap_activate_sw(). Besides removing checks at runtime, it
	also
	makes the code much more cleanly structured and readable.</li>

	<li>TLB and cache flush implementation.</li>

	<li>memcpy/memmove, copyin/copyout variants selection for ERMS
	and SMAP.</li>

	<li>FPU state save and restore, depending on the support for
	AVX or not,
	this is also used on i386.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	For amd64 userspace, we currently use ifunc for
	optimization of the
	architecture dependent TLS base set and get functions.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Intel Work on Core Enabling and Security</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Ben Widawsky</name>
	<email>bwidawsk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A new team has been formed within Intel to help with side
	channel security
	mitigations as well as core enabling. They are evaluating
	work from all areas
	except networking. The team is currently focusing on two
	areas:</p>

      <ol><li>Power Management improvements</li>
	<li>NVDIMM namespace support</li></ol>

      <p>The ultimate goal of the power management work is to get
	runtime power
	management to hit "opportunistic idle". What this means is
	when devices are
	idle, the OS will power them down, and when everything
	goes idle certain SoCs
	will allow you to hit very low power states across the
	platform. FreeBSD
	currently doesn't have any notion of runtime power
	management, and many devices
	don't properly implement suspend and resume. In addition,
	some preliminary work
	is in process as it was thought to help when eventually
	enabling opportunistic
	idle. That preliminary work has been happening and is now
	up for review:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><a
	href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17675">https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17675</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17676">https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17676</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	NVDIMM namespace support has also been put up for review.
	ACPI spec defines
	namespaces as a way of partitioning the device into
	separate labels. The current
	work will integrate with geom(4). How these are used is
	application dependent.
	This work is up for review as well: <a
	href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17619">https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D17619</a></p>

      <p>The team has additionally taken on smaller tasks like
	porting turbostat(8),
	working on git svn init scripts, some small modifications
	to acpi tooling, and
	an effort to create a port PMDK.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>LLVM 7.0 - Sanitizers support improvements / Static code analysis</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>David Carlier</name>
	<email>devnexen@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://releases.llvm.org/7.0.0/docs/ReleaseNotes.html">Release notes</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In order to increase the FreeBSD tooling to uncover
	code bugs in the userland, further compiler-rt components
	support and static code analysis improvements had been
	added
	since the last 6.0 version.</p>

      <p>Starting with the sanitizers, Memory Sanitizer (for amd64)
	mainly to
	detect unitialized pointers. There is also a simple W^X
	paging
	requests detection available from most of sanitizers.</p>

      <p>Also libFuzzer support finally had been possible.
	It allows code to be tested with random values from corpus
	inputs.
	Mutation and combination algorithms of those random inputs
	can be overwritten. Can also be used in addition to ubsan,
	asan, msan and so on.</p>

      <p>At last, the X-Ray instrumentation feature is also
	supported.
	It is mainly about performance profiling purposes for a
	reasonable performance runtime cost.</p>

      <p>In the static code analysis department, reliable strlcpy
	(unfortunately strlcat
	did not get merged in due time for the release) wrong
	usage
	cases are now covered and W^X code detection tooling had
	been added.</p>

      <p>At the moment, this 7.0 version is imported by Dimitry
	Andric, within
	its own git branch available only for FreeBSD after 12
	releases.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Boot Loader</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Warner Losh</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Kyle Evans</name>
	<email>kevans@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Toomas Soome</name>
	<email>tsoome@Freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD boot loader lives in src/stand (prior releases
	had it in
	sys/boot and lib/libstand). It covers all the code that
	the project
	provides that interacts with the hardware before the
	kernel starts.</p>

      <p>The LUA interpreter added earlier in 2018 was made default
	in 2018Q3.
	Due to undiagnosed booting issues, the LUA interpreter has
	been
	disabled on sparc64 and all powerpc. The LUA interpreter
	is scheduled
	to replace the FORTH interpreter entirely in FreeBSD 13,
	although the
	FORTH interpreter will remain available as a build option
	in FreeBSD
	12. The plans are not to remove the FORTH loader for about
	a year
	after 12.0 release, or approximately January 2020.
	Platforms not
	currently working with the LUA interpreter
	have until that date to resolve the issues.</p>

      <p>At this point, the LUA scripts implement everything that
	the FORTH scripts
	did. Where there was ambiguity in the spec, or where the
	FORTH scripts
	were more forgiving than was strictly documented, every
	effort has
	been made to improve the documentation and follow the old
	FORTH
	behavior, or document the new behavior where the old
	behavior was
	clearly a bug.</p>

      <p>It's anticipated that no further changes to the FORTH
	loader or the
	FORTH scripts will happen. They are quite mature and
	bullet proof at
	this point and it's unlikely that an undiscovered bug will
	need to be
	fixed before retirement.</p>

      <p>Other work in progress includes Toomas Soome's port to
	OpenIndiana. In
	addition to porting, he's enhanced the code in a number of
	ways (both
	in the block layer, and UEFI). Many of his improvements
	have been
	committed to FreeBSD, though a few remain and hopefully
	will be
	entering the tree soon after the freeze lifts.</p>

      <p>UEFI booting has been greatly enhanced. There are still
	some
	machines that have issues with the default BootXXXX
	variables or
	something else in the environment that are being
	investigated. We hope
	to understand the problems well enough to provide a fix
	for FreeBSD
	12.0.</p>

      <p>Ian Lepore has reworked the GELI support so that it is
	architecture independent and can be
	used on any architecture we support.</p>

      <p>There are also efforts underway to support booting signed
	images, improved
	crypto booting options, and implement Multiboot 2.0
	support.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Usermode mapping of PCI BARs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Modern PCI(e) devices typically define memory-mapped BARs
	(Base Address Registers) to make a memory region available
	to the device.
	Each BAR
	has a separate page-aligned boundary and memory region
	associated with it.
	This is enforced by the need
	of hypervisors to provide the pass-through using VT-d,
	which operates
	with memory and has the granularity of one page for access
	control.
	As is, it
	also means that the BARs have a suitable configuration for
	providing
	access to usermode, controlling access by the normal page
	tables.</p>

      <p>Linux already gives a way for userspace mapping of BARs
	using sysfs.</p>

      <p>Of course, if a userspace program has enough privileges,
	it can read a BAR,
	determine the physical address of the mapping as seen by
	CPU, and use
	mem(4) (aka /dev/mem) to mmap() that region of memory.
	This is very cumbersome, and leaves many unresolved
	issues.
	For example, a BAR might be not activated, which would
	require
	involvement of the IOMMU on some architectures. Also this
	rude approach
	makes it very hard to create mappings with the correct
	caching
	attributes.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD pci(4) driver was enhanced to support such
	mappings, and pciconf(8) utility was extended to use the
	new support.
	See pci(4)
	for PCIOCBARMMAP ioctl(2) request description for details,
	and
	pciconf(8) for the -D switch.</p>

      <p>TODO: automatically activate the BAR on mapping, this is
	not done yet.
	There is a problem with avoiding the resource conflicts on
	possible future attachmens of the kernel driver.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Device Mode USB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Edward Tomasz Napierala</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/usb-device-mode.html">Handbook chapter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Many embedded boards include hardware which supports
	device
	side USB - the ability for the board to present itself to
	another
	system as a USB drive, network adapter, or a virtual
	serial port.
	The FreeBSD USB stack has supported this functionality for
	quite some
	time, but it has not been used to its fullest extent.</p>

      <p>The goal of this project was to fix that - to document the
	functionality, possibly fix some bugs, and to make it easy
	to use, automating it as much as possible.</p>

      <p>Starting with FreeBSD 12.0, this functionality is enabled
	out of the box. This means you can connect your BeagleBone
	Black's (using its USB client socket) or a Raspberry Pi 0
	(using the On-The-Go (OTG) port) to your laptop, and
	you'll get a virtual
	USB serial port, which serves as a system console, with
	getty(8)
	waiting for you to log in. This means you no longer need
	to
	look for a keyboard and a screen, or mess with the console
	cables just to configure your system. You can also switch
	it to provide network interface, or present itself as a
	USB
	drive - it's all documented in the FreeBSD Handbook.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Performance improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Matthew Macy</name>
	<email>mmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>FreeBSD 12 saw the introduction of a number of performance
	improvements:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The introduction of the new synchronization primitive
	epoch(9) to
	replace the use of reader locks for providing existence
	guarantees
	for data structures.</li>

	<li>epoch(9) was used to provide an 85+% reduction in the
	overhead of
	pcb lookup in high core count systems.</li>

	<li>epoch(9) was used to provide an 85+% reduction in UDP send
	overhead
	on high core count systems. See the link for a bit more
	detail:
	<a
	href="http://scalebsd.org/blog/2018/06/16/UDP-and-epoch-for-liveness-guarantees">http://scalebsd.org/blog/2018/06/16/UDP-and-epoch-for-liveness-guarantees</a></li>
	<li>System call overhead is now half that of FreeBSD 11.</li>

	<li>UNIX sockets now scale near linearly (previously maxed out
	at 3-4 threads).</li>

	<li>The NUMA work has lead to a 20x-80x improvement in the
	scalability
	of page fault handling.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Armada 38x FreeBSD support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Marcin Wojtas</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Patryk Duda</name>
	<email>pdk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Rafał Kozik</name>
	<email>rk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.marvell.com/documents/egrkpyqzpoebxblyeept/">PRODUCT BRIEF</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Marvell Armada 38x is a very poplular ARMv7-based dual
	core SoC.
	Thanks to the multiple low and high speed interfaces
	the platform is used in a wide range of products, such
	as Network-Attached Storage (NAS), Wi-Fi Access Point
	(WAP) and others.</p>

      <p>Since last report, remaining Armada 38x support was
	integrated to HEAD, which can now compile with the
	armv7
	GENERIC config and use unmodified sys/gnu/dts device
	trees. The details are as follows:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>GENERIC config</li>

	<li>Introduce a vast rework of the sys/arm/mv directory for
	arm and armv7 platforms.</li>

	<li>Enable PLATFORM support for Marvell ARMv7 SoCs, which can
	now can boot with GENERIC kernel.</li>

	<li>Base on dynamic detection of SoC type and device tree
	instead of using ifdefs
	and enable more flexible environment for maintaining
	Marvell platforms.</li>

	<li>sys/gnu/dts device trees</li>

	<li>Improve platform code and the drivers (e.g. CESA, PCIE,
	GPIO) to properly work with original
	Linux device trees.</li>

	<li>GPIO</li>

	<li>Add multiple fixes and improvements to the
	sys/arm/mv/gpio.c</li>

	<li>Rework driver to properly integrate with HEAD GPIO
	frameworks (main and gpioled)</li>

	<li>Enable support for both old and Linux GPIO device tree
	bindings, so that multiple controllers
	can be used.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Stormshield
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Semihalf
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>PINE64-LTS Image</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>We now produce an image for the PINE64-LTS.
	This image works on the PINE64-LTS and the Sopine with
	Baseboard.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>PocketBeagle Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Tom Jones</name>
	<email>thj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.beagleboard.org/pocket">Pocket Beagle</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Pocket Beagle is the latest member of the BeagleBoard
	family.
	Support for it was added and the Beaglebone image can be
	used on it directly.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Allwinner SoC Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <ul>
	<li>SPI driver added for A64 SoC</li>

	<li>Thermal driver added/fixed for A64/H3/H5 SoCs</li>

	<li>Lot of bugs where fixed in the mmc driver, stability
	should be better</li>

	<li>New driver for AXXP803 which is the power chip companion
	of the A64 SoC</li>

	<li>Add overlays to use another timer controller as the
	default one in A64 if faulty
	These overlay is enabled in the PINE64/LTS images by
	default</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>ARMv6 and ARMv7 image now use EFI loader</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Instead of using the ubldr version of the loader which
	uses the U-Boot
	API, all images now use loader.efi as their primary
	FreeBSD loader.
	This allow us to have a common boot path for all arm and
	arm64 images.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>DTS Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>DTS files (Device Tree Sources) were updated to be on par
	with Linux 4.18 for
	the 12.0 release.</p>

      <p>The DTS are now compiled for some arm64 boards as the one
	present in U-Boot are
	now always up-to-date.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>RPI Firmware/DTB/U-Boot Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Emmanuel Vadot</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>U-Boot mailing list</name>
	<email>uboot@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The RaspberryPi firmware loads the DTB from the FAT
	partition based on
	the model. U-Boot now uses this DTB and passes it to the
	FreeBSD loader/kernel
	instead of using the DTS embedded in U-Boot.
	This allow the FreeBSD Kernel to use the RaspberryPi
	Foundation provided DTB overlays to enable
	HATs.
	The overlays can be obtained by installing the
	rpi-firmware package.</p>

      <p>A new U-Boot port for the W variant of the RPI0 was
	committed as
	u-boot-rpi-0-w. Some experiments started by Edward Tomasz
	Napierala
	(trasz@) have shown that we could possibly produce a
	generic image
	for all armv6 RPI (RPI-B, RPI0 and RPI0W).</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>FreeBSD on PowerNV (ppc64)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Patryk Duda</name>
	<email>pdk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Wojciech Macek</name>
	<email>wma@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Michal Stanek</name>
	<email>mst@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Nathan Whitehorn</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Semihalf is happy to announce that FreeBSD is now running
	on IBM POWER8. This project is a continuation of
	work done by Nathan Whitehorn who provided basic
	support for a PowerNV emulator.</p>

      <p>The IBM POWER8 family of CPUs offers superior performance
	compared to previous Power series. It provides
	complete NUMA support with up to 192 cores in a
	two socket system (up to 8 threads per core). All
	IO communication is handled by integrated PCIe
	interface equipped with multiple IOMMU engines.</p>

      <p>The support for POWER8 system running FreeBSD in
	Non-Virtualized environment contains:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Generic driver for OPAL hypervisor</li>

	<li>kboot loader modifications to allow Little-Endian loader
	to load a Big-Endian kernel ELF</li>

	<li>skiboot update for ELF-parser allowing it to understand
	FreeBSD kernel file format</li>

	<li>Basic support for PowerNV architecture, including modes of
	operation, MMU, interrupt controller</li>

	<li>SMP operation (tested with 128 CPU configuration)</li>

	<li>PHB subsystem driver, including IOMMU mapping for external
	buses</li>

	<li>PCIe host controller driver</li>

	<li>USB-3.0 XHCI driver</li>

	<li>Reworked drivers to be Big-Endian compatible:</li>

	<li>Chelsio cxgbe(4) 10/25G network adapter</li>

	<li>NVMe SSD drive</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	All work has been merged into HEAD and will be included in
	FreeBSD 12.0-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>Sponsors: IBM, FreeBSD Foundation, QCM Technologies,
	Semihalf, Limelight Networks.</p>

      <p>The project is kindly initiated and supported by Limelight
	Networks (Kevin Bowling).</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>FreeBSD on POWER9</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Matthew Macy</name>
	<email>mmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Once Justin Hibbits largely stabilized the powerpc64 port
	on the POWER9
	based Talos II I decided to procure one. I've been slowly
	working towards
	taking powerpc64 to parity with amd64. I've been working
	in an out of tree
	GitHub project - in part to eliminate the need to continue
	to support the 11
	year old in tree gcc4.</p>

      <p>Progress so far:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Adapted lock_delay to use POWER's SMT scheduling hints
	rather than
	using the yield hint from an older ISA</li>

	<li>Added ifunc support</li>

	<li>Ported the amd64 pmap so FreeBSD can use POWER9's new
	radix tree
	page tables. This will give us superpages mostly for free.</li>

	<li>Reduced the overhead of copyinout primitives for radix.</li>

	<li>Converted the copyinout primitives to ifuncs to switch
	between the
	old and the new at initialization time.</li>

	<li>Converted pmap to use ifuncs to eliminate the overhead of
	kobj dispatch.</li>

	<li>Hot patch out trap handling paths only needed by the older
	hashed page
	table support.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Work in Progress:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>NMI semantics: NMIs need to be emulated by only soft
	disabling interrupts,
	disabling interrupts blocks all interrupts except machine
	check exceptions
	and system resets.</li>

	<li>Superpage support: Superpages work in the functional
	simulator running SMT4
	but currently crash on real hardware due to incomplete
	page walk cache /
	TLB invalidation.</li>

	<li>Kernel minidump - with radix MMU enabled minidump support
	was a fairly
	straightforward port but time needs to be spent on test /
	debug.</li>

	<li>EARLY_AP_STARTUP - preliminary patches exist, but this is
	more work on !x86
	architectures due to IPI setup not being tied to the CPU
	code.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	A list of the other items needed to achieve kernel feature
	parity with a
	(wishful) list of milestones can be found at:
	<a
	href="https://github.com/POWER9BSD/freebsd/projects/1">https://github.com/POWER9BSD/freebsd/projects/1</a></p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>FreeBSD on RISC-V</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Ruslan Bukin</name>
	<email>br@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>FreeBSD/RISC-V has been one of the actively supported
	projects during the past year.</p>

      <p>On a compiler front we have upstreamed FreeBSD
	OS-dependent bits for GNU toolchain. It was
	updated to GCC 8.1 and Binutils 2.30. FreeBSD
	packages are available.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD Testsuite and required dependencies were
	successfully built for RISC-V and we did a test
	run: 152 tests failed out of 5186, which
	demonstrates a very good result for initial run
	and reveals areas to work on.</p>

      <p>We have added support for compressed ISA extension to KDB
	debugger and DTrace FBT provider enabling
	C-compressed kernel and userland by default. The
	output of disassembling instructions in KDB is
	looking similar to objdump.</p>

      <p>QEMU has updated to latest privilege spec allowing us to
	bring up FreeBSD on it. The emulation is quite
	fast: it takes one second only to boot FreeBSD to
	single-user mode in QEMU: <a
	href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FnWpRBaWF18">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FnWpRBaWF18</a></p>

      <p>Platform-Level Interrupt Controller (PLIC) driver was
	added. Interrupt support was converted to INTRNG.
	PLIC is used in QEMU for virtio network and block devices.
	With these changes, a full FreeBSD distribution
	can now be booted in QEMU.</p>

      <p>Network virtualization support (VIMAGE) was fixed and
	enabled by default now.</p>

      <p>In order to support RocketChip and derivatives we had to
	work on A(accessed), D(dirty) PTE (page table
	entry) bits management.
	We have successfully tested this on a lowRISC board and it
	is booting to multiuser just fine. lowRISC UART
	driver was added.</p>

      <p>Superuser-User-Modify (SUM) bit in status register is now
	used: kernel can access userspace only within
	certain functions that explicitly handle crossing
	user/kernel boundary.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE on FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Adriaan de Groot</name>
	<email>adridg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Tobias C. Berner</name>
	<email>tcberner@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/">KDE FreeBSD</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>KDE FreeBSD is responsible for the ports of the Plasma5
	and KDE4 desktops, and
	all associated applications. Further we also manage the
	Qt4 and Qt5 ports, as
	well as CMake.</p>

      <p>We also care for the FreeBSD builders for KDE's upstream
	CI on build.kde.org.</p>

      <p>Since the last status report a lot of things have changed.
	First and foremost,
	the Plasma5 Desktop and the Qt5 based KDE Applications
	have finally made their
	way into the official ports tree after lingering for
	multiple years in our
	development repository.</p>

      <p>Secondly KDE4 has been marked deprecated and will be
	removed at the end of the
	year. With Qt4 following no later than the next year (due
	to the exponentially
	increasing burden of maintenance).</p>

      <p>On a more technical side, bsd.qt.mk has been replaced by
	qt.mk and qt-dist.mk.
	The porter's handbook is being updated (with thanks to
	Tobias Kortkamp).</p>

      <p>Further we have been keeping CMake and Qt5 and almost
	every other port under our
	control up to date. SDDM has been updated to the
	next-to-latest release with
	backported security fixes.</p>

      <p>One big issue we have is www/qt5-webengine, which requires
	too much time to keep
	up to date, as the underlying chromium is in need of many
	patches, which change
	with every release. Another upcoming issue is the way in
	which FreeBSD's libinput
	lags behind. This blocks future updates to KDE Plasma as
	well as Wayland
	improvements. Thankfully x11@ is looking at this issue
	already, so it should be
	fixed soon -- for the meantime people who want to give the
	latest KDE Plasma
	Desktop a try can use the appropriate branch from our
	GitHub.</p>

      <p>People who are willing to contribute can find us on
	#kde-freebsd on freenode,
	the kde@FreeBSD.org mailing list. Further, we accept
	pull-requests and
	contributions on github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ports-kde.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Puppet</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Puppet Team</name>
	<email>puppet@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://puppetcommunity.slack.com/messages/C6CK0UGB1/">PuppetLab's FreeBSD slack channel</url>
      <url href="https://www.bsdcan.org/2018/schedule/events/930.en.html">BSDCan 2018: IT automation with Puppet</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since our last status report last year, the puppet@ team
	regularly updated the
	Puppet ports to catch on upstream releases. We have also
	held a Puppet talk at
	BSDCan.</p>

      <p>More recently, Puppet 6 was released, and a bunch of new
	ports appeared in the
	FreeBSD ports tree: sysutils/puppet6,
	sysutils/puppetserver6,
	databases/puppetdb6 being (obviously) the main ones. In
	this update, the Puppet
	language has not been heavily modified. As a consequence,
	upgrading from Puppet
	5 to Puppet 6 is an easy task compared to the experience
	you may have
	encountered from previous major version bumps. If you are
	still using Puppet 4,
	we recommend to schedule an upgrade soon: Puppet 4 is
	expected to be EOL by the
	end of 2018.</p>

      <p>Because distributing Marionette Collective modules via
	Puppet is more efficient
	than using packages, the
	sysutils/mcollective-\*-{agent,client} ports have
	been
	deprecated. Marionette Collective itself being phased out
	by PuppetLabs, the
	sysutils/mcollective port is expected to be deprecated at
	some point in the
	future, but we plan to keep it until an alternative is
	available. This
	alternative, called Choria, is in active development by
	R.I.Pienaar the
	original author of Marionette Collective. We are actively
	working with him to
	support FreeBSD out of the box, and will commit
	sysutils/choria to the tree as
	soon as it is considered a drop-in replacement for
	Marionette Collective.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>scarab: CLI tool for Bugzilla-related workflows</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Oleksandr Tymoshenko</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/gonzoua/scarab">GitHub repo</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>scarab is a CLI tool that makes some of Bugzilla
	functionality
	available from the command line. Normally users interact
	with the
	<a
	href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/">bugtracker</a>
	using a web browser
	but for certain workflows, Web UI may be more of an
	obstacle
	than help requiring to perform more steps compared to CLI
	tool.</p>

      <p>Bugzilla provides XML-RPC interfaces that can be used for
	automation/integration and there are several CLI tools
	like
	<a href="https://github.com/williamh/pybugz">pybugz</a>
	that can be used
	with bugs.FreeBSD.org as-is. They are generic
	one-size-fits-all
	tools which mean they can do a lot of thing at the cost of
	more complex CLI.</p>

      <p>scarab was created to be more specialized and less complex
	with following
	principles in mind:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Be an auxiliary tool, not a replacement for the web UI</li>

	<li>Move complexity to a configuration file, keep arguments as
	simple as possible</li>

	<li>Optimize for most common/tedious tasks</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Based on my experience with Bugzilla following tasks were
	identified as
	candidates for inclusion in the first release of the tool:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Downloading attachment on host machine and copying it to
	devbox</li>

	<li>Creating a file on the devbox and copying it to a host
	machine to be attached through Web UI</li>

	<li>Creating PRs with common fields' values</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	First two operations were implemented as <tt>files</tt>,
	<tt>fetch</tt>, <tt>fetchall</tt>, <tt>attach</tt>
	commands of the tool.</p>

      <p>The third operation was implemented by introducing PR
	templates, set of
	predefined field/value pairs, that can be combined
	run-time to provide higher
	flexibility. More information and usage examples can be
	found in the
	<a
	href="https://github.com/gonzoua/scarab/blob/master/examples/scarabrc">config
	file example</a></p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>Quarterly Reports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Edward Tomasz Napierała</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mateusz Piotrowski</name>
	<email>0mp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Quarterly Reports have been resurrected after almost a
	year long hiatus.
	The old workflow, which consisted of users submitting
	XML-formatted entries,
	which would then get hand-assembled into DocBook, was
	replaced with a new
	one, using Markdown instead. The XML submission form was
	replaced with
	GitHub Pull Requests. This should make submissions and
	editing much easier
	and user-friendly.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>Cleaning up the Wiki</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name></name>
	<email>wiki-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/WikiFixitGroup/">Wiki Fixit Group Website</url>
      <url href="irc://freebsd-wiki@irc.freenode.net">IRC channel</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Wiki used to be a scratch pad for the FreeBSD
	developers to
	organize projects, store notes and publish articles that
	were about to be added
	to the handbook. Recently, however, the FreeBSD wiki
	started to attract more
	and more people from the wider FreeBSD community, which
	resulted in a change of
	the character of the wiki.</p>

      <p>As a result we decided to discuss the future of the tools
	we want to use for
	documentation in FreeBSD (one of such discussions was held
	during BSDCam 2018,
	you may see some notes
	<a
	href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DevSummit/201808/DeveloperTools">here</a>).
	The general
	conclusion is that wiki is a great tool for what it was
	meant for: organizing
	projects and notes in the community of developers. We
	should not move all our
	documentation (especially handbooks) to Wiki as the
	quality and maintainability
	would suffer. On the other hand, the current workflow of
	submitting
	documentation patches, which involves checking out the doc
	tree and patching
	XML files is not ideal for many end users. This is why we
	are trying to approach the problem from various
	directions:</p>

      <ol><li>The wiki is being cleaned up of old content. We are
	trying to define a clear
	hierarchy of subpages and categories to make navigating
	the wiki easier.</li>
      <li>Some articles from the wiki are going to be migrated to
	either the doc tree
	or manual pages.</li></ol>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='third'>
    <title>HardenedBSD 2018Q3 Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Shawn Webb</name>
	<email>shawn.webb@hardenedbsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Our last report was
	<a
	href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/news/status/report-2017-04-2017-06.html#HardenedBSD">June
	2017</a>.
	A lot has transpired since then. In this status report, we
	will
	attempt to briefly cover all the progress we've made,
	including the
	few commits that made it upstream to FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>On 01 Jul 2018, we switched back to
	<a
	href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/shawn-webb/2018-04-30/hardenedbsd-switching-back-openssl">OpenSSL</a>
	as the crypto library provider in base. We did this
	because we lack
	the resources and the documentation for properly
	supporting LibreSSL
	in base. We still maintain LibreSSL in base; however,
	OpenSSL is
	simply the default crypto library (aka,
	<tt>WITHOUT_LIBRESSL</tt> is the
	default). We look forward to building a development
	community around
	LibreSSL in HardenedBSD such that we can re-enable
	LibreSSL by
	default, providing enhanced security for our users through
	the
	rejection of software monocultures.</p>

      <p>Cross-DSO Control Flow Integrity (Cross-DSO CFI) is an
	exploit
	mitigation from llvm that provides forward-edge
	protections across
	shared library and application boundaries. With
	HardenedBSD 12-STABLE,
	we launched non-Cross-DSO CFI support in base. Meaning,
	CFI is only
	applied to applications and not shared libraries. Along
	with
	SafeStack, which provides backward-edge protections,
	Cross-DSO CFI
	requires both ASLR and W^X for effectiveness as they store
	crucial
	metadata needing protection. HardenedBSD expertly,
	efficiently, and
	robustly fulfill those requirements through its PaX ASLR
	and PaX
	NOEXEC implementations.</p>

      <p>Over the past two years, we have slowly worked on
	Cross-DSO CFI
	support in HardenedBSD. In mid-2018, we made enough
	progress that we
	could publish an alpha
	<a
	href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/shawn-webb/2018-07-16/preliminary-call-testing-cross-dso-cfi">Call-For-Testing
	(CFT)</a>.
	We need to integrate the Cross-DSO CFI support with the
	RTLD such that
	function pointers resolved through
	<tt>dlopen(3)</tt>/`dlsym(3)` work properly
	with the cfi-icall scheme. We also need to perform
	experimental
	package builds, find breakages, and fix those breakages.
	We hope to
	officially debut Cross-DSO CFI in the latter half of 2019
	with the
	possibility of pushing back to 2020. HardenedBSD remains
	the first and
	only enterprise operating system to use CFI across the
	base set of
	applications.</p>

      <p>On 20 Aug 2018, we launched a new tool called
	<tt>hbsdcontrol(8)</tt> to
	toggle exploit mitigations on a per-application basis.
	<tt>hbsdcontrol(8)</tt> uses filesystem extended
	attributes and is the
	preferred method for exploit mitigation toggling for those
	filesystem
	that support extended attributes (UFS, ZFS). Our original
	utility,
	<tt>secadm</tt>, should be used with filesystems that do
	not support extended
	attributes (NFS).</p>

      <p>In <a
	href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/shawn-webb/2018-09-17/announcing-hardenedbsd-foundation">September
	2018</a>,
	the HardenedBSD Foundation Corp became a 501(c)(3)
	tax-exempt,
	not-for-profit organization in the USA. This means that
	donations by
	US persons are eligible for tax deductions. The creation
	of the
	HardenedBSD Foundation will ensure that HardenedBSD
	remains successful
	long-term. We look forward to working with the BSD
	community to
	provide an open source, clean-room reimplementation of the
	grsecurity
	patchset based on publicly-available documentation.</p>

      <p>We assisted Kyle Evans with the new <tt>bectl(8)</tt>
	utility, primarily
	enhancing jail support and fixing regressions. We are
	grateful for
	Kyle Evans' assistance in landing the enhancements
	upstream in FreeBSD
	and his overall responsiveness and helpfulness.</p>

      <p>Relevant commits for the <tt>bectl(8)</tt> are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><a
	href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=339047">r339047</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=338221">r338221</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=337993">r337993</a></li>

	<li><a
	href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=337947">r337947</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	We taught <tt>bhyve(8)</tt> how to live in a
	<a href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/rS337023">jailed
	environment</a>, allowing users to
	jail the hypervisor. We hardened the virtual address space
	of
	<tt>bhyve(8)</tt> by using <a
	href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/rS338511">guard
	pages</a>.
	This work made it upstream to FreeBSD. We are grateful to
	those in
	FreeBSD who provided insight to increase the quality and
	efficiency
	of our patches.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

</report>
