<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>April-June</month>

    <year>2014</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <?ignore
    <p><strong>This is a draft of the April-June 2014 status report.
	Please check back after it is finalized, and an announcement
	email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
	list.</strong></p>
    ?>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between April and
      June 2014.  This is the second of four reports planned for
      2014.</p>

    <p>The second quarter of 2014 was a very busy and productive time
      for the &os;&nbsp;Project.  A new &os;&nbsp;Core Team was
      elected, the &os;&nbsp;Ports Management Team branched the second
      quarterly <q>stable</q> branch, the &os;&nbsp;Release
      Engineering Team was in the process of finalizing the
      &os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE cycle, and many exciting new features have
      been added to &os;.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This
      report contains 24 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from July to
      September 2014 is October 7th, 2014.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <?ignore
  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>
  ?>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>CUSE4BSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/266581">Commit</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The so-called <quote>CUSE4BSD</quote> has been imported into the base
	system of &os;-11.  CUSE is short for <quote>character device in
	  userspace</quote>.  The CUSE library is a wrapper for the
	<tt>devfs(8)</tt> kernel functionality which is exposed
	through /dev/cuse.  In order to function, the CUSE kernel code
	must either be enabled in the kernel configuration file or
	loaded separately as a module.  Follow the commit message link
	to get more information.
      </p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>RPC/NFS and CTL/iSCSI Performance Optimizations</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; RPC stack, used as a base for its NFS server,
	received multiple optimizations to improve performance and SMP
	scalability.  Algorithmic optimizations reduced processing
	overhead, while improved locking allowed it to scale up to at
	least 40 processor cores without significant lock congestion.
	Combined with some other kernel optimizations, the peak NFS
	request rate increased by many times, reaching up to 600K
	requests per second on modern hardware.</p>

      <p>The CAM Target Layer (CTL), used as the base for the new kernel iSCSI
	server, also received a series of locking optimizations which
	allowed its peak request rate to increase from ~200K to ~600K
	IOPS with the potential of reaching a rate of 1M requests per
	second.  That rate is sufficient to completely saturate
	2x10Gbit Ethernet links with 4KB requests.  For comparison,
	the port of net/istgt (user-level iSCSI server) on the same
	hardware with an equivalent configuration showed only 100K
	IOPS.</p>

      <p>There is also ongoing work on improving CTL functionality.
	It was already made to support three of four VMware VAAI
	storage acceleration primitives (<tt>net/istgt</tt> supports
	2), while the goal is to reach full VAAI support during next
	months.</p>

      <p>With all these improvements, and earlier improvements in CAM,
	GEOM, ZFS, and a number of other kernel areas coming soon,
	&os;&nbsp;10.1 may become the fastest storage release ever.
	;)</p>

      <p>These projects are sponsored by iXsystems, Inc.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="arch">
    <title>&os;/arm64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/projects/arm64/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Arm64 is the name of the in-progress port of &os; to the
	ARMv8 CPU when it is in AArch64 mode.  Until recently, all ARM
	CPU designs were 32-bit only.  With the introduction of the
	ARMv8 architecture, ARM has added a new 64-bit mode.  This new
	mode has been named AArch64.</p>

      <p>Booting &os; on the ARM Foundation Model has made a lot of
	progress since the last status report.  An initial pmap
	implementation has been written.  With this, &os; is able to
	enter the Machine Independent boot code.  The required
	autoconf functions have been added allowing &os; to start
	scheduling tasks.  Finally the cpu_switch and copystr
	functions were added.  With these two, &os; will boot to the
	mountroot prompt.</p>

      <p>Work has started on supporting exceptions, including
	interrupts.  This will allow more developers to start
	working on device drivers.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish exception and interrupt handling</task>

      <task>Read the Device Tree or ACPI tables from UEFI</task>

      <task>Test on real hardware</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Updated <tt>vt(4)</tt> System Console</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Aleksandr</given>
	  <common>Rybalko</common>
	</name>
	<email>ray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warren</given>
	  <common>Block</common>
	</name>
	<email>wblock@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Newcons">Project wiki page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>vt(4)</tt> (aka <tt>Newcons</tt>) project provides
	a replacement for the legacy <tt>syscons</tt> system console.
	It brings a number of improvements, including better
	integration with graphics modes and broader character set
	support.</p>

      <p>Since the last <a
	  href="http://www.freebsd.org/news/status/report-2014-01-2014-03.html#Updated-vt%284%29-System-Console">report</a>,
	<tt>vt(4)</tt> gained the ability to make early driver
	selection.  <tt>vt(4)</tt> selects the best
	successfully-probed driver before most other kernel
	subsystems are initialized.  Also, to facilitate migration from
	<tt>syscons(4)</tt> to <tt>vt(4)</tt>, multiple virtual
	terminal subsystems in the kernel are now supported.  It is
	controlled by a small module with just one kernel environment
	variable.  Users can select the virtual terminal system to use
	by setting <tt>kern.vty=sc</tt> or <tt>kern.vty=vt</tt>.</p>

      <p>The GENERIC kernel configuration for the amd64 and i386
	platforms now includes both <tt>syscons(4)</tt> and
	<tt>vt(4)</tt> by default.  This configuration is also planned
	to be in &os;&nbsp;10.1-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>The project finally received a man page, so now
	<tt>vt(4)</tt> is not only the project name, but also a link
	to its documentation.  Great thanks to &a.wblock; for
	that.</p>

      <p>Major highlights:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Unicode support.</li>

	<li>Double-width character support for CJK characters.</li>

	<li><tt>xterm(1)</tt>-like terminal emulation.</li>

	<li>Support for Kernel Mode Setting (KMS) drivers
	  (<tt>i915kms</tt>, <tt>radeonkms</tt>).</li>

	<li>Support for different fonts per terminal window.</li>

	<li>Simplified drivers.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Brief status of supported architectures and hardware:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>amd64 (VGA/<tt>i915kms</tt>/<tt>radeonkms</tt>) &mdash;
	  works.</li>

	<li>ARM framebuffer &mdash; works.</li>

	<li>i386 (VGA/<tt>i915kms</tt>/<tt>radeonkms</tt>) &mdash;
	  works.</li>

	<li>IA64 &mdash; untested.</li>

	<li>MIPS &mdash; untested.</li>

	<li>PPC and PPC64 &mdash; work, but without X.Org yet.</li>

	<li>SPARC &mdash; works on certain hardware (e.g., Ultra
	  5).</li>

	<li><tt>vesa(4)</tt> &mdash; in progress.</li>

	<li>i386/amd64 nVidia driver &mdash; not supported.  VGA
	  should be used (VESA planned).</li>

	<li>Xbox framebuffer driver &mdash; will be deleted as
	  unused.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Implement the remaining features supported by
	<tt>vidcontrol(1)</tt>.</task>

      <task>Write manual pages for <tt>vt(4)</tt> drivers and kernel
	interfaces.</task>

      <task>Support direct handling of keyboard by the <tt>kbd</tt>
	device (without <tt>kbdmux(4)</tt>).</task>

      <task>CJK fonts.  (This is in progress).</task>

      <task>Address performance issues on some architectures.</task>

      <task>Switch to <tt>vt(4)</tt> by default.</task>

      <task>Convert keyboard maps for use with <tt>vt(4)</tt>.</task>

      <task>Implement compatibility mode to be able to use single-byte
	charsets/key-codes in <tt>vt(4)</tt>.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>QEMU <tt>bsd-user</tt>-Enabled Ports Building</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Stacey</given>
	  <common>Son</common>
	</name>
	<email>sson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juergen</given>
	  <common>Lock</common>
	</name>
	<email>nox@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sean</given>
	  <common>Bruno</common>
	</name>
	<email>sbruno@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/QemuUserModeHowTo">Overview of technology</url>
      <url href="http://dirty.ysv.freebsd.org/">Status of ports building</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/seanbruno/qemu-bsd-user">Master repository for collaboration</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>ports-mgmt/poudriere-devel</tt> port is capable of
	building ports via an emulator.  Configuration of the
	miscellaneous binary image activator is required prior to a
	poudriere-devel run.</p>

      <p>ARMV6, MIPS32 and MIPS64 packages can be produced via full
	emulation.  There are several packages that block a full run
	of builds.  They can be viewed on the "Status of ports
	building" link.</p>

      <p>To build packages via emulation, on current or latest
	stable/10:</p>

      <p>Clone the github repository, and switch to the bsd-user
	branch.  Then run:</p>

      <p><tt>./configure --static \<br/>
	  --target-list="arm-bsd-user i386-bsd-user \<br/>
	  mips-bsd-user mips64-bsd-user mips64el-bsd-user \<br/>
	  mipsel-bsd-user ppc-bsd-user ppc64-bsd-user sparc-bsd-user \<br/>
	  sparc64-bsd-user x86_64-bsd-user"</tt></p>

      <p><tt>gmake; gmake install</tt></p>

      <p>Then set up the <tt>binmiscctl</tt> tools to do some evil
	hackery to redirect execution of armv6 binaries to qemu:</p>

      <p><tt>binmiscctl add armv6 --interpreter \
	  "/usr/local/bin/qemu-arm" --magic \
	  "\x7f\x45\x4c\x46\x01\x01\x01\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x00\x02 \<br/>
	  \x00\x28\x00" --mask "\xff\xff\xff\xff\xff\xff\xff\x00\xff\xff\xff\xff \<br/>
	   \xff\xff\xff\xff\xfe\xff\xff\xff" --size 20 --set-enabled</tt></p>

      <p>Install poudriere-devel from ports.  It knows how to set up
	things.</p>

      <p>Create a poudriere jail to do all the magic:</p>

      <p><tt>poudriere jail -c -j 11armv632 -m svn -a armv6 \<br/>
	  -v head</tt></p>

      <p>Now run poudriere against that jail to build all the
	ports:</p>

      <p><tt>poudriere bulk -j 11armv632 -a</tt></p>

      <p>Nullfs mount the ports tree into the jail:</p>

      <p><tt>mkdir /usr/local/poudriere/jails/11armv632/usr/ports<br/>
	  mount -t nullfs /usr/ports /usr/local/poudriere/jails/11armv632/usr/ports</tt></p>

      <p>To chroot into the jail:</p>

      <p><tt>mount -t devfs devfs /usr/local/poudriere/jails/11armv632/dev<br/>
	  chroot /usr/local/poudriere/jails/11armv632/</tt></p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>PPC on AMD64 emulation.  This is a work in progress as
	there appear to be some serious issues running the bsd-user
	binary on big-endian hardware.  Justin Hibbits is working on
	this.</task>

      <task>SPARC64 on AMD64 emulation is non-functional and instantly
	segfaults.  We are looking for someone to poke at the bits
	here.</task>

      <task>External Toolchain, XDEV support.  There is partial
	support for using an AMD64 toolchain that can output binaries
	for other architecture (e.g., using an AMD64 toolchain to
	build MIPS64 packages).  We are currently tracking a linking
	issue with <tt>ports-mgmt/pkg</tt>.  Thanks to Warner Losh,
	Baptiste Daroussin, Dimitry Andric for poking at bits in here
	to make the XDEV target useful.</task>

      <task>Signal handling. The MIPS/ARMV6 target stills display a
	failure that manifests itself when building
	<tt>devel/p5-Sys-SigAction</tt>.</task>

      <task>Massive documentation update needed.  These modifications
	actually allow chrooting into a MIPS or ARMv6 environment
	and using native toolchains and libraries to prototype
	software for a target platform.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Python Ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os;</given>
	  <common>Python Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>python@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Python">The &os; Python Team Page</url>
      <url href="irc://freebsd-python@irc.freenode.net">IRC channel</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are pleased to announce the availability of conflict-free
	Python package support across different Python versions based
	on the USES=uniquefiles feature recently introduced to the
	Ports framework.  A Python package can be marked as buildable
	and installable in parallel for different Python versions at
	the same time on the same host.  The package building tools,
	however, do not support this feature yet and the Python team
	will work closely with portmgr and the pkg developers to enable
	support on a global ports and packages scale.</p>

      <p>In May and June a huge clean-up operation took place to
	remove the last bits and pieces targeting easy_install.  In
	the beginning of July we committed the final changes to remove
	easy_install support completely from the ports framework.
	This greatly simplifies the infrastructure and allows us to
	modernize and maintain it with less effort.</p>

      <p>We added Python 3.4, removed Python 3.1 after its end of
	life, updated the setuptools ports to version 5.1 and PyPy's
	development version to 2.3.1. The latest Python 2.7.8 and an
	updated setuptools will hit the tree shortly.</p>

      <p>Our upstreaming effort continues to produce good outcomes for
	simplifying maintenance and reducing complexity.</p>

      <p>Looking forward, one of the top priorities is to comply with
	the USES framework in the foreseeable future and to roll out a
	consistent maintainer policy for integrating new
	Python-related ports into the tree.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Migrate bsd.python.mk to the Uses framework.</task>

      <task>Develop a high-level and lightweight Python Ports
	Policy.</task>

      <task>Add support for granular dependencies (for example
	&gt;=1.0,&lt;2.0).</task>

      <task>See what adding pip (Python Package Index) support will
	require.</task>

      <task>Add default QA targets and functions for Python ports
	(TEST_DEPENDS, regression-test, etc.)</task>

      <task>More tasks can be found on the team's wiki page (see
	links).</task>

      <task>To get involved, come and say "hi" on IRC and let us know
	what you are interested in!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>UEFI Boot</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/UEFI">&os; UEFI wiki page</url>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/snapshots/">&os;&nbsp;snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) provides
	boot- and run-time services for x86 and other computers.  For
	the x86 architecture it replaces the legacy BIOS.  This
	project will adapt the &os; loader and kernel boot process for
	compatibility with UEFI firmware, found on contemporary
	servers, desktops, and laptops.</p>

      <p>Ed and Nathan completed a number of integration tasks over
	the past three months.  Nathan added a first-stage loader,
	boot1.efi, to support chain-loading the rest of the system
	from a UFS filesystem.  This allows the UEFI boot process to
	proceed in a similar fashion as with BIOS boot.  Nathan also
	added UEFI support to the &os; installer and release image
	creation script.</p>

      <p>The EFI framebuffer requires the <tt>vt(4)</tt> system
	console &mdash; a framebuffer driver is not implemented for
	the legacy <tt>syscons(4)</tt> console.  Ed added automatic
	<tt>vt(4)</tt> selection to the UEFI boot path.</p>

      <p>Snapshots are now built as dual-mode images, and should boot
	via both BIOS and UEFI.  Our plan is to merge the UEFI and
	<tt>vt(4)</tt> work to stable/10 to appear in &os;
	10.1-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Document manual installation, including dual-boot
	configurations.</task>

      <task>Implement boot1.efi for ZFS file systems.</task>

      <task>Add support for UEFI variables stored in non-volatile
	memory (NVRAM).</task>

      <task>Debug boot failures with certain UEFI firmware
	implementations.</task>

      <task>Support secure boot.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Core Team constitutes the project's "Board of
	Directors", responsible for deciding the project's overall
	goals and direction as well as managing specific areas of the
	&os; project landscape.</p>

      <p>Topics for core this quarter have included some far-reaching
	policy reviews and some significant changes to the project
	development methodology.</p>

      <p>In May, a new release policy was published and
	presented at the BSDCan developer conference by John Baldwin.
	The idea is that each major release branch (for example, 10.X)
	is guaranteed to be supported for at least five years, but
	individual point releases on each branch, like 10.0-RELEASE,
	will be issued at regular intervals and only the latest point
	release will be supported.</p>

      <p>Another significant change did not receive approval.  When
	the change to the Bylaws reforming the core team election
	process was put to the vote of all &os; developers, it failed
	to reach a quorum.</p>

      <p>June saw the culmination of a long running project to replace
	the project's bug tracking system.  As of June 3, the &os;
	project has switched to Bugzilla as its bug tracking system.
	All of the history of GNATS PRs has been preserved, so there
	is no need to re-open old tickets.  Work is still going on to
	replicate some of the integration tweaks that had been applied
	to GNATS, but all necessary functionality has been implemented
	and the project is already seeing the benefits of the new
	capabilities brought by Bugzilla.</p>

      <p>An election to select core members for the next two year term
	of office took place during this period.  We would like to
	thank retiring members of core for their years of service.
	The new core team provides continuity with previous core
	teams: about half are incumbents from the previous team, and
	several former core team members have returned after a hiatus.
	Core now includes two members of the &os; Foundation board and
	one other Foundation staff member, aiding greater coordination
	at the top level of the project.  At the same time the
	core-secretary role was passed on to a new volunteer.</p>

      <p>Other activities included providing consultation on licensing
	terms for software within the &os; source tree, and oversight
	of changes to the membership of postmaster and clusteradm.</p>

      <p>Three new src commit bits were issued during this quarter,
	and one was taken into safekeeping.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>&os; Host Support for OpenStack and OpenContrail</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grzegorz</given>
	  <common>Bernacki</common>
	</name>
	<email>gjb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Dubiel</common>
	</name>
	<email>md@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dominik</given>
	  <common>Ermel</common>
	</name>
	<email>der@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafal</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.openstack.org" />
      <url href="http://www.opencontrail.org" />
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/openstack-devstack" />
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/openstack-nova" />
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/contrail-vrouter" />
      <url href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/nova/+spec/freebsd-compute-node" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenStack is a cloud operating system that controls large
	pools of compute, storage, and networking resources in
	a datacenter.</p>

      <p>OpenContrail is a network virtualization (SDN) solution
	comprising network controller, virtual router, and analytics
	engine, which can be integrated with cloud orchestration
	systems like OpenStack or CloudStack.</p>

      <p>The goal of this work is to enable &os; as a fully supported
	compute host for OpenStack using OpenContrail virtualized
	networking.  The main areas of development are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Libvirt hypervisor driver for bhyve.</li>
	<li>Support for bhyve (via libvirt compute driver) and the
	  overall &os; platform in nova-compute.</li>
	<li>OpenContrail vRouter (forwarding plane kernel module) port
	  to &os;.</li>
	<li>OpenContrail Agent (network controller node) port to
	  &os;.</li>
	<li>Integration and performance optimizations.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Since the last report the following items have been
	completed, which allow for a working demo of an OpenStack compute
	node on a &os; host using OpenContrail for network
	virtualization:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Port of the OpenContrail vRouter kernel module for &os;
	  (MPLS over GRE mode only)</li>
	<li>Port of the OpenContrail Agent for &os;</li>
	<li>&os; version of a Devstack installation/configuration
	  script with support for the OpenContrail solution (Compute
	  node components only)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>A demo was presented at the DevSummit during BSDCan2014
	in Ottawa.  Also, a meetup regarding the subject was organized
	in Krakow, Poland.</p>

      <p>Work on this project is sponsored by Juniper Networks.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>The &os; Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/"/>
      <url href="http://freebsdjournal.com/">&os; Journal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization
	dedicated to supporting and promoting the &os;&nbsp;Project
	and community worldwide.  Most of the funding is used to
	support &os; development projects, conferences and developer
	summits, purchase equipment to grow and improve the &os;
	infrastructure, and provide legal support for the Project.</p>

      <p>We published our third issue of the &os; Journal.  We have
	over 2700 subscriptions so far.  We continued working on the
	digital edition, which will allow subscribers to read the
	magazine in different web browsers, including those than run
	on &os;.  This will be available for the July/August issue of
	the Journal.</p>

      <p>We hired Anne Dickison, on a freelance basis, as our new
	marketing director, to help us promote the Foundation and
	Project.</p>

      <p>The annual board meeting was held in Ottawa, Canada, in May.
	Directors and officers were elected, and we did some long-term
	planning.  We worked on our vision, core values, project road
	mapping, and our near-term goals.  We also met with the core
	team to discuss roles and responsibilities, project
	roadmapping, and what we can do to help the Project more.</p>

      <p>We were a Gold+ sponsor for BSDCan, May 16-17 and provided
	7 travel grants for developers to attend the conference.  We
	also were the sponsor for both the developer and vendor
	summits.</p>

      <p>Justin Gibbs gave a &os; presentation at a &os; user's
	internal technology summit.  Company visits like this help
	users understand the Project structure better and gives us
	a chance to communicate what &os; people are working on as
	well as learn what different companies are doing with &os;, as
	well as what they'd like to see supported.  We can then help
	facilitate collaboration between the companies and &os;
	developers.</p>

      <p>We were represented at Great Wide Open, April 2-3
	(greatwideopen.org), Texas LinuxFest, June 13-14
	(texaslinuxfest.org), and SouthEast LinuxFest, June 20-22
	(southeastlinuxfest.org).</p>

      <p>Hardware was purchased to support an upgrade at Sentex.  A
	new high-capacity 1Gbps switch was deployed to allow for more
	systems to be added to the test lab.  The main file server and
	development box was upgraded to allow more users in the lab
	simultaneously.</p>

      <p>We purchased hardware, including package builders, and
	a larger server to allow NYI to be a full replica of all
	Project systems, comparable to what is in place at Yahoo Inc.
	and ISC.</p>

      <p>We worked with our lawyer to create an NDA between the
	Foundation and individuals for third party NDAs.  This allows
	developers who need access to proprietary documents, to go
	through the Foundation, via an NDA for access.</p>

      <p>&os; Foundation Systems Administrator and Release Engineer,
	Glen Barber, continued work on producing regularly-updated
	&os;/arm snapshots for embedded devices, such as the
	Raspberry Pi, ZedBoard, and BeagleBone.</p>

      <p>In addition to producing weekly development snapshots from
	the head/ and stable/ branches, with feedback and help from Ed
	Maste, Glen finished work to produce release images that will,
	by default, provide debugging files for userland and kernel
	available on the &os;&nbsp;Project FTP mirrors.  Note that the
	debugging files will not be included on the bootonly.iso,
	disc1.iso, or dvd1.iso images due to the size of the resulting
	images.</p>

      <p>Foundation staff member Konstantin Belousov completed an
	investigation into poor performance of PostgreSQL on &os;.
	This uncovered scalability problems in the &os; kernel, and
	changes to address these issues are in progress.</p>

      <p>Some previously completed Foundation-sponsored projects
	received enhancements or additional work.  The ARM
	superpages project was completed last year, but is now enabled
	by default in &os;-CURRENT.  Many stability fixes and
	enhancements have been committed to the in-kernel iSCSI stack.
	The iSCSI project was released in &os;&nbsp;10.0.  Many
	stability fixes and enhancements have been committed and will
	be included in &os;&nbsp;10.1.</p>

      <p>Work continues on the Foundation-sponsored autofs automount
	daemon, UEFI boot support, the updated <tt>vt(4)</tt> system
	video console, virtual machine images, and the Intel graphics
	driver update.  Foundation-sponsored work resulted in 226
	commits to &os; over the April to June period.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>SDIO Driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ilya</given>
	  <common>Bakulin</common>
	</name>
	<email>ilya@bakulin.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/SDIO">SDIO project page on &os;&nbsp;Wiki</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/kibab/freebsd/tree/mmccam">Source code</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>SDIO is an interface designed as an extension of the existing
	SD card standard, which allows the connecting of different
	peripherals to a host with a standard SD controller.
	Peripherals currently sold on the general market include
	WLAN/BT modules, cameras, fingerprint readers, and barcode
	scanners.  Additionally, SDIO is used to connect some
	peripherals in products like Chromebooks and Wandboards.  A
	prototype of the driver for the Marvell SDIO WLAN/BT (Avastar
	88W8787) module is also being developed, using the existing
	Linux driver as the reference.</p>

      <p>SDIO card detection and initialization already work.  Most
	necessary bus methods are implemented and tested.</p>

      <p>The WiFi driver is able to load firmware onto the card and
	initialize it.  A rewrite of the MMC stack as a transport
	layer for the CAM framework is in progress.  This will allow
	utilization of the well-tested CAM locking model and debug
	features.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>SDIO stack: finish CAM migration.  The initialization of
	the MMC/SD card is implemented in the XPT layer, but cannot be
	tested with real hardware because of the lack of any device
	drivers that implement peripheral drivers and SIMs for CAM
	MMC.  The plan is to use a modified version of the BeagleBone
	Black SDHCI controller driver for the SIM and a modified version
	of <tt>mmcsd(4)</tt> as a peripheral driver.</task>

      <task>Marvell SDIO WiFi: connect to the &os; network stack,
	write the code to implement required functions (such as
	sending/receiving data, network scanning and so on).</task>
    </help>
  </project>
  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os;</given>
	  <common>Release Engineering Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/9.3R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os; development snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is responsible for setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project releases
	of &os;, and announcing code freezes and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>In early May, the &os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE cycle entered the
	code slush phase.  The &os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE cycle is nearing
	the final phases, and 9.3-RC3 builds will be starting soon.
	9.3-RC3 is planned to be the final release candidate for this
	release cycle, and at the time of this writing, 9.3-RELEASE
	should be available on schedule.</p>

      <p>Work is ongoing to integrate support for embedded
	architectures into the release build process.  At this
	time, support exists for a number of ARM kernels, in
	particular the Raspberry Pi, BeagleBone, and WandBoard.</p>

      <p>Additionally, work is in progress to produce virtual machine
	images as part of the release cycle, supporting various cloud
	services such as Microsoft Azure, Amazon EC2, and Google
	Compute Engine.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Running &os; as an Application on Top of the Fiasco.OC
      Microkernel</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ilya</given>
	  <common>Bakulin</common>
	</name>
	<email>ilya@bakulin.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L4_microkernel_family">L4 microkernel family</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/201407DevSummit/BSDUserspace">A brief description of the project on the &os; wiki (short talk during &os; DevSummit in Cambridge)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Fiasco.OC belongs to the L4 microkernel family.  A
	microkernel provides a bare minimum of services to the
	applications running on top of it, unlike traditional kernels
	that incorporate complex code like IP stacks and device
	drivers.  This allows a dramatic decrease in the amount of
	code running in the privileged mode of the CPU, achieving
	higher security while still providing an acceptable level of
	performance.</p>

      <p>Running an operating system kernel on top of the microkernel
	allows leveraging any software that was developed for that
	operating system.  The OS kernel runs in user-mode
	side-by-side with other microkernel applications such as
	real-time components.  Multiple OSes, each with their userland
	applications, can even be run in parallel, thus allowing
	construction of products where processing of corporate data is
	strictly separated from the processing of private data.</p>

      <p>The project aims to create a port of &os; to the Fiasco.OC
	microkernel, a high performance L4 microkernel
	developed by TU Dresden.  Existing ports of OpenBSD and
	Linux are used as a reference.  This will allow the use of
	unique &os; features like ZFS in L4-based projects.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish opensourcing the port of L4OpenBSD/amd64 made by
	genua mbh.  This is a work in progress.</task>

      <task>Publish the sources of the L4&os; port that is largely
	based on the L4OpenBSD code.</task>

      <task>Improve the port, the first task being adopting the
	<tt>pmap(9)</tt> module to work with L4 microkernel memory
	allocation services.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="proj">
    <title><tt>pkg(8)</tt></title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Baptiste</given>
	  <common>Daroussin</common>
	</name>
	<email>bapt@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>Drewery</common>
	</name>
	<email>bdrewery@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Matthew</given>
	  <common>Seaman</common>
	</name>
	<email>matthew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Vsevolod</given>
	  <common>Stakhov</common>
	</name>
	<email>vsevolod@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>The pkg mailing list</name>
	<email>freebsd-pkg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd/pkg">The main <tt>pkg(8)</tt> git repository.</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd/pkg/issues">The preferred place to raise bug reports concerning <tt>pkg(8)</tt>.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><tt>pkg(8)</tt> is the new package management tool for &os;.
	It is now the only supported package management tool for &os;
	releases from 10.0-RELEASE, including the upcoming
	9.3-RELEASE.  <tt>pkg(8)</tt> is available on all currently
	supported releases.  Support for the legacy pkg_tools is due
	to be discontinued at the beginning of September 2014.</p>

      <p>The release of <tt>pkg(8)</tt> 1.3 is imminent.  This
	includes major improvements in the dependency solver.  Now we
	can:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Switch versions of, for example, Perl or PHP and resolve
	  all the conflicts with packages that depend on them
	  automatically.  No more need to manually switch package
	  origins.</li>

	<li>Deal more gracefully with complex upgrade or install
	  scenarios.</li>

	<li>Sandbox operations dealing with freshly downloaded data
	  until it can be verified as trustworthy by checking the
	  package signature.</li>

	<li>Deal with provides-and-requires style of dependencies, so
	  for example we can say "this package needs to use a web
	  server" and allow that dependency to be fulfilled by apache
	  or nginx or any other alternative that provides web-server
	  functionality.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Beyond the next release, we have work in progress on allowing
	ranges of versions in dependency rules and handling
	a selection of "foreign" package repositories, such as CPAN or
	CTAN or PyPi.</p>

      <p>There are plans to use <tt>pkg(8)</tt> to package up the base
	system.  Along with other benefits, this will allow writing a
	universal installer: download one installer image and from
	there install any available version of &os;, including
	snapshots.</p>

      <p>We are also intending to use <tt>pkg(8)</tt> within the ports
	tree at package-build time to handle fulfilling build
	dependencies.  This opens the possibility of installing
	build-dependencies by downloading binary packages, which means
	you can install a package with customized options with the
	minimum amount of time spent compiling anything else.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We are sorely lacking a comprehensive testing setup.
	Integrating automated regression testing into the development
	cycle is becoming an imperative.</task>

      <task>We need testers who can run development versions of pkg in
	as many distinct types of use-cases as possible, and report
	feedback from their experiences to the freebsd-pkg@freebsd.org
	mailing list or our issues list on github.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>The Graphics Stack on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <common>&os; Graphics team</common>
	</name>
	<email>x11@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Graphics">Graphics stack roadmap and supported hardware matrix</url>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-announce/2014-July/001570.html">WITH_NEW_XORG repository announce</url>
      <url href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/ports/browser/trunk">Ports-related development repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We were generally short on time this quarter.  We made less
	progress than expected on all fronts.</p>

      <p>The alternate <tt>pkg(8)</tt> repository, built with
	WITH_NEW_XORG, is now available.  This alleviates the need for
	users to rebuild their ports with WITH_NEW_XORG.  See the
	announcement, linked above for further information.</p>

      <p>Thanks to a contribution from Jan Kokemüller, Radeon 32bit
	ioctls are now working on 64bit hosts.  This was tested
	successfully with Wine and StarCraft II on &os; 9.x and 11.
	This required modifications to
	<tt>emulators/i386-wine-devel</tt> so that it works with
	WITH_NEW_XORG, and the creation of a new port,
	<tt>libtxc_dxtn</tt>, to support the texture compression used
	by StarCraft II.  We have not yet had the time to polish
	everything, so this still requires manual steps.</p>

      <p>The DRM generic code update is ready, but it breaks the
	current i915 driver.  Therefore, the i915 driver must be
	updated before anything is committed.</p>

      <p>Compared to the previous status report, OpenCL test programs
	are running fine now, thanks to upgrades and fixes to libc++
	and Clang.  The relevant ports are still not ready to hit the
	ports tree, unfortunately.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>See the "Graphics" wiki page for up-to-date
	information.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Chelsio iSCSI Offload Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sreenivasa</given>
	  <common>Honnur</common>
	</name>
	<email>shonnur@chelsio.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links></links>

    <body>
      <p>Building on the new in-kernel iSCSI target and initiator
	stack released in &os;&nbsp;10.0, Chelsio Communications has
	begun developing an offload interface to take advantage of the
	hardware offload capabilities of Chelsio T4 and T5 10 and 40
	gigabit Ethernet adapters.</p>

      <p>The code currently implements a working prototype of offload
	for the initiator side, and target side offload should begin
	shortly.  The code will be released under the BSD license and
	is expected to be completed later in the year and be committed
	to &os;-HEAD, and will likely ship in a &os; release in
	early 2015.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete testing and debugging of the initiator
	offload.</task>

      <task>Start development of target offload.</task>

      <task>Create hardware-independent offload APIs, based on
	experiences with target and initiator proof-of-concept
	implementations.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>TMPFS Stability</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Peter</given>
	  <common>Holm</common>
	</name>
	<email>pho@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Extensive testing of <tt>tmpfs(5)</tt> using the stress2
	kernel test suite was done.  The issues found were debugged
	and fixed.</p>

      <p>Most of the problems are related to bugs in the
	interaction of the vnode and node lifetime, culminating in e.g.,
	unmount races and dotdot lookup bugs.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>PostgreSQL Performance Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.kib.kiev.ua/kib/pgsql_perf_v2.0.pdf" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Analysis of the performance of the latest 9.3 version of
	PostgreSQL on &os;-CURRENT has been performed.  The issues
	which prevented good scalability on a 40-core machine were
	determined, and changes prototyped which solve the
	bottlenecks.</p>

      <p>The URL above provides a paper which contains a detailed
	explanation of the issues and solutions, together with a
	graph demonstrating the effects on scalability.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ZFSguru</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jason</given>
	  <common>Edwards</common>
	</name>
	<email>sub.mesa@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://zfsguru.com" />
      <url href="http://zfsguru.com/news/stateoftheproject/2014" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ZFSguru is a multifunctional server appliance with a strong
	emphasis on storage.  ZFSguru began as simple web-interface
	frontend to ZFS, but has since grown into a &os; derivative
	with its own infrastructure.  The scope of the project has
	also grown with the inclusion of add-on packages that add
	functionality beyond the traditional NAS functionality found
	in similar product like FreeNAS and NAS4Free.  ZFSguru aims to
	be a true multifunctional server appliance that is extremely
	easy to setup and can unite both novice and more experienced
	users in a single user interface.  The modular nature of the
	project combats the danger of bloat, whilst still allowing
	extended functionality to be easily deployed.</p>

      <p>Where development in the first quarter of this year brought
	drag-and-drop permissions for Samba and NFS, development in
	the second quarter focused on strengthening the infrastructure
	of the project.  A new library and toolkit solution dubbed
	'Mesa' is in the works, providing a cleaner foundation to the
	project.  A new master server providing secure remote services
	is being setup, to be located in a high-speed datacenter.  But
	most importantly, a new system build infrastructure has shown
	great progress and will soon be able to provide automated
	system builds to our users.  This not only improves the
	frequency of system releases but also frees much developer
	time to be spent on different areas of the project.</p>

      <p>Furthermore, a new website and forum is being worked on,
	replacing the old-fashioned website that offers only limited
	functionality.  The new website will be linked to the server
	database, providing real-time updates about the project.</p>

      <p>In addition, a new platform for collaborative development is
	in the works.  A service addon has been created for the GitLab
	project, which is a drop-in replacement of the popular GitHub
	website.  The choice was made to host our own solution and not
	rely on GitHub itself.  In retrospect this appears to be a
	good decision.  The recent development where GitHub removed
	projects after DCMA takedowns being sent is incompatible with
	the philosophy of free-flow-of-information, which the ZFSguru
	project is a strong proponent of.  By hosting our own
	solution, we have avoided any dependency on third party
	projects.</p>

      <p>It is expected that after the infrastructure of the project
	has been revamped, work on the web-interface itself can
	continue.  New functionality such as GuruDB and Service
	Bulletins provide a tighter connection between the server
	infrastructure and the web-interface.  The Migration Manager
	is one of the last remaining features still missing in the
	web-interface.  This functionality provides an easy way to
	upgrade the current system by performing a new clean
	installation, but migrate all relevant configuration to the
	new installation.  It also allows to backup all system
	configuration in a single file to be stored on a different
	machine should things go awry.</p>

      <p>A longer version of this status report giving a wider
	perspective on the project can be found at the
	<quote>stateoftheproject</quote> link.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>&os; and Summer of Code 2014</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Glen</given>
	  <common>Barber</common>
	</name>
	<email>gjb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wojciech</given>
	  <common>Koszek</common>
	</name>
	<email>wkoszek@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://gsoc.FreeBSD.org" />
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2014" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; received 39 project proposals this year, many of
	which were of a very high standard.  After a difficult
	selection process narrowing these down into the slots we had
	been allocated, a total of 16 projects were selected to
	participate in Google Summer of Code 2014 with &os;.</p>

      <p>The projects selected span a wide range of areas within &os;,
	covering both the base system and ports infrastructure,
	userland and kernel.  We have students working on firewall
	optimisation, ports packaging tools, embedded systems,
	debugging infrastructure, improved Unicode support,
	enhancements to the loader and to the installer, and several
	other areas of work.  We are just over halfway through the
	allocated time this year, and are very much looking forward to
	integrating code produced by these projects into &os;.</p>

      <p>This is the tenth time &os; has taken part in Google's
	Summer of Code, and we are grateful to Google to have accepted
	us as a participating organisation.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Port Management Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Frederic</given>
	  <common>Culot</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Port Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/" />
      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/index.html" />
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html" />
      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr" />
      <url href="http://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree slowly approaches the 25,000 ports threshold,
	while the PR count is slightly below 1800.</p>

      <p>In Q2 we added three new committers, took in one commit bit
	for safekeeping, and reinstated one commit bit.</p>

      <p>In May, &a.tabthorpe; was replaced by &a.culot; as portmgr
	secretary, and &a.swills; became a member of the portmgr
	team.</p>

      <p>Commencing July 1, the third intake of
	<tt>portmgr-lurkers</tt> started active duty on
	<tt>portmgr</tt> for a four month duration.  The next two
	candidates are &a.wg; and &a.nivit;.</p>

      <p>This quarter also saw the release of the second quarterly
	branch, namely 2014Q2. This branch was not only built for 10
	(as 2014Q1) but for 9 as well (both i386 and amd64).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>As previously noted, many PRs continue to languish, we
	would like to see committers dedicate themselves to closing as
	many as possible.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>Quarterly Status Reports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Quarterly Status Report Team</name>
	<email>monthly@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>These quarterly status reports help the &os; community stay
	up-to-date with the happenings in and around the project.
	Updates from &os; teams, new features being developed in-
	or out-of-tree, products derived from &os;, and &os; events
	are all welcome additions to the status reports.</p>

      <p>The Monthly team has been busy since the last report, with
	longtime organizer &a.pgj; having stepped down from the team
	&mdash; thank you G&aacute;bor for all your hard work!  This
	has left something of a void in the preparation of this
	report, for which the call for items was issued quite late.
	To help fill the void, &a.wblock; and &a.bjk; have been added
	to the monthly@ team, joining &a.gjb;, &a.gavin;, &a.emaste;,
	and the rest of the team in preparing this report.  Special
	thanks to Glen for doing most of the work while simultaneously
	getting 9.3-RELEASE out the door!</p>

      <p>The next cycle is sooner than you think!  The deadline for
	submitting entries for the Q3 report is October 7th, 2014.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Submit reports for Q42014 to monthly@FreeBSD.org!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>New Automounter</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napiera&#322;a</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links></links>

    <body>
      <p>Deficiencies in the current automounter, <tt>amd(8)</tt>, are
	a recurring problem reported by many &os; users.  A new
	automounter is being developed to address these concerns.</p>

      <p>The automounter is a cleanroom implementation of
	functionality available in most other Unix systems, using
	proper kernel support implemented via an autofs filesystem.
	The automounter supports a standard map format, and will
	integrate with the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol
	(LDAP) service.</p>

      <p>The project is at the early testing stage.  A patch will be
	released as part of a broader call for testing after
	additional review on some critical components (in particular,
	the autofs filesystem).  After fixing reported problems, the
	code will be committed to &os;&nbsp;11-CURRENT.  It is expected
	to ship in the &os;&nbsp;10.2 release.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Fix bad interaction with <tt>fts(3)</tt>.</task>

      <task>Debug a problem with Kerberos NFS mounts.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE/FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>KDE/FreeBSD Team</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">KDE/FreeBSD home page</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">area51</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE/FreeBSD team has continued to improve the experience
	of KDE software and Qt under FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>During this quarter, the team has kept most of the KDE and Qt
	ports up-to-date, working on the following releases:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>KDE SC: 4.12.5; Workspace: 4.11.9</li>
      </ul>

      <p>As a result &mdash; according to PortScout &mdash; kde@ has
	526 ports (up from 526), of which 84.63% are up-to-date (down
	from 98.86%).  iXsystems Inc. continues to provide a machine
	for the team to build packages and to test updates.
	iXsystems Inc. has been providing the KDE/FreeBSD team with
	support for quite a long time and we are very grateful for
	that.</p>

      <p>As usual, the team is always looking for more testers and
	porters so please contact us at kde@FreeBSD.org and visit our
	home page at
	<a href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">http://FreeBSD.kde.org</a>.
	It would be especially useful to have more helping hands on
	tasks such as getting rid of the dependency on the defunct
	HAL project and providing integration with KDE's Bluedevil
	Bluetooth interface.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Updating out-of-date ports, see
	<a href="http://portscout.freebsd.org/kde@freebsd.org.html">PortScout</a>
	for a list</task>
      <task>Removing the dependency on HAL</task>
    </help>
  </project>

</report>
