<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2015</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p><strong>This is a draft of the October&ndash;December 2015
      status report.  Please check back after it is finalized, and
      an announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
      list.</strong></p>

    <?ignore
    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between October and
      December 2015.  This is the last of four reports planned for
      2015.</p>

    <p>The fourth quarter of 2015 was another productive quarter for
      the &os; project and community. [...]</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from January
      to March 2016 is April 7, 2016.</p>
     ?>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Linux Kernel as a Library Added to the Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/lkl/linux">Upstream LKL Github repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LKL (&quot;Linux Kernel as a Library&quot;) is a special
	&quot;architecture&quot; of the full Linux kernel that builds as a
	userspace library on various platforms, including &os;.  One
	application of such a library is using Linux's filesystem drivers
	to implement a FUSE backend.</p>

      <p>fusefs-lkl's <tt>lklfuse</tt> binary is such a FUSE
	filesystem.  It can mount <tt>ext4/3/2</tt>, <tt>XFS</tt>, and
	<tt>BTRFS</tt> read-write, using the native drivers from
	Linux.</p>

      <p>The <tt>sysutils/fusefs-lkl</tt> port may now be installed from
	packages or ports, providing access to these filesystems on
	&os; via FUSE.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>Style(9) enhanced to allow C99 'bool'</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bruce</given>
	  <common>Evans</common>
	</name>
	<email>brde@optusnet.com.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/svn-src-head/2015-December/079671.html">Bruce's email requesting bool be added to <tt>style(9)</tt></url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4384">Differential Revision for the change</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Use of <tt>bool</tt> is now allowed.  It was allowed
	previously, as well, but now it's <em>really</em> allowed.  Party
	like it's 1999!</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Specify <tt>style(9)</tt>'s opinion on <tt>iso646.h.</tt></p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix <tt>intmax_t</tt> to be 128-bit on platforms where
	  <tt>__int128_t</tt> is used.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Sysctl enhancements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ravi</given>
	  <common>Pokala</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpokala@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcelo</given>
	  <common>Araujo</common>
	</name>
	<email>araujo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_data_types#Fixed-width_integer_types">Wikipedia Entry on C99 Fixed-Width Integer Types</url>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=203918"><tt>sysctl(8)</tt> -t Submission PR</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> This quarter, support was added for fixed-width sysctls
	(signed and unsigned 8-bit, 16-bit, 32-bit, and 64-bit integers).
	The new KPIs are documented in the <tt>sysctl(9)</tt> manual page.
	The <tt>sysctl(8)</tt> command line tool supports all of the new
	types.</p>

      <p><tt>sysctl(8)</tt> gained the '-t' flag, which prints sysctl type
	information (the original patch was submitted by Yoshihiro Ota).
	This support includes the newly added fixed-width types.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>ioat(4) driver enhancements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I/O_Acceleration_Technology">Wikipedia on I/OAT</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/news/status/report-2015-07-2015-09.html#ioat%284%29-Driver-Import">Last quarter's <tt>ioat(4)</tt> report</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> I/OAT DMA engines are bulk memory operation offload
	engines built into some Intel Server/Storage platform
	CPUs.</p>

      <p>This quarter, several enhancements were made to the driver.
	The driver now avoids memory allocation in locked paths, which
	should avoid deadlocking in memory pressure scenarios.  Support
	for Broadwell-EP devices has been added.  The
	&quot;blockfill&quot; operation and a non-contiguous 8 KB copy
	operation have been added to the API.  The driver can recover from
	various programming errors by resetting the hardware.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>XOR and other advanced (&quot;RAID&quot;) operation support.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>ntb_hw(4)/if_ntb(4) driver synced up to Linux</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/jonmason/ntb/wiki">Jon Mason's NTB wiki</url>
      <url href="https://www-ssl.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/white-papers/xeon-c5500-c3500-non-transparent-bridge-paper.pdf">Intel NTB whitepaper</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><tt>ntb_hw(4)</tt> is now up-to-date with the Linux NTB driver as
	of the work-in-progress 4.4 kernel (and actually, contains some
	fixes that haven't landed in the mainline Linux tree yet but will
	land in 4.5).  Only Back-to-back (&quot;B2B&quot;) configurations
	are supported at this time.  Going forward, newer hardware may
	only support the B2B configuration.</p>

      <p><tt>if_ntb(4)</tt> is mostly up-to-date with the Linux NTB netdevice
	driver.  Notably absent is support for changing the MTU at
	runtime.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Improving <tt>if_ntb(4)</tt> to avoid using the entire Base
	  Address Register (BAR) when very large BAR sizes are configured
	  (e.g., 512 GB).</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improving <tt>pmap_mapdev(9)</tt> to somehow allocate only
	  superpage mappings for large BARs, on platforms that support
	  superpages.  (NTB BARs can be as large as 512 GB.)</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on newer ARM boards</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Wehle</common>
	</name>
	<email>john@feith.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ganbold</given>
	  <common>Tsagaankhuu</common>
	</name>
	<email>ganbold@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/arm/Odroid-C1">&os; on Odroid-C1</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/291683">Commit adding glue driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This quarter, we made the changes necessary to support the
	Amlogic Meson Ethernet controller on the Hardkernel ODROID-C1
	board which has an Amlogic aml8726-m8b SoC.  The main effort
	needed was to write a glue driver for the Ethernet controller
	&mdash; the Amlogic Meson Ethernet controller is compatible with
	Synopsys DesignWare 10/100/1000 Ethernet MAC
	(<tt>if_dwc</tt>).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Mellanox Drivers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mellanox.com/page/ethernet_cards_overview">Hardware Information</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/290650">Commit Adding the Driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Mellanox &os; team is proud to announce support for the
	ConnectX-4 series of network cards in &os; 11-current and &os;
	10-stable.  These devices deliver top performance, with up to
	100GBit/s of raw transfer capacity, and support both Ethernet and
	Infiniband.  Currently, the Ethernet driver is ready for use and
	the Infiniband support for ConnectX-4 is making good progress.  We
	hope that it will be complete before &os; 11.0 is released.  For
	more technical information, refer to the <tt>mlx5en(4)</tt> manual
	page in 11-current.  The new driver for ConnectX-4 cards is called
	<tt>mlx5</tt> and is put under <tt>/sys/dev</tt> and not under
	<tt>/sys/ofed</tt> as was done for the previous
	<tt>mlx4</tt> driver.  The <tt>mlx5en(4)</tt> kernel module is
	compiled by default in GENERIC kernels.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>&quot;FreeBSD Mastery: Specialty Filesystems&quot; early access version now available</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michael</given>
	  <common>Lucas</common>
	</name>
	<email>mwlucas@michaelwlucas.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.michaelwlucas.com/nonfiction/fmsf">Book site</url>
      <url href="https://www.tiltedwindmillpress.com/?product=fmspf">Early access version</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><u>FreeBSD Mastery: Specialty Filesystems</u> is now in
	copyediting.  The ebook should be available by the end of January
	at all major vendors, and the print in February.</p>

      <p>The book covers everything from removable media, to FUSE,
	NFSv4 ACLs, iSCSI, CIFS, and more.</p>

      <p>If you act really quickly, you can get the electronic early
	access version at a 10% discount.  You'll get the final ebook when
	it comes out as well. (This offer evaporates when the final
	version comes out.)</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Updates to GDB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Baldwin</common>
	</name>
	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/bsdjhb/gdb/tree/FreeBSD-threads">New 1:1-only thread target for &os;</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KGDB option is now on by default in the devel/gdb
	port.</p>

      <p>The changes to support cross-debugging of crashdumps in
	libkvm were committed to HEAD in r291406.</p>

      <p>A new thread target for &os; that is suitable for merging
	upstream has been written and lightly tested.  However, it is not
	yet available as an option in the port.  This thread target uses
	<tt>ptrace(2)</tt> directly rather than <tt>libthread_db</tt> and
	as such supports threads on all ABIs (such as &os;/i386 binaries
	on &os;/amd64 and possibly Linux binaries, though that is not yet
	tested).  It also requires less-invasive changes in the MD targets
	in GDB compared to the <tt>libthread_db</tt>-based target.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add a port option for the new 1:1-only thread target.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Test the new 1:1-only thread target.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Figure out why the powerpc kgdb targets are not able to
	  unwind the stack past the initial frame.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for more platforms (arm, mips, aarch64) to
	  upstream <tt>gdb</tt> for both userland and <tt>kgdb</tt>.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for debugging powerpc vector registers.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>iMX.6 video output support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/292574">Commit Adding Basic Video Support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>iMX.6 is a family of SoC used in multiple hobbyist ARM
	boards such as the Hummingboard, RIoTboard, and Cubox.  Most of
	these products have HDMI output, but until recently, &os; did not
	benefit from it.  As of r292574, there is basic video output
	support so you can use the console on iMX6-based boards and
	probably run Xorg (not yet tested).</p>

      <p>Due to the lack of some kernel functionality (see open
	tasks), the only supported mode is 1024x768.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Proper pixel clock initialization (relies on a clock
	  framework).</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>More flexible video output path (support multiple IPUs
	  and DIs).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Touchscreen support for Raspberry Pi and Beaglebone Black</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://kernelnomicon.org/?p=534">Beaglebone Black with 4DCAPE-43T Demo</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201510DevSummit/GraphicsStack">Input Stack Plans</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SummerOfCode2014/evdev_Touchscreens">evdev Port</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are two working proof-of-concept drivers for the
	AM335x touchscreen and for the official Raspberry Pi's touchscreen
	LCD.</p>
	
      <p>Proper touchscreen support would consist of a userland event
	reading API, a kernel event reporting API, and kernel hardware
	drivers for specific devices.  There is an ongoing effort to port
	the Linux evdev API to &os; so applications that use libraries like
	libinput or tslib could be used without any major changes.  Since
	it is not yet complete, I created a naive evdev-like API for both
	kernel and tslib and was able to run a demo on a Beaglebone Black
	with 4DCAPE-43T.</p>

      <p>Once evdev makes it into the tree, both hardware drivers
	can be modified to include &quot;report events&quot;
	portions and committed.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Kernel Vnode Cache Tuning</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kirk</given>
	  <common>McKusick</common>
	</name>
	<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bruce</given>
	  <common>Evans</common>
	</name>
	<email>bde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Peter</given>
	  <common>Holm</common>
	</name>
	<email>pho@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mateusz</given>
	  <common>Guzik</common>
	</name>
	<email>mjg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/rS292895">MFC to stable/10</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This completed project includes changes to better manage
	the vnode freelist and to streamline the allocation and freeing of
	vnodes.</p>

      <p>Vnode cache recycling was reworked to meet free and unused
	vnodes targets.  Free vnodes are rarely completely free; rather,
	they are just ones that are cheap to recycle.  Usually they are
	for files which have been stat'd but not read; these usually have
	inode and namecache data attached to them.  The free vnode target
	is the preferred minimum size of a sub-cache consisting mostly of
	such files.  The system balances the size of this sub-cache with
	its complement to try to prevent either from thrashing while the
	other is relatively inactive.  The targets express a preference
	for the best balance.</p>

      <p>&quot;Above&quot; this target there are 2 further targets
	(watermarks) related to the recyling of free vnodes.  In the
	best-operating case, the cache is exactly full, the free list has
	size between vlowat and vhiwat above the free target, and
	recycling from the free list and normal use maintains this state.
	Sometimes the free list is below vlowat or even empty, but this
	state is even better for immediate use, provided the cache is not
	full.  Otherwise, vnlru_proc() runs to reclaim enough vnodes
	(usually non-free ones) to reach one of these states.  The
	watermarks are currently hard-coded as 4% and 9% of the available
	space.  These, and the default of 25% for wantfreevnodes, are too
	large if the memory size is large.  E.g., 9% of 75% of MAXVNODES
	is more than 566000 vnodes to reclaim whenever vnlru_proc()
	becomes active.</p>

      <p>The <tt>vfs.vlru_alloc_cache_src</tt> sysctl is removed.
	New code frees namecache sources as the last chance to satisfy the
	highest watermark, instead of selecting source vnodes randomly.
	This provides good enough behaviour to keep vn_fullpath() working
	in most situations.  Filesystem layouts with deep trees, where the
	removed knob was required, is thus handled automatically.</p>

      <p>As the kernel allocates and frees vnodes, it fully
	initializes them on every allocation and fully releases them on
	every free.  These are not trivial costs: it starts by zeroing a
	large structure, then initializes a mutex, a lock manager lock, an
	rw lock, four lists, and six pointers.  Looking at
	<tt>vfs.vnodes_created</tt>, these operations are being done
	millions of times an hour on a busy machine.</p>

      <p>As a performance optimization, this code update uses the
	uma_init and uma_fini routines to do these initializations and
	cleanups only as the vnodes enter and leave the vnode zone.  With
	this change, the initializations are done <tt>kern.maxvnodes</tt>
	times at system startup, and then only rarely again.  The frees
	are done only if the vnode zone shrinks, which never happens in
	practice.  For those curious about the avoided work, look at the
	vnode_init() and vnode_fini() functions in sys/kern/vfs_subr.c to
	see the code that has been removed from the main vnode
	allocation/free path.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Improvements to QLogic HBA driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The QLogic HBA driver <tt>isp(4)</tt> received a
	substantial set of changes.  Their primary goal was to make Fibre
	Channel target role work well with CTL, but many other things were
	also fixed/improved:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Added support for modern 16Gbps 26xx FC cards.</li>

	<li>The firmware in <tt>ispfw(4)</tt> were updated to the
	  latest versions.</li>

	<li>Target role support was fixed and tested for all FC cards from
	  ancient 1Gbps 22xx to modern 16Gbps 26xx.</li>

	<li>Port database handling was unified for target and initiator
	  roles, allowing HBA port to play both roles at the same time.</li>

	<li>The maximal number of ports was increased from 256 to
	  1024.</li>

	<li>Multi-ID (NPIV) functionality was fixed/implemented, allowing
	  24xx and above cards to provide up to 255 virtual FC ports per
	  physical port.</li>

	<li>Added support for 8-byte LUNs for 24xx and above cards.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The code is committed to &os; head and stable/10 branches.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      iXsystems, Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>NVRAM data reading is hackish and requires rework.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>FCoE support for 26xx cards was not tested yet.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Raspberry Pi: VideoCore userland application packaging</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mika&euml;l</given>
	  <common>Urankar</common>
	</name>
	<email>mikael.urankar@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Raspberry Pi SoC consists of two parts: ARM and GPU
	(VideoCore).  Many interesting features like OpenGL, video
	playback, and HDMI controls are implemented on the VideoCore side
	and can be accessed from the OS through libraries provided by
	Broadcom (userland repo).  These libraries were ported to &os;
	some time ago, so Mika&euml;l created the port
	<tt>misc/raspberrypi-userland</tt> for them.  He also created a
	port for <tt>omxplayer</tt> (a low-level video player that
	utilizes VideoCore APIs) and is working on a port for Kodi
	(ex-XBMC), a more user-firendly media player software with
	Raspberry Pi support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>LXQt on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Olivier</given>
	  <common>Duchateau</common>
	</name>
	<email>olivierd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/LXQt">&os; LXQt Project</url>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/lxqt/subversion/source">LXQt Devel Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><a href="http://lxqt.org/">LXQt</a> is the Qt port of and
	the upcoming version of LXDE, the Lightweight Desktop Environment.
	It is the product of the merge between the LXDE-Qt and the
	Razor-qt projects.</p>

      <p>The porting effort remains heavily a work in progress: it
	needs some components of Plasma 5 (the new major KDE's
	workspace).</p>

      <p>Currently, only the 0.10 branch is functional.  See our
	wiki page for a complete list of applications.</p>

      <p>We also sent updates for some components of LXDE (required
	for the LXQt desktop):</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>x11/menu-cache</tt> 1.0.1</li>

	<li><tt>x11/lxmenu-data</tt> 0.1.4</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Binary packages are available (only for test purposes)
	which are regularly tested with the KDE development
	repository.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Port libsysstat to BSD systems.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix some issues that need to be resolved, especially the
	  shutdown and reboot commands.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Node.js Modules</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Olivier</given>
	  <common>Duchateau</common>
	</name>
	<email>olivierd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/cozycloud/subversion/source">Node.js Modules Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Node.js is a platform built on Chrome's JavaScript runtime
	for easily building fast, scalable network applications.  It uses
	an event-driven, non-blocking I/O model that makes it lightweight
	and efficient &mdash; perfect for data-intensive real-time applications
	that run across distributed devices.</p>

      <p>The goal of this project is to make it easy to install the
	modules available in the <a href="http://npmjs.org/">npm package
	registry</a>.</p>

      <p>Currently, the repository contains slightly fewer than 300
	new ports, in particular:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Socket.IO (a library for realtime web applications)</li>

	<li>Jison (a JavaSript parser generator)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We have improved the USES framework:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Users can define which version of Node.js will be
	  installed through <tt>/etc/make.conf</tt>.</li>

	<li><tt>node-gyp</tt> is now well-integrated into the USES
	  framework, via the <strong>build</strong> argument.</li>

	<li>The <tt>pkg-plist</tt> is now automatically generated,
	  in order to make the <tt>portlint</tt> utility happy.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Each port is up-to-date.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Update the pre-draft documentation.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Bring in grunt.js (and modules), the JavaScript task runner.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Xfce on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Xfce Team</name>
	<email>xfce@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Xfce">&os; Xfce Project</url>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/xfce4/subversion/source">&os; Xfce Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xfce is a free software desktop environment for Unix and
	Unix-like platforms, such as &os;.  It aims to be fast and
	lightweight, while still being visually appealing and easy to
	use.</p>

      <p>During this quarter, the team has kept these applications
	up-to-date:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>audio/xfce4-pulseaudio-plugin</tt> 0.2.4</li>
	<li><tt>multimedia/xfce4-parole</tt> 0.8.1</li>
	<li><tt>x11/xfce4-whiskermenu-plugin</tt> 1.5.2</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We also follow the unstable releases (available in our
	experimental repository) of:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>x11/xfce4-dashboard</tt> 0.5.4</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Propose a patch to upstreamto fix Xfdashboard with our
	  version of OpenGL (it currently coredumps).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Supporting Variants in the Ports Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brendan</given>
	  <common>Molloy</common>
	</name>
	<email>brendan+freebsd@bbqsrc.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/poudriere/compare/master...feature/variants">Poudriere PoC with Variants</url>
      <url href="https://gist.github.com/bbqsrc/e7e3a54d84706485aa3a">Ports Makefile PoC with Examples</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I recently became involved with &os; (as in, the last 2-3
	weeks), and found myself quickly involved with Ports development.
	What quickly struck me was the difficulty in providing a Python
	package that was depended upon by multiple versions of Python.  As
	it turns out, poudriere can currently only generate one package
	per port, meaning that a Python version-neutral (compatible with
	2.x and 3.x) port cannot simultaneously be packaged for each
	variant at the same time.</p>

      <p>I discussed the issue with &a.koobs;, who suggested that I
	look into implementing a &quot;variants protocol&quot; within the
	Ports framework and the necessary changes to poudriere in order to
	allow a port to generate more than one package.</p>

      <p>Support for variants is strongly needed in Ports and
	provides significant benefits.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>It would allow Python and other languages to provide
	  packages for dependencies for multiple language versions from the
	  same port.</li>

	<li>It alleviates the need for so-called &quot;slave
	  ports&quot;, as a single port could now have multiple generated
	  packages from a single port.</li>

	<li>It would have a very small impact on the greater Ports
	  ecosystem: adding only two new variables, <tt>VARIANT</tt> and
	  <tt>VARIANTS</tt>.</li>

	<li>It would provide a more consistent approach between
	  different packaging teams for handling variations.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>For a simple example, <tt>editors/vim-lite</tt> could
	be folded into the <tt>editors/vim</tt> port, while still
	generating a <tt>vim</tt> and <tt>vim-lite</tt> package.
	For Python, <tt>VARIANTS</tt> can be derived from the already
	used <tt>USES</tt> flags and generate compatible packages.
	<tt>py27-foobar</tt> and <tt>py34-foobar</tt> could now be
	consistently generated by poudriere without issue.</p>

      <p>Fortunately, this is not a wishful thinking piece.  I dug
	in my heels and have implemented a proof-of-concept implementation
	of variants in the Ports framework, including the necessary
	modifications to poudriere in order to support it.  It was mildly
	upsetting to find that poudriere is mostly written in Bourne shell
	scripts, but press on I did nonetheless.</p>

      <p>I started with <a
	  href="https://github.com/bapt/ports-wip/compare/variants">the
	  prototype made by &a.bapt;</a> as a base, and built from there.
	The poudriere PoC aims to limit changes as much as possible to
	merely adding support for the new variants flags, while also at
	the request of &a.koobs; making the logging output more
	package-centric (as opposed to port-centric) as a result of these
	changes.</p>

      <p>This is a <strong>work in progress</strong>, and I would
	love to hear your feedback.  I've enjoyed my first few weeks
	working on &os;, and I hope to stay here for quite some time.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Any constructive feedback on the implementation would be
	  very welcome!</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Hopefully the code will be of sufficient quality to be considered
	  for formal review in the coming months.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>New tools to enhance the porting experience</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
      <name>
	<given>Brendan</given>
	<common>Molloy</common>
      </name>
      <email>brendan+freebsd@bbqsrc.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/pytoport">pytoport: Generate &os; Ports from Python modules on PyPI</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/bandar">bandar: Create Development Overlays for the Ports tree</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/skog-python">skog: Generate Visual Dependency Trees for &os; Ports</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/spdx-lookup-python">spdx-lookup: SPDX License List Query Tool</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>When I starting working on ports for &os; in the last
	couple of weeks, I found that my workflow was not as efficient as
	it could be, using just the available tools, so I made a few that
	could be useful to the development community at large.  All of
	these have been added to the Ports tree, or otherwise will soon be
	added, so you can play with them today!</p>

      <p><tt>pytoport</tt> is a command-line application that
	generates a skeleton port for a given PyPI package name.  It
	attempts to generate the correct dependencies, makes a good
	attempt at guessing the license using <tt>spdx-lookup</tt>, and
	generates a <tt>pkg-descr</tt>.  This made generating the fifteen
	or so ports I was working on a complete breeze.</p>

      <p>While doing this, however, I noticed that some ports were
	bringing in dependencies that I did not expect, and I needed some
	way to visualise this.  <tt>skog</tt> builds a dependency tree
	from the depends lists output by the Ports framework, and displays
	it on the command line (with extra shiny output if you are using
	UTF-8).  No more pesky example and documentation dependencies
	being dragged in when you <em>clearly</em> toggled that
	<tt>OPTION</tt> as far off as it would go.</p>

      <p>While doing all of this, I found it cumbersome to be
	copying ports back and forth between my small development tree
	living in git and the larger upstream SVN tree I was using in
	poudriere.  I built a tool called <tt>bandar</tt> that takes
	advantage of the FUSE version of unionfs to easily overlay my dev
	tree on the upstream tree, run linting, poudriere and generate
	archives with ease.</p>

      <p>I'm very impressed with how easy it was to build more
	tooling for &os;.  I hope some of these tools will be of some use
	to you, and as always, I'd love to hear your feedback!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Improve skog to support searching a tree for a certain
	  port.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Get the bandar port completed.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Continue to improve pytoport, adding trove support and better
	  depedency handling.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Patches welcome for all of the above!</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Out of Memory Handler Rewrite</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Out of Memory (OOM) code is intended to handle the
	situation where the system needs free memory to make progress,
	while no memory can be reused.  Most often, the situation is that
	to free memory, the system needs more free memory.  Consider a
	case where the system needs to page-out dirty pages, but needs to
	allocate structures to track the writes.  OOM &quot;solves&quot;
	the problem by killing some selection of user processes.  In other
	words, it trades away system deadlock by suffering a partial loss
	of user data.  The assumption is that it is better to kill a
	process and recover data in other processes, than lose
	everything.</p>

      <p>Free memory in the &os; Virtual Memory (VM) system appears
	from two sources.  One is the voluntary reclamation of pages used
	by a process, for example unmapping private anonymous regions, or
	the last unlink of an otherwise unreferenced file with cached
	pages.  Another source is the pagedaemon, which forcefully frees
	pages which carry data, of course, after the data is moved to some
	other storage, like swap or file blocks.  OOM is triggered when
	the pagedaemon definitely cannot free memory to satisfy the
	requests.</p>

      <p>The old criteria to trigger OOM action was a combination of
	low free swap space and a low count of free pages (the later is
	expressed precisely with the paging targets constants, but this is
	not relevant to the discussion).  That test is mostly incorrect,
	e.g., a low free page state might be caused by a greedy consumer
	allocating all pages freed by the page daemon in the current pass,
	but this does not preclude the page daemon from producing more
	pages.  Also, since page-outs are asynchronous, the previous page
	daemon pass might not immmediately produce any free pages, but
	they would appear some short time later.</p>

      <p>More seriously, low swap space does not necessarily indicate
	that we are in trouble: lots of pages may not require swap
	allocations to freed, e.g., clean pages or pages backed by files.
	The last notion is serious, since swap-less systems were
	considered as having full swap.</p>

      <p>Instead of trying to deduce the deadlock from looking at
	the current VM state, the new OOM handler tracks the history of
	page daemon passes.  Only if several consequtive passes failed to
	meet the paging target is an OOM kill considered neccessary.  The
	count of consequent failed passes was selected empirically, by
	testing on small (32M) and large (512G) machines.  Auto-tuning of
	the counter is possible, but requires some more architectural
	changes to the I/O subsystem.</p>

      <p>Another issue was identified with the algorithm which
	selects a victim process for OOM kill.  It compared the counts of
	pages mapping entries (PTEs) installed into the machine paging
	structures.  For different reasons, machine-dependent VM code
	(pmap) may remove the pte for a memory-resident page.  Under some
	circumstances, related to other measures to prevent low memory
	deadlock, very large processes which consume all system memory,
	could have few or no ptes, and the old OOM selector ignored the
	process which caused the deadlock, killing unrelated
	processes.</p>

      <p>A new function vm_pageout_oom_pagecount() was written which
	applies a reasonable heuristic to estimate the number of pages
	which would be freed by killing the given process.  This
	eliminates the effect of selecting small unrelated processes for
	OOM kill.</p>

      <p>The rewrite was committed to HEAD in r290917 and r290920.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Chelsio iSCSI Offload Driver (Initiator and Target)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Navdeep</given>
	  <common>Parhar</common>
	</name>
	<email>navdeep@chelsio.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/292740">Commit Adding Hardware Acceleration Support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A new driver, <tt>cxgbei</tt>, that enables hardware
	accelerated iSCSI with Chelsio's T5- and T4-based offload-capable
	cards, has been committed to HEAD.  Both Initiator and Target are
	supported.  The wire traffic is standard iSCSI (SCSI over TCP as
	per RFC 3720, etc.) so an Initiator/Target using this driver will
	interoperate with all other standards-compliant
	implementations.</p>

      <p>Hardware assistance provided by the T5 and T4 ASICs includes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Complete TCP processing.</li>

	<li>iSCSI PDU identification and extraction from the byte
	  oriented TCP stream.</li>

	<li>Header and/or data digest generation and
	  verification.</li>

	<li>Zero copy support for both transmit and receive.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Chelsio Communications
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>The <tt>cxgbei(4)</tt> man page is missing but will be
	  committed shortly.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The driver is in advanced stage QA and will see some
	  bugfixes and performance enhancements in the very near future.
	  MFC is possible as soon as the QA cycle completes.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>OpenBSM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Christian</given>
	  <common>Brueffer</common>
	</name>
	<email>brueffer@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>TrustedBSD audit mailing list</name>
	<email>trustedbsd-audit@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.openbsm.org">OpenBSM: Open Source Basic Security Module (BSM) Audit Implementation</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm">OpenBSM on GitHub</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/audit.html">&os; Audit Handbook Chapter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenBSM is a BSD-licensed implementation of Sun's Basic
	Security Module (BSM) API and file format.  It is the user-space
	side of the CAPP Audit implementations in &os; and Mac OS X.
	Additionally, the audit trail processing tools are expected to
	work on Linux.</p>

      <p>Progress has been slow but steady this quarter, culminating
	in OpenBSM 1.2 alpha 4, the first release in three years.  It
	features various bug fixes and documentation improvements; the
	complete list of changes is documented in the <a
	  href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm/blob/master/NEWS">NEWS</a>
	file on GitHub.  The release was imported into &os; HEAD and
	merged to &os; 10-STABLE.  As such it will be part of &os;
	10.3-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Test the new release on different versions of &os;, Mac
	  OS X and Linux.  In particular, testing on Mac OS X 10.9 (Mavericks)
	  and newer would be greatly appreciated.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix problems that have been reported via GitHub and the
	  &os; bug tracker.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Implement features mentioned in the
	  <a href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm/blob/master/TODO">TODO</a>
	  list on GitHub.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Marvell Armada38x</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcin</given>
	  <common>Wojtas</common>
	</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Stanek</common>
	</name>
	<email>mst@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bartosz</given>
	  <common>Szczepanek</common>
	</name>
	<email>bsz@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jan</given>
	  <common>Dabros</common>
	</name>
	<email>jsd@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>&os; has been ported to run on the Marvell Armada38x
	platform.  This SoC family boasts single/dual high-performance ARM
	Cortex-A9 CPUs.</p>

      <p>The multi-user SMP system is fully working and has been
	tested on Marvell DB-88F6288-GP and SolidRun ClearFog development
	boards.</p>

      <p>The root filesystem can be hosted on a USB 3.0/2.0 drive or
	via NFS using a PCIe network card.  Experimental support is
	available for on-chip Gigabit Ethernet (NETA).</p>

      <p>Additional features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>GIC+MPIC cascaded interrupts courtesy of INTRNG</li>

	<li>CESA dual-channel cryptographic engine</li>

	<li>USB 3.0 and 2.0</li>

	<li>PCIe 2.0</li>

	<li>I2C</li>

	<li>GPIO</li>

	<li>Watchdog</li>

	<li>RTC</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The port is under community review and will be integrated
	into HEAD soon.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Stormshield
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Semihalf
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Optimize performance of NETA and prepare for
	  submission.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Bringing GitLab into the Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Z&uuml;hlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>ports@toco-domains.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=202468">PR for the new Port</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/t-zuehlsdorff/gitlabhq/blob/master/doc/install/installation-FreeBSD.md">Installation Guide</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/gitlabhq/gitlabhq/">Upstream GitLab website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>GitLab is a web-based Git repository manager with many
	features that is used by more than 100.000 organizations including
	NASA and Alibaba.  It also is a very long-standing entry on the
	&quot;Wanted Ports&quot; list of the &os; Wiki.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter, there was steady progress in the
	project itself and the porting.  The current release of GitLab 8.3
	is now based on Rails 4.2, which obsoletes the need for around 50
	new ports.  Now there are only 5 dependencies left to be
	committed!</p>

      <p>While the new version of GitLab 8.3 eases the porting,
	there are big changes between the last working port of GitLab
	7.14.  Nonetheless, it could be expected to see the next working
	port in the first quarter of 2016</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      anyMOTION GRAPHICS GmbH, D&uuml;sseldorf, Germany
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Update the patches from GitLab 7.14 to 8.3.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Update the documentation.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Provide an updated patch.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>IPv6 Promotion Campaign</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Z&uuml;hlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>ports@toco-domains.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IPv6PortsTODO" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are more and more machines on the internet that
	<strong>only</strong> support IPv6.  I manage some of them, and
	was regularly hit by missing IPv6 support when building ports.</p>

      <p>I did some research into the impact of missing IPv6 support
	on the ports tree.  The results are that 10.308 of 25.522 ports
	are not fetchable when using IPv6.  This renders &mdash; through
	dependencies &mdash; a total of 17.715 ports unbuildable from
	IPv6-only systems.  All you can do than is wait and hope that
	distcache.FreeBSD.org caches the distfile.  But this will take
	some time, which may not be a luxury available when a piece of
	software in use is hit by a security issue.</p>

      <p>Based on the research, a promotion campaign for IPv6 was
	started.  Some volunteers will contact the relevant system
	administrators and try to convince them to support IPv6.  This
	will start in January 2016 and will hopefully create some progress
	soon.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>KDE on &os; team</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/">KDE on &os; website</url>
      <url href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">Experimental KDE ports staging area</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/KDE">KDE on &os; Wiki</url>
      <url href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-FreeBSD">KDE/&os; Mailing List</url>
      <url href="http://src.mouf.net/area51/log/branches/plasma5">Development Repository for Integrating KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE on &os; team focuses on packaging and making sure
	that the experience of KDE and Qt on &os; is as good as
	possible.</p>

      <p>The team kept busy during the last quarter of 2015.  Quite
	a few big updates were committed to the ports tree, and a few more
	are being worked on in our experimental repository.</p>

      <p>As in previous quarters, we would like to thank several
	people who have contributed with machines, patches and general
	help.  Tobias Berner, &a.madpilot; (madpilot@), Adriaan de Groot, Ralf
	Nolden, &a.swills; (swills@), and &a.jpaetzel; (jpaetzel@) have been
	essential to our work.</p>

      <p>The following big updates were landed in the ports tree
	this quarter.  In many cases, we have also contributed patches to
	the upstream projects.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>CMake 3.4.0 and 3.4.1</li>

	<li>Calligra 2.9.1, the latest release of the integrated
	  work applications suite.  Calligra had last been updated in the
	  ports tree in the end of 2013!</li>

	<li>PyQt4 4.11.4, QScintilla2 2.9.1 and SIP 4.17.</li>

	<li>PyQt5 5.5.1.  Thanks to the work spearheaded by Guido
	  Falsi and Tobias Berner in the previous quarter, the PyQt5 ports
	  have finally been committed to the ports tree.  Not only was this
	  long-awaited on its own, but it also allows other ports to be
	  updated to their latest versions.</li>

	<li>QtCreator 3.5.1 and 3.6.0.</li>

	<li>A couple of Qt5 packaging bugs were fixed: it should now
	  be more straightforward to use the Qt5 ports to build software
	  outside the ports tree, and it is now possible to build ports that
	  require a C++11 compiler and Qt5 on &os; 9.x.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Work on updating the Qt5 ports to their latest version, as
	well as porting KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5 to &os;, is well
	underway in our experimental area51 repository.  At the moment, it
	contains Qt5 5.5.1, KDE Frameworks 5.17.0, Plasma 5.5.1 and KDE
	Applications 15.12.0.</p>

      <p>Users interested in testing those ports are encouraged to
	follow the instructions in
	<a href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">our website</a> and
	report their results to our mailing list.  Qt5 5.5.1 is in our
	&quot;qt-5.5&quot; branch, and Plasma 5 and the rest is in
	the &quot;plasma5&quot; branch (which also contains Qt 5.5.1).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Commit the Qt5 5.5.1 update.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Land the KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5 ports to the
	  tree.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Investigate what needs to be done to make QtWebEngine,
	  the Chromium-based replacement for QtWebKit, work on &os;.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Frederic</given>
	  <common>Culot</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Frederic</given>
	  <common>Culot</common>
	</name>
	<email>culot@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">Ports Collection Landing Page</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">Contributor's Guide</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">Ports Monitoring Service</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team Website</url>
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr">Portmgr on Facebook</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As of the end of Q4 the ports tree holds a bit more
	than 25,000 ports, and the PR count is around 2,000.
	The activity on the ports tree remains steady, with
	about 7,000 commits performed by almost 120 active
	committers.</p>

      <p>On the problem reports front, figures show an
	encouraging trend, with a significant increase in the
	number of PRs fixed during Q4.  Indeed, almost 1,800
	reports were fixed, which makes an increase of about
	20% compared to Q3.</p>

      <p>In Q4 8 commit bits were taken in for safekeeping,
	following an inactivity period of more than 18 months
	(lioux, lippe, simon, jhay, max, sumikawa, alexey, sperber).
	Three new developers were granted a ports commit bit (Kenji
	Takefu, Carlos Puga Medina, and Ian Lepore), and one
	returning committer (miwi) had his commit bit reinstated.</p>

      <p>Also related to the management of ports commit bits,
	nox's grants were revoked, since the &os; developers
	learnt that Juergen Lock passed away.</p>

      <p>On the management side, no changes were made to the
	portmgr team during Q4.</p>

      <p>On QA side 33 exp-runs were performed to validate sensitive
	updates or cleanups.  Amongst those noticeable changes are
	the update to GCC 4.9, CMake to 3.4.1, PostgreSQL to 9.4, and
	ruby-gems to 2.5.0.  Some infrastructure changes included the
	usage of a WRKSRC different from WRKDIR when NO_WRKSUBDIR
	is set, the removal of bsd.cpu.mk from sys.mk, and the
	move of QT_NONSTANDARD to bsd.qt.mk.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>We would like to remind everyone that the ports tree is
	  built and run by volunteers, and any help is greatly
	  appreciated.  While Q4 saw a significant increase in the
	  number of problem reports fixed, we encourage all ports
	  committers to have a look at the issues reported by our
	  users and try to fix as many as possible.  Many thanks to
	  all who made a contribution during Q4, and keep up the
	  good work in 2016!</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Issue Tracking (Bugzilla)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Bugmeisters</name>
	<email>bugmeister@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mahdi</given>
	  <common>Mokhtari</common>
	</name>
	<email>mokhi64@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla Home Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This quarter, the bugmeister team has gained a new member,
	Mahdi Mokhtari (mokhi64@gmail.com).  Mahdi has been contributing
	to the &os; Project for just over one month.  After getting
	started by creating ports for Chef-Server and MySQL 5.7 (With
	Bernard Spil's help), an introduction to &a.koobs; led to
	guidance on appropriate projects, such as Bugzilla development,
	helping Bugmeister, the Bugzilla Triage team, Developers, and the
	Community by making issue tracking better.  This is how things are
	going so far:</p>

      <p>Issue Tracking can be either &quot;Defect Tracking for
	Systems&quot; or &quot;Bug-Tracking for Systems&quot;.  System
	Defect Tracking is to allow individual or groups of developers to
	keep track of outstanding issues in their product effectively.  We
	use Bugzilla to manage issues for the &os; project.  </p>

      <p>We are pleased to announce some developments on our issue
	management systems:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>We have made improvements to the AutoAssigner module
	  (not yet deployed) that was previousely developed by Marcus to
	  assign ports' bugs to their maintainers by default, such as:

	  <ul>
	    <li>Improvements and bugfixes to port detection in
	      the Summary: field of issues, for automatic assignment
	      to their maintainers in a better way.</li>

	    <li>Refactoring code to make future development easier
	      and faster in a more modular way.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>We have developed a new module (FBSDAttachment), which
	  automates setting maintainer-approval flag values on attachments
	  under most conditions.  This will improve time to resolution,
	  consistency of triage, and save manual effort on behalf of
	  triagers and maintainers.</li>

	<li>We reported and upstreamed a number of bugs in Bugzilla, working
	  with the upstream Bugzilla developers.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Major improvements to templates for usability and
	  simplicity.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Further improvements to automation (for example,
	  additional processing of commit logs).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Root Remount</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>One of the long-missing features of &os; was the ability to
	boot up with a temporary rootfs, configure the kernel to be able
	to access the real rootfs, and then replace the temporary root
	with the real one.  In Linux, this functionality is known as
	pivot_root.  The reroot projects provides similar functionality in
	a different, slightly more user-friendly way: rerooting.  Simply
	put, from the user point of view it looks like the system performs
	a partial shutdown, killing all processes and unmounting the
	rootfs, and then partial bringup, mounting the new rootfs, running
	init, and running the startup scripts as usual.</p>

      <p>The project is finished.  All the relevant code has been committed
	to &os; 11-CURRENT, and is expected to ship with &os; 11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>RCTL Disk IO Limits</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>An important missing piece of the RCTL resource limits
	mechanism was the ability to limit disk throughput.  This project
	aims to fill that hole by making it possible to add RCTL rules for
	read bytes per second (BPS), write BPS, read I/O operations per
	second (IOPS), and write IOPS.  It also adds a new throttling
	mechanism, to delay process execution when a limit gets hit.</p>

      <p>The project is at the late implementation stage.  The major
	piece of work left, apart from testing, is to integrate it with
	ZFS.  The project is expected to ship with &os; 11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os;&nbsp;Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/releases/10.3R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;10.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os; Development Snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is responsible for setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project releases
	of &os;, announcing code freezes and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>During the last quarter of 2015, the Release Engineering team
	added support for three additional &os;/arm systems:
	<tt>BANANAPI</tt>, <tt>CUBIEBOARD</tt>, and
	<tt>CUBIEBOARD2</tt>.</p>

      <p>In addition to regular development snapshot builds for
	&os;&nbsp;11.0-CURRENT and &os;&nbsp;10.2-STABLE, several
	changes and enhancements were made to the release build code.
	Of note, the release build code no longer produces MD5
	checksums, in favor of SHA512.</p>

      <p>Toward the end of the year, much of the primary focus was
	centered around the upcoming &os;&nbsp;10.3 release cycle,
	which will begin during January 2016.</p>

      <p>As always, help testing development snapshot builds is
	crucial to producing quality releases, and we encourage
	testing development snapshots whenever possible.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>MMC Stack Under CAM Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ilya</given>
	  <common>Bakulin</common>
	</name>
	<email>ilya@bakulin.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bakulin.de/FreeBSD/mmccam.html">Project Information</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/kibab/FreeBSD/tree/mmccam">Source Code</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4761">Patch for Review</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of this project is to reimplement the exisitng
	MMC/SD stack using the CAM framework.  This will permit utilizing
	the well-tested CAM locking model and debug features.
	Additionally, it will be possible to process interrupts generated
	by the inserted card, which is a prerequisite for implementing the
	SDIO interface.</p>

      <p>The first version of the code was uploaded to
	Phabricator for review.  The new stack is able to attach to the SD
	card and bring it to an operational state, so it is possible to
	read and write to/from the card.</p>

      <p>The only supported SD controller driver is
	<tt>ti_sdhci</tt>, which is used on the BeagleBone Black.
	Modifying other SDHCI-compliant drivers should not be
	difficult.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Rework bus/target/LUN enumeration and the locking model
	  &mdash; I don't really understand the CAM locking and am likely to
	  do it incorrectly.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Modify the SDHCI driver on at least one x86 platform
	  &mdash; this will make development and collaboration easier.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Begin implementing SDIO-specific bits.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>The Graphics stack on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Graphics team</name>
	<email>freebsd-x11@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Graphics">Graphics Stack Roadmap and Supported Hardware Matrix</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/freebsd-ports-graphics">Ports Development Tree on GitHub</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Several important ports were updated: Mesa to 11.0.8, the
	X.Org server to 1.17.4, libdrm to 2.4.65, as well as many
	applications and libraries.  The latest release of the X.Org
	server, 1.18, is being tested in our Ports development tree.</p>

      <p>On the kernel side, the i915 update is almost ready to
	land.  There are a couple known regressions for currently
	supported GPUs that we want to fix before committing.</p>

      <p>We started a discussion on the FreeBSD-x11@ mailing list to
	organize future contributions to the kernel drivers.  We have
	already received some valuable comments.  We are confident that
	future updates will happen at a faster pace, thanks to several
	motivated people!</p>

      <p>FOSDEM is held in Brussels on the 30th and 31st of January.
	We will attend this conference.  It will be a perfect time to see
	people again from &os; and from the XDC.  On Sunday, we will give
	a talk about how to contribute to the Graphics Stack.</p>

      <p>Our blog is currently down because the service was
	discontinued.  We hope to get a dump of our data to put it back
	online elsewhere.  Unfortunately, there is no ETA for this
	item.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>See the &quot;Graphics&quot; wiki page for up-to-date
	  information.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Encrypted Kernel Crash Dumps</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konrad</given>
	  <common>Witaszczyk</common>
	</name>
	<email>def@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-security/2015-December/008780.html">Technical Details</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4712">Patch Review</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Kernel crash dumps contain information about currently
	running processes.  This can include sensitive data, for example
	passwords kept in memory by a browser when a kernel panic
	occurred.  An entity that can read data from a dump device or a
	crash directory can also extract this information from a core
	dump.  In order to prevent this situation, the core dump should be
	encrypted before it is stored on the dump device.</p>

      <p>This project allows a kernel to encrypt a core dump during
	a panic.  A user can configure the kernel for encrypted dumps and
	save the core dump after reboot using the existing tools,
	<tt>dumpon(8)</tt> and <tt>savecore(8)</tt>.  A new tool
	<tt>decryptcore(8)</tt> was added to decrypt the core files.</p>

      <p>A patch has been uploaded to Phabricator for review.  The
	project is currently being updated to address the review comments,
	and should be committed as soon as it is accepted.  For more
	technical details, please visit the FreeBSD-security mailing list
	archive or see the Phabricator review.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Issue Triage Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Bugmeister</name>
	<email>bugmeister@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Vladimir</given>
	  <common>Krstulja</common>
	</name>
	<email>vlad-fbsd@acheronmedia.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rodrigo N.</given>
	  <common>Hernandez</common>
	</name>
	<email>rodrigo.FreeBSD@minasambiente.com.br</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://pad.riseup.net/p/FreeBSD-triage-brainstorming">Issue Triage Team's Brainstorming Pad</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>By the end of the Q4 2015 period, &a.koobs; (koobs@)
	started an initiative to form an experimental Bugzilla Triage
	Team.  The main goals of the team are to increase community
	involvement (addition/training of new triagers) and enhance
	current procedures and tools, among others.  This experiment was
	started with the participation of Vladimir (blackflow on
	irc/freenode) and Rodrigo (DanDare on irc/freenode), who
	approached koobs@ with a desire to contribute and get more
	involved with the &os; Project.  This experimental pilot project
	has the task of setting up procedures for enhanced Issue (Problem
	Report) management that include better
	classification/prioritization, eventually leading to faster
	resolution of the issues.</p>

      <p>We are now happy to report on the progress of this
	experimental team:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>We have set up the #FreeBSD-bugs IRC channel on
	  Freenode and we are successfully using it to exchange information
	  about triage processes, ask for help, propose changes and discuss
	  related topics.</li>

	<li>We have identified the primary role of an Issue Triage
	  Team to be that of classification of problem reports of all kinds
	  (currently limited mostly to ports and obvious src issues) and
	  facilitation of issue assignment, which is making sure that the
	  reported issues are explained well, contain all the appropriate
	  information (or as much of it as possible), and are brought to
	  attention of the people who can act upon them.</li>

	<li>Vladimir and Rodrigo are successfully training in bug
	  triage as well as porting processes (Vladimir is also taking
	  maintainership of some ports).</li>

	<li>This experiment is benefiting from the introduction of
	  newcomers to issue tracking.  It naturally resulted in a entire
	  review of the tracking proccess from its very elementary aspects.
	  This &quot;fresh eyes&quot; participation spotted minor details
	  along the proccess, giving the opportunity to scrutinize actual
	  procedures on a number of smaller points, followed by proposals on
	  how to improve the overall Issue Tracking and Management.  The new
	  ideas include both organizational and technical ideas and
	  solutions, such as new or modified keywords or flags for better
	  classification, the triage workflow, and Bugzilla technical
	  improvements among others.</li>

	<li>An important goal is producing documentation not only
	  aimed at people directly engaged on issue triage tasks, but also
	  documentation aimed at general users, about best practices for
	  using Bugzilla and the issue management workflow.  Another
	  relevant point is that feedback from triage team can be used to
	  improve Bugzilla in terms of adjusting existing features to best
	  fit &os;'s needs, and development of new features (please see
	  Mahdi &quot;Magic&quot; Mokhtari's report on &quot;Bugzilla
	  improvements&quot;).</li>

	<li>We are still collating ideas in preparation of setting
	  up a Wiki namespace for the overall topic of issue management,
	  containing information for all the parties involved in issue
	  tracking: from users (reporters) to maintainers and committers.
	  The unorganized brainstorming document is linked in this
	  report.</li> </ul>

      <p>Since the Issue Triage Team is very young, we expect more
	information be available and more actions be reported upon in the
	next Status report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Set up the Wiki namespace and organize the brainstorm
	  document into a meaningful set of documents.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Recruit more suitable triagers into the team.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>relaunchd</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Heily</common>
	</name>
	<email>mark@heily.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/mheily/relaunchd">Development tree on GitHub</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>relaunchd</tt> project provides a service
	management daemon that is similar to the original
	<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Launchd">launchd</a>
	introduced in Apple OS X.</p>

      <p>It is not limited to the original features of
	<tt>launchd</tt>, however: interesting work is being done to add
	support for launching programs in jails, passing socket
	descriptors from the host to a jail, and launching programs within
	a preconfigured <tt>capsicum(4)</tt> sandbox.  Additionally,
	<tt>relaunchd</tt> uses UCL for its configuration files, so jobs
	can be defined in JSON or other formats supported by UCL.</p>

      <p>While there is still work to be done, most of the important
	features of the original <tt>launchd</tt> have been implemented,
	and <tt>relaunchd</tt> has been made available in the &os; Ports
	Collection.  It should still be considered experimental and not
	ready for production use, but everyone is welcome to try it,
	report issues, and contribute code or ideas for improvement.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add support for restarting jobs if they crash.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Implement the <tt>cron(8)</tt> emulation feature.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for monitoring files and directories for
	  changes, and launching jobs when changes are detected.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Finish things that are incomplete, such as support for
	  jails and passing open socket descriptors to child processes.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve the documentation and providing more examples of
	  how to use it.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; Integration Services (BIS) </title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dexuan</given>
	  <common>Cui</common>
	</name>
	<email>decui@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hongjiang</given>
	  <common>Zhang</common>
	</name>
	<email>honzhan@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HyperV">&os; Virtual Machines on Microsoft Hyper-V</url>
      <url href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn531030.aspx">Linux and &os; Virtual Machines on Hyper-V</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>When &os; virtual machines (VMs) run on Hyper-V,  in order
	to get the best network and storage performance and make full use
	of all the benefits that Hyper-V provides, it is recommended to
	use Hyper-V synthetic devices.  The collection of drivers that are
	required to run Hyper-V synthetic devices in &os; are known as
	&os; Integration Services (BIS).  Some of the BIS drivers (like
	network and storage drivers) have existed in &os; 9.x and 10.x for
	years, but there are still some performance and stability issues
	and bugs.  Additionally, compared with Windows and Linux VMs, the
	current BIS lacks some important features, such as the virtual
	Receive Side Scaling (vRSS) support in the Hyper-V network driver
	and the support for UEFI VM (boot from UEFI), among others.</p>

      <p>We are now working more on the issues and performance
	tuning to make &os; VM run better on Hyper-V and the Hyper-V based
	cloud platform Azure.</p>

      <p>Our work during 2015Q4 is documented below:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Optimizing the VMBus driver and Hyper-V network driver
	  for performance:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Sent out patches to enable <tt>INTR_MPSAFE</tt> for
	      the interrupt handling thread, speed up
	      relid-to-channel lookup in the thread by map table,
	      and optimize the VMBus ringbuffer writable
	      notification to the host.</li>

	    <li>Developing a patch to enable the virtual Receive
	      Side Scaling (vRSS) for Hyper-V network device driver.
	      This will greatly improve the network performance for
	      SMP virtual machine (VM).</li>

	    <li>Sent out a patch to enable the Hyper-V timer, which
	      will improve the accuracy of timekeeping when &os; VMs
	      run on Hyper-V.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>Fixing bugs and cleaning up the code:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Fixed a bug in checksum offloading (PR 203630
	      &mdash; [Hyper-V] [nat] [tcp] 10.2 NAT bug in TCP stack
	      or hyperv netsvc driver) in the Hyper-V network driver,
	      making &os; VM based NAT gateways work more reliably.</li>

	    <li>Fixed a serialization issue in the initialization of
	      VMBus devices, fixing PR 205156 ([Hyper-V] NICs' (hn0,
	      hn1) MAC addresses can appear in an uncertain way across
	      reboot).</li>

	    <li>Fixed a KVP (Key-Value Pair) issue (retrieving a
	      key's value can hang for an uncertain period of
	      time).</li>

	    <li>Added ioctl support for SIOCGIFMEDIA for the Hyper-V
	      network driver, fixing PR 187006 ([Hyper-V] dynamic
	      address (DHCP) obtaining doesn't work on HYPER-V OS
	      2012 R2).</li>

	    <li>Sent out patches to add an interrupt counter for
	      Hyper-V VMBus interrupts (so the user can easily get
	      the statistical information about VMBus interrupts),
	      and fix the KVP daemon's poll timeout (so the daemon
	      will avoid unnecessary polling every 100
	      milliseconds.</li>

	    <li>Identified a TSC calibration issue: the i8254 PIT
	      timer emulation of Hyper-V is not fully reliable, so
	      the Hyper-V time counter should be used to calibrate
	      the TSC.  A patch was drafted.  With the patch, it looks
	      the warning kernel message (e.g., &quot;calcru: runtime
	      went backwards from 46204978 usec to 23362331 usec for
	      pid 0 (kernel)&quot;) will go away, and the time-based
	      tracing of Dtrace will be more accurate.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>We plan to add support for UEFI VMs (a.k.a., Hyper-V
	  Generation-2 VMs).  Currently some issues and to-do items were
	  identified: e.g., we cannot use the i8254 PIT to calibrate the
	  TSC because the i8254 PIT does not exist in a UEFI VM, and we
	  need to add support for the Hyper-V synthetic
	  keyboard/mouse/framebuffer device.</li>

	<li>We are working on a disk detection issue: when a &os; VM
	  runs on a Windows Server 2016 Technical Preview host, the VM
	  will detect 16 disks whereas only 1 disk is configured for the
	  VM.  Due to this issue, VMs running on these hosts can fail to
	  boot.  A workaround patch was made and we are trying to make a
	  formal fix.</li>

	<li>We are tidying up some internal BIS test cases and plan
	  to publish them on github.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Microsoft
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Mellanox iSCSI Extensions For RDMA (iSER) Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Max</given>
	  <common>Gurtovoy</common>
	</name>
	<email>maxg@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sagi</given>
	  <common>Grimberg</common>
	</name>
	<email>sagig@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>

    </contact>

    <links>
    <url href="https://github.com/sagigrimberg/iser-FreeBSD">GitHub repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Building on the new in-kernel iSCSI initiator stack
	released in &os; 10.0 and the recently added iSCSI offload
	interface, Mellanox Technologies has developed iSCSI extensions for
	RDMA (iSER) initiator support to enable efficient data movement
	using the hardware offload capabilities of Mellanox's 10, 40, 56,
	and 100 Gigabit Infiniband (IB)/Ethernet adapters.</p>

      <p>Remote Direct Memory Access (RDMA) has been shown to have a
	great value for storage applications.  RDMA infrastructure
	provides benefits such as zero-copy, CPU offload, reliable
	transport, fabric consolidation, and many more.  The iSER protocol
	eliminates some of the bottlenecks in the traditional iSCSI/TCP
	stack, provides low latency and high throughput, and is well
	suited for latency aware workloads.</p>

      <p>This work includes a new ICL module that implements the
	iSER initiator.  The iSCSI stack is slightly modified to support
	some extra features such as asynchronous IO completions, unmapped
	data buffers, and data-transfer offloads.  The user will be able
	to choose iSER as the iSCSI transport with iscsictl.</p>

      <p>The project is in the process of being merged to &os;
	11-CURRENT and is expected to ship with &os; 11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Improvements for ARMv6/v7 support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dominik</given>
	  <common>Ermel</common>
	</name>
	<email>der@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wojciech</given>
	  <common>Macek</common>
	</name>
	<email>wma@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zbigniew</given>
	  <common>Bodek</common>
	</name>
	<email>zbb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Numerous improvements for the ARMv6/v7 kernel and tools
	have been developed by the Semihalf team.  Those include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fixes for KGDB support.</li>

	<li>Support for branch instructions in <tt>ptrace</tt> single
	  stepping.</li>

	<li>Fixes for kernel minidumps.</li>

	<li>Improvements for LIBUSBBOOT.</li>

	<li>Support for Exynos EHCI in the loader.</li>

	<li>A fix for instruction single stepping in DDB.</li>

	<li>Support for hardware watchpoints, including watchpoints
	  on SMP systems.</li>

	<li>Single stepping using the ARM Debug Architecture.</li>

	<li>Support for gzip-compressed kernel modules in
	  <tt>kldload</tt>.</li>

	<li>Backport of the new pmap VM code to &os; 10-STABLE (not
	  yet sent to upstream).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Most of the introduced changes have been committed to HEAD
	and more are on the way.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Juniper Networks Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Semihalf
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Finish upstreaming the hardware watchpoints support.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Two major concerns have occupied much of core's attention
	during the last quarter: the reorganisation of the Security
	Team and the question of whether to import GPLv3 licensed code
	into the source repository.</p>

      <p>The Security Team reorganisation, first proposed to Core
	during a meeting at BSDCan this year by Gleb Smirnoff &mdash; core
	member and newly-appointed deputy Security Officer (SO) &mdash; has now
	been accomplished.  In order to improve the project's
	responsiveness to security alerts, to maintain security on
	privileged information received in confidence before general
	publication and, not least, to reduce the work load on the
	security officer, the role of the SO team has been redefined as
	the controller of the distribution of security sensitive
	information within the project; they are responsible for
	interfacing with external bodies and individuals reporting
	security problems, and connecting them with appropriate
	individuals within the project with the technical expertise to
	address the identified concerns.  The SO team was cut down to just
	the Security Officer and their deputy, assisted by a secretary, and
	with input and help in drafting security advisories from former
	and any potential future Security Officers plus liasons with Core,
	Cluster Administration and Release Engineering.</p>

      <p>Core would particularly like to thank the former members of
	the Security Team group for their past contributions, now that
	the Security Team role has been merged into the Security
	Officer's responsibilities.</p>

      <p>The other large question concerning Core is how to provide a
	modern toolchain for all supported achitectures.  Tier 1
	architectures are required to ship with a toolchain
	unencumbered by onerous license terms.  This is currently
	provided for i386 and arm64 by the LLVM suite, including the
	Clang compiler, LLD and LLDB.  However LLVM support for other
	(Tier 2 or below) architectures is not yet of sufficient quality
	to be viable, and the older but pre-existing GPLv2 toolchain
	cannot support some of the interesting new architectures such
	as arm64 and RISC V.  Pragmatically, in order for the project
	to support these, until LLVM support arrives we must turn to the
	GNU project's GPLv3 licenced toolchain.</p>

      <p>The argument here is whether to import GPLv3 licensed code
	into the &os; src repository with all of the obligations on
	patent terms and source code redistribution that would entail,
	not only for the &os; project itself but for numerous
	downstream consumers of &os; code.  Not having a toolchain
	readily available is a big impediment to working on a new
	architecture.</p>

      <p>One potential solution is to create a range of &quot;GPLv3
	toolchain&quot; base-system packages out of a completely separate
	source code repository, for instance within the &os; area on
	Github.  These would be distributed equivalently to the other
	base system binary packages when that mechanism is
	introduced.</p>

      <p>Core recognises that this is a decision with wide-ranging
	consequences and will be producing a position paper for
	circulation amongst all interested parties in order to judge
	community opinion on the matter.  Core welcomes feedback from
	all interested parties on the subject.</p>

      <p>Beyond these two big questions, Core has handled a number of
	lesser items:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Core approved the formation of a wiki-admin team to take
	  over managing the Wiki, to curate the Wiki content and work
	  on navigation and organization of existing technical content
	  and to evaluate new Wiki software with the aim of opening up
	  the Wiki to contributions from the public.</li>

	<li>An external review board has been assembled to look at
	  the Code of Conduct, including a mixture of project members
	  and experts from external groups.  The review process is
	  getting under way and Core is awaiting their report.</li>

	<li>The standard documentation license was found to be
	  unfit for its purpose, and the doceng group had temporarily
	  reverted to the previous license while a new replacement was
	  drafted.  This new license is now the default for new
	  documentation submissions.  However, one factor emerging from
	  this review was the difficulty of maintaining correct
	  authorial attributions for sections of documentation, some of
	  which may only be a few words long.  Unlike source code,
	  blocks of documentation are frequently moved around within
	  individual files, or even between files.  Consequently Core
	  would like to introduce a &quot;Voluntary Contribution
	  Agreement&quot; along the lines of the one operated
	  by the Apache Foundation.  With this, copyrights are signed
	  over to the &os; Foundation, with individual contributions
	  being recognised by recording names in a general
	  &quot;Authors&quot; file.  This will be another alternative
	  alongside the existing copyright mechanisms used in the
	  project.  Core is interested to hear any opinions on the
	  subject.</li>

	<li>Core approved the formation of a new
	  &quot;dev-announce&quot; mailing list, which all &os; committers
	  should be members of.  This will be a low-traffic moderated list
	  to contain important announcements, heads-ups, warnings of code
	  freezes, changes in policy and notifications of events that
	  affect the project as a whole.</li>

	<li>Around eight years ago, an attempt was made to import the
	  OpenBSD sensors framework.  This was rejected at the time as
	  potentially blocking the development of a better designed
	  framework.  However, no such development has occurred in the
	  intervening time whilst the sensors framework has been in
	  use successfully by both OpenBSD and FreeNAS.  Despite some
	  concerns about the efficiency of the framework and potential
	  impacts on power consumption and hence battery lifetime, core
	  is minded to approve the import, but wants to consult with
	  interested developers first.</li>

	<li>Core is exploring the legal ramifications for the project
	  of the &quot;Right to Be Forgotten&quot; established by
	  the European Court of Justice.</li>

	<li>Core is also seeking an alternative means for holding
	  their regular monthly conference calls.  The current,
	  paid-for, service has less than satisfactory sound quality
	  and reliability, and Core would like to switch to a free
	  video conferencing solution.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>This quarter also saw a particularly large influx of new
	commit bit requests, with on occasion, four votes running
	simultaneously.  Please welcome Kurt Lidl, Svatopluk Kraus,
	Michal Meloun, Jonathan Looney (Juniper), Daisuke Aoyama, Phil
	Shafer (Juniper), Ravi Pokala (Panasas), Anish Gupta and Mark
	Bloch (Mellanox) to the ranks of src committers.  In addition,
	core was delighted to restore commit privileges for Eric
	Melville after a hiatus of many years.</p>

      <p>No commit bits were taken in during the quarter.  A
	non-committer account was approved for Kevin Bowling of
	LimeLight Networks.  Kevin will be doing systems administration
	work with clusteradm with particular interest in the parts of
	the cluster that are now hosted in LLNW's facilities.  Deb
	Goodkin of the &os; Foundation was added to the developers
	mailing list: she was one of the few members of the Foundation
	Board not already on the list, and having awareness of what is
	going on in the developer community will help her to support
	the project more effectively.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Routing Stack Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Chernikov</common>
	</name>
	<email>melifaro@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/ProjectsRoutingProposal">Initial Proposal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>projects/routing</tt> Subversion branch is a
	FreeBSD routing system rework aimed at providing performance,
	scalability and the ability to add advanced features to the
	routing stack.</p>

      <p>Currently, the packet output path suffers from excessive
	locking, acquiring and releasing 4 distinct contested locks is
	required in order to convert a packet to a frame suitable to put
	on the wire.  The first project goal is to reduce the number of
	locks needed to just two <tt>rmlock(9)</tt>s for the output path,
	which permits close-to-linear scaling.</p>

      <p>Since September, one of the locks (used to protect
	link-level entries) is completely eliminated from the packet data
	path.  A new routing API was introduced, featuring better
	scalability and hiding routing internals.  Most of the consumers
	of the old routing API were converted to use the new API.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Base System Build Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>Drewery</common>
	</name>
	<email>bdrewery@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-arch/2015-December/017571.html">&os;-Arch Post Describing Plans</url>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2014/schedule/events/460.en.html">BSDCan 2014 META_MODE Presentation</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=290433">WITH_FAST_DEPEND Details</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=290526">WITH_CCACHE_BUILD Details</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&a.bdrewery; (bdrewery@) has been working to improve the
	build framework as well as buildworld build times.  The build
	system has largely been untouched by large-scale changes for many
	years.  Most of the effort has been on improving the recent
	<tt>META_MODE</tt> merge that was presented at BSDCan 2014.  This
	is a new build system that is not currently enabled by default but
	brings many benefits.  Beyond that, some highlights of the work
	changing buildworld are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>WITH_FAST_DEPEND</tt>, which avoids calling
	  &quot;mkdep&quot; during the <tt>make depend</tt> phase and
	  instead generates dependency files during compilation.  The old
	  scheme was pre-processing all source files twice.  The new version
	  saves 16-35% in build times.</li>

	<li><tt>WITH_CCACHE_BUILD</tt> adds built-in ccache support,
	  avoiding many of the historical pitfalls of changing <tt>CC</tt>
	  in <tt>make.conf</tt> to use ccache.</li>

	<li>Many improvements for parallelization of the build.</li>

	<li><tt>LIBADD</tt> improvements to ensure proper usage of
	  this tool to replace duplicate <tt>LDADD</tt> and <tt>DPADD</tt>
	  statements.  Further work is underway to reduce overlinking.</li>

	<li>A lot of cleanup of improper framework usage.</li>

	<li>Ensuring that installing files from the build tree fails
	  if the destination directory is missing, rather than installing a
	  file as the directory name.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>See the &os;-arch mail for more information on planned
	  work.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>ELF Tool Chain tools</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://elftoolchain.sourceforge.net">ELF Tool Chain Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ELF Tool Chain project provides BSD-licensed
	implementations of compilation tools and libraries for building
	and analyzing ELF objects.  The project began as part of &os;
	but later became an independent project in order to encourage
	wider participation from others in the open-source developer
	community.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter of 2015 the ELF Tool Chain tools were
	updated to a snapshot of upstream Subversion revision 3272.
	Improvements include better input file validation, RISC-V
	support, support for Xen ELF notes, additional MIPS and ARM
	relocations, better performance, and bug fixes.</p>

      <p>The ELF Tool Chain project is planning a new release in
	the first quarter of 2016, which should facilitate wider
	testing and use by projects other than &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add missing functionality (PE/COFF suppor) to
	  <tt>elfcopy</tt> and migrate the base system build.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix issues found by fuzzing inputs to the tools.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add automatic support for separate debug files.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>The LLDB Debugger</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/lldb">&os; LLDB Wiki Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LLDB is the debugger from the LLVM family of projects.
	Originally developed for Mac OS X, it now also supports &os;,
	NetBSD, Linux, Android, and Windows.  It builds on existing
	components in the larger LLVM project, for example using Clang's
	expression parser and LLVM's disassembler.</p>

      <p>LLDB in the &os; base system was upgraded to version 3.7.0
	as part of the Clang and LLVM upgrade, and it will similarly be
	upgraded again, to 3.8.0 for &os; 11.0-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>LLDB is now enabled by default on the amd64 and arm64 platforms.
	It is now a functional basic debugger on arm64, after a number of
	fixes were made in the last quarter to both LLDB and the
	&os; kernel.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Rework the LLDB build to use LLVM and Clang shared libraries.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Port a remote debugging stub to &os;.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for local and core file kernel debugging.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve support on architectures other than amd64 and arm64.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>UEFI Boot and Framebuffer Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A number of UEFI bug fixes were committed over the last
	quarter, further improving compatibility with different UEFI
	implementations.  Specifically, on some implementations, &os;
	failed to boot with an &quot;ExitBootServices() returned
	0x8000000000000002&quot; error.  This has been fixed with a retry
	loop (as required by UEFI), in r292515 and r292338.</p>

      <p>UEFI improvements from other developers have recently been
	commited or are in progress.  These include support for environment
	variables set on the EFI loader command line, improved text console
	mode setting, support for nvram variables, and root-on-ZFS
	support.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Test &os;-CURRENT snapshots on a variety of UEFI
	  implementations.</p></task>

      <task>
	<p>Merge UEFI changes to stable/10, for &os;
	  10.3-RELEASE.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/">Foundation Website</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSDJournal.com/">FreeBSD Journal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit
	organization dedicated to supporting and promoting the &os;
	Project and community worldwide.  Funding comes from individual
	and corporate donations and is used to fund and manage
	development projects, conferences and developer summits, and
	provide travel grants to &os; developers.  The Foundation
	purchases hardware to improve and maintain &os; infrastructure
	and publishes &os; white papers and marketing material to
	promote, educate, and advocate for the &os; Project.  The
	Foundation also represents the &os; Project in executing
	contracts, license agreements, and other legal arrangements
	that require a recognized legal entity.</p>

      <p>Here are some highlights of what we did to help &os;
	last quarter:</p>

      <p>On the advocacy front, the Foundation attended and
	sponsored EuroBSDcon, which took place Oct 1-4 (<a
	  href="https://2015.eurobsdcon.org/">https://2015.eurobsdcon.org/</a>
	)in Stockholm, Sweden.  Two days prior, during the developer
	summit, Deb Goodkin ran a session on Recruiting to &os;.  The
	Foundation was also very active during the event itself; in
	addition to Deb, we had &a.dru;, &a.mckusick;, &a.erwin;,
	&a.emaste;, &a.hrs;, and &a.trasz; attend the conference.  Deb
	and Ed gave a presentation on how the Foundation supports a
	BSD project.  Kirk gave a presentation on &quot;a Brief
	History of the BSD Fast File System,&quot; and he taught the
	two-day tutorial &quot;Introduction to the &os; Open-Source
	Operating System.&quot;</p>

      <p>Deb then attended the 2015 Grace Hopper Conference
	that was held in Houston, TX, October 14-16.  The conference is
	for women in computing and most of the attendees were female
	computer science majors, female software developers, and
	college professors.  The Foundation was proud to be a Silver
	Sponsor.  The conference was very successful for us; our
	presence allowed us to to raise awareness of the Project, help
	recruit more women,  and get more professors to include &os;
	in their curriculum.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; traveled to Bangkok, Thailand to present
	talks on DTrace, &os;, and teaching with DTrace, at
	Chulalongkorn University, which is the largest University in
	Thailand with the largest engineering school.  The first talk
	he gave was his practitioner's introduction to DTrace in which
	he explains the technology, history and usage, without diving
	into all the kernel subsystems.  The second was the sales
	pitch for teaching with Dtrace and with &os;.  The pitch
	was well received and there was some very good points made by
	the audience.  The facts that the course materials are both
	open source and hosted on github were also well received.</p>

      <p>&a.mckusick; completed a 10-hour tutorial about &os;
	for Pearson Education in their &quot;Live Lesson&quot;
	program.  In particular, there is a great free snippet from
	that course comparing &os; against Linux here:
	<a href="http://youtu.be/dTpqALCwQ1Y?a">http://youtu.be/dTpqALCwQ1Y?a</a> .
	Find out more about the whole session at:
	<a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=NZS3W7D*uS0&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=163217.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=3559&amp;RD_PARM1=http%253A%252F%252Fwww.informit.com%252Fstore%252Fintroduction-to-the-FreeBSD-open-source-operating-system-9780134305868">http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=NZS3W7D*uS0&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=163217.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=3559&amp;RD_PARM1=http%253A%252F%252Fwww.informit.com%252Fstore%252Fintroduction-to-the-freebsd-open-source-operating-system-9780134305868</a> .</p>

      <p>Anne Dickison resumed the Faces of &os; series
	with interviews featuring Michael Dexter and Erin Clark.  She
	also continued to produce and distribute &os; materials for
	conferences, as well as advocating for &os; over our social
	channels.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; headed up the latest Silicon Valley Vendor
	and Developer Summit, November 2-3, at the NetApp campus in
	Sunnyvale, California.  Topics of discussion ranged over new
	developments in persistent memory, the use of &os; by a
	company that builds rackscale systems, developments in our
	compiler and tool suite, as well as others.  Additional
	Foundation Board and Staff attending the summit included: Deb
	Goodkin, &a.gjb;, &a.gibbs;, &a.mckusick;, &a.emaste;, and
	&a.hrs;.  The complete schedule, and some of the slides, are
	available on the &os; Wiki
	<a href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201511VendorDevSummit">https://wiki.freebsd.org/201511VendorDevSummit</a> .</p>

      <p>Notes from the always lively &quot;Have/Need/Want
	session&quot; are available at
	<a href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201511VendorDevSummit/HaveNeedWant">https://wiki.freebsd.org/201511VendorDevSummit/HaveNeedWant</a> .</p>

      <p>While in the Bay Area, some Foundation members visited
	commercial users of &os; to help understand their needs, update
	them on the work the Foundation is doing, and facilitate
	collaboration between them and the Project.</p>

      <p>We were a sponsor of the 2015 OpenZFS Developer
	Summit, which took place October 19-20, in San Francisco, CA.
	&a.gibbs; and &a.mckusick; attended the conference.</p>

      <p>&a.gibbs; continued his semester long class teaching
	Intro to Computer Science using &os; at a middle
	school.</p>

      <p>&a.emaste;, &a.trasz;, and &a.kib; continue to make
	progress on Foundation funded development projects.  More
	specifically:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Ed Worked on a number of items relating to the
	  tool chain: LLD linker, ELF Tool Chain components, and LLDB
	  debugger, and tested, integrated, and merged outstanding UEFI
	  work.</li>

	<li>Edward finished work on the reroot project as well
	  spending some time on a certificate-transparency port.  He also
	  implemented a prototype to support disk IO limit in RCTL.</li>

	<li>Konstantin rewrote the out of memory killer logic,
	  which, in particular, fixed &os; operation on systems
	  without swap, especially systems with verry little memory.  The
	  later are becoming more and more common with popularity of
	  embedded ARM platforms were &os; runs, but it also affects
	  large systems which are usually configured without swap.  He
	  also finalized and committed the shared page support for the
	  ARMv7 and ARMv8 systems.  This allows for a non-executable
	  stack on ARMv7, and a much faster, userspace gettimeofday(2)
	  for both, similar to on x86.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>&a.emaste; presented a &os;/arm64 talk and a hands-on
	demo at ARM Techcon, which took place November 10-12, 2015, in
	Santa Clara, CA.</p>

      <p>We continued publishing our monthly newsletters and
	acquiring new company testimonials about using &os;, including
	from Verisign and Nginx.</p>

      <p>Anne Dickison, &a.dru;, and &a.gjb; represented the
	Foundation at USENIX LISA '15, which took place November 3-8,
	in Washington D.C..  The Foundation had a booth in the Expo
	Hall and participated in a BoF.  In addition to connecting with
	current community members, we spoke with attendees who were
	interested in getting involved with the Project, and helped
	set them on the correct path.  We also took the opportunity to
	remind those who had not used &os; in a while what they were
	missing.  Glen also attended the USENIX Release Engineering
	Summit, which was co-located with LISA '15.</p>

      <p>We published the Sept/Oct and Nov/Dec issues of the
	&os; Journal.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; and &a.rwatson; announced the release of
	their TeachBSD initiative:
	<a href="http://teachbsd.com/">http://teachbsd.com/</a>.
	TeachBSD offers a set of reusable course materials designed to
	allow others to teach both university students and software
	practitioners &os; operating system fundamentals.  The
	Foundation is proud to have partly sponsored their efforts to
	teach the initial graduate level course on operating systems
	with tracing at the University of Cambridge.</p>

      <p>Deb Goodkin invited a representative from the
	Outreachy program to talk at the Ottawa &os; Developer Summit
	about the program and how we can get involved.</p>

      <p>Deb also started discussions with CS professors from
	the University of Colorado, Boulder to offer some Intro to
	&os; workshops.</p>

      <p>&a.gjb; continued wearing many hats to support to the Project.
	For Release Engineering:
	<ul>
	  <li>Added support for building <tt>BANANAPI</tt>,
	    <tt>CUBIEBOARD</tt>, and <tt>CUBIEBOARD2</tt> arm
	    images.</li>

	  <li>Deprecated use of MD5 checksums used for
	    verifying installation media downloaded from the &os; Project
	    mirrors.</li>

	  <li>Various miscellaneous updates and fixes to release
	    build code.</li>

	  <li>Continued providing regular development snapshot
	    builds.</li>
	</ul>
	Under Systems Administration:
	<ul>
	  <li>Assisted the Admins team with migrating various
	    services to two new colocation facilities near Sunnyvale,
	    generously provided by RootBSD and LimeLight Networks.</li>

	  <li>Moved email services for the Foundation to a new
	    server.</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <p>&a.emaste; attended the Reproducible Builds World
	Summit, which took place in Athens, Greece, December 1-3,
	2015.</p>

      <p>We wrapped up our 2015 fundraising efforts with our
	End-of-Year fundraising campaign by participating in
	#GivingTuesday, and continuing with weekly email and social
	media requests for support of the Foundation.  Final
	fundraising numbers will be available in Q1 2016.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; Xen</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Roger</given>
	  <common>Pau Monn&eacute;</common>
	</name>
	<email>royger@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wei</given>
	  <common>Liu</common>
	</name>
	<email>wei.liu2@citrix.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/&os;_PVH">&os; PVH DomU Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/&os;_Dom0">&os; PVH Dom0 Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://xenbits.xen.org/gitweb/?p=people/royger/FreeBSD.git;a=shortlog;h=refs/heads/new_entry_point_v5">&os;/Xen HVMlite Implementation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xen is a hypervisor using a microkernel design, providing
	services that allow multiple computer operating systems to execute
	on the same computer hardware concurrently.  Xen support for &os;
	on x86 as a guest was introduced in version 8, and ARM support is
	currently being worked on.  Support for running &os; as an amd64
	Xen host (Dom0) is available in HEAD.</p>

      <p>Regarding x86, the work done during this quarter has been
	focused in rewriting the PVH implementation inside of Xen, to what
	is now being called HVMlite (in order to differentiate it with the
	previous PVH implementation).  The Xen side of patches have
	already been committed to the Xen source tree, and will be
	available in Xen 4.7 (the next version).  Work has also begun on
	implementing HVMlite Dom0 support, although no patches have yet
	been published.</p>

      <p>HVMlite support for &os; has not yet been committed,
	although an initial implementation is available in a personal git
	repository.  The plan is to completely replace PVH with HVMlite on
	&os; as soon as HVMlite supports Dom0 mode.</p>

      <p>Apart from this, Wei Liu is working on improving netfront
	performance on &os;; initial patches have been posted to the &os;
	review system.</p>

      <p>During this time frame, the x86 unmapped bounce buffer code
	has also been improved, and unmapped IO support has been added to
	the <tt>blkfront</tt> driver.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Citrix Systems R&amp;D
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Finish HVMlite Dom0 support inside of Xen.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Deprecate and remove PVH support from Xen.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Remove PVH support from &os; and switch to HVMlite.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Generalize the event channel code so it can be used on
	  ARM.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve the performance of the various backends
	  (<tt>netback</tt>, <tt>blkback</tt>).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/arm64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/arm64">&os; arm64 Wiki Entry</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Support was added for kernel modules.  This included adding
	the needed relocation types to the in-kernel relocator, and
	updating the build logic to build modules for arm64.  CTF data is
	currently not generated for modules due to a linker bug.</p>

      <p>Shared page support was added.  This allows
	<tt>gettimeofday(2)</tt> to be implemented in userland by directly
	accessing the timer register.  This reduces the overhead of these
	calls as we no longer need to call into the kernel.  This also
	moves the signal trampoline code away from the stack allowing for
	the stack to become non-executable.</p>

      <p>CloudABI support for arm64 was added.  This included moving
	the machine-independent code into a separate file to be shared
	among all architectures.  An issue in the arm64 kernel was found
	and fixed thanks to the CloudABI test suite.</p>

      <p>Self-hosted poudriere package builds have been tested.
	These complement the previous build strategy of using qemu
	usermode emulation.  With this combination of self-hosted and qemu
	usermode building, many ports that used to be broken on arm64 have
	been fixed resulting in over 17000 ports building for the
	architecture.</p>

      <p>The machine-dependent portions of kernel support for
	single-stepping userland binaries has been started.  This will
	allow debuggers, such as <tt>lldb</tt>, to step through an
	application while debugging.</p>

      <p>Many small fixes have been made to &os;/arm64.  These
	include fixing stack tracing through exceptions, printing more
	information about &quot;data abort&quot; kernel panics, cleaning
	up the atomic functions, supporting multi-pass driver attachment,
	fixing userland stack alignment, cleaning up early page table
	creation, fixing asynchronous software trap handling, and enabling
	interrupts in exception handlers.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      ABT Systems Ltd
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on SoftIron Overdrive 3000</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://softiron.co.uk/products/">SoftIron Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The SoftIron Overdrive 3000 is an ARMv8 based server with an
	8-core AMD Opteron A1100 processor.  The Overdrive 3000 has
	two 10Gbase-T ethernet ports, two PCI Express ports, and eight
	SATA ports.  &os; has been updated to be able to boot on this
	hardware.</p>

      <p>Support for the SATA device was added to the
	<tt>ahci(4)</tt> driver.  Unlike on x86, this is a Memory Mapped
	(mmio) device, and not on the PCI bus.  To support this, a new
	ahci mmio driver attachment has been added.</p>

      <p>The generic PCIe driver has been updated to improve interrupt
	handling.  This includes supporting the interrupt-map devicetree
	property, and supporting MSI and MSI-X interrupts on arm64.</p>

      <p>Support for MSI and MSI-X interrupts has been added to the ARM
	Generic Interrupt Controller v2 (gicv2) driver.  This allows devices
	to use these interrupts.  This has been tested with a collection
	of PCIe NIC hardware.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      SoftIron Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Write a driver for the 10Gbase-T NIC.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
