<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2017</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p><strong>This is a draft of the October&ndash;December 2017
      status report.  Please check back after it is finalized, and
      an announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
      list.</strong></p>

    <?ignore
    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between October and
      December 2017.  This is the fourth of four reports planned for
      2017.</p>

    <p>The fourth quarter of 2017 was another productive quarter for
      the &os; project and community. [...]</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from January
      to March 2018 is April 7, 2018.</p>
     ?>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>

    <p>Entries from the various official and semi-official teams,
      as found in the <a href="&enbase;/administration.html">Administration
	Page</a>.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>

    <p>Projects that span multiple categories, from the kernel and userspace
      to the Ports Collection or external projects.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>

    <p>Updates to kernel subsystems/features, driver support,
      filesystems, and more.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>

    <p>Updating platform-specific features and bringing in support
      for new hardware platforms.</p>.
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>

    <p>Changes affecting the base system and programs in it.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>

    <p>Changes affecting the Ports Collection, whether sweeping
      changes that touch most of the tree, or individual ports
      themselves.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>

    <p>Noteworthy changes in the documentation tree or new external
      books/documents.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>

    <p>Objects that defy categorization.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>third</name>

    <description>Third-Party Projects</description>

    <p>Many projects build upon &os; or incorporate components of
      &os; into their project.  As these projects may be of interest 
      to the broader &os; community, we sometimes include brief
      updates submitted by these projects in our quarterly report.
      The &os; project makes no representation as to the accuracy or
      veracity of any claims in these submissions.</p>
  </category>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>LibreNMS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zane</given>
	  <common>Bowers-Hadley</common>
	</name>
	<email>vvelox@vvelox.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/librenms/librenms/pull/7938">LibreNMS ZFS Addition</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LibreNMS is an autodiscovering PHP/MySQL/SNMP-based network
	monitoring solution which includes support for a wide range of
	network hardware and operating systems, including Cisco,
	Linux, &os;, Juniper, Brocade, Foundry, HP and many more.</p>

      <p>Among other things, it can monitor applications and other
	functionality running on a server via SNMP extensions.  This
	has been the area of focus for my present work.</p>

      <p>ZFS support has been committed towards the end of December,
	which was too late to make the December release, but it will
	be in the January release.</p>

      <p>This brings the ability to monitor ARC and pool information,
	with each pool having its own separate set of graphs.</p>

      <p>The ARC graphing is as below.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>ARC size in bytes</li>

	<li>ARC size, percent of max size</li>

	<li>ARC size breakdown</li>

	<li>ARC efficiency</li>

	<li>ARC cache hits by list</li>

	<li>ARC cache hits by type</li>

	<li>ARC cache misses by type</li>

	<li>ARC cache hits</li>

	<li>ARC cache misses</li>

	<li>ARC misc (deleted, skips, and recycle misses)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The pool tracking is comparatively much simpler, using the
	output from <tt>zpool list</tt>.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Pool Space</li>

	<li>Pool Capacity</li>

	<li>Pool Fragmentation</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Suggestions are needed for additional statistics or other
	information to monitor, whether &os;-specific or
	otherwise.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>RDMA stack update based on Linux v4.9</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Mellanox Drivers Team</name>
	<email>FreeBSD-drivers@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=326169">Subversion Commit Adding the Driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An update to the &os; RDMA stack based on code from Linux
	v4.9 was merged into &os; 12-CURRENT on November 4th,
	including many bug fixes and new features with a focus on
	RoCEv2 &mdash; Routable RoCE.</p>

      <p>RDMA over Converged Ethernet (RoCE) is a network protocol
	that leverages Remote Direct Memory Access (RDMA) capabilities
	to accelerate communications between applications hosted on
	clusters of servers and storage arrays.  RoCE incorporates the
	IBTA RDMA semantics to allow devices to perform direct memory
	to memory transfers at the application level without involving
	the host CPU.  Both the transport processing and the memory
	translation and placement are performed by hardware resulting
	in lower latency, higher throughput, and better performance
	compared to software based protocols.</p>

      <p>RoCEv2 is the most recent version of RoCE, adding some routing
	capabilities as both IP and UDP headers are included in the
	packet format.  To complete the RoCEv2 solution, Support for
	ECN (Explicit Congestion Notification, lossy fabric) and PFC
	(Priority Flow Control, lossless fabric) protocols with rate
	limiting options will be added in the first quarter of
	2018.</p>

      <p>This project also introduces the following updates:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>libibverbs</tt>, <tt>librdmacm</tt>,
	  <tt>libibumad</tt> and vendor-specific libraries
	  ported from the Linux rdma-core v15+</li>

	<li>InfiniBand diagnostic tools,
	  <tt>infiniband-diags</tt>, version 1.6.7</li>

	<li>InfiniBand subnet manager &mdash; OpenSM, version 3.3.20+</li>

	<li>LinuxKPI support</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Important notes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>GPL-only (non dual-licensed) portions of the Linux code were either
	excluded or written from scratch under a BSD license by
	&a.hselasky;.</li>

	<li>The code has been tested by several RDMA vendors
	  that also support iWARP.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>Mellanox Technologies</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Add ECN (Explicit Congestion Notification) and PFC
	(Priority Flow Control) support.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>René</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">About &os; Ports</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">Contributing to ports</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">&os; Ports Monitoring</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team</url>
      <url href="https://twitter.com/FreeBSD_portmgr/">&os; Ports Managemnet Team on Twitter (@FreeBSD_portmgr)</url>
      <url href="https://www.facebook.com/portmgr">&os; Ports Management Team on Facebook</url>
      <url href="https://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383">&os; Ports Management Team on Google+</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The last quarter of 2017 ended with over 27,000 ports in the
	repository.  There are currently just under 2,800 open ports
	PRs with 685 of them unassigned.  There were 6,700 commits
	made by 178 committers.  The statistics did not change much
	since last quarter, however the number of unassigned PRs
	dropped slightly.</p>

      <p>This quarter, we welcomed Yuri Victorovich (yuri@), Jason
	Bacon (jwb@), and Wolfram Scheider (wosch@) as new or
	returning port committers.  No commit bits were taken in for
	safekeeping.</p>

      <p>Portmgr, together with postmaster@, changed the policy of the
	FreeBSD-ports@ mailing list.  It is now required to be
	subscribed to the list before one can post to it.  This will
	help in reducing spam on this list and help users finding
	better questions to their answers while browsing the list
	archive.</p>

      <p>This quarter ports &quot;flavors&quot; went live.  Flavors
	can be used to build multiple variations of a port, for
	example <tt>py27-sarge</tt> and <tt>py36-sarge</tt>.  All
	Python ports and some other ports are now flavored.  Other
	uses of flavors could be including or excluding X11
	(<tt>foo</tt> vs <tt>foo-x11</tt> or <tt>foo-nox11</tt>) or
	selecting the printer paper size (A4 vs letter).</p>

      <p><tt>USES=fmake</tt> has been removed as it was no longer
	useful.</p>

      <p>Some default versions got updated: Ruby to 2.4 and Samba to
	4.6.  Firefox got updated to version 57.0.3 and <tt>pkg</tt> to
	1.10.3.</p>

      <p>During the last quarter, antoine@ ran 33 exp-runs to validate changes
	to the base system, fix Qt5 ports, test Python flavors and other port
	updates, and make rubygem port builds reproducible.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Clang 6 is being imported into base.  There is a PR that keeps track
	of ports failing with this compiler, see <url
	  href="http://bugs.FreeBSD.org/224669">PR 224669</url>.  If you use
	any ports mentioned here, please consider fixing them.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on PowerNV (ppc64)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Patryk</given>
	  <common>Duda</common>
	</name>
	<email>pdk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wojciech</given>
	  <common>Macek</common>
	</name>
	<email>wma@FreeBSD.org</email>
	<email>wma@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Stanek</common>
	</name>
	<email>mst@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nw@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/powernv">Semihalf PowerNV Official Repository</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/open-power/skiboot">Skiboot Repository with the Latest OPAL Firmware</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> Semihalf is happy to announce that &os; is running on an IBM
	Power8 processor.  This project is a continuation of work done
	by Nathan Whitehorn, who provided a basic support for a
	PowerNV emulator.</p>

      <p>The IBM Power8 family of CPUs offers superior performance
	compared to previous CPUs in the Power series.  It provides
	complete NUMA support with up to 128 execution threads in
	two-socket system (2 sockets, 8 cores per socket, 8 threads
	per core).  All I/O communication is handled by an integrated
	PCIe interface equipped with multiple IOMMU engines.</p>

      <p>The support for Power8 system running &os; in a non-virtualized
	environment contains:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>A generic driver for the OPAL hypervisor</li>

	<li><tt>kboot</tt> loader modifications to allow for a
	  little-endian to load a big-endian kernel ELF image</li>

	<li>An update to the ELF parser in <tt>skiboot</tt>, allowing
	  it to understand the &os; kernel file format</li>

	<li>Basic support for the PowerNV architecture, including
	  modes of operation, memory-management unit (MMU), and
	  interrupt controller</li>

	<li>SMP operation with up to 128 CPUs</li>

	<li>PCI host bridge subsystem driver, including IOMMU mapping
	  for external busses</li>

	<li>PCIe host controller driver</li>

	<li>USB-3.0 XHCI driver</li>

	<li>Reworked several drivers to be big-endian compatible</li>

	<li>Chelsio cxgbe(4) 10/25G network adapter</li>

	<li>NVMe SSD driver</li>
      </ul>

      <p>All work is available in the linked GitHub repository.  The
	process of getting this work into the official repository has
	already started and eventually, all commits will be integrated
	into &os;-12 CURRENT.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>IBM</sponsor>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>

    <sponsor>QCM Technologies</sponsor>

    <sponsor>Semihalf</sponsor>

    <sponsor>Limelight Networks (Kevin Bowling)</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The most significant action by Core during the final quarter of
	2017 was the approval of the new Code of Conduct after a long
	period of development and review.  Core added a preamble to the
	text emphasizing the principles behind the Code of Conduct over
	detailed interpretation of the rules.  The new code delegates
	the handling of complaints to a Code of Conduct review board; we
	are currently finalizing practical arrangements around setting
	up the review board before announcing the adoption of the new
	code.</p>

      <p>John Hixson of iXsystems was proposed, and accepted, as the
	first new Project Member under the new rules adopted earlier
	this year.  Core feels that John is an excellent choice as the
	first member, and looks forwards to adding many other project
	members in the future.</p>

      <p>There have been some significant changes around the Security
	Officer and secteam.  Gordon Tetlow has formally taken over the
	role of Security Officer from Xin Li.  Xin remains an active
	member of secteam, and Ed Maste has now joined secteam as well.
	</p>

      <p>Gordon joined Secteam at a point where they were struggling
	with handling the widely publicised WPA2 vulnerability
	(&os;-SA-17:07.wpa), and had an immediate impact simply by
	making a public response, even though the technical fixes were
	not entirely ready.  Gordon's remit from Core is to examine how
	Secteam operates and work out how to manage their case-load while
	avoiding the problems of burn-out and overload that have impeded
	Secteam's effectiveness in the past.</p>

      <p>One of the key problems is that security problems are handled
	in a completely separate bug handling system to general PRs.
	This is unusual compared to most similar OS projects, and leads
	to difficulties in bringing in available talent from amongst the
	entire body of &os; developers in order to be able to share
	the load and react quickly.  Secteam is working with Bugmeister
	to enable suitable access controls within our main Bugzilla
	instance, so that we can both conform to bug embargoes and other
	confidentiality requirements but also make it easy to solicit
	fixes from a wider range of developers and to transition
	security bugs to open handling like any other bug once there is
	no more need for secrecy.</p>

      <p>This quarter also saw the creation of a 10.4-RELEASE branch,
	and the extension of the lifetime of 11.0-RELEASE by one month.
	The former was in response to requests from a number of
	prominent &os; consumers, who needed access to new
	functionality but could not immediately upgrade to 11.0-RELEASE.
	Releasing 10.4 permitted this without making a significant
	extension to the lifetime of the 10.x release series.</p>

      <p>The extension to 11.0-RELEASE EoL was a consequence of failing
	to communicate the impending switch to 11.1-RELEASE in good
	time.  Since this was the first minor version transition under
	the new release schedule, in discussion with Secteam and Release
	Engineering, we concluded that a delay was necessary to allow
	the userbase sufficient warning to upgrade before 11.0-RELEASE
	went out of support.  This was not a cost-free decision: as
	Portmgr reminded us, this affected package building and delayed
	implementation of some important updates.</p>

      <p>&os; will be participating in Google Summer of Code again in
	2018.  This has become one of our most important routes for
	recruiting the new, young developers vital for ensuring the
	longevity of the project.</p>

      <p>Pedro Giffuni proposed adopting the SPDX license tagging system
	as used by many other projects, including the Linux kernel, in
	order to facilitate programatic license management by downstream
	consumers.  Core agreed enthusiasticly.</p>

      <p>Core has agreed to promote the MIPS architecture to Tier-2
	status.</p>

      <p>A proposal to enhance security by discontinuing HTTP or other
	unencrypted channels for all &os; services was not something
	Core could approve for the immediate future.  While switching to
	HTTPS has obvious security benefits, we would need to distribute
	appropriate CA certificates as part of the base system and make
	certain other changes before this could be achieved relatively
	seamlessly.  All &os; services are already available over
	secure channels, but our documentation did not necessarily
	present secure access methods as the preferred routes.  Action
	is being taken to address the documentation, and this question
	will be revisited once the necessary groundwork is in place.</p>

      <p>The <tt>fortune(6)</tt> program has long been a focus for controversy,
	and previous Cores have needed to impose a lock on updates to
	the fortune data files.  The argument blew up again over the
	re-deletion of a number of apparently pro-Nazi quotations.  Core
	decided that enough was enough and removed all of the fortune
	data files except for <tt>FreeBSD-tips.dat</tt> from the base system.
	The tacit approval of many questionable or controversial
	opinions by shipping them as a part of the base system is a
	liability the project simply cannot afford.</p>

      <p>No new commit bits were issued during this quarter, but we did
	see two former committers: Sean Eric Fagan and Wolfram
	Schneider, reactivate their commit bits.  One committer, Ngie
	Cooper, has handed back their bit.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
