<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2015</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p><strong>This is a draft of the October&ndash;December 2015
	status report.  Please check back after it is finalized, and
	an announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
	list.</strong></p>

    <p>The fourth quarter of 2015 saw a great deal of activity for
      &os;.  This is now the third quarter running for which I can say
      that this is the largest report yet published!  Many thanks to the
      developers who proactively submitted topics and entries &mdash; it
      is great to have more complete coverage of ongoing development for
      the community to learn about in these reports.</p>

    <p>An experimental new team was formed this quarter to triage
      newly-reported bugs and improve the procedures and tooling for
      managing bug submissions.  Making more effective use of automation
      and tooling can help to increase developer productivity and the
      quality of &os;, just as the adoption of Jenkins and continual
      integration tooling catches regressions quickly and maintains the
      high standards for the system.</p>

    <p>Efforts to bring our BSD high standards to new
      architectures continue, with impressive work on arm64 leading to
      its promotion to Tier-2 status and a flurry of work bringing up
      the new RISC-V hardware architecture.  Software architecture is
      also under active development, including system startup and
      service management.  A handful of potential init system
      replacements are mentioned in this report: <tt>launchd</tt>,
      <tt>relaunchd</tt>, and <tt>nosh</tt>.  Architectural changes
      originating both from academic research (multipath TCP) and from
      the realities of industry (<tt>sendfile(2)</tt> improvements) are
      also under way.  It is heartening to see how &os; provides a
      welcoming platform for contributions from both research and
      industry.</p>

    <p>To all the readers, whether from academia or industry,
      hobbyist or professional: I hope you are as excited as I am to
      read about all of the progress and projects covered in this
      report, and the future of &os;!</p>

    <p>&mdash;Ben Kaduk</p>

    <p><hr /></p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from January
      to March 2016 is April 7, 2016.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Linux Kernel as a Library Added to the Ports
      Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/lkl/linux">Upstream LKL Github repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LKL (&quot;Linux Kernel as a Library&quot;) is a special
	&quot;architecture&quot; of the full Linux kernel that builds
	as a userspace library on various platforms, including &os;.
	One application of such a library is using Linux filesystem
	drivers to implement a FUSE backend.</p>

      <p>fusefs-lkl's <tt>lklfuse</tt> binary is such a FUSE
	filesystem.  It can mount <tt>ext4/3/2</tt>, <tt>XFS</tt>, and
	<tt>BTRFS</tt> read-write, using the native drivers from
	Linux.</p>

      <p><tt>sysutils/fusefs-lkl</tt> can now be installed either from
	packages or ports, providing access to these filesystems on
	&os; via FUSE.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title><tt>style(9)</tt> Enhanced to Allow C99
      <tt>bool</tt></title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bruce</given>
	  <common>Evans</common>
	</name>
	<email>brde@optusnet.com.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/svn-src-head/2015-December/079671.html">Bruce's email requesting bool be added to <tt>style(9)</tt></url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4384">Differential Revision for the change</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Use of <tt>bool</tt> is now allowed.  It was allowed
	previously, as well, but now it is <em>really</em> allowed.
	Party like it's 1999!</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Specify <tt>style(9)</tt>'s opinion on
	  <tt>iso646.h.</tt></p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix <tt>intmax_t</tt> to be 128-bit on platforms where
	  <tt>__int128_t</tt> is used.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title><tt>sysctl</tt> Enhancements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ravi</given>
	  <common>Pokala</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpokala@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcelo</given>
	  <common>Araujo</common>
	</name>
	<email>araujo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_data_types#Fixed-width_integer_types">Wikipedia Entry on C99 Fixed-Width Integer Types</url>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=203918"><tt>sysctl(8)</tt> -t Submission PR</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Support was added for fixed-width sysctls (signed and
	unsigned 8-bit, 16-bit, 32-bit, and 64-bit integers).  The new
	KPIs are documented in the <tt>sysctl(9)</tt> manual page.
	The <tt>sysctl(8)</tt> command line tool supports all of the
	new types.</p>

      <p><tt>sysctl(8)</tt> gained the <tt>-t</tt> flag, which prints
	sysctl type information (the original patch was submitted by
	Yoshihiro Ota).  This support includes the newly added
	fixed-width types.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title><tt>ioat(4)</tt> Driver Enhancements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I/O_Acceleration_Technology">Wikipedia on I/OAT</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/news/status/report-2015-07-2015-09.html#ioat%284%29-Driver-Import">Last quarter's <tt>ioat(4)</tt> report</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I/OAT DMA engines are bulk memory operation offload engines
	built into some Intel Server/Storage platform CPUs.</p>

      <p>Several enhancements were made to the driver.  It now avoids
	memory allocation in locked paths, which should avoid
	deadlocking in memory pressure scenarios.  Support for
	Broadwell-EP devices has been added.  The
	&quot;blockfill&quot; operation and a non-contiguous 8 KB copy
	operation have been added to the API.  The driver can recover
	from various programming errors by resetting the hardware.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>XOR and other advanced (&quot;RAID&quot;) operation
	  support.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title><tt>ntb_hw(4)</tt>/<tt>if_ntb(4)</tt> Driver Synced up to
      Linux</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Conrad</given>
	  <common>Meyer</common>
	</name>
	<email>cem@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/jonmason/ntb/wiki">Jon Mason's NTB wiki</url>
      <url href="https://www-ssl.intel.com/content/dam/www/public/us/en/documents/white-papers/xeon-c5500-c3500-non-transparent-bridge-paper.pdf">Intel NTB whitepaper</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><tt>ntb_hw(4)</tt> is now up-to-date with the Linux NTB
	driver as of the work-in-progress 4.4 kernel (and actually,
	contains some fixes that haven't landed in the mainline Linux
	tree yet but will land in 4.5).  Only Back-to-back
	(&quot;B2B&quot;) configurations are supported at this time.
	Going forward, newer hardware may only support the B2B
	configuration.</p>

      <p><tt>if_ntb(4)</tt> is mostly up-to-date with the Linux NTB
	netdevice driver.  Notably absent is support for changing the
	MTU at runtime.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Improving <tt>if_ntb(4)</tt> to avoid using the entire Base
	  Address Register (BAR) when very large BAR sizes are
	  configured (e.g., 512 GB).</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improving <tt>pmap_mapdev(9)</tt> to somehow allocate only
	  superpage mappings for large BARs, on platforms that support
	  superpages.  (NTB BARs can be as large as 512 GB.)</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Newer ARM Boards</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Wehle</common>
	</name>
	<email>john@feith.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ganbold</given>
	  <common>Tsagaankhuu</common>
	</name>
	<email>ganbold@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/arm/Odroid-C1">&os; on Odroid-C1</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/291683">Commit adding glue driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We made the changes required to support the Amlogic Meson
	Ethernet controller on the Hardkernel ODROID-C1 board, which
	has an Amlogic aml8726-m8b SoC.  The main effort needed was to
	write a glue driver for the Ethernet controller &mdash; the
	Amlogic Meson Ethernet controller is compatible with Synopsys
	DesignWare 10/100/1000 Ethernet MAC (<tt>if_dwc</tt>).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Mellanox Drivers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mellanox.com/page/ethernet_cards_overview">Hardware Information</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/290650">Commit Adding the Driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Mellanox &os; team is proud to announce support for the
	ConnectX-4 series of network cards in &os; 11-current and &os;
	10-stable.  These devices deliver top performance, with up to
	100GBit/s of raw transfer capacity, and support both Ethernet
	and Infiniband.  Currently, the Ethernet driver is ready for
	use and the Infiniband support for ConnectX-4 is making good
	progress.  We hope that it will be complete before &os; 11.0
	is released.  For more technical information, refer to the
	<tt>mlx5en(4)</tt> manual page in 11-current.  The new driver
	for ConnectX-4 cards is called <tt>mlx5</tt> and is put under
	<tt>/sys/dev</tt> and not under <tt>/sys/ofed</tt> as was done
	for the previous <tt>mlx4</tt> driver.  The <tt>mlx5en(4)</tt>
	kernel module is compiled by default in GENERIC kernels.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>&quot;FreeBSD Mastery: Specialty Filesystems&quot; Early Access Version Now Available</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michael</given>
	  <common>Lucas</common>
	</name>
	<email>mwlucas@michaelwlucas.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.michaelwlucas.com/nonfiction/fmsf">Book site</url>
      <url href="https://www.tiltedwindmillpress.com/?product=fmspf">Early access version</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><u>FreeBSD Mastery: Specialty Filesystems</u> is now in
	copyediting.  The ebook should be available by the end of
	January at all major vendors, and the print in February.</p>

      <p>The book covers everything from removable media, to FUSE,
	NFSv4 ACLs, iSCSI, CIFS, and more.</p>

      <p>If you act really quickly, you can get the electronic early
	access version at a 10% discount.  You will get the final
	ebook when it comes out as well.  (This offer evaporates when
	the final version comes out.)</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Updates to GDB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Baldwin</common>
	</name>
	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/bsdjhb/gdb/tree/FreeBSD-threads">New 1:1-only thread target for &os;</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KGDB option is now on by default in the
	<tt>devel/gdb</tt> port.</p>

      <p>Changes to support cross-debugging of crashdumps in libkvm
	were committed to HEAD in r291406.</p>

      <p>A new thread target for &os; that is suitable for merging
	upstream has been written and lightly tested.  However, it is
	not yet available as an option in the port.  This thread
	target uses <tt>ptrace(2)</tt> directly rather than
	<tt>libthread_db</tt> and as such supports threads on all ABIs
	(such as &os;/i386 binaries on &os;/amd64 and possibly Linux
	binaries, though that is not yet tested).  It also requires
	less-invasive changes in the MD targets in GDB compared to the
	<tt>libthread_db</tt>-based target.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add a port option for the new 1:1-only thread target.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Test the new 1:1-only thread target.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Figure out why the powerpc kgdb targets are not able to
	  unwind the stack past the initial frame.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for more platforms (arm, mips, aarch64) to
	  upstream <tt>gdb</tt> for both userland and
	  <tt>kgdb</tt>.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for debugging powerpc vector registers.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>iMX.6 Video Output Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/changeset/base/292574">Commit Adding Basic Video Support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>iMX.6 is a family of SoC used in multiple hobbyist ARM boards
	such as the Hummingboard, RIoTboard, and Cubox.  Most of these
	products have HDMI output, but until recently, &os; did not
	benefit from it.  As of r292574, there is basic video output
	support so you can use the console on iMX6-based boards and
	probably run Xorg (not yet tested).</p>

      <p>Due to the lack of some kernel functionality (see open
	tasks), the only supported mode is 1024x768.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Proper pixel clock initialization (relies on a clock
	  framework).</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>More flexible video output path (support multiple IPUs
	  and DIs).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Touchscreen Support for Raspberry Pi and Beaglebone
      Black</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://kernelnomicon.org/?p=534">Beaglebone Black with 4DCAPE-43T Demo</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201510DevSummit/GraphicsStack">Input Stack Plans</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SummerOfCode2014/evdev_Touchscreens">evdev Port</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are two working proof-of-concept drivers for the
	AM335x touchscreen and for the official Raspberry Pi's
	touchscreen LCD.</p>

      <p>Proper touchscreen support would consist of a userland event
	reading API, a kernel event reporting API, and kernel hardware
	drivers for specific devices.  There is an ongoing effort to
	port the Linux evdev API to &os; so applications that use
	libraries like libinput or tslib could be used without any
	major changes.  Since it is not yet complete, I created a
	naive evdev-like API for both kernel and tslib and was able to
	run a demo on a Beaglebone Black with 4DCAPE-43T.</p>

      <p>Once evdev makes it into the tree, both hardware drivers
	can be modified to include &quot;report events&quot;
	portions and committed.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Kernel Vnode Cache Tuning</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kirk</given>
	  <common>McKusick</common>
	</name>
	<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bruce</given>
	  <common>Evans</common>
	</name>
	<email>bde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Peter</given>
	  <common>Holm</common>
	</name>
	<email>pho@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mateusz</given>
	  <common>Guzik</common>
	</name>
	<email>mjg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/rS292895">MFC to stable/10</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This completed project includes changes to better manage
	the vnode freelist and to streamline the allocation and
	freeing of vnodes.</p>

      <p>Vnode cache recycling was reworked to meet free and unused
	vnode targets.  Free vnodes are rarely completely free;
	rather, they are just ones that are cheap to recycle.  Usually
	they are for files which have been stat'd but not read; these
	usually have inode and namecache data attached to them.  The
	free vnode target is the preferred minimum size of a sub-cache
	consisting mostly of such files.  The system balances the size
	of this sub-cache with its complement to try to prevent either
	from thrashing while the other is relatively inactive.  The
	targets express a preference for the best balance.</p>

      <p>&quot;Above&quot; this target there are 2 further targets
	(watermarks) related to the recyling of free vnodes.  In the
	best-operating case, the cache is exactly full, the free list
	has size between vlowat and vhiwat above the free target, and
	recycling from the free list and normal use maintains this
	state.  Sometimes the free list is below vlowat or even empty,
	but this state is even better for immediate use, provided the
	cache is not full.  Otherwise, <tt>vnlru_proc()</tt> runs to
	reclaim enough vnodes (usually non-free ones) to reach one of
	these states.  The watermarks are currently hard-coded as 4%
	and 9% of the available space.  These, and the default of 25%
	for wantfreevnodes, are too large if the memory size is large.
	For example, 9% of 75% of MAXVNODES is more than 566000 vnodes
	to reclaim whenever <tt>vnlru_proc()</tt> becomes active.</p>

      <p>The <tt>vfs.vlru_alloc_cache_src</tt> sysctl is removed.  The new
	code frees namecache sources as the last chance to satisfy the
	highest watermark, instead of selecting source vnodes
	randomly.  This provides good enough behavior to keep
	<tt>vn_fullpath()</tt> working in most situations.  Filesystem
	layouts with deep trees, where the removed knob was required,
	are thus handled automatically.</p>

      <p>As the kernel allocates and frees vnodes, it fully
	initializes them on every allocation and fully releases them
	on every free.  These are not trivial costs: it starts by
	zeroing a large structure, then initializes a mutex, a lock
	manager lock, an rw lock, four lists, and six pointers.
	Looking at <tt>vfs.vnodes_created</tt>, these operations are
	being done millions of times an hour on a busy machine.</p>

      <p>As a performance optimization, this code update uses the
	uma_init and uma_fini routines to do these initializations and
	cleanups only as the vnodes enter and leave the vnode zone.
	With this change, the initializations are done
	<tt>kern.maxvnodes</tt> times at system startup, and then only
	rarely again.  The frees are done only if the vnode zone
	shrinks, which never happens in practice.  For those curious
	about the avoided work, look at the <tt>vnode_init()</tt> and
	<tt>vnode_fini()</tt> functions in sys/kern/vfs_subr.c to see
	the code that has been removed from the main vnode
	allocation/free path.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Improvements to the QLogic HBA Driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The QLogic HBA driver, <tt>isp(4)</tt>, received a
	substantial set of changes.  The primary goal was to make the
	Fibre Channel target role work well with CTL, but many other
	things were also fixed/improved:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Added support for modern 16Gbps 26xx FC cards.</li>

	<li>The firmware in <tt>ispfw(4)</tt> were updated to the
	  latest versions.</li>

	<li>Target role support was fixed and tested for all FC cards
	  from ancient 1Gbps 22xx to modern 16Gbps 26xx.</li>

	<li>Port database handling was unified for target and
	  initiator roles, allowing an HBA port to play both roles at the
	  same time.</li>

	<li>The maximal number of ports was increased from 256 to
	  1024.</li>

	<li>Multi-ID (NPIV) functionality was fixed/implemented,
	  allowing 24xx and above cards to provide up to 255 virtual
	  FC ports per physical port.</li>

	<li>Added support for 8-byte LUNs for 24xx and above
	  cards.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The code is committed to &os; head and stable/10
	branches.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      iXsystems, Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>NVRAM data reading is hackish and requires rework.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>FCoE support for 26xx cards was not tested yet.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Raspberry Pi: VideoCore Userland Application
      Packaging</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mika&euml;l</given>
	  <common>Urankar</common>
	</name>
	<email>mikael.urankar@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Raspberry Pi SoC consists of two parts: ARM and GPU
	(VideoCore).  Many interesting features like OpenGL, video
	playback, and HDMI controls are implemented on the VideoCore
	side and can be accessed from the OS through libraries
	provided by Broadcom (userland repo).  These libraries were
	ported to &os; some time ago, so Mika&euml;l created the port
	<tt>misc/raspberrypi-userland</tt> for them.  He also created
	a port for <tt>omxplayer</tt> (a low-level video player that
	utilizes VideoCore APIs) and is working on a port for Kodi
	(formerly XBMC), a more user-firendly media player software
	with Raspberry Pi support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>LXQt on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Olivier</given>
	  <common>Duchateau</common>
	</name>
	<email>olivierd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/LXQt">&os; LXQt Project</url>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/lxqt/subversion/source">LXQt Devel Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><a href="http://lxqt.org/">LXQt</a> is the Qt port of and
	the upcoming version of LXDE, the Lightweight Desktop
	Environment.  It is the product of the merge between the
	LXDE-Qt and the Razor-qt projects.</p>

      <p>The porting effort remains very much a work in progress: it
	needs some components of Plasma 5, the new major KDE
	workspace.</p>

      <p>Currently, only the 0.10 branch is functional.  See our wiki
	page for a complete list of applications.</p>

      <p>We also sent updates for some components of LXDE, required
	for the LXQt desktop:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>x11/menu-cache</tt> 1.0.1</li>

	<li><tt>x11/lxmenu-data</tt> 0.1.4</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Binary packages are available (only for test purposes) which
	are regularly tested with the KDE development repository.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Port libsysstat to BSD systems.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix some issues that need to be resolved, especially the
	  shutdown and reboot commands.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Node.js Modules</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Olivier</given>
	  <common>Duchateau</common>
	</name>
	<email>olivierd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/cozycloud/subversion/source">Node.js Modules Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Node.js is a platform built on Chrome's JavaScript runtime
	for easily building fast, scalable network applications.  It
	uses an event-driven, non-blocking I/O model that makes it
	lightweight and efficient &mdash; perfect for data-intensive
	real-time applications that run across distributed
	devices.</p>

      <p>The goal of this project is to make it easy to install the
	modules available in the
	<a href="http://npmjs.org/">npm package registry</a>.</p>

      <p>Currently, the repository contains slightly fewer than 300
	new ports, in particular:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Socket.IO, a library for realtime web applications</li>

	<li>Jison, a JavaSript parser generator</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We have improved the USES framework:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Users can define which version of Node.js will be
	  installed through <tt>/etc/make.conf</tt>.</li>

	<li><tt>node-gyp</tt> is now well-integrated into the USES
	  framework, via the <strong>build</strong> argument.</li>

	<li>The <tt>pkg-plist</tt> is now automatically generated
	  to make <tt>portlint</tt> happy.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Each port is up-to-date.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Update the pre-draft documentation.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Bring in grunt.js (and modules), the JavaScript task
	  runner.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Xfce on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Xfce Team</name>
	<email>xfce@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Xfce">&os; Xfce Project</url>
      <url href="https://www.assembla.com/spaces/xfce4/subversion/source">&os; Xfce Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xfce is a free software desktop environment for Unix and
	Unix-like platforms, such as &os;.  It aims to be fast and
	lightweight, while still being visually appealing and easy to
	use.</p>

      <p>During this quarter, the team has kept these applications
	up-to-date:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>audio/xfce4-pulseaudio-plugin</tt> 0.2.4</li>
	<li><tt>multimedia/xfce4-parole</tt> 0.8.1</li>
	<li><tt>x11/xfce4-whiskermenu-plugin</tt> 1.5.2</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We also follow the unstable releases (available in our
	experimental repository) of:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>x11/xfce4-dashboard</tt> 0.5.4</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Propose a patch to upstream to fix Xfdashboard with our
	  version of OpenGL (it currently coredumps).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Supporting Variants in the Ports Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brendan</given>
	  <common>Molloy</common>
	</name>
	<email>brendan+freebsd@bbqsrc.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/poudriere/compare/master...feature/variants">Poudriere PoC with Variants</url>
      <url href="https://gist.github.com/bbqsrc/e7e3a54d84706485aa3a">Ports Makefile PoC with Examples</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I recently became involved with &os; (as in, the last 2-3
	weeks), and found myself quickly involved with Ports
	development.  What struck me immediately was the difficulty in
	providing a Python package that was depended upon by multiple
	versions of Python.  As it turns out, poudriere can currently
	only generate one package per port, meaning that a Python
	version-neutral (compatible with 2.x and 3.x) port cannot
	simultaneously be packaged for each variant at the same
	time.</p>

      <p>I discussed the issue with &a.koobs;, who suggested that I
	look into implementing a &quot;variants protocol&quot; within
	the Ports framework and the necessary changes to poudriere to
	allow a port to generate more than one package.</p>

      <p>Support for variants is strongly needed in Ports and
	provides significant benefits.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>It would allow Python and other languages to provide
	  packages for dependencies for multiple language versions
	  from the same port.</li>

	<li>It alleviates the need for so-called &quot;slave
	  ports&quot;, as a single port could now have multiple
	  generated packages from a single port.</li>

	<li>It would have a very small impact on the greater Ports
	  ecosystem: adding only two new variables, <tt>VARIANT</tt>
	  and <tt>VARIANTS</tt>.</li>

	<li>It would provide a more consistent approach between
	  different packaging teams for handling variations.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>For a simple example, <tt>editors/vim-lite</tt> could
	be folded into the <tt>editors/vim</tt> port, while still
	generating a <tt>vim</tt> and <tt>vim-lite</tt> package.
	For Python, <tt>VARIANTS</tt> can be derived from the already
	used <tt>USES</tt> flags and generate compatible packages.
	<tt>py27-foobar</tt> and <tt>py34-foobar</tt> could now be
	consistently generated by poudriere without issue.</p>

      <p>Fortunately, this is not a wishful thinking piece.  I dug
	in my heels and have implemented a proof-of-concept
	implementation of variants in the Ports framework, including
	the necessary modifications to poudriere in order to support
	it.  It was mildly upsettling to find that poudriere is mostly
	written in Bourne shell scripts, but I pressed on
	nonetheless.</p>

      <p>I started with
	<a href="https://github.com/bapt/ports-wip/compare/variants">the prototype made by &a.bapt;</a>
	as a base, and built from there.  The poudriere PoC aims to
	limit changes as much as possible to merely adding support for
	the new variants flags, while also at the request of &a.koobs;
	making the logging output more package-centric (as opposed to
	port-centric) as a result of these changes.</p>

      <p>This is a <strong>work in progress</strong>, and I would
	love to hear your feedback.  I have enjoyed my first few weeks
	working on &os;, and I hope to stay here for quite some
	time.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Any constructive feedback on the implementation would be
	  very welcome!</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Hopefully the code will be of sufficient quality to be
	  considered for formal review in the coming months.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>New Tools to Enhance the Porting Experience</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
      <name>
	<given>Brendan</given>
	<common>Molloy</common>
      </name>
      <email>brendan+freebsd@bbqsrc.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/pytoport">pytoport: Generate &os; Ports from Python modules on PyPI</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/bandar">bandar: Create Development Overlays for the Ports tree</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/skog-python">skog: Generate Visual Dependency Trees for &os; Ports</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/bbqsrc/spdx-lookup-python">spdx-lookup: SPDX License List Query Tool</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>When I starting working on ports for &os; in the last couple
	of weeks, I found that my workflow was not as efficient as it
	could be using just the available tools, so I made a few that
	could be useful to the development community at large.  All of
	these have been or will soon be added to the Ports tree, so
	you can play with them today!</p>

      <p><tt>pytoport</tt> is a command-line application that
	generates a skeleton port for a given PyPI package name.  It
	attempts to generate the correct dependencies, makes a good
	attempt at guessing the license using <tt>spdx-lookup</tt>,
	and generates a <tt>pkg-descr</tt>.  This made generating the
	fifteen or so ports I was working on a complete breeze.</p>

      <p>While doing this, however, I noticed that some ports were
	bringing in dependencies that I did not expect, and I needed
	some way to visualise this.  <tt>skog</tt> builds a dependency
	tree from the depends lists output by the Ports framework, and
	displays it on the command line (with extra shiny output if
	you are using UTF-8).  No more pesky example and documentation
	dependencies being dragged in when you <em>clearly</em>
	toggled that <tt>OPTION</tt> as far off as it would go.</p>

      <p>While doing all of this, I found it cumbersome to be copying
	ports back and forth between my small development tree living
	in git and the larger upstream SVN tree I was using in
	poudriere.  I built a tool called <tt>bandar</tt> that takes
	advantage of the FUSE version of unionfs to easily overlay my
	dev tree on the upstream tree, run linting, poudriere, and
	generate archives with ease.</p>

      <p>I am very impressed with how easy it was to build more
	tooling for &os;.  I hope some of these tools will be of some
	use to you, and as always, I'd love to hear your feedback!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Improve <tt>skog</tt> to support searching a tree for a
	  certain port.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Get the <tt>bandar</tt> port completed.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Continue to improve <tt>pytoport</tt>, adding
	  <tt>trove</tt> support and better dependency handling.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Patches welcome for all of the above!</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Out of Memory Handler Rewrite</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Out of Memory (OOM) code is intended to handle the
	situation where the system needs free memory to make progress,
	but no memory can be reused.  Most often, the situation is
	that to free memory, the system needs more free memory.
	Consider a case where the system needs to page-out dirty
	pages, but needs to allocate structures to track the writes.
	OOM &quot;solves&quot; the problem by killing some selection
	of user processes.  In other words, it trades away system
	deadlock by suffering a partial loss of user data.  The
	assumption is that it is better to kill a process and recover
	data in other processes than to lose everything.</p>

      <p>Free memory in the &os; Virtual Memory (VM) system appears
	from two sources.  One is the voluntary reclamation of pages
	used by a process, for example unmapping private anonymous
	regions, or the last unlink of an otherwise unreferenced file
	with cached pages.  Another source is the pagedaemon, which
	forcefully frees pages which carry data, of course after the
	data is moved to some other storage, like swap or file blocks.
	OOM is triggered when the pagedaemon definitely cannot free
	memory to satisfy the requests.</p>

      <p>The old criteria to trigger the OOM action was a combination
	of low free swap space and a low count of free pages (the
	latter is expressed precisely with the paging targets
	constants, but this is not relevant to the discussion).  That
	test is mostly incorrect.  For example, a low free page state
	might be caused by a greedy consumer allocating all pages
	freed by the page daemon in the current pass, but this does
	not preclude the page daemon from producing more pages.  Also,
	since page-outs are asynchronous, the previous page daemon
	pass might not immmediately produce any free pages, but they
	would appear some short time later.</p>

      <p>More seriously, low swap space does not necessarily indicate
	that we are in trouble: lots of pages might not require swap
	allocations to be freed, like clean pages or pages backed by
	files.  The last notion is serious, since swap-less systems
	were considered as having full swap.</p>

      <p>Instead of trying to deduce the deadlock from looking at the
	current VM state, the new OOM handler tracks the history of
	page daemon passes.  Only when several consecutive passes
	failed to meet the paging target is an OOM kill considered
	necessary.  The count of consequent failed passes was selected
	empirically, by testing on small (32M) and large (512G)
	machines.  Auto-tuning of the counter is possible, but
	requires some more architectural changes to the I/O
	subsystem.</p>

      <p>Another issue was identified with the algorithm which selects
	a victim process for OOM kill.  It compared the counts of
	pages mapping entries (PTEs) installed into the machine paging
	structures.  For different reasons, the machine-dependent VM code
	(pmap) may remove the pte for a memory-resident page.  Under
	some circumstances related to other measures to prevent low
	memory deadlock, very large processes which consume all system
	memory could have few or no ptes.  The old OOM selector
	ignored the process which caused the deadlock, killing
	unrelated processes.</p>

      <p>A new function, <tt>vm_pageout_oom_pagecount()</tt>, was
	written which applies a reasonable heuristic to estimate the
	number of pages freed by killing the given process.  This
	eliminates the effect of selecting small unrelated processes
	for OOM kill.</p>

      <p>The rewrite was committed to HEAD in r290917 and r290920.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Chelsio iSCSI Offload Driver (Initiator and Target)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Navdeep</given>
	  <common>Parhar</common>
	</name>
	<email>navdeep@chelsio.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/292740">Commit Adding Hardware Acceleration Support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A new driver, <tt>cxgbei</tt>, enabling hardware accelerated
	iSCSI with Chelsio's T5- and T4-based offload-capable cards,
	has been committed to HEAD.  Both Initiator and Target are
	supported.  The wire traffic is standard iSCSI (SCSI over TCP
	as per RFC 3720, etc.) so an Initiator/Target using this
	driver will interoperate with all other standards-compliant
	implementations.</p>

      <p>Hardware assistance provided by the T5 and T4 ASICs
	includes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Complete TCP processing.</li>

	<li>iSCSI PDU identification and extraction from the byte
	  oriented TCP stream.</li>

	<li>Header and/or data digest generation and
	  verification.</li>

	<li>Zero copy support for both transmit and receive.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Chelsio Communications
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>The <tt>cxgbei(4)</tt> man page is missing but will be
	  committed shortly.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The driver is in advanced stage QA and will see some
	  bugfixes and performance enhancements in the very near
	  future.  MFC is possible as soon as the QA cycle
	  completes.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>OpenBSM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Christian</given>
	  <common>Brueffer</common>
	</name>
	<email>brueffer@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>TrustedBSD audit mailing list</name>
	<email>trustedbsd-audit@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.openbsm.org">OpenBSM: Open Source Basic Security Module (BSM) Audit Implementation</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm">OpenBSM on GitHub</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/audit.html">&os; Audit Handbook Chapter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenBSM is a BSD-licensed implementation of Sun's Basic
	Security Module (BSM) API and file format.  It is the
	user-space side of the CAPP Audit implementations in &os; and
	Mac OS X. Additionally, the audit trail processing tools are
	expected to work on Linux.</p>

      <p>Progress has been slow but steady this quarter, culminating
	in OpenBSM 1.2 alpha 4, the first release in three years.  It
	features various bug fixes and documentation improvements; the
	complete list of changes is documented in the
	<a href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm/blob/master/NEWS">NEWS</a>
	file on GitHub.  The release was imported into &os; HEAD and
	merged to &os; 10-STABLE.  As such, it will be part of &os;
	10.3-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Test the new release on different versions of &os;, Mac OS
	  X, and Linux.  In particular, testing on Mac OS X 10.9
	  (Mavericks) and newer would be greatly appreciated.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix problems that have been reported via GitHub and the
	  &os; bug tracker.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Implement features mentioned in the
	  <a href="https://github.com/openbsm/openbsm/blob/master/TODO">TODO</a>
	  list on GitHub.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Marvell Armada38x</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcin</given>
	  <common>Wojtas</common>
	</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Stanek</common>
	</name>
	<email>mst@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bartosz</given>
	  <common>Szczepanek</common>
	</name>
	<email>bsz@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jan</given>
	  <common>Dabros</common>
	</name>
	<email>jsd@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>&os; has been ported to run on the Marvell Armada38x
	platform.  This SoC family boasts single/dual high-performance
	ARM Cortex-A9 CPUs.</p>

      <p>The multi-user SMP system is fully working and has been
	tested on Marvell DB-88F6288-GP and SolidRun ClearFog
	development boards.</p>

      <p>The root filesystem can be hosted on a USB 3.0/2.0 drive or
	via NFS using a PCIe network card.  Experimental support is
	available for on-chip Gigabit Ethernet (NETA).</p>

      <p>Additional features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>GIC+MPIC cascaded interrupts courtesy of INTRNG</li>

	<li>CESA dual-channel cryptographic engine</li>

	<li>USB 3.0 and 2.0</li>

	<li>PCIe 2.0</li>

	<li>I2C</li>

	<li>GPIO</li>

	<li>Watchdog</li>

	<li>RTC</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The port is under community review and will be integrated
	into HEAD soon.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Stormshield
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Semihalf
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Optimize performance of NETA and prepare for
	  submission.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Bringing GitLab into the Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Z&uuml;hlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>ports@toco-domains.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=202468">PR for the new Port</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/t-zuehlsdorff/gitlabhq/blob/master/doc/install/installation-FreeBSD.md">Installation Guide</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/gitlabhq/gitlabhq/">Upstream GitLab website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>GitLab is a web-based Git repository manager with many
	features that is used by more than 100,000 organizations
	including NASA and Alibaba.  It also is a very long-standing
	entry on the &quot;Wanted Ports&quot; list of the &os;
	Wiki.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter, there was steady progress in the project
	itself and the porting.  The current release of GitLab 8.3 is
	now based on Rails 4.2, which obsoletes the need for around 50
	new ports.  Now there are only 5 dependencies left to be
	committed!</p>

      <p>While the new version of GitLab 8.3 eases the porting, there
	are big changes since the last working port of GitLab 7.14.
	Nonetheless, it could be expected to see the next working port
	in the first quarter of 2016.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      anyMOTION GRAPHICS GmbH, D&uuml;sseldorf, Germany
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Update the patches from GitLab 7.14 to 8.3.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Update the documentation.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Provide an updated patch.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>IPv6 Promotion Campaign</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Z&uuml;hlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>ports@toco-domains.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IPv6PortsTODO" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are more and more machines on the internet that
	<strong>only</strong> support IPv6.  I manage some of them,
	and was regularly hit by missing IPv6 support when building
	ports.</p>

      <p>I did some research into the impact of missing IPv6 support
	on the ports tree.  The results are that 10,308 of 25,522
	ports are not fetchable when using IPv6.  This renders,
	through dependencies, a total of 17,715 ports unbuildable from
	IPv6-only systems.  All you can do then is wait and hope that
	<tt>distcache.FreeBSD.org</tt> caches the distfile.  But this
	will take some time, which might not be a luxury available
	when a piece of software in use is hit by a security
	issue.</p>

      <p>Based on the research, a promotion campaign for IPv6 was
	started.  Some volunteers will contact the relevant system
	administrators and try to convince them to support IPv6.  This
	will start in January 2016 and will hopefully create some
	progress soon.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>KDE on &os; team</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/">KDE on &os; website</url>
      <url href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">Experimental KDE ports staging area</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/KDE">KDE on &os; Wiki</url>
      <url href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-FreeBSD">KDE/&os; Mailing List</url>
      <url href="http://src.mouf.net/area51/log/branches/plasma5">Development Repository for Integrating KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE on &os; team focuses on packaging and making sure
	that the experience of KDE and Qt on &os; is as good as
	possible.</p>

      <p>The team kept busy during the last quarter of 2015.  Quite
	a few big updates were committed to the ports tree, and a few
	more are being worked on in our experimental repository.</p>

      <p>As in previous quarters, we would like to thank several
	people who have contributed with machines, patches, and
	general help.  Tobias Berner, &a.madpilot; (madpilot@),
	Adriaan de Groot, Ralf Nolden, &a.swills; (swills@), and
	&a.jpaetzel; (jpaetzel@) have been essential to our work.</p>

      <p>The following big updates landed in the ports tree this
	quarter.  In many cases, we have also contributed patches to
	the upstream projects.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>CMake 3.4.0 and 3.4.1</li>

	<li>Calligra 2.9.1, the latest release of the integrated
	  work applications suite.  Calligra had last been updated in
	  the ports tree at the end of 2013!</li>

	<li>PyQt4 4.11.4, QScintilla2 2.9.1 and SIP 4.17.</li>

	<li>PyQt5 5.5.1.  Thanks to the work spearheaded by Guido
	  Falsi and Tobias Berner in the previous quarter, the PyQt5
	  ports have finally been committed to the ports tree.  Not
	  only was this long-awaited on its own, it allows other ports
	  to be updated to their latest versions.</li>

	<li>QtCreator 3.5.1 and 3.6.0.</li>

	<li>A couple of Qt5 packaging bugs were fixed: it should now
	  be more straightforward to use the Qt5 ports to build
	  software outside the ports tree, and it is now possible to
	  build ports that require a C++11 compiler and Qt5 on &os;
	  9.x.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Work on updating the Qt5 ports to their latest version, as
	well as porting KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5 to &os;, is well
	under way in our experimental area51 repository.  At the
	moment, it contains Qt5 5.5.1, KDE Frameworks 5.17.0, Plasma
	5.5.1 and KDE Applications 15.12.0.</p>

      <p>Users interested in testing those ports are encouraged to
	follow the instructions in
	<a href="https://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">our website</a>
	and report their results to our mailing list.  Qt5 5.5.1 is in
	our &quot;qt-5.5&quot; branch, and Plasma 5 and the rest is in
	the &quot;plasma5&quot; branch (which also contains Qt
	5.5.1).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Commit the Qt5 5.5.1 update.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Land the KDE Frameworks 5 and Plasma 5 ports in the
	  tree.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Investigate what needs to be done to make QtWebEngine,
	  the Chromium-based replacement for QtWebKit, work on
	  &os;.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Frederic</given>
	  <common>Culot</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Frederic</given>
	  <common>Culot</common>
	</name>
	<email>culot@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">Ports Collection Landing Page</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">Contributor's Guide</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">Ports Monitoring Service</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team Website</url>
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr">Portmgr on Facebook</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As of the end of the fourth quarter, the ports tree holds a
	bit more than 25,000 ports, and the PR count is around 2,000.
	The activity on the ports tree remains steady, with about
	7,000 commits performed by almost 120 active committers.</p>

      <p>On the problem reports front, figures show an encouraging
	trend, with a significant increase in the number of PRs fixed
	during Q4.  Indeed, almost 1,800 reports were fixed, which
	makes an increase of about 20% compared to Q3.</p>

      <p>In Q4, eight commit bits were taken in for safekeeping,
	following an inactivity period of more than 18 months (lioux,
	lippe, simon, jhay, max, sumikawa, alexey, sperber).  Three
	new developers were granted a ports commit bit (Kenji Takefu,
	Carlos Puga Medina, and Ian Lepore), and one returning
	committer (miwi) had his commit bit reinstated.</p>

      <p>Also related to the management of ports commit bits, nox's
	grants were revoked, since the &os; developers learned that
	Juergen Lock had passed away.</p>

      <p>On the management side, no changes were made to the portmgr
	team during Q4.</p>

      <p>On QA side 33 exp-runs were performed to validate sensitive
	updates or cleanups.  Amongst those noticeable changes are the
	update to GCC 4.9, CMake to 3.4.1, PostgreSQL to 9.4, and
	ruby-gems to 2.5.0.  Some infrastructure changes included the
	usage of a <tt>WRKSRC</tt> different from <tt>WRKDIR</tt> when
	<tt>NO_WRKSUBDIR</tt> is set, the removal of
	<tt>bsd.cpu.mk</tt> from <tt>sys.mk</tt>, and the move of
	<tt>QT_NONSTANDARD</tt> to <tt>bsd.qt.mk</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>We would like to remind everyone that the ports tree is
	  built and run by volunteers, and any help is greatly
	  appreciated.  While Q4 saw a significant increase in the
	  number of problem reports fixed, we encourage all ports
	  committers to have a look at the issues reported by our
	  users and try to fix as many as possible.  Many thanks to
	  all who made a contribution during Q4, and keep up the
	  good work in 2016!</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Issue Tracking (Bugzilla)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Bugmeisters</name>
	<email>bugmeister@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mahdi</given>
	  <common>Mokhtari</common>
	</name>
	<email>mokhi64@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla Home Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The bugmeister team has gained a new member, Mahdi Mokhtari
	(mokhi64@gmail.com).  Mahdi has been contributing to the &os;
	Project for just over one month.  After getting started by
	creating ports for Chef-Server and MySQL 5.7 (with Bernard
	Spil's help), an introduction to &a.koobs; led to guidance on
	appropriate projects, such as Bugzilla development to help
	Bugmeister, the Bugzilla Triage team, Developers, and the
	community by making issue tracking better.  This is how things
	are going so far:</p>

      <p>Issue Tracking can be either &quot;Defect Tracking for
	Systems&quot; or &quot;Bug-Tracking for Systems&quot;.  System
	Defect Tracking is to allow individual or groups of developers
	to keep track of outstanding issues in their product
	effectively.  We use Bugzilla to manage issues for the &os;
	project.</p>

      <p>We are pleased to announce some developments on our issue
	management systems:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>We have made improvements to the AutoAssigner module
	  (not yet deployed) that was previously developed by &a.mva;
	  to assign port bugs to their maintainers by default, such
	  as:

	  <ul>
	    <li>Improvements and bugfixes to port detection in
	      the Summary: field of issues, for automatic assignment
	      to their maintainers in a better way.</li>

	    <li>Refactoring code to make future development easier
	      and faster in a more modular way.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>We have developed a new module (FBSDAttachment), which
	  automates setting maintainer-approval flag values on
	  attachments under most conditions.  This will improve time
	  to resolution, consistency of triage, and reduce manual
	  effort by triagers and maintainers.</li>

	<li>We reported and upstreamed a number of bugs in Bugzilla,
	  working with the upstream Bugzilla developers.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Major improvements to templates for usability and
	  simplicity.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Further improvements to automation (for example,
	  additional processing of commit logs).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Root Remount</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=290548">Commit to Head</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/head/sbin/reboot/reboot.8?r1=290548&amp;r2=290547&amp;pathrev=290548"><tt>reboot(8)</tt> Manual Page Changes</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>One of the long-missing features of &os; was the ability to
	boot up with a temporary rootfs, configure the kernel to be
	able to access the real rootfs, and then replace the temporary
	root with the real one.  In Linux, this functionality is known
	as pivot_root.  The reroot projects provides similar
	functionality in a different, slightly more user-friendly way:
	rerooting.  Simply put, from the user point of view it looks
	like the system performs a partial shutdown, killing all
	processes and unmounting the rootfs, and then partial bringup,
	mounting the new rootfs, running init, and running the startup
	scripts as usual.</p>

      <p>The project is finished.  All the relevant code has been
	committed to &os; 11-CURRENT and is expected to ship with &os;
	11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>RCTL Disk IO Limits</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>An important missing piece of the RCTL resource limits
	mechanism was the ability to limit disk throughput.  This
	project aims to fill that hole by making it possible to add
	RCTL rules for read bytes per second (BPS), write BPS, read
	I/O operations per second (IOPS), and write IOPS.  It also
	adds a new throttling mechanism to delay process execution
	when a limit is reached.</p>

      <p>The project is at the late implementation stage.  The major
	piece of work left apart from testing is to integrate it with
	ZFS.  The project is expected to ship with &os; 11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os;&nbsp;Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/releases/10.3R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;10.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os; Development Snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is responsible for setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project releases
	of &os;, announcing code freezes, and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>During the last quarter of 2015, the Release Engineering team
	added support for three additional &os;/arm systems:
	<tt>BANANAPI</tt>, <tt>CUBIEBOARD</tt>, and
	<tt>CUBIEBOARD2</tt>.</p>

      <p>In addition to regular development snapshot builds for
	&os;&nbsp;11.0-CURRENT and &os;&nbsp;10.2-STABLE, several
	changes and enhancements were made to the release build code.
	Of note, the release build code no longer produces MD5
	checksums, in favor of SHA512.</p>

      <p>Toward the end of the year, focus was primarily
	centered on the upcoming &os;&nbsp;10.3 release cycle,
	which will begin in January 2016.</p>

      <p>As always, help testing development snapshot builds is
	crucial to producing quality releases, and we encourage
	testing development snapshots whenever possible.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>MMC Stack Under CAM Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ilya</given>
	  <common>Bakulin</common>
	</name>
	<email>ilya@bakulin.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bakulin.de/FreeBSD/mmccam.html">Project Information</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/kibab/FreeBSD/tree/mmccam">Source Code</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4761">Patch for Review</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of this project is to reimplement the existing
	MMC/SD stack using the CAM framework.  This will permit
	utilizing the well-tested CAM locking model and debug
	features.  It will also be possible to process interrupts
	generated by the inserted card, which is a prerequisite for
	implementing the SDIO interface.</p>

      <p>The first version of the code was uploaded to Phabricator for
	review.  The new stack is able to attach to the SD card and
	bring it to an operational state so it is possible to read and
	write to the card.</p>

      <p>The only supported SD controller driver is <tt>ti_sdhci</tt>,
	which is used on the BeagleBone Black.  Modifying other
	SDHCI-compliant drivers should not be difficult.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Rework bus/target/LUN enumeration and the locking model.
	  I do not really understand the CAM locking and am likely to
	  do it incorrectly.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Modify the SDHCI driver on at least one x86 platform.
	  This will make development and collaboration easier.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Begin implementing SDIO-specific bits.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="proj">
    <title>The Graphics Stack on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Graphics team</name>
	<email>freebsd-x11@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Graphics">Graphics Stack Roadmap and Supported Hardware Matrix</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/freebsd-ports-graphics">Ports Development Tree on GitHub</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Several important ports were updated: Mesa to 11.0.8, the
	X.Org server to 1.17.4, libdrm to 2.4.65, as well as many
	applications and libraries.  The latest release of the X.Org
	server, 1.18, is being tested in our Ports development
	tree.</p>

      <p>On the kernel side, the i915 update is almost ready to
	land.  There are a couple known regressions for currently
	supported GPUs that we want to fix before committing.</p>

      <p>We started a discussion on the FreeBSD-x11@ mailing list to
	organize future contributions to the kernel drivers.  We have
	already received some valuable comments.  We are confident
	that future updates will happen at a faster pace, thanks to
	several motivated people!</p>

      <p>FOSDEM is held in Brussels on the 30th and 31st of January.
	We will attend this conference.  It will be a perfect time to
	see people again from &os; and from the XDC.  On Sunday, we
	will give a talk about how to contribute to the Graphics
	Stack.</p>

      <p>Our blog is currently down because the service was
	discontinued.  We hope to get a dump of our data to put it
	back online elsewhere.  Unfortunately, there is no ETA for
	this item.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>See the &quot;Graphics&quot; wiki page for up-to-date
	  information.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Encrypted Kernel Crash Dumps</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konrad</given>
	  <common>Witaszczyk</common>
	</name>
	<email>def@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-security/2015-December/008780.html">Technical Details</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4712">Patch Review</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Kernel crash dumps contain information about currently
	running processes.  This can include sensitive data, for
	example passwords kept in memory by a browser when a kernel
	panic occurred.  An entity that can read data from a dump
	device or a crash directory can also extract this information
	from a core dump.  To prevent this situation, the core dump
	should be encrypted before it is stored on the dump
	device.</p>

      <p>This project allows a kernel to encrypt a core dump during
	a panic.  A user can configure the kernel for encrypted dumps
	and save the core dump after reboot using the existing tools,
	<tt>dumpon(8)</tt> and <tt>savecore(8)</tt>.  A new tool
	<tt>decryptcore(8)</tt> was added to decrypt the core
	files.</p>

      <p>A patch has been uploaded to Phabricator for review.  The
	patch is currently being updated to address the review
	comments, and should be committed as soon as it is accepted.
	For more technical details, please visit the FreeBSD-security
	mailing list archive or see the Phabricator review.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Issue Triage Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Bugmeister</name>
	<email>bugmeister@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Vladimir</given>
	  <common>Krstulja</common>
	</name>
	<email>vlad-fbsd@acheronmedia.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rodrigo N.</given>
	  <common>Hernandez</common>
	</name>
	<email>rodrigo.FreeBSD@minasambiente.com.br</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://pad.riseup.net/p/FreeBSD-triage-brainstorming">Issue Triage Team's Brainstorming Pad</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>By the end of the Q4 2015 period, &a.koobs; (koobs@)
	started an initiative to form an experimental Bugzilla Triage
	Team.  The main goals of the team are to increase community
	involvement (addition/training of new triagers) and enhance
	current procedures and tools, among others.  This experiment
	was started with the participation of Vladimir (blackflow on
	irc/freenode) and Rodrigo (DanDare on irc/freenode), who
	approached koobs@ with a desire to contribute and get more
	involved with the &os; Project.  This experimental pilot
	project has the task of setting up procedures for enhanced
	Issue (Problem Report) management that include better
	classification and prioritization, eventually leading to
	faster resolution of issues.</p>

      <p>We are now happy to report on the progress of this
	experimental team:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The #FreeBSD-bugs IRC channel has been set up on Freenode
	  and we are successfully using it to exchange information
	  about triage processes, ask for help, propose changes and
	  discuss related topics.</li>

	<li>We have identified the primary role of an Issue Triage
	  Team to be that of classification of problem reports of all
	  kinds (currently limited mostly to ports and obvious src
	  issues) and facilitation of issue assignment, which is
	  making sure that the reported issues are explained well,
	  contain all the appropriate information (or as much of it as
	  possible), and are brought to attention of the people who
	  can act upon them.</li>

	<li>Vladimir and Rodrigo are successfully training in bug
	  triage as well as porting processes (Vladimir is also taking
	  maintainership of some ports).</li>

	<li>This experiment is benefiting from the introduction of
	  newcomers to issue tracking.  It naturally resulted in a
	  entire review of the tracking process from its very
	  elementary aspects.  This &quot;fresh eyes&quot;
	  participation spotted minor details during the process,
	  giving the opportunity to scrutinize actual procedures on a
	  number of smaller points, followed by proposals on how to
	  improve the overall Issue Tracking and Management.  The new
	  ideas include both organizational and technical ideas and
	  solutions, such as new or modified keywords or flags for
	  better classification, the triage workflow, and Bugzilla
	  technical improvements, among others.</li>

	<li>An important goal is producing documentation about best
	  practices for using Bugzilla and issue management workflow.
	  This documentation should be aimed not only at people
	  directly engaged in issue triage tasks, but also at general
	  users.  Another relevant point is that feedback from the triage
	  team can be used to improve Bugzilla in terms of adjusting
	  existing features to best fit &os;'s needs, and the development
	  of new features (please see Mahdi &quot;Magic&quot;
	  Mokhtari's report on &quot;Bugzilla
	  improvements&quot;).</li>

	<li>We are still collating ideas in preparation of setting up
	  a Wiki namespace for the overall topic of issue management,
	  containing information for all the parties involved in issue
	  tracking: from users (reporters) to maintainers and
	  committers.  The unorganized brainstorming document is
	  linked in this report.</li> </ul>

      <p>Since the Issue Triage Team is very young, we expect more
	information be available and more actions to be reported in the
	next status report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Set up the Wiki namespace and organize the brainstorming
	  document into a meaningful set of documents.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>We are actively recruiting to grow our &os; Triage Team.
	  If you are interested in participating and contributing to
	  one of the most important community-facing areas of the &os;
	  project, join #freebsd-bugs on the freenode IRC and let us
	  know!</p>

	<p>Experience with issue tracking is desirable, but not
	  required.  No prior internal project knowledge or technical
	  skills are required, just bring your communication skills
	  and awesome attitude.  Training is provided.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title><tt>relaunchd</tt></title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Heily</common>
	</name>
	<email>mark@heily.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/mheily/relaunchd">Development tree on GitHub</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>relaunchd</tt> project provides a service
	management daemon that is similar to the original
	<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Launchd">launchd</a>
	introduced in Apple OS X.</p>

      <p>It is not limited to the original features of
	<tt>launchd</tt>, however: interesting work is being done to
	add support for launching programs in jails, passing socket
	descriptors from the host to a jail, and launching programs
	within a preconfigured <tt>capsicum(4)</tt> sandbox.
	Additionally, <tt>relaunchd</tt> uses UCL for its
	configuration files, so jobs can be defined in JSON or other
	formats supported by UCL.</p>

      <p>While there is still work to be done, most of the important
	features of the original <tt>launchd</tt> have been
	implemented, and <tt>relaunchd</tt> has been made available in
	the &os; Ports Collection.  It should still be considered
	experimental and not ready for production use, but everyone is
	welcome to try it, report issues, and contribute code or ideas
	for improvement.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add support for restarting jobs if they crash.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Implement the <tt>cron(8)</tt> emulation feature.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for monitoring files and directories for
	  changes and launching jobs when changes are detected.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Finish things that are incomplete, such as support for
	  jails and passing open socket descriptors to child
	  processes.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve the documentation and provide more examples of
	  usage.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; Integration Services (BIS)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dexuan</given>
	  <common>Cui</common>
	</name>
	<email>decui@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hongjiang</given>
	  <common>Zhang</common>
	</name>
	<email>honzhan@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HyperV">&os; Virtual Machines on Microsoft Hyper-V</url>
      <url href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn531030.aspx">Linux and &os; Virtual Machines on Hyper-V</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>When &os; virtual machines (VMs) run on Hyper-V, using
	Hyper-V synthetic devices is recommended to get the best
	network and storage performance and make full use of all the
	benefits that Hyper-V provides.  The collection of drivers
	that are required to run Hyper-V synthetic devices in &os; are
	known as &os; Integration Services (BIS).  Some of the BIS
	drivers (like network and storage drivers) have existed in
	&os; 9.x and 10.x for years, but there are still some
	performance and stability issues and bugs.  Compared with
	Windows and Linux VMs, the current BIS lacks some important
	features, such as virtual Receive Side Scaling (vRSS) support
	in the Hyper-V network driver and support for UEFI VM (boot
	from UEFI), among others.</p>

      <p>We are now working more on the issues and performance tuning
	to make &os; VMs run better on Hyper-V and the Hyper-V based
	cloud platform Azure.</p>

      <p>Our work during 2015Q4 is documented below:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Optimizing the VMBus driver and Hyper-V network driver
	  for performance:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Sent out patches to enable <tt>INTR_MPSAFE</tt> for
	      the interrupt handling thread, speed up relid-to-channel
	      lookup in the thread by map table, and optimize the
	      VMBus ringbuffer writable notification to the host.</li>

	    <li>Developing a patch to enable the virtual Receive
	      Side Scaling (vRSS) for Hyper-V network device driver.
	      This will greatly improve the network performance for
	      SMP virtual machine (VM).</li>

	    <li>Sent out a patch to enable the Hyper-V timer, which
	      will improve the accuracy of timekeeping when &os; VMs
	      run on Hyper-V.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>Fixing bugs and cleaning up the code:
	  <ul>
	    <li>Fixed a bug in checksum offloading (PR 203630
	      &mdash; [Hyper-V] [nat] [tcp] 10.2 NAT bug in TCP stack
	      or hyperv netsvc driver) in the Hyper-V network driver,
	      making &os; VM based NAT gateways work more
	      reliably.</li>

	    <li>Fixed a serialization issue in the initialization of
	      VMBus devices, fixing PR 205156 ([Hyper-V] NICs' (hn0,
	      hn1) MAC addresses can appear in an uncertain way across
	      reboot).</li>

	    <li>Fixed a KVP (Key-Value Pair) issue (retrieving a
	      key's value can hang for an uncertain period of
	      time).</li>

	    <li>Added ioctl support for SIOCGIFMEDIA for the Hyper-V
	      network driver, fixing PR 187006 ([Hyper-V] dynamic
	      address (DHCP) obtaining does not work on HYPER-V OS
	      2012 R2).</li>

	    <li>Sent out patches to add an interrupt counter for
	      Hyper-V VMBus interrupts (so the user can easily get
	      statistical information about VMBus interrupts),
	      and fix the KVP daemon's poll timeout (so the daemon
	      will avoid unnecessary polling every 100
	      milliseconds.</li>

	    <li>Identified a TSC calibration issue: the i8254 PIT
	      timer emulation of Hyper-V is not fully reliable, so
	      the Hyper-V time counter should be used to calibrate
	      the TSC.  A patch was drafted.  With the patch, it looks
	      the warning kernel message (e.g., &quot;calcru: runtime
	      went backwards from 46204978 usec to 23362331 usec for
	      pid 0 (kernel)&quot;) will go away, and the time-based
	      tracing of Dtrace will be more accurate.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>We plan to add support for UEFI VMs (Hyper-V Generation-2
	  VMs).  Currently some issues and to-do items were
	  identified.  For example, we cannot use the i8254 PIT to
	  calibrate the TSC because the i8254 PIT does not exist in a
	  UEFI VM, and we need to add support for the Hyper-V
	  synthetic keyboard/mouse/framebuffer device.</li>

	<li>We are working on a disk detection issue: when a &os; VM
	  runs on a Windows Server 2016 Technical Preview host, the VM
	  will detect 16 disks when only one disk is configured for
	  the VM.  VMs running on these hosts can fail to boot.  A
	  workaround patch was created and we are trying to make a
	  formal fix.</li>

	<li>We are tidying up some internal BIS test cases and plan
	  to publish them on github.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Microsoft
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Mellanox iSCSI Extensions for RDMA (iSER) Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Max</given>
	  <common>Gurtovoy</common>
	</name>
	<email>maxg@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sagi</given>
	  <common>Grimberg</common>
	</name>
	<email>sagig@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>

    </contact>

    <links>
    <url href="https://github.com/sagigrimberg/iser-FreeBSD">GitHub repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Building on the new in-kernel iSCSI initiator stack
	released in &os; 10.0 and the recently added iSCSI offload
	interface, Mellanox Technologies has developed iSCSI
	extensions for RDMA (iSER) initiator support to enable
	efficient data movement using the hardware offload
	capabilities of Mellanox's 10, 40, 56, and 100 Gigabit
	Infiniband (IB)/Ethernet adapters.</p>

      <p>Remote Direct Memory Access (RDMA) has been shown to have
	great value for storage applications.  RDMA infrastructure
	provides benefits such as zero-copy, CPU offload, reliable
	transport, fabric consolidation, and many more.  The iSER
	protocol eliminates some of the bottlenecks in the traditional
	iSCSI/TCP stack, provides low latency and high throughput, and
	is well suited for latency aware workloads.</p>

      <p>This work includes a new ICL module that implements the iSER
	initiator.  The iSCSI stack is slightly modified to support
	some extra features such as asynchronous IO completions,
	unmapped data buffers, and data-transfer offloads.  The user
	will be able to choose iSER as the iSCSI transport with
	iscsictl.</p>

      <p>The project is in the process of being merged to &os;
	11-CURRENT and is expected to ship with &os; 11.0.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Improvements for ARMv6/v7 Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dominik</given>
	  <common>Ermel</common>
	</name>
	<email>der@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wojciech</given>
	  <common>Macek</common>
	</name>
	<email>wma@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zbigniew</given>
	  <common>Bodek</common>
	</name>
	<email>zbb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Numerous improvements for the ARMv6/v7 kernel and tools
	have been developed by the Semihalf team.  Those include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fixes for KGDB support.</li>

	<li>Support for branch instructions in <tt>ptrace</tt> single
	  stepping.</li>

	<li>Fixes for kernel minidumps.</li>

	<li>Improvements for LIBUSBBOOT.</li>

	<li>Support for Exynos EHCI in the loader.</li>

	<li>A fix for instruction single stepping in DDB.</li>

	<li>Support for hardware watchpoints, including watchpoints
	  on SMP systems.</li>

	<li>Single stepping using the ARM Debug Architecture.</li>

	<li>Support for gzip-compressed kernel modules in
	  <tt>kldload</tt>.</li>

	<li>Backport of the new pmap VM code to &os; 10-STABLE (not
	  yet sent to upstream).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Most of the introduced changes have been committed to HEAD
	and more are on the way.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Juniper Networks Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      Semihalf
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Finish upstreaming the hardware watchpoints support.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Two major issues have occupied much of core's attention
	during the last quarter: the reorganisation of the Security
	Team and the question of whether to import GPLv3 licensed code
	into the source repository.</p>

      <ol>
	<li>
	  <p>The idea of reorganizing the Security team was first
	    proposed to Core during a meeting at BSDCan this year by
	    Gleb Smirnoff &mdash; core member and newly-appointed
	    deputy Security Officer (SO).  The &quot;Security
	    Team&quot;, which previously could contain several people
	    (a varying number over time, but more than two) has been
	    refashioned into just two roles: Security Officer and
	    Deputy Security Officer.  Accordingly, the role of the SO
	    team has been redefined to be the controller of the
	    distribution of security sensitive information into and
	    within the project: they are responsible for interfacing
	    with external bodies and individuals reporting security
	    problems to the project, and connecting those reports to
	    the appropriate individuals within the project with the
	    technical expertise to address the identified concerns.
	    These changes will improve the project's responsiveness to
	    security alerts, help maintain security on privileged
	    information received in confidence before general
	    publication and, not least, reduce the work load on the
	    security officer.  The SO team will continue to benefit
	    from liasons with the Core, Cluster Administration, and
	    Release Engineering teams, and will be assisted by a
	    secretary; they will also be able to obtain input and
	    assistance in drafting security advisories from former and
	    potential future (Deputy) Security Officers.</p>

	  <p>Core would particularly like to thank the former members
	    of the Security Team group for their past contributions,
	    now that the Security Team role has been merged into the
	    Security Officer's responsibilities.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>The other large question concerning Core is how to
	    provide a modern toolchain for all supported achitectures.
	    Tier 1 architectures are required to ship with a toolchain
	    unencumbered by onerous license terms.  This is currently
	    provided for i386 and arm64 by the LLVM suite, including
	    the Clang compiler, LLD and LLDB.  However LLVM support
	    for other (Tier 2 or below) architectures is not yet of
	    sufficient quality to be viable, and the older but
	    pre-existing GPLv2 toolchain cannot support some of the
	    interesting new architectures such as arm64 and RISC-V.
	    Pragmatically, in order for the project to support
	    these architectures,
	    until LLVM support arrives we must turn to the GNU
	    project's GPLv3 licenced toolchain.</p>

	  <p>The argument here is whether to import GPLv3 licensed
	    code into the &os; src repository with all of the
	    obligations on patent terms and source code redistribution
	    that would entail, not only for the &os; project itself
	    but for numerous downstream consumers of &os; code.  Not
	    having a toolchain readily available is a big impediment
	    to working on a new architecture.</p>

	  <p>One potential solution is to create a range of
	    &quot;GPLv3 toolchain&quot; base-system packages out of a
	    completely separate source code repository, for instance
	    within the &os; area on Github.  These would be
	    distributed equivalently to the other base system binary
	    packages when that mechanism is introduced.</p>

	  <p>Core recognises that this is a decision with wide-ranging
	    consequences and will be producing a position paper for
	    circulation amongst all interested parties in order to
	    judge community opinion on the matter.  Core welcomes
	    feedback from all interested parties on the subject.</p>
	</li>
      </ol>

      <p>Beyond these two big questions, Core has handled a number of
	lesser items:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Core approved the formation of a wiki-admin team to take
	  over managing the Wiki, to curate the Wiki content and work
	  on navigation and organization of existing technical content
	  and to evaluate new Wiki software with the aim of opening up
	  the Wiki to contributions from the public.</li>

	<li>An external review board has been assembled to look at
	  the Code of Conduct, including a mixture of project members
	  and experts from external groups.  The review process is
	  getting under way and Core is awaiting their report.</li>

	<li>The standard documentation license was found to be
	  unfit for its purpose, and the doceng group had temporarily
	  reverted to the previous license while a new replacement was
	  drafted.  This new license is now the default for new
	  documentation submissions.  However, one factor emerging
	  from this review was the difficulty of maintaining correct
	  authorial attributions for sections of documentation, some
	  of which may only be a few words long.  Unlike source code,
	  blocks of documentation are frequently moved around within
	  individual files, or even between files.  Consequently, Core
	  would like to introduce a Voluntary Contribution
	  Agreement along the lines of the one operated by the
	  Apache Foundation.  With this, copyrights are signed over to
	  the &os; Foundation, with individual contributions being
	  recognised by recording names in a general
	  &quot;Authors&quot; file.  This will be another alternative
	  alongside the existing copyright mechanisms used in the
	  project.  Core is interested to hear any opinions on the
	  subject.</li>

	<li>Core approved the formation of a new
	  &quot;dev-announce&quot; mailing list, which all &os;
	  committers should be members of.  This will be a low-traffic
	  moderated list to contain important announcements,
	  heads-ups, warnings of code freezes, changes in policy and
	  notifications of events that affect the project as a
	  whole.</li>

	<li>Around eight years ago, an attempt was made to import the
	  OpenBSD sensors framework.  This was rejected at the time as
	  potentially blocking the development of a better designed
	  framework.  However, no such development has occurred in the
	  intervening time whilst the sensors framework has been in
	  use successfully by both OpenBSD and FreeNAS.  Despite some
	  concerns about the efficiency of the framework and potential
	  impacts on power consumption and hence battery lifetime,
	  core is minded to approve the import, but wants to consult
	  with interested developers first.</li>

	<li>Core is exploring the legal ramifications for the project
	  of the &quot;Right to Be Forgotten&quot; established by
	  the European Court of Justice.</li>

	<li>Core is also seeking an alternative means for holding
	  their regular monthly conference calls.  The current,
	  paid-for, service has less than satisfactory sound quality
	  and reliability, and Core would like to switch to a free
	  video conferencing solution.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>This quarter also saw a particularly large influx of new
	commit bit requests, with on occasion, four votes running
	simultaneously.  Please welcome Kurt Lidl, Svatopluk Kraus,
	Michal Meloun, Jonathan Looney (Juniper), Daisuke Aoyama, Phil
	Shafer (Juniper), Ravi Pokala (Panasas), Anish Gupta and Mark
	Bloch (Mellanox) to the ranks of src committers.  In addition,
	core was delighted to restore commit privileges for Eric
	Melville after a hiatus of many years.</p>

      <p>No commit bits were taken in during the quarter.  A
	non-committer account was approved for Kevin Bowling of
	LimeLight Networks.  Kevin will be doing systems
	administration work with clusteradm, with particular interest
	in the parts of the cluster that are now hosted in LLNW's
	facilities.  Deb Goodkin of the &os; Foundation was added to
	the developers mailing list: she was one of the few members of
	the Foundation Board not already on the list, and having
	awareness of what is going on in the developer community will
	help her to support the project more effectively.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Routing Stack Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Chernikov</common>
	</name>
	<email>melifaro@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/ProjectsRoutingProposal">Initial Proposal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>projects/routing</tt> Subversion branch is a FreeBSD
	routing system rework aimed at providing performance,
	scalability and the ability to add advanced features to the
	routing stack.</p>

      <p>The current packet output path suffers from excessive
	locking.  Acquiring and releasing four distinct contested
	locks is required to convert a packet to a frame suitable to
	put on the wire.  The first project goal is to reduce the
	number of locks needed to just two <tt>rmlock(9)</tt>s for the
	output path, which permits close-to-linear scaling.</p>

      <p>Since September, one of the locks (used to protect
	link-level entries) has been completely eliminated from the
	packet data path.  A new routing API was introduced, featuring
	better scalability and hiding routing internals.  Most of the
	consumers of the old routing API were converted to use the new
	API.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Base System Build Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>Drewery</common>
	</name>
	<email>bdrewery@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-arch/2015-December/017571.html">&os;-Arch Post Describing Plans</url>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2014/schedule/events/460.en.html">BSDCan 2014 META_MODE Presentation</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=290433">WITH_FAST_DEPEND Details</url>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=290526">WITH_CCACHE_BUILD Details</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&a.bdrewery; (bdrewery@) has been working to improve the
	build framework as well as <tt>buildworld</tt> build times.
	The build system has been largely untouched by large-scale
	changes for many years.  Most of the effort has been on
	improving the recent <tt>META_MODE</tt> merge that was
	presented at BSDCan 2014.  This is a new build system that is
	not currently enabled by default but brings many benefits.
	Beyond that, some highlights of the work changing
	<tt>buildworld</tt> are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>WITH_FAST_DEPEND</tt>, which avoids calling
	  &quot;mkdep&quot; during the <tt>make depend</tt> phase and
	  instead generates dependency files during compilation.  The
	  old scheme was pre-processing all source files twice.  The
	  new version saves 16-35% in build times.</li>

	<li><tt>WITH_CCACHE_BUILD</tt> adds built-in <tt>ccache</tt>
	  support, avoiding many of the historical pitfalls of
	  changing <tt>CC</tt> in <tt>make.conf</tt> to use
	  <tt>ccache</tt>.</li>

	<li>Many improvements for parallelization of the build.</li>

	<li><tt>LIBADD</tt> improvements to ensure proper usage of
	  this tool to replace duplicate <tt>LDADD</tt> and
	  <tt>DPADD</tt> statements.  Further work is under way to
	  reduce overlinking.</li>

	<li>A lot of cleanup of improper framework usage.</li>

	<li>Ensuring that installing files from the build tree fails
	  if the destination directory is missing, rather than
	  installing a file as the directory name.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      EMC / Isilon Storage Division
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>See the &os;-arch mail for more information on planned
	  work.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>ELF Tool Chain Tools</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://elftoolchain.sourceforge.net">ELF Tool Chain Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ELF Tool Chain project provides BSD-licensed
	implementations of compilation tools and libraries for
	building and analyzing ELF objects.  The project began as part
	of &os; but later became an independent project in order to
	encourage wider participation from others in the open-source
	developer community.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter of 2015 the ELF Tool Chain tools were
	updated to a snapshot of upstream Subversion revision 3272.
	Improvements include better input file validation, RISC-V
	support, support for Xen ELF notes, additional MIPS and ARM
	relocations, better performance, and bug fixes.</p>

      <p>The ELF Tool Chain project is planning a new release in
	the first quarter of 2016, which will facilitate wider
	testing and use by projects in addition to &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add missing functionality (PE/COFF support) to
	  <tt>elfcopy</tt> and migrate the base system build.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Fix issues found by fuzzing inputs to the tools.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add automatic support for separate debug files.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>The LLDB Debugger</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/lldb">&os; LLDB Wiki Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LLDB is the debugger from the LLVM family of projects.
	Originally developed for Mac OS X, it now also supports &os;,
	NetBSD, Linux, Android, and Windows.  It builds on existing
	components in the larger LLVM project, for example using
	Clang's expression parser and LLVM's disassembler.</p>

      <p>LLDB in the &os; base system was upgraded to version 3.7.0
	as part of the Clang and LLVM upgrade, and it will similarly
	be upgraded again to 3.8.0 for &os; 11.0-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>LLDB is now enabled by default on the amd64 and arm64
	platforms.  It is now a functional basic debugger on arm64,
	after a number of fixes were made in the last quarter to both
	LLDB and the &os; kernel.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Rework the LLDB build to use LLVM and Clang shared
	  libraries.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Port a remote debugging stub to &os;.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support for local and core file kernel debugging.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve support on architectures other than amd64 and
	  arm64.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>UEFI Boot and Framebuffer Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A number of UEFI bug fixes were committed over the last
	quarter, further improving compatibility with different UEFI
	implementations.  Specifically: on some implementations, &os;
	failed to boot with an &quot;ExitBootServices() returned
	0x8000000000000002&quot; error.  This has been fixed with a
	retry loop (as required by UEFI) in r292515 and r292338.</p>

      <p>UEFI improvements from other developers have recently been
	committed or are in progress.  These include support for
	environment variables set on the EFI loader command line,
	improved text console mode setting, support for nvram
	variables, and root-on-ZFS support.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Test &os;-CURRENT snapshots on a variety of UEFI
	  implementations.</p></task>

      <task>
	<p>Merge UEFI changes to stable/10 for &os;
	  10.3-RELEASE.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/">Foundation Website</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSDJournal.com/">FreeBSD Journal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit
	organization dedicated to supporting and promoting the &os;
	Project and community worldwide.  Funding comes from
	individual and corporate donations and is used to fund and
	manage development projects, conferences and developer
	summits, and provide travel grants to &os; developers.  The
	Foundation purchases hardware to improve and maintain &os;
	infrastructure and publishes &os; white papers and marketing
	material to promote, educate, and advocate for the &os;
	Project.  The Foundation also represents the &os; Project in
	executing contracts, license agreements, and other legal
	arrangements that require a recognized legal entity.</p>

      <p>Here are some highlights of what we did to help &os;
	last quarter:</p>

      <p>On the advocacy front, the Foundation attended and
	sponsored EuroBSDcon, which took place Oct 1-4
	(<a href="https://2015.eurobsdcon.org/">https://2015.eurobsdcon.org/</a>)
	in Stockholm, Sweden.  Two days prior, during the developer
	summit, Deb Goodkin ran a session on Recruiting to &os;.  The
	Foundation was also very active during the event itself; in
	addition to Deb, we had &a.dru;, &a.mckusick;, &a.erwin;,
	&a.emaste;, &a.hrs;, &a.bcr;, and &a.trasz; attend the
	conference.  Deb and Ed gave a presentation on how the
	Foundation supports a BSD project.  Kirk gave a presentation
	on &quot;a Brief History of the BSD Fast File System,&quot;
	and he taught the two-day tutorial &quot;Introduction to the
	&os; Open-Source Operating System.&quot;</p>

      <p>Deb then attended the 2015 Grace Hopper Conference that was
	held in Houston, TX, October 14-16.  The conference is for
	women in computing and most of the attendees were female
	computer science majors, female software developers, and
	college professors.  The Foundation was proud to be a Silver
	Sponsor.  The conference was very successful for us.  Our
	presence allowed us to raise awareness of the Project, help
	recruit more women, and get more professors to include &os; in
	their curriculum.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; traveled to Bangkok, Thailand to present talks on
	DTrace, &os;, and teaching with DTrace.  The talks were
	presented at Chulalongkorn University, which is the largest
	University in Thailand with the largest engineering school.
	The first talk was the practitioner's introduction to DTrace
	in which the technology, history and usage is explained
	without diving into all the kernel subsystems.  The second was
	the sales pitch for teaching with Dtrace and with &os;.  The
	pitch was well received and there were some very good points
	made by the audience.  The facts that the course materials are
	both open source and hosted on github were also well
	received.</p>

      <p>&a.mckusick; completed a 10-hour tutorial about &os; for
	Pearson Education in their &quot;Live Lesson&quot; program.
	In particular, there is a great free snippet from that course
	comparing &os; against Linux here:
	<a href="http://youtu.be/dTpqALCwQ1Y?a">http://youtu.be/dTpqALCwQ1Y?a</a>.
	Find out more about the whole session at:
	<a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=NZS3W7D*uS0&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=163217.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=3559&amp;RD_PARM1=http%253A%252F%252Fwww.informit.com%252Fstore%252Fintroduction-to-the-FreeBSD-open-source-operating-system-9780134305868">http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=NZS3W7D*uS0&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=163217.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=3559&amp;RD_PARM1=http%253A%252F%252Fwww.informit.com%252Fstore%252Fintroduction-to-the-freebsd-open-source-operating-system-9780134305868</a>.</p>

      <p>Anne Dickison resumed the Faces of &os; series with
	interviews featuring Michael Dexter and Erin Clark.  She also
	continued to produce and distribute &os; materials for
	conferences, as well as advocating for &os; over our social
	channels.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; headed up the latest Silicon Valley Vendor and
	Developer Summit, November 2-3, at the NetApp campus in
	Sunnyvale, California.  Topics of discussion ranged over new
	developments in persistent memory, the use of &os; by a
	company that builds rackscale systems, developments in our
	compiler and tool suite, as well as others.  Additional
	Foundation Board and Staff attending the summit included: Deb
	Goodkin, &a.gjb;, &a.gibbs;, &a.mckusick;, &a.emaste;, and
	&a.hrs;.  The complete schedule, and some of the slides, are
	available on the &os; Wiki
	<a href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201511VendorDevSummit">https://wiki.freebsd.org/201511VendorDevSummit</a>.</p>

      <p>Notes from the always lively &quot;Have/Need/Want
	session&quot; are available at
	<a href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201511VendorDevSummit/HaveNeedWant">https://wiki.freebsd.org/201511VendorDevSummit/HaveNeedWant</a>.</p>

      <p>While in the Bay Area, some Foundation members visited
	commercial users of &os; to help understand their needs,
	update them on the work the Foundation is doing, and
	facilitate collaboration between them and the Project.</p>

      <p>We were a sponsor of the 2015 OpenZFS Developer
	Summit, which took place October 19-20, in San Francisco, CA.
	&a.gibbs; and &a.mckusick; attended the conference.</p>

      <p>&a.gibbs; continued his semester long class teaching
	Intro to Computer Science using &os; at a middle
	school.</p>

      <p>&a.emaste;, &a.trasz;, and &a.kib; continue to make
	progress on Foundation funded development projects.  More
	specifically:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Ed Worked on a number of items relating to the
	  tool chain: LLD linker, ELF Tool Chain components, and LLDB
	  debugger, and tested, integrated, and merged outstanding
	  UEFI work.</li>

	<li>Edward finished work on the reroot project as well as
	  spending some time on a certificate-transparency port.  He
	  also implemented a prototype to support disk IO limit in
	  RCTL.</li>

	<li>Konstantin rewrote the out of memory killer logic, which,
	  in particular, fixed &os; operation on systems without swap,
	  especially systems with very little memory.  The latter are
	  becoming more and more common with popularity of embedded
	  ARM platforms were &os; runs, but it also affects large
	  systems which are usually configured without swap.  He also
	  finalized and committed the shared page support for the
	  ARMv7 and ARMv8 systems.  This allows for a non-executable
	  stack on ARMv7, and a much faster userspace
	  <tt>gettimeofday(2)</tt> for both, similar to x86.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>&a.emaste; presented a &os;/arm64 talk and a hands-on
	demo at ARM Techcon, which took place November 10-12, 2015, in
	Santa Clara, CA.</p>

      <p>We continued publishing our monthly newsletters and
	acquiring new company testimonials about using &os;, including
	from Verisign and Nginx.</p>

      <p>Anne Dickison, &a.dru;, and &a.gjb; represented the
	Foundation at USENIX LISA '15, which took place November 3-8,
	in Washington D.C..  The Foundation had a booth in the Expo
	Hall and participated in a BoF.  Besides connecting with
	current community members, we spoke with attendees who were
	interested in getting involved with the Project and helped
	set them on the correct path.  We also took the opportunity to
	remind those who had not used &os; in a while what they were
	missing.  Glen also attended the USENIX Release Engineering
	Summit, which was co-located with LISA '15.</p>

      <p>We published the Sept/Oct and Nov/Dec issues of the
	&os; Journal.</p>

      <p>&a.gnn; and &a.rwatson; announced the release of
	their TeachBSD initiative:
	<a href="http://teachbsd.com/">http://teachbsd.com/</a>.
	TeachBSD offers a set of reusable course materials designed to
	allow others to teach both university students and software
	practitioners &os; operating system fundamentals.  The
	Foundation is proud to have partly sponsored their efforts to
	teach the initial graduate level course on operating systems
	with tracing at the University of Cambridge.</p>

      <p>Deb Goodkin invited a representative from the
	Outreachy program to talk at the Ottawa &os; Developer Summit
	about the program and how we can get involved.</p>

      <p>Deb also started discussions with CS professors from
	the University of Colorado, Boulder to offer some Intro to
	&os; workshops.</p>

      <p>&a.gjb; continued wearing many hats to support to the
	Project.  For Release Engineering:
	<ul>
	  <li>Added support for building <tt>BANANAPI</tt>,
	    <tt>CUBIEBOARD</tt>, and <tt>CUBIEBOARD2</tt> arm
	    images.</li>

	  <li>Deprecated use of MD5 checksums used for verifying
	    installation media downloaded from the &os; Project
	    mirrors.</li>

	  <li>Various miscellaneous updates and fixes to release
	    build code.</li>

	  <li>Continued providing regular development snapshot
	    builds.</li>
	</ul>
	Under Systems Administration:
	<ul>
	  <li>Assisted the Admins team with migrating various
	    services to two new colocation facilities near Sunnyvale,
	    generously provided by RootBSD and LimeLight
	    Networks.</li>

	  <li>Moved email services for the Foundation to a new
	    server.</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <p>&a.emaste; attended the Reproducible Builds World
	Summit, which took place in Athens, Greece, December 1-3,
	2015.</p>

      <p>We wrapped up our 2015 fundraising efforts with our
	End-of-Year fundraising campaign by participating in
	#GivingTuesday, and continuing with weekly email and social
	media requests for support of the Foundation.  Final
	fundraising numbers will be available in Q1 2016.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; Xen</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Roger</given>
	  <common>Pau Monn&eacute;</common>
	</name>
	<email>royger@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wei</given>
	  <common>Liu</common>
	</name>
	<email>wei.liu2@citrix.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/&os;_PVH">&os; PVH DomU Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/&os;_Dom0">&os; PVH Dom0 Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://xenbits.xen.org/gitweb/?p=people/royger/FreeBSD.git;a=shortlog;h=refs/heads/new_entry_point_v5">&os;/Xen HVMlite Implementation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xen is a hypervisor using a microkernel design, providing
	services that allow multiple computer operating systems to
	execute on the same computer hardware concurrently.  Xen
	support for &os; on x86 as a guest was introduced in version
	8, and ARM support is currently being worked on.  Support for
	running &os; as an amd64 Xen host (Dom0) is available in
	HEAD.</p>

      <p>The x86 work done during this quarter has been focused on
	rewriting the PVH implementation inside of Xen, into what is
	now being called HVMlite to differentiate it with the previous
	PVH implementation.  The Xen side of patches have already been
	committed to the Xen source tree, and will be available in Xen
	4.7, the next version.  Work has also begun on implementing
	HVMlite Dom0 support, although no patches have yet been
	published.</p>

      <p>HVMlite support for &os; has not yet been committed,
	although an initial implementation is available in a personal
	git repository.  The plan is to completely replace PVH with
	HVMlite on &os; as soon as HVMlite supports Dom0 mode.</p>

      <p>Apart from this, Wei Liu is working on improving netfront
	performance on &os;.  Initial patches have been posted to the
	&os; review system.</p>

      <p>The x86 unmapped bounce buffer code has also been improved,
	and unmapped IO support has been added to the
	<tt>blkfront</tt> driver.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Citrix Systems R&amp;D
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Finish HVMlite Dom0 support inside of Xen.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Deprecate and remove PVH support from Xen.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Remove PVH support from &os; and switch to HVMlite.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Generalize the event channel code so it can be used on
	  ARM.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Improve the performance of the various backends
	  (<tt>netback</tt>, <tt>blkback</tt>).</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/arm64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/arm64">&os; arm64 Wiki Entry</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Support was added for kernel modules.  This included adding
	the needed relocation types to the in-kernel relocator, and
	updating the build logic to build modules for arm64.  CTF data
	is currently not generated for modules due to a linker
	bug.</p>

      <p>Shared page support was added.  This allows
	<tt>gettimeofday(2)</tt> to be implemented in userland by
	directly accessing the timer register.  This reduces the
	overhead of these calls as we no longer need to call into the
	kernel.  This also moves the signal trampoline code away from
	the stack allowing for the stack to become non-executable.</p>

      <p>CloudABI support for arm64 was added.  This included moving
	the machine-independent code into a separate file to be shared
	among all architectures.  An issue in the arm64 kernel was
	found and fixed thanks to the CloudABI test suite.</p>

      <p>Self-hosted poudriere package builds have been tested.
	These complement the previous build strategy of using qemu
	usermode emulation.  With this combination of self-hosted and
	qemu usermode building, many ports that used to be broken on
	arm64 have been fixed, resulting in over 17,000 ports building
	for the architecture.</p>

      <p>The machine-dependent portions of kernel support for
	single-stepping userland binaries has been started.  This will
	allow debuggers like <tt>lldb</tt> to step through an
	application while debugging.</p>

      <p>Many small fixes have been made to &os;/arm64.  These
	include fixing stack tracing through exceptions, printing more
	information about &quot;data abort&quot; kernel panics,
	cleaning up the atomic functions, supporting multi-pass driver
	attachment, fixing userland stack alignment, cleaning up early
	page table creation, fixing asynchronous software trap
	handling, and enabling interrupts in exception handlers.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      ABT Systems Ltd
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on SoftIron Overdrive 3000</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://softiron.co.uk/products/">SoftIron Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The SoftIron Overdrive 3000 is an ARMv8 based server with an
	8-core AMD Opteron A1100 processor.  The Overdrive 3000 has
	two 10Gbase-T Ethernet ports, two PCI Express ports, and eight
	SATA ports.  &os; has been updated to be able to boot on this
	hardware.</p>

      <p>Support for the SATA device was added to the
	<tt>ahci(4)</tt> driver.  Unlike on x86, this is a Memory
	Mapped (mmio) device, and not on the PCI bus.  To support
	this, a new ahci mmio driver attachment has been added.</p>

      <p>The generic PCIe driver has been updated to improve interrupt
	handling.  This includes supporting the interrupt-map
	devicetree property, and supporting MSI and MSI-X interrupts
	on arm64.</p>

      <p>Support for MSI and MSI-X interrupts has been added to the
	ARM Generic Interrupt Controller v2 (gicv2) driver.  This
	allows devices to use these interrupts.  This has been tested
	with a collection of PCIe NIC hardware.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      SoftIron Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Write a driver for the 10Gbase-T NIC.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Jenkins Continuous Integration for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Craig</given>
	  <common>Rodrigues</common>
	</name>
	<email>rodrigc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>Jenkins Administrators</name>
	<email>jenkins-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Testing</name>
	<email>FreeBSD-testing@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://jenkins.FreeBSD.org">The Jenkins CI Server in the &os; Cluster</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/Ultima1252/portest">Portest Script</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jenkinsci/workflow-plugin">Jenkins Workflow Plugin</url>
      <url href="https://cloudbees.com">Cloudbees</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/uber/phabricator-jenkins-plugin">Jenkins Phabricator Plugin</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/uber/phabricator-jenkins-plugin/pull/110">Phabricator Plugin Fixes</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jenkinsci/durable-task-plugin/pull/14">Durable Task Plugin Fixes</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jenkinsci/clang-scanbuild-plugin/commits/master">Clang Scanbuild Plugin Fixes</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jenkinsci/multiple-scms-plugin/commits/master">Multiple SCMs Plugin Fixes</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jenkinsci/scm-sync-configuration-plugin/commits/master">SCM Sync Configuration Plugin Fixes</url>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-testing/2016-January/001285.html">Porting Jobs to the Workflow Plugin</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/kohsuke/akuma/pull/9">Akuma Fixes for &os;</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/jmmv/kyua/pull/148">Kyua Fix for Invalid Characters</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Jenkins Continuous Integration and Testing project
	has been helping to improve the quality of &os;.  Since the
	last status report, we have quickly found commits that caused
	build breakage or test failures.  &os; developers saw these
	problems and quickly fixed them.  Some of the highlights
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Ricky Gallagher wrote a script named <tt>portest</tt>,
	  which can take a patch to the &os; ports tree as input, and
	  can generate a sequence of commands to check out the ports
	  tree from Subversion, apply the patch, and then invoke
	  <tt>poudriere</tt> to build the affected part of the ports
	  tree.  Ricky consulted with Torsten Z&uuml;hlsdorff
	  during its development.
	  This script will be used later to test changes to the ports
	  tree.</li>

	<li>
	  <p>&a.rodrigc; converted some Jenkins builds to use the
	    Workflow plugin.  Workflow is a plugin written by Jesse
	    Glick and other developers at Cloudbees, the main company
	    providing commercial support for Jenkins.  With this
	    plugin, a Jenkins job can be written in a Domain Specific
	    Language (DSL) which is written in the Groovy scripting
	    language.  Workflow scripts are meant to provide
	    sophisticated access to Jenkins functionality, in a simple
	    scripting language.  As Jenkins jobs get more complicated
	    and have more interdependencies, using a DSL is easier for
	    maintainability instead of creating Jenkins jobs via
	    menus.</p>

	  <p>&a.rodrigc; worked with Jesse Glick to identify and fix a
	    problem with the Durable Task plugin used by the workflow
	    plugin.  This problem seemed to show up mostly on
	    non-Linux platforms such as OS X and &os;.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>&a.eadler; worked with &a.rodrigc; to test a Jenkins
	    plugin written by Aiden Scandella at Uber which integrates
	    Phabricator and Jenkins.  With this plugin, if someone
	    submits a code review with Phabricator's Differential
	    tool, a Jenkins build with this code change will be
	    triggered.  The Phabricator code review would then be
	    updated with the result of the build.</p>

	  <p>&a.eadler; and &a.rodrigc; had some initial success
	    testing this plugin using the &os; docs repository, but
	    this plugin still has a lot of hardcoded dependencies
	    specific to Uber's environment which make it difficult to
	    use out-of-the-box for &os;.  Alexander Yerenkow submitted
	    some patches upstream to fix some of these problems, but
	    this plugin still needs more work.  &a.rodrigc; thinks
	    that it might be better to write a workflow script to call
	    Phabricator commands directly.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>&a.rodrigc; pushed fixes upstream to several
	    plugins including:</p>

	  <ul>
	    <li>SCM Sync configuration plugin</li>

	    <li>NodeLabel parameter plugin</li>

	    <li>Subversion plugin</li>

	    <li>Multiple SCMs plugin</li>

	    <li>Clang Scanbuild plugin</li>
	  </ul>

	  <p>&a.rodrigc; was granted commit access to the SCM
	    Sync configuration plugin, Multiple SCMs plugin, and Clang
	    Scanbuild plugin.</p>
	</li>

	<li>&a.lwhsu; set up multiple builds using jails on machines
	  located at NYI and administered by the &os; Cluster
	  Administrators.  One of these builds targets 64-bit
	  ARM.</li>

	<li>Michael Zhilin fixed the Akuma library for &os;.  The
	  Akuma library is used by Jenkins to determine what
	  command-line arguments were passed to a running process.  To
	  fix it, Michael invoked an &os;-specific <tt>sysctl()</tt>
	  with KERN_PROC_ARGS to determine the arguments for a running
	  pid.  This fix allows a running Jenkins instance to restart
	  itself after new plugins are installed.</li>

	<li>&a.jmmv; accepted a fix for Kyua from &a.rodrigc; to fix
	  writing out XML characters to test report files.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Work more on using the workflow plugin for various
	  builds.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Set up a build to test <tt>bmake</tt>'s meta-mode.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Finish off integration with Phabricator.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>People interested in helping out should join the
	  freebsd-testing@FreeBSD.org list.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Multipath TCP for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nigel</given>
	  <common>Williams</common>
	</name>
	<email>njwilliams@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://bitbucket.org/nw-swin/caia-mptcp-FreeBSD/">MPTCP for &os; Repository</url>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/mptcp/">MPTCP for &os; Project Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Multipath TCP (MPTCP) is an extension to TCP that allows for
	the use of multiple network interfaces on a standard TCP
	session.  The addition of new addresses and scheduling of data
	across these occurs transparently from the perspective of the
	TCP application.</p>

      <p>The goal of this project is to deliver an MPTCP kernel patch
	that interoperates with the reference MPTCP implementation,
	along with additional enhancements to aid network
	research.</p>

      <p>A v0.51 release has been tagged in our repository, with
	some minor improvements over v0.5.</p>

      <p>We have now removed much of the MPTCP code that was inside
	the functions <tt>tcp_do_segment</tt>, <tt>tcp_output</tt>,
	and other code used for standard TCP connections.  The goal of
	this is to restrict the added MPTCP code to just MPTCP
	connections, leaving regular TCP connections using the
	existing code.</p>

      <p>We are currently in the process of implementing a subflow
	socket buffer upcall and event processing.  These will handle
	changes in subflow socket state, MP-signalling, and incoming
	data segments.</p>

      <p>This also requires some re-working of the MP option
	processing, particularly how incoming DSN maps are parsed and
	stored for use during MP-layer reassembly.</p>

      <p>We are also looking at how our changes might take advantage
	of the new TCP stack modularisation enhancements to create
	subflow-specific TCP functions.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The Cisco University Research Program Fund at Community
      Foundation Silicon Valley
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Complete the implementations of subflow event processing
	  and new option parsing.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Update documentation and task lists.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/RISC-V</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ruslan</given>
	  <common>Bukin</common>
	</name>
	<email>br@bsdpad.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Arun</given>
	  <common>Thomas</common>
	</name>
	<email>arun.thomas@baesystems.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/riscv">Project Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We have begun work on support for the RISC-V
	architecture.</p>

      <p>RISC-V is a new ISA designed to support computer architecture
	research and education that is now set to become a standard
	open architecture for industry implementations.</p>

      <p>A minimal set of changes needed to compile the kernel
	toolchain has been committed, along with machine headers,
	run-time linker (rtld-elf) support, and libc/libstand.</p>

      <p>All development has been happening in a separate branch,
	with a goal of moving development to head in a few weeks.</p>

      <p>At present, &os;/RISC-V boots to multiuser in the Spike
	simulator.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      DARPA, AFRL
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      HEIF5
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>We plan to commit the rest of userspace (i.e., libc),
	  kernel support, etc., in a few weeks.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title><tt>sendfile(2)</tt> Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gleb</given>
	  <common>Smirnoff</common>
	</name>
	<email>glebius@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=293439">Commit to Head</url>
      <url href="http://www.slideshare.net/facepalmtarbz2/new-sendfile-in-english">Slides</url>
      <url href="https://events.yandex.ru/lib/talks/2682/">Presentation (in Russian)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> system call was introduced in
	1998 as an alternative to a traditional
	<tt>read(2)</tt>/<tt>write(2)</tt> loop, speeding up server
	performance by a factor of ten at the time.  Since it was
	adopted by all major operating systems, it is now used by any
	serious web server software.  Wherever there is high traffic,
	there is <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> under the hood.</p>

      <p>Now, with &os; 11, we are making the next revolutinary step
	in serving traffic.  <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> no longer blocks
	waiting on disk I/O.  Instead, it immediately returns control
	to the application, performing the necessary I/O in the
	background.  The original <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> waited for the
	disk read operation to complete and then put the data that was
	read into the socket, then returned to userspace.  If a web
	server served thousands of clients with thousands of requests,
	it was forced to spawn extra contexts from which to run
	<tt>sendfile(2)</tt> to avoid stalls.  Alternatively, it could
	use special tricks like the <tt>SF_NODISKIO</tt> flag that
	forces <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> to serve only content that is
	cached in memory.  Now, these tricks are in the past, and a
	web server can simply use <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> as it would use
	<tt>write(2)</tt>, without any extra care.  The new sendfile
	cuts out the overhead of extra contexts, short writes, and
	extra syscalls to prepopulate the cache, bringing performance
	to a new level.</p>

      <p>The new syscall is built on top of two newly-introduced
	kernel features.  The first is an asynchronous VM pager
	interface and the corresponding <tt>VOP_GETPAGES_ASYNC()</tt>
	file system method for UFS.  The second is the concept of
	&quot;not ready&quot; data in sockets.  When
	<tt>sendfile(2)</tt> is called, first
	<tt>VOP_GETPAGES_ASYNC()</tt> is called, which dispatches I/O
	requests for completion.  Buffers with pages to be populated
	are put into the socket buffer, but flagged as not-yet-ready.
	Control immediately returns to the application.  When the I/O
	is finished, the buffers are marked as ready, and the socket
	is activated to continue transmission.</p>

      <p>Additional features of the new <tt>sendfile</tt> are new
	flags that provide an application with extra control over the
	transmitted content.  Now it is possible to prevent caching of
	content in memory, which is useful when it is known that the
	content is unlikely to be reused any time soon.  In such
	cases, it is better to let the associated storage be freed,
	rather than putting the data in cache.  It is also possible to
	specify a readahead with every syscall, if the application can
	predict client behavior.</p>

      <p>The new <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> is a drop-in replacement, API
	and ABI compatible with the old one.  Applications do not even
	need to recompile to benefit from the new implementation.</p>

      <p>This work is a joint effort between two companies: NGINX,
	Inc., and Netflix.  There were many people involved in the
	project.  At its initial stage, before code was written, the
	idea of such an asynchronous drop-in replacement was discussed
	amongst &a.glebius;, &a.scottl;, &a.kib;, &a.adrian;, and Igor
	Sysoev.  The initial prototype was coded by Gleb under the
	supervision of Kostik on the VM parts of patch, and under
	constant pressure from Igor, who demanded that nginx be
	capable of running with the new <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> with no
	modifications.  The prototype demonstrated good performance
	and stability and quickly went into Netflix production in late
	2014.  During 2015, the code matured and continued serving
	production traffic at Netflix.  &a.scottl;, &a.rrs;, &a.emax;,
	and &a.gallatin; added their contributions to the code.</p>

      <p>Now we are releasing the code behind our success to the
	&os; community, making it available to all &os; users
	worldwide!</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Netflix
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      NGINX, Inc.
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p><tt>SSL_sendfile()</tt> &mdash; an extension to the new
	  <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> that allows uploading session keys to
	  the kernel, and then using <tt>sendfile(2)</tt> on an
	  SSL-enabled socket.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>System Initialization and Service Management</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Heily</common>
	</name>
	<email>mark@heily.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jonathan</given>
	  <common>de Boyne Pollard</common>
	</name>
	<email>J.deBoynePollard-newsgroups@NTLWorld.COM</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jordan</given>
	  <common>Hubbard</common>
	</name>
	<email>jkh@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonspawn.org/2016/01/a-comparison-of-alternatives-to-init8.html">A Comparison of <tt>init(8)</tt> and <tt>rc(8)</tt> Replacements</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are three active projects to provide an alternative
	to the traditional <tt>init(8)</tt> and <tt>rc(8)</tt>
	subsystems that manage the boot process and system services.
	There are a number of reasons driving the desire for change,
	including:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Faster boot times, made possible by launching services
	  in parallel</li>

	<li>Greater reliability, by ensuring that services are
	  automatically restarted if they terminate unexpectedly</li>

	<li>Simplified dependency management, using socket
	  activation and similar techniques</li>

	<li>The ability to launch services &quot;on demand&quot;,
	  and have them self-terminate when idle</li>

	<li>Improved security, by removing the need to start common
	  daemons as the root user</li>
      </ul>

      <p> Two of the projects, <tt>launchd</tt> and
	<tt>relaunchd</tt>, are based on the <tt>launchd(8)</tt> API
	introduced by Apple in Mac OS X.  The NextBSD project has
	ported the original Apple source code by writing a Mach
	compatibility layer that allows <tt>launchd</tt> to run on
	&os;.  The <tt>relaunchd</tt> project started from scratch
	with the goal of creating a more modular, lightweight, and
	portable implementation of the <tt>launchd</tt> API.  The
	third project, <tt>nosh</tt>, is a unique creation that
	borrows concepts from <tt>launchd</tt>, <tt>systemd</tt>, and
	several other Unix operating systems.</p>

      <p>While the &os; Project has not made a decision to replace the
	current <tt>init(8)</tt> and <tt>rc(8)</tt> subsystems, the
	existence and active development of alternatives will continue
	to drive innovation in this space.</p>

      <p>Jordan Hubbard is the contact point for the NextBSD
	<tt>launchd</tt>, Jonathan de Boyne Pollard is the contact
	point for <tt>nosh</tt>, and Mark Heily is the contact point
	for <tt>relaunchd</tt>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>NanoBSD Modernization</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The NanoBSD updates target three main areas.  First,
	building a NanoBSD image required root privileges.  Second,
	building for embedded platforms required detailed knowledge of
	the format required to boot.  Third, the exact image sizes
	needed to be known to produce an image.</p>

      <p>When NanoBSD was written, &os;'s build system required root
	privileges for the install step and onward.  NanoBSD added to
	this by creating a <tt>md(4)</tt> device to construct the
	image.  Some configurations of NanoBSD added further to this
	by creating a chroot in which to cleanly build packages.
	NanoBSD solves the first problem using the new
	<tt>NO_ROOT</tt> build option to create a meta file.  NanoBSD
	also augments this record as files are created and removed.
	The meta file is then fed into <tt>makefs(8)</tt> to create a
	UFS image with the proper permissions.  The UFS image, and
	sometimes a DOS FAT partition, are then passed to
	<tt>mkimg(1)</tt> to create the final SD image.  The
	<tt>mtree</tt> manipulation has been written as a separate
	script to allow it to move into the base system where it could
	assist with other build orchestration tools (though the move
	has not happened yet).</p>

      <p>The detailed knowledge of how to build each embedded image
	(as well as some of the base images for qemu) has always been
	hard to enshrine.  Crochet puts this knowledge into its
	builds.  The &os; release system puts it into its system.
	NanoBSD, prior to the current work, provided no way to access
	its knowledge of how to build images.  The current state of
	this project allows the user to set a simple image type and
	have NanoBSD deal with all of the details needed to create
	that image type.  This includes using the u-boot ports and
	installing the right files into a FAT partition so that &os;
	can boot with <tt>ubldr(8)</tt>, creating the right
	<tt>boot1.elf</tt> file for powerpc64 qemu booting, or the
	more familiar (though needlessly complicated) x86 setup.
	Previous versions of NanoBSD required too much specialized
	knowledge from the user.  This work aims to concentrate the
	knowledge into a set of simple scripts for any build
	orchestration system to use.</p>

      <p>Finally, NanoBSD images in the past have needed very
	specific knowledge of the target device.  Part of this is a
	legacy of the BIOS state-of-the-art a decade ago, which
	required very careful matching of the image to the actual
	device in the deployed system.  Although relevant at the time,
	such systems are now vanishingly rare.  Support for them will
	be phased out (though given the flexibility of NanoBSD, it can
	be moved to the few remaining examples in the tree and also
	partially covered by the generic image scripts).  Today, the
	typical use case is to create an SD or microSD card image, and
	have the image resize itself on boot.  NanoBSD now supports
	that workflow.</p>

      <p>In addition to these items, a number of minor improvements
	have been made:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Support for <tt>CPUTYPE</tt>-specialized builds.  This
	  includes both NanoBSD support as well as important bug fixes
	  in the base system.</li>

	<li>Support for marking MBR partitions as active.</li>

	<li>Support for more partition types.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p><tt>mkimg(8)</tt> needs to be augmented to create images
	  for the i.MX6 and Allwinner (and others) SoCs.  These SoCs
	  require a boot image to be written after the MBR, but before
	  the first partition starts.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The chroot functionality of some NanoBSD configurations
	  has not yet been migrated for non-privileged builds.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The functionality to manipulate <tt>mtree(8)</tt> files
	  should be moved into the base system for use by other build
	  orchestration tools.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The script to create a bootable image from one or more
	  trees of files, as well as some creation of those trees,
	  should be moved into the base system for use with other
	  build orchestration tools.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>The <tt>growfs</tt> functionality works great for single
	  images growing to the whole disk.  However, NanoBSD would
	  prefer that the boot FS/partition grow to approximately 1/2
	  the size of the media and another identical (or close)
	  partition be created for the ping-ponging upgrades that
	  NanoBSD is setup for.  This needs to be implemented in the
	  <tt>growfs</tt> <tt>rc.d(8)</tt> script.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title><tt>armv6</tt> Hard Float Default ABI</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://bsdimp.blogspot.com/2015/12/hard-float-api-coming-soon-by-default.html">Blog Entry</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work on moving armv6 from a &quot;soft float&quot; ABI (but
	still using hardware floating point) to a fully &quot;hardware
	float&quot; API moves forward.  The ability to have both soft
	and hard ABI libraries on the same system is now functional.
	All armv6 and armv7 systems we support have hardware floating
	point capabilities.  We currently use the floating-point
	hardware, but with a slightly un-optimal ABI, for
	compatibility with older versions of &os;.  The ABI
	differences are only at the userspace level &mdash; the kernel
	does not care what floating-point ABI is used, and both types
	of binaries can run at the same time.</p>

      <p>The run-time linker now knows if a binary uses the hardware
	float ABI or the software float ABI by examining some fields
	in the ELF header.  The linker uses different paths and config
	files for hard versus soft binaries.  The <tt>rc</tt> system
	has been enhanced to load the software float paths.
	<tt>ldconfig</tt> now understands soft libraries in much the
	same way that it understands 32-bit libraries on 64-bit
	systems.  No additional kernel support was necessary for this,
	apart from a minor patch to pass the ELF header information to
	the binary, which has been in the tree since last summer.</p>

      <p>The experimental armv6hf <tt>MACHINE_ARCH</tt> will be
	retired after a transition period.  It will cease to mean
	anything different from armv6 after the build system changes
	go in.  Support for building soft-float ABI libraries will
	remain in the tree, to support the <tt>WITH_LIBSOFT</tt> build
	option.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Complete documentation needs to be written.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Hooks into the &os; build system to generate soft float and
	  transition to hard float after a flag day need to be
	  polished up and committed.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>A number of different upgrade/coexistence scenarios need
	  to be tested, and a full package run needs to be done to
	  assess the latest state of the ports tree.  This work should
	  be completed by the end of January.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>CAM I/O Scheduler</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://people.FreeBSD.org/~imp/bsdcan2015/iosched-v3.pdf">BSDCan Paper</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D4609">Phabricator Review</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Reviews have begun on the CAM I/O scheduler that I wrote
	for Netflix.  It is anticipated that this process will be done
	in time for the &os; 11 branch.</p>

      <p>Details about this work can be found in the linked BSDcan
	paper from last year.</p>

      <p>Briefly, the scheduler allows one to differentiate I/O types
	and limit I/O based on the type and characteristics of the
	I/Os (including the latency of recent requests relative to
	historical averages).  This is most useful when tuning system
	loads to SSD performance.  Both a simple default scheduler,
	the same that we use today in &os;, as well as a scheduler
	that can be well-tuned for system loads related to video
	streaming will be included.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Netflix, Inc
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Minimal Kernel with PNP-Based Autoloading</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://bsdimp.blogspot.com/2016/01/details-on-coming-automatic-module.html">Blog Post</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work on automatically loading modules based on the
	plug-and-play data from devices that are scanned and found to
	not already have a driver attached is in progress.  Digging
	this information out from kernel modules, as well as tagging
	relevant bits of driver tables, has been committed.  PC Card,
	USB, and some PCI devices now have these markings.  This data
	is stored in a file that the kernel, boot loader, and userland
	processes all can access.</p>

      <p>When complete, a user will be able to run a minimal kernel
	(currently checked in as the <tt>MINIMAL</tt> config).
	Devices necessary for booting will be loaded by
	<tt>loader(8)</tt>.  Other devices may be loaded there, or
	early in the boot (depending on which gives better
	performance).  Users will still be able to run more
	monolithic; configurations, as well as limit which
	kernel modules are available as can be done today, though
	without the convenience that automatic loading will provide.
	This work remains ongoing.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Go through all the simplebus drivers and add plug-and-play
	  information there.  Some additional minor simplebus
	  functionality is needed.  There is some work in progress for
	  this.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Go through all the PCI drivers and add plug-and-play
	  information to them.  Unlike PC Card or USB, the PCI bus
	  does not have a stylized table of PCI IDs, so each driver
	  invents its own method, meaning that the semi-mechanical
	  conversion that was done with PC Card and USB will not be
	  possible.  Instead, customized code for each driver will be
	  needed.  Since a large number of drivers have their own
	  device tables, the work will be primarily writing a
	  description of the current table style.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Run-time parsing and loading is still needed.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="proj">
    <title>The <tt>nosh</tt> Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jonathan</given>
	  <common>de Boyne Pollard</common>
	</name>
	<email>J.deBoynePollard-newsgroups@NTLWorld.COM</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh.html">Introduction</url>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh/FreeBSD-binary-packages.html">&os; binary packages</url>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh/timorous-admin-installation-how-to.html">Installation How-To</url>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh/roadmap.html">Roadmap</url>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh/commands.html">Commands</url>
      <url href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com./jonathan.deboynepollard/Softwares/nosh/guide/index.html">A Slightly Outdated User Guide</url>
      <url href="https://www.mail-archive.com/supervision@list.skarnet.org/">The Supervision Mailing List</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The nosh project is a suite of system-level utilities for
	initializing, running, and shutting down BSD systems, and for
	managing daemons, terminals, and logging.  It supersedes BSD
	<tt>init</tt> and the NetBSD <tt>rc.d</tt> system, drawing
	inspiration from Solaris SMF for named milestones,
	daemontools-encore for service control/status mechanisms,
	UCSPI, and IBM AIX for separated service and system
	management.  It comprises a range of compatibility mechanisms,
	including shims for familiar commands from other systems, and
	an automatic import mechanism that takes existing
	configuration data from <tt>/etc/fstab</tt>,
	<tt>/etc/rc.conf{,.local}</tt>, <tt>/etc/ttys</tt>, and
	elsewhere, applying them to its native service definitions and
	creating additional native services.  It is portable
	(including to Linux) and composable, it provides a migration
	path from the world of systemd Linux, and it does not require
	new kernel APIs.  It provides clean service environments,
	orderings and dependencies between services, parallelized
	startup and shutdown (including <tt>fsck</tt>), strictly
	size-capped and autorotated logging, the service manager as a
	&quot;subreaper&quot;, and uses <tt>kevent(2)</tt> for
	event-driven parallelism.</p>

      <p>Since the last status report, in October 2015, the project
	has seen: the complete replacement of its event-handling
	subsystem on Linux; the introduction of tools for exporting
	cyclog/multilog logs via RFC 5426 to remote log handlers (such
	as logstash); and the switching of the user-mode virtual
	terminal subsystem on BSD to using USB devices directly, a
	more powerful device interface than sysmouse et al. because it
	permits directly positioning touch devices for mice and other
	things (thus permitting &quot;mouse integration&quot; under
	VirtualBox for those who run PC-BSD/&os; on VirtualBox virtual
	machines), but sysmouse et al. can still be used if
	desired.</p>

      <p>In version 1.24, released shortly before publication of this
	report, there are extensive additions for supporting a
	purely-ZFS system with an empty <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> (as the
	PC-BSD 10.2 system installer creates), and the ability to
	convert <tt>systemd</tt> unit files' process priority settings
	to BSD's rtprio/idprio.</p>

      <p>Version 1.24 also sees a large chunk taken out of the
	remainder of the on-going project to create enough native
	service bundles and ancillary utilities to entirely supplant
	the <tt>rc.d</tt> system.  The progress of this project has
	been open from the start, and can be followed on the nosh
	roadmap web page.  As of version 1.24, there are a mere 27
	items remaining out of the original target list of 157, with a
	28th and a 29th (from PC-BSD 10.2) added.  Items crossed off
	by version 1.24 include (amongst others) <tt>mfs</tt> support
	for <tt>/tmp</tt>, static ARP and networking, persistent
	entropy for the randomness subsystem,
	<tt>pefs</tt>, and <tt>hald</tt>.</p>

      <p>The remaining items in the task list are mostly aimed at
	making the overall system integration cleaner and friendlier
	to modern systems.  We are also interested in receiving
	suggestions, bug reports, and other feedback from users.  Try
	following the how-to guide and see how things go!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Add kernel support for passing a <tt>-b</tt> option to
	  PID 1, and support for a <tt>boot_bare</tt> variable in the
	  loader, to allow &quot;emergency&quot; (where no shell
	  dotfiles are loaded) and &quot;rescue&quot; mode bootstraps,
	  akin to Linux.  (History: the <tt>-b</tt> mechanism and idea
	  date back to version 2.57d of Miquel van Smoorenburg's
	  System 5 init clone, dated 1995-12-03, and was already known
	  as "emergency boot" by 1997.)</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Add support to &os;'s <tt>fsck(8)</tt> for outputting
	  machine-readable progress reports to a designated file
	  descriptor, so that <tt>nosh</tt> can provide progress bars
	  for multiple <tt>fsck</tt>s running in parallel.
	  <tt>nosh</tt> already provides this functionality on Linux,
	  where <tt>fsck(8)</tt> does provide machine-readable
	  output.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Identify when the configuration import system needs to be
	  triggered, such as when <tt>bsdconfig</tt> alters
	  configuration files, and create the necessary hooks to
	  import external configuration changes into nosh.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>MIPS: Ralink/Mediatek Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Stanislav</given>
	  <common>Galabov</common>
	</name>
	<email>sgalabov@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/sgalabov/&os;/tree/local/sgalabov_mtk">Github Branch With Work in Progress</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project is aimed at adding &os; support for
	Ralink/Mediatek's family of WiFi router system-on-chip (SoC)
	devices based on MIPS processors.  These SoCs are commonly
	found in embedded network devices such as WiFi routers.
	Having support for these SoCs would allow &os; to run on a
	number of additional low-cost devices, which could help spread
	&os;'s popularity in the embedded systems world.</p>

      <p>The project currently aims to support the following
	Ralink/Mediatek chipsets: RT3050, RT3052, RT3350, RT3352,
	RT3662, RT3883, RT5350, RT6855, RT6856, MT7620, MT7621, MT7628
	and MT7688. The following functionality (where applicable) is
	currently planned to be supported: Interrupt controller, UART,
	GPIO, USB, PCI/PCIe, Ethernet, and SPI.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Smartcom - Bulgaria AD
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>Help with adding WiFi driver support (possibly to
	  <tt>ral(4)</tt>) for the above SoCs would be greatly
	  appreciated.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Help with refactoring <tt>if_rt(4)</tt> to be usable on
	  all of the above SoCs would be appreciated.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Help wth testing target boards (e.g., WiFi routers)
	  would be appreciated.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>HardenedBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Shawn</given>
	  <common>Webb</common>
	</name>
	<email>shawn.webb@hardenedbsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oliver</given>
	  <common>Pinter</common>
	</name>
	<email>oliver.pinter@hardenedbsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://hardenedbsd.org/" />
      <url href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/shawn-webb/2015-12-31/introducing-hardenedbsds-new-binary-updater">Introducing HardenedBSD's New Binary Updater</url>
      <url href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/shawn-webb/2015-11-22/introducing-secadm-030-beta-01"><tt>secadm</tt> Beta Published</url>
      <url href="https://hardenedbsd.org/article/admin/2015-11-22/new-package-building-server">New Package Building Server</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/HardenedBSD/secadm"><tt>secadm</tt></url>
      <url href="https://github.com/HardenedBSD/hardenedBSD-playground/tree/hardened/experimental/master-i915">HardenedBSD Haswell Support</url>
      <url href="http://jenkins.hardenedbsd.org/builds/HardenedBSD-CURRENT-i915kms-amd64-LATEST/">Nightly Builds for HardenedBSD Haswell Support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>HardenedBSD has been hard at work improving the performance
	and stability of our security enhancements.  Security flags
	are now per-thread instead of per-process, removing some
	locking overhead.  ASLR for mmap(MAP_32BIT) requests has been
	refactored, but lib32 is now disabled by default.</p>

      <p>We have developed a new binary update utility,
	<tt>hbsd-update</tt> akin to <tt>freebsd-update</tt>.  In
	addition to normal OS installs, it can also update jails and
	ZFS Boot Environments (ZFS BEs).  Updates are signed using
	X.509 certificates.</p>

      <p><tt>secadm</tt> 0.3-beta has landed.  It has been rewritten
	from scratch to be more efficient.  As part of the rewrite,
	the rule syntax has changed and users must update their
	rulesets as described in the README.</p>

      <p>Thanks to generous donations of a server from G2, Inc and
	hosting from Automated Tendencies, we can now do full
	package builds in just 35 hours, down from 75 hours.
	This machine will also provide weekly binary updates for
	the kernel and base system.</p>

      <p>Owing partly to the needs of the developers, we have
	an experimental branch that includes the work &a.dumbbell; has
	under way for Haswell graphics support, on top of &os;
	11-current.  Binary updates are also provided for this
	branch.</p>

      <p>Unfortunately, in order to focus our efforts on improving
	HardenedBSD, we have had to pull back from submitting our ASLR
	patches to &os;.  The past two years' efforts to address
	comments on the submission have taken their toll, and the
	effort is no longer sustainable.  We are proud to be based on
	&os; and believe that the whole community could benefit from
	the security technologies we are developing.  We hope that
	someone else will be able to step forward and finish off the
	task of integrating ASLR into &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Automated Tendencies
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      G2, Inc
    </sponsor>

    <sponsor>
      SoldierX
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>GNOME on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; GNOME Team</name>
	<email>freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome">&os; Gnome Website</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/freebsd-ports-gnome">Devel Repository</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Jhbuild/&os;">Upstream Build Bot</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook/using-gnome.html">USE_GNOME Porter's Handbook Chapter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; GNOME Team maintains the GNOME, MATE, and CINNAMON
	desktop environments and graphical user interfaces for &os;.
	GNOME 3 is part of the GNU Project.  MATE is a fork of the
	GNOME 2 desktop.  CINNAMON is a desktop environment using
	GNOME 3 technologies but with a GNOME 2 look and feel.</p>

      <p>This quarter, due to limited available time there was not
	much progress.  This began to change in December, when work
	started on porting MATE 1.12 and CINNAMON 2.8 to &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
	<p>The &os; GNOME website is stale.  Work is under way to
	  improve it.</p>
      </task>

      <task>
	<p>Continue working on investigating the issues blocking
	  GNOME 3.18.</p>
      </task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
