<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd">

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>June</month>

    <year>2001</year>
  </date>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">
      $FreeBSD$
    </cvs:keyword>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>One of the benefits of the FreeBSD development model is a focus
    on centralized design and implementation, in which the operating
    system is maintained in a central repository, and discussed on
    centrally maintained lists. This allows for a high level of
    coordination between authors of various components of the system,
    and allows policies to be enforced over the entire system, covering
    issues ranging from architecture to style. However, as the FreeBSD
    developer community has grown, and the rate of both mailing list
    traffic and tree modifications has increased, making it difficult
    even for the most dedicated developer to remain on top of all the
    work going on in the tree.</p>

    <p>The FreeBSD Monthly Development Status Report attempts to
    address this problem by providing a vehicle that allows developers
    to make the broader community aware of their on-going work on
    FreeBSD, both in and out of the central source repository. This is
    the first issue, and as such is an experiment. For each project and
    sub-project, a one paragraph summary is included, indicating
    progress since the last summary (in this case, simply recent
    progress, as there have been no prior summaries).</p>

    <p>This status report may be reproduced in whole or in part, as
    long as the source is clearly identified and appropriate credit
    given.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Future Editions</title>

    <p>Assuming there is some positive feedback on this idea, and that
    future submissions get made such that there is content for future
    issues, the goal is to release a development status report once a
    month. As such, the next deadline will be July 31, 2001, with a
    scheduled publication date in the first week of August. This will
    put the status report on a schedule in line with the calendar, as
    well as providing a little over a month until the next deadline,
    which will include a number of pertinent events, including the
    Annual USENIX Technical Conference in Boston, MA. Submissions
    should be e-mailed to:</p>

    <blockquote>
      <a href="mailto:robert+freebsd.monthly@cyrus.watson.org">
      robert+freebsd.monthly@cyrus.watson.org</a>
    </blockquote>

    <p>Many submitters will want to wait until the last week of July so
    as to provide the most up-to-date status report; however,
    submissions will be accepted at any time prior to that date.</p>

    <p>
      <i>-- Robert Watson &lt;
      <a href="mailto:rwatson@FreeBSD.org">rwatson@FreeBSD.org</a>

      &gt;</i>
    </p>
  </section>

  <project>
    <title>Binary Updater Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Eric</given>

          <common>Melville</common>
        </name>

        <email>eric@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Murray</given>

          <common>Stokely</common>
        </name>

        <email>murray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~murray/updater.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Binary Updater Project aims to provide a secure
      mechanism for the distribution of binary updates for FreeBSD.
      This project is complementary to the Open Packages and libh
      efforts and there should be very little overlap with those
      projects. The system uses a client / server mechanism that allows
      clients to install any known "profile" or release of FreeBSD over
      the network. Where a specific profile might contain a specific
      set of FreeBSD software to install, additional packages, and
      configuration actions that make it more ideal for a specific
      environment (ie FreeBSD 4.3 Secure Web Server Profile)</p>

      <p>The system can currently be used to install a FreeBSD system
      or perform the most simple of upgrades but many features are
      absent. In particular, the client is in its infancy and much work
      remains to be done. We need additional developers so please get
      in touch with us at
      <a href="mailto:updater@osd.bsdi.com">updater@osd.bsdi.com</a>

      if you are interested in spending some cycles on this.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Problem Reports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

        <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://phk.freebsd.dk/Gnats/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Poul-Henning Kamp kicked off a drive to get our GNATS PR
      database cleaned up so the wheat can be sorted from the chaff.
      Progress is good, but there is still a lot of work to do. Give a
      hand if you can. Remember: every unhandled PR is a pissed off
      contributor or user.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>CVSROOT script rewrite/tidy</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Josef</given>

          <common>Karthauser</common>
        </name>

        <email>joe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>I'm in the process of rewriting the CVSROOT/scripts to make
      them more clean and configurable. A lot of other projects also
      use these and so it makes sense to make them as easy to use in
      other environments as possible.</p>

      <p>Status: work in progress. There is now a configuration file,
      but not all the scripts use it yet.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>DEVFS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

        <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work is progressing on implementing true cloning devices in
      DEVFS. Brian Somers and Poul-Henning Kamp are working to make
      if_tun the first truly cloning driver in the system. Next will be
      the pty driver and the bpf driver.</p>

      <p>From July 1st DEVFS will be standard in -current.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>digi driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brian</given>

          <common>Somers</common>
        </name>

        <email>brian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Added the digi driver. Initial work was done by John Prince
      &lt;johnp@knight-trosoft.com&gt;, but all the modular stuff was
      done by me and initial work on supporting Xe and Xi cards (ala
      dgb) was done by me. I'm now awaiting an Xe card being sent from
      joerg@ (almost a donation) so that I can get that side of things
      working properly.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Diskcheckd</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

        <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://phantom.cris.net/freebsd/projects/viewproj.php?p_id=15" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Ben Smithurst has written a "diskcheckd" daemon which will
      read all sectors on the disks over a configured period. With
      recent increases in disksizes it is by no means a given that disk
      read errors will be discovered before they are fatal. This daemon
      will hopefully result in the drive firmware being able to
      relocate bad sectors before they become unreadable. This code is
      now committed to 5.0-CURRENT.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>if_fxp driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jonathan</given>

          <common>Lemon</common>
        </name>

        <email>jlemon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>In the last month (May-June), the new fxp driver was brought
      into -stable. This new driver uses the common MII code, so
      support for new PHYs is easy to add. Support for the new Intel
      82562 chips was added. The driver was updated to add VLAN support
      and a workaround for a bug affecting Intel 815-based boards.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Java Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Greg</given>

          <common>Lewis</common>
        </name>

        <email>glewis@eyesbeyond.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Java Project has continued its "behind the scenes"
      work over the last month. Progress was made both technically,
      with the help of Bill Huey (of Wind River), on a port of JDK
      1.3.1 and legally, with Nate Williams continuing negotiations
      with Sun on a mutually acceptable license to release a binary
      Java 2 SDK under. The JDK 1.2.2 port has also seen some
      development, with a new patchset likely to be released soon which
      includes JPDA and NetBSD support (the latter courtesy of Scott
      Bartram).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Kernel Graphics Interface port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Nicolas</given>

          <common>Souchu</common>
        </name>

        <email>nsouch@fr.alcove.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://kgi.sourceforge.net/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Kernel Graphics Interface project has worked for several
      years to provide a framework for graphic drivers under Linux
      receiving input from other groups like the UDI project. Currently
      the KGI core implementation is quite settled, as is the driver
      coding model as a whole. Work is being done to newbussify KGI and
      produce a kld, as part of a future redesign of the graphics
      subsystem in FreeBSD. KGI will be an alternative for graphic card
      producers that don't accept the XFree86 model of userland graphic
      adapters and will also provide accelerated support for any other
      graphic alternative.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>libh Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Langer</common>
        </name>

        <email>alex@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Nathan</given>

          <common>Ahlstrom</common>
        </name>

        <email>nra@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~alex/libh/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The libh project is a next generation sysinstall. It is
      written in C++ using QT for its graphical frontend and tvision
      for its console support. The menus are scriptable via an embedded
      tcl interpreter. It has been growing functionality quite a bit
      lately, including a new disklabel editor. Current work is on
      installation scripts for CDROM, FTP, ... installs as well as a
      fully functional standalone disk-partition and label editor. The
      GUI API was extended a little and many bugs were fixed. There
      seems to be some interest in i18n work.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Mount(2) API</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

        <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Maxime Henrion is working on implementing a new and more
      extensible mount(2) systemcall, mainly to overcome the 32 bits
      for mountoptions limit, secondary goal to make it possible to
      mount filesystems from inside the kernel.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>OLDCARD pccard implementation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

        <email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>In the last two months, the OLDCARD pccard implementation was
      rototilled to within an inch of its life. Many new pci cardbus
      bridges were added. Power handling was improved. PCI Card cardbus
      bridges are nearly supported and should be committed in early
      June to the tree. This will likely be the last major work done on
      OLDCARD. After pci cards are supported, work will shift to
      improving NEWCARD.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PowerPC Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Benno</given>

          <common>Rice</common>
        </name>

        <email>benno@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The PowerPC port is proceeding well. All seems to be working
      in pmap.c after a number of problems encountered where FreeBSD
      passes a vm_page_t to a NetBSD-derived function that expects a
      vm_offset_t. Then after debugging the atomic operations code, I'm
      now at the point where VM appears to be initialized and it's now
      hanging while in sys/kern/kern_malloc.c:kmeminit(). Progress
      continues. =)</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PPP</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brian</given>

          <common>Somers</common>
        </name>

        <email>brian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Developing full MPPE support for Andre Opperman @ Monzoon in
      Switzerland. Work is now complete and will eventually be brought
      into -current, but no dates are yet known.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>pseudofs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dag-Erling</given>

          <common>Smorgrav</common>
        </name>

        <email>des@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Pseudofs is a framework for pseudo-filesystems, like procfs
      and linprocfs. The goal of pseudofs is twofold:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>eliminate code duplication between (and within) procfs and
        linprocfs</li>

        <li>isolate procfs and linprocfs from the complexities of the
        vfs system to simplify maintenance and further
        development.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Pseudofs has reached the point where it is sufficiently
      functional and stable that linprocfs has been almost fully
      reimplemented on top of it; the only bit that's missing is the
      proc/&lt;pid&gt;/mem file.</p>

      <p>The primary to-do item for pseudofs right now is to add
      support for writeable files (which are required for procfs, and
      are quite a bit less trivial to handle than read-only files). In
      addition, pseudofs needs either generic support for raw
      (non-sbuf'ed, possibly mmap'able) files, or failing that,
      special-case code to handle proc/&lt;pid&gt;/mem.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>RELNOTESng</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bruce</given>

          <common>A. Mah</common>
        </name>

        <email>bmah@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bmah/relnotes/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>RELNOTESng is the name I've given to the rewrite of the *.TXT
      files that typically accompany a FreeBSD release. The information
      from these files (which include, among other things, the release
      notes and the supported hardware list) have been reorganized and
      converted to SGML. This helps us produce the documentation in
      various formats, as well as facilitating the maintenance of
      documentation for multiple architectures. This work was recently
      committed to -CURRENT, and I intend to MFC it to 4-STABLE before
      4.4-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>

          <common>Baldwin</common>
        </name>

        <email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jake</given>

          <common>Burkholder</common>
        </name>

        <email>jake@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>SMP</given>

          <common>Mailing list</common>
        </name>

        <email>smp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~jasone/smp/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The SMPng project aims to provide multithreaded support for
      the FreeBSD kernel. Currently the kernel still runs almost
      exclusively under the Giant kernel lock. Recently, progress has
      been made in locking the process group and session structures as
      well as file descriptors by Seigo Tanimura-san. Alfred Perlstein
      has also added in a giant lock around the entire virtual memory
      (VM) subsystem which will eventually be split up into several
      smaller locks. The locking of the VM subsystem has proved tricky,
      and some of the current effort is focused on finding and fixing a
      few remaining bugs in on the alpha architecture.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng mbuf allocator</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bosko</given>

          <common>Milekic</common>
        </name>

        <email>bmilekic@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bmilekic/code/mb_slab/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>mb_alloc is a new specialized allocator for mbufs and mbuf
      clusters. Presently, it offers various important advantages over
      the old (status quo) mbuf allocator, particularly for MP
      machines. Additionally, it is designed with the possibility of
      future enhancements in mind.</p>

      <p>Presently in initial review &amp; testing stages, most of the
      code is already written.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Sparc64 Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jake</given>

          <common>Burkholder</common>
        </name>

        <email>jake@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work has (re)started on a port of FreeBSD to the UltraSPARC
      architecture, specifically targeting PCI based workstations. Jake
      Burkholder will be porting the kernel, and Ade Lovett has
      expressed an interest in working on userland. Recent work on the
      project includes:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>built a gnu cross toolchain targeting sparc64</li>

        <li>obtained remote access to an ultra 5 development machine
        (thanks to emmy)</li>

        <li>developed a minimal set of headers and source files to
        allow the kernel to be compiled and linked</li>

        <li>implemented a mini-loader which relocates the kernel, maps
        it into the tlbs and calls it</li>

        <li>nabbed Benno Rice's openfirmware console driver which
        allows printf and panic to work</li>
      </ul>

      <p>At this point the kernel can be net-booted and prints the
      FreeBSD copyright before calling code that is not yet
      implemented. I am currently working on a design for the pmap
      module and plan to begin implementation in the next few days.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The TrustedBSD Project seeks to improve the security of the
      FreeBSD operating system by adding new security features, many
      derived from common trusted operating system requirements. This
      includes Access Control Lists (ACLs), Fine-grained Event Logging
      (Audit), Fine-grained Privileges (Capabilities), Mandatory Access
      Control (MAC), and other architecture features, including file
      system extended attributes, and improved object labeling.</p>

      <p>Individual feature status reports are documented separately
      below; in general, basic features (such as EAs, ACLs, and kernel
      support for Capabilities) will be initially available in
      5.0-RELEASE, conditional on specific kernel options. A
      performance-enhanced version of EAs is currently being targeted
      at 6.0-RELEASE, along with an integrated capability-aware
      userland, and MAC support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD: ACLs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Chris</given>

          <common>D. Faulhaber</common>
        </name>

        <email>jedgar@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Patches are now available to add ACL support to cp(1) and
      mv(1) along with preliminary support for install(1). Ilmar's i18n
      patches for getfacl(1) and setfacl(1) need to be updated for the
      last set of changes and committed. Some other functional
      improvements are also in the pipeline.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Capabilities</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Thomas</given>

          <common>Moestl</common>
        </name>

        <email>tmm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The kernel part of the capability implementation is mostly
      finished; all uses of suser() and suser_xxx() and nearly all
      comparisons of uid's with 0 have been converted to use the newly
      introduced cap_check() call. Some details still need
      clarification. More documentation for this needs to be done.</p>

      <p>POSIX.2c-compatible getfcap and setfcap programs have been
      written. Experimental capability support in su(1), login(1),
      install(1) and bsd.prog.mk is being tested.</p>

      <p>Support for capabilities, ACL's, capabilities and MAC labels
      in tar(1) is being developed; only the capability part is tested
      right now. Generic support for extended attributes is planned,
      this will require extensions to the current EA interface, which
      are written and will probably be committed to -CURRENT in a few
      weeks. A port of these features to pax(1) is planned.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD MAC and Object Labeling</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An initial prototype of a Mandatory Access Control
      implementation was completed earlier this year, supporting
      Multi-Level Security, Biba Integrity protection, and a more
      general jail-based access control model. Based on that
      implementation, I'm now in the process of improving the FreeBSD
      security abstractions to simplify both the implementation and
      integration of MAC support, as well as increase the number of
      kernel objects protected by both discretionary and mandatory
      protection schemes. Generic object labeling introduces a
      structure not dissimilar in properties to the kernel ucred
      structure, only it is intended to be associated with kernel
      objects, rather than kernel subjects, permitting the creation of
      generic security protection routines for objects. This would
      allow the easy extension of procfs and devfs to support ACLs and
      MAC, for example. A prototype is underway, with compiling and
      running code and simple protections now associated with
      sysctl's.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
