<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>April-June</month>

    <year>2016</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>Now available: the 2016Q2 model of the &os; Project Status
      Report!</p>

    <p>This quarter brings several exciting improvements over previous
      models.  We have enhancements from different teams, new features
      like robust mutexes and support for full disk encryption with
      GELI.  You'll find expanded graphics support, both at the chipset
      and window manager levels, and ongoing development in many pending
      features.</p>

    <p>Perhaps most exciting, under the hood you'll find a brand-new
      Core Team.</p>

    <p>Don't wait.  Take &os; for a spin today.</p>

    <p>&mdash;Michael W. Lucas</p>

    <p><hr /></p>

    <p>Please submit status reports for the third quarter of 2016 by
      October 7.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os;&nbsp;Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/10.3R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;10.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/11.0R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;11.0-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os; Development Snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is responsible for setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project releases
	of &os;, announcing code freezes and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team completed the 10.3-RELEASE
	cycle late April, led by &a.marius;.  The release was one week
	behind the original schedule, to accommodate for a few
	last-minute critical issues that were essential to fix in the
	final release.</p>

      <p>The &os;&nbsp;11.0-RELEASE cycle started late May, one month
	behind the original schedule.  The schedule slip was primarily
	to accommodate efforts for packaging the &os; base system with the
	<tt>pkg(8)</tt> utility.  However, as work on this progressed,
	it became apparent that there were too many outstanding
	issues.  As a result, packaged base will be a &quot;beta&quot; feature
	for 11.0-RELEASE, with the goal of promoting it to a
	first-class feature in 11.1-RELEASE.  It is expected that
	provisions will be made to ensure a seamless transition from older
	supported releases.</p>

      <p>Despite the fact that packaged base is not going to be a
	prime feature for &os;&nbsp;11.0-RELEASE, the Release
	Engineering Team would like to thank everyone who tested,
	provided patches, provided ideas and feedback, and in some
	cases, shot themselves in the foot due to bugs.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The &os; Foundation
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Obsoleting Rails 3</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Zühlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>tz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Ruby on Rails is the base for most of the rubygems in the
	Ports Collection.  Currently, versions 3.2 and 4.2 coexist.
	Since Rails 3.2 is running out of support, the time has
	come to switch to 4.2.</p>

      <p>While there is ongoing progress to remove Rails 3.2 from
	the ports tree, there are some ports for which this is a major
	update that blocks the overall process.  The most recent blocker
	was the outstanding update of <tt>www/redmine</tt> from 2.6 to
	3.2.  This has completed successfully, so we can now move on.</p>

      <p>To help with porting or testing, feel free to contact me or
	the <tt>ruby@FreeBSD.org</tt> mailing list.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>ARM Allwinner SoC Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jared</given>
	  <common>McNeill</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmcneill@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Emmanuel</given>
	  <common>Vadot</common>
	</name>
	<email>manu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/arm/Allwinner">Allwinner &os; Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Allwinner SoCs are used in multiple hobbyist devboards and
	single-board computers.  Recently, support for these SoCs
	received many updates.</p>

      <p>Theses tasks were completed during the second quarter of
	2016:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Switch to upstream DTS</li>

	<li>A83T SoC support</li>

	<li>H3 SoC support</li>

	<li>Switch to the new clock framework</li>

	<li>Convert the A10 interrupt controller to <tt>INTRNG</tt></li>

	<li>OHCI support</li>

	<li>A generic <tt>ALLWINNER</tt> kernel config file</li>

	<li>A20/A31 NMI support</li>

	<li>AXP209 PMU interrupts, GPIO, and sensors support</li>

	<li>A83T thermal sensor support</li>

	<li>RSB (Reduced Serial Bus) support</li>

	<li>AXP813/AXP818 PMU support</li>

	<li>A83T Security ID support</li>

	<li>Support for the Allwinner Gigabit Ethernet controller found
	  in H3/A83T/A64</li>

	<li>USB OTG
	  <a href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D5881">(in review)</a></li>

	<li>A10/A20 Security ID support
	  <a href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D6383">(in review)</a></li>

	<li>A13 SoC Support
	  <a href="https://reviews.FreeBSD.org/D6809">(in review)</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>Ongoing work:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>A64 support</li>

	<li>Use U-Boot EFI implementation for ARM32/ARM64</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>SPI driver</task>

      <task>LCD Support</task>

      <task>Any unsupported hardware device that might be of
	interest.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Robust Mutexes</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Now that process-shared locks are implemented for our
	POSIX threads implementation, <tt>libthr</tt>,
	the only major feature lacking for POSIX compliance is robust
	mutexes.  Robust mutexes allow applications to detect, and
	theoretically recover from, crashes which occur while
	modifying the shared state.  The supported model is to protect
	shared state by a <tt>pthread_mutex</tt>, and the crash is
	detected as thread termination while owning the mutex.  A
	thread might terminate alone, or it could be killed due to the
	termination of the containing process.   As such, the robust
	attribute is applicable to both process-private and -shared
	mutexes.</p>

      <p>An application must be specifically modified to handle and
	recover from failures.  The <tt>pthread_mutex_lock()</tt>
	function may return a new error <tt>EOWNERDEAD</tt>, which
	indicates that the previous owner of the lock terminated while
	still owning the lock.  Despite returning this non-zero value,
	the lock is granted to the caller.  In the simplest form, an
	application may detect the error and refuse to operate until
	the persistent shared data is recovered, such as by manual
	reinitialization.  More sophisticated applications could try
	to automatically recover from the condition, in which case
	<tt>pthread_mutex_consistent(3)</tt> must be called on the
	lock before unlocking it.  However, such recovery can be
	considered to be very hard.  Still, even the detection of
	inconsistent shared state is useful, since it avoids further
	corruption and random faults of the affected application.
      </p>

      <p>It is curious but not unexpected that this interface is not
	used widely.  The only real-life application which utilizes it
	is Samba.  Using Samba with an updated &os; base uncovered
	minor bugs both in the &os; robust mutex implementation, and
	in Samba itself.</p>

      <p>It is believed that <tt>libthr</tt> in &os; 11 is
	POSIX-compliant for major features.  Further work is planned
	to look at inlining the lock structures to remove overhead
	and improve the performance of the library.</p>

      <p>Most of the implementation of the robustness feature
	consisted of making small changes in the lock and unlock
	paths, both in <tt>libthr</tt> and in <tt>kern_umtx.c</tt>.
	This literally required reading all of the code dealing with
	mutexes and condition variables, which was something I
	wanted to help future developers with.  In the end, with the
	help of Ed Maste, man pages for <tt>umtx(2)</tt> and all
	<tt>thr*(2)</tt> syscalls were written and added to the base
	system's documentation set.
      </p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Use the implementation in real-word applications and
	report issues.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>EFI Refactoring and GELI Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Eric</given>
	  <common>McCorkle</common>
	</name>
	<email>eric@metricspace.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/emc2/freebsd/tree/geli_efi">GELI Support Branch</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/emc2/freebsd/tree/efize">EFI Refactoring Branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The EFI bootloader has undergone considerable refactoring to
	make more use of the EFI API.  The filesystem code in
	<tt>boot1</tt> has been eliminated, and a single codebase for
	filesystems now serves both <tt>boot1</tt> and
	<tt>loader</tt>.  This codebase is organized around the EFI
	driver model and it should be possible to export any
	filesystem implementation as a standalone EFI driver without
	too much effort.</p>

      <p>Both <tt>boot1</tt> and <tt>loader</tt> have been refactored
	to utilize the <tt>EFI_SIMPLE_FILE_SYSTEM</tt> interface.
	In the loader, this is accomplished with a dummy
	filesystem driver that is just a translation layer between the
	loader filesystem interface and
	<tt>EFI_SIMPLE_FILE_SYSTEM</tt>.  A reverse translation layer
	allows the existing filesystem drivers to function as EFI
	drivers.</p>

      <p>The EFI refactoring by itself exists in a
	<a href="https://github.com/emc2/freebsd/tree/efize">branch
	  on github</a>.</p>

      <p>Additionally, GELI support has been added using the EFI
	refactoring.  This allows booting from a GELI-encrypted
	filesystem.  Note that the EFI system partition, which
	contains <tt>boot1</tt>, must be a plaintext msdosfs
	partition.  This patch adds an intake buffer to the crypto
	framework, which allows injection of keys directly into a
	loaded kernel, without the need to pass them through
	arguments or environment variables.  This patch only uses the
	intake buffer for EFI GELI support, as legacy BIOS GELI support
	still uses environment variables.</p>

      <p>EFI GELI support depends on the
	<a href="https://github.com/emc2/freebsd/tree/geli_efi">efize branch</a>.</p>

      <p>These patches have been tested and used and should be able
	to handle use by early adopters.  Note that the
	<tt>LOADER_PATH</tt> variable has been changed to
	<tt>/boot/loader.tst</tt>, to facilitate safe testing.</p>

      <strong>IMPORTANT:</strong>

      <p>As this is an encrypted filesystem patch, an error can
	potentially leave data inaccessible.  It is
	<em>strongly</em> recommended to use the following procedure
	for testing:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>
	  <p>Back up your data!</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Do not forget to back up your data!</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Install an EFI shell on the EFI System Partition (ESP).</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Install the patched <tt>boot1</tt> on the ESP to
	    something like <tt>/boot/efi/BOOTX64.TST</tt>.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Install the patched loader to <tt>/boot/loader.tst</tt>
	    on your machine.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Create a GELI partition outside of the normal boot
	    partition.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>First, try booting <tt>/boot/efi/BOOTX64.TST</tt> and
	    make sure it properly handles the encrypted partition.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Copy a boot environment, including the patched loader, to
	    the encrypted partition.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Use the loader prompt to load a kernel from the encrypted
	    partition.</p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Try switching over to an encrypted main partition once
	    everything else is working.</p>
	</li>
      </ol>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Testing is needed.</task>

      <task>The code will need review, and some <tt>style(9)</tt>
	normalization must occur before it goes into &os;.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Updates to GDB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Baldwin</common>
	</name>
	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Luca</given>
	  <common>Pizzamiglio</common>
	</name>
	<email>luca.pizzamiglio@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>devel/gdb</tt> port has been updated to GDB 7.11.1.</p>

      <p>Support for system call catchpoints has been committed
	upstream.  Support for examining ELF auxiliary vector data via
	<tt>info auxv</tt> has been committed upstream.  Both features
	will be included in GDB 7.12.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Figure out why the <tt>powerpc</tt> <tt>kgdb</tt> targets are not
	able to unwind the stack past the initial frame.</task>

      <task>Add support for more platforms, such as <tt>arm</tt>,
	<tt>mips</tt>, and <tt>aarch64</tt>, to upstream <tt>gdb</tt> for both
	userland and <tt>kgdb</tt>.</task>

      <task>Add support for debugging <tt>powerpc</tt> vector
	registers.</task>

      <task>Add support for <tt>$_siginfo</tt>.</task>

      <task>Implement <tt>info proc</tt> commands.</task>

      <task>Implement <tt>info os</tt> commands.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>VIMAGE Virtualized Network Stack Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern A.</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
       <url href="https://svnweb.FreeBSD.org/base/projects/vnet/">Project Workspace (Now Merged to Head).</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>VIMAGE is a virtualization framework on top of &os; jails
	that was introduced to the kernel about eight years ago with
	the <tt>vnet</tt> virtualized network stack.</p>

      <p>Over the last few years, many people started to use VIMAGE
	in production, production-like setups, and appliances.  This
	adoption increased the urgency to finish the work to avoid
	panics on network stack teardown and to avoid memory
	leaks.</p>

      <p>The <tt>vnet</tt> teardown has been changed to be from top to
	bottom, trying to tear down layer by layer.  This is
	preferable to removing interfaces first and then cleaning
	everything up, as no more packets could flow once the
	interfaces are gone.  Along with this
	work, various paths with potential memory leaks were plugged.
	Lastly, <tt>vnet</tt> support was added to formerly
	unvirtualized components, such as the <tt>pf</tt> and
	<tt>ipfilter</tt> firewalls and some virtual interfaces.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Please test &os; 11.0-ALPHA6 or later.  When reporting
	a problem, use the <tt>vimage</tt> keyword in the &os; bug
	tracker.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>IPv6 Promotion Campaign</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Zühlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>tz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IPv6PortsTODO">Wiki Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Half a year ago, I started a promotion campaign to improve
	support for fetching ports via IPv6.  Research performed in
	December 2015 showed that 10,308 of 25,522 ports were not
	fetchable when using IPv6-only, as these ports ignore the <a
	  href="http://distcache.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD.org <tt>pkg</tt> mirror</a>.</p>

      <p>As a result of the campaign, the following servers now
	successfully support IPv6:</p>

      <ol>
	<li><a href="http://mirror.amdmi3.ru">mirror.amdmi3.ru</a></li>

	<li><a href="http://vault.centos.org">vault.centos.org</a></li>

	<li><a href="http://mirror.centos.org">mirror.centos.org</a></li>

	<li><a href="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org">gstreamer.freedesktop.org</a></li>

	<li><a href="http://people.FreeBSD.org">people.FreeBSD.org</a></li>
      </ol>

      <p>This enables 711 more ports to be fetched via IPv6.</p>

      <p>I would like to thank Wolfgang Zenker, who is very active in
	supporting the adoption of IPv6.  During the latest RIPE
	meeting, he brought up the topic of non-support of IPv6
	being a hindrance to business.  I am hopeful that his talk
	changed some more minds and will help widen the support of
	IPv6.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; on Hyper-V and Azure</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sepherosa</given>
	  <common>Ziehau</common>
	</name>
	<email>sepherosa@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hongjiang</given>
	  <common>Zhang</common>
	</name>
	<email>honzhan@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dexuan</given>
	  <common>Cui</common>
	</name>
	<email>decui@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kylie</given>
	  <common>Liang</common>
	</name>
	<email>kyliel@microsoft.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HyperV">&os; Virtual Machines on Microsoft Hyper-V</url>
      <url href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn531030.aspx">Supported Linux and &os; virtual machines for Hyper-V on Windows</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During BSDCan 2016, Microsoft <a
	  href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/freebsd-now-available-in-azure-marketplace/">announced</a>
	the global availability of &os; 10.3 images in Azure.
	There are many &os;-based Azure virtual appliances in the
	Azure Marketplace, including Citrix Systems' NetScaler and
	Netgate's pfSense.  Microsoft also made an in-depth technical
	presentation to introduce how the performance of the Hyper-V
	network device driver was optimized to reach full line rate on
	10Gb networks and achieved decent performance on 40Gb
	networks.  The slides and video from the presentation are
	available from the <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2016/schedule/events/681.en.html">BSDCan website</a>.</p>

      <p>Microsoft continues to strive to further optimize the
	performance of Hyper-V network and storage device drivers.
	Work is ongoing to replace the internal data structure in the
	LRO kernel API from a singly-linked list to a double-linked
	list, to speed up the LRO lookup by hash table, and to evaluate
	the performance with <tt>tcp_lro_queue_mbuf()</tt>.</p>

      <p>The handling of SCSI inquiry in the Hyper-V storage driver is
	enhanced to make sure that disk hotplug and <tt>smartctl(8)</tt>
	work reliably.  Refer to <a
	  href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=210425">PR 210425</a>
	and <a
	  href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=209443">PR 209443</a>
	for details.</p>

      <p>BIS test cases are available on GitHub for <a
	  href="https://github.com/FreeBSDonHyper-V/Test-BIS">Hyper-V</a>
	and for <a
	  href="https://github.com/FreeBSDonHyper-V/azure-freebsd-automation">Azure</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Microsoft
    </sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Ceph on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Willem Jan</given>
	  <common>Withagen</common>
	</name>
	<email>wjw@digiware.nl</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://ceph.com">Ceph Main Site</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/ceph/ceph">Main Repository</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/wjwithagen/ceph">My Fork </url>
      <url href="https://github.com/ceph/ceph/pull/7573">Pull Request With &os;-Specific Changes to Ceph</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Ceph is a distributed object store and filesystem designed
	to provide excellent performance, reliability, and
	scalability.  It provides the following features:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>Object Storage: Ceph provides seamless access to objects
	  using native language bindings or <tt>radosgw</tt>, a REST
	  interface that is compatible with applications written for
	  S3 and Swift.</li>

	<li>Block Storage: Ceph’s RADOS Block Device (RBD) provides
	  access to block device images that are striped and
	  replicated across the entire storage cluster.</li>

	<li>File System: Ceph provides a POSIX-compliant network
	  filesystem that aims for high performance, large data storage,
	  and maximum compatibility with legacy applications.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>I started looking into Ceph because using HAST with CARP and
	<tt>ggate</tt> did not meet my requirements.  My primary goal
	with Ceph is to run a storage cluster of ZFS storage nodes
	where the clients run <tt>bhyve</tt> on RBD disks stored in Ceph.</p>

      <p>The &os; build process can build most of the tools in
	Ceph.  However, the RBD-dependent items do not work, since
	&os; does not yet provide RBD support.</p>

      <p>Since the last quarterly report, the following progress was
	made:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>Switching to using CMake from Automake results in a
	  much cleaner development environment and better test output.
	  The changes can be found in the
	  <tt>wip-wjw-freebsd-cmake</tt> branch.</li>

	<li>The throttling code has been overhauled to prevent live locks.
	  These mainly occur on &os; but also manifest on Linux.</li>

	  <li>A few more tests were fixed.  On one occasion, I was able to
	  complete the full test suite without errors.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>11-CURRENT is used to compile and build-test Ceph.  The
	Clang toolset needs to be at least version 3.7, as the Clang 3.4
	available on stable/10
	does not have all of the capabilities required to compile
	everything.</p>

      <p>This setup will get things running for &os;:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>
	  <p>Install <tt>bash</tt> and link to it in <tt>/bin</tt>
	    (requires root privileges):</p>

	  <p><tt>sudo pkg install bash</tt></p>

	  <p><tt>sudo ln -s /usr/local/bin/bash /bin/bash</tt></p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>Build Ceph:</p>

	  <p><tt>git clone https://github.com/wjwithagen/ceph.git</tt></p>

	  <p><tt>cd ceph</tt></p>

	  <p><tt>git checkout wip-wjw-freebsd-tests</tt></p>

	  <p><tt>./do_freebsd-cmake.sh --deps</tt></p>
	</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The <tt>--deps</tt> argument is only needed for the initial
	installation, to pull in the necessary dependencies; it should be
	omitted for subsequent builds.</p>

      <p>CMake is now used to build Ceph on &os;; the old method
	using automake is no longer used.</p>

      <p>Parts Not Yet Included:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>RBD: Rados Block Devices are currently implemented in the
	  Linux kernel, but there used to be a userspace
	  implementation.  It is possible that <tt>ggated</tt> could
	  be used as a template, since it provides some of the same
	  functionality and it has a userspace counterpart.</li>

	<li>BlueStore: &os; and Linux have a different AIO API which
	  needs to be bridged.  There has been some
	  discussion about <tt>aio_cancel</tt> not working for all
	  device types in &os;.</li>

	<li>CephFS: Cython tries to access an internal field in
	  <tt> struct dirent</tt>, which fails to compile.</li>

	<li>Tests that verify the correct functionality of these features are
	  also excluded from the test suite.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Tests Not Yet Included:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>ceph-detect-init/run-tox.sh</tt>: the current
	  implementation does not know anything about &os;'s
	  <tt>rc</tt> system.</li>

	<li>Tests that make use of <tt>nosetests</tt> do not really
	  work since <tt>nosetests</tt> is not in <tt>/usr/bin</tt>,
	  and calling <tt>/usr/bin/env nosetests</tt> does not work on
	  &os;.</li>

	<li><tt>test/pybind/test_ceph_argparse.py</tt></li>

	<li><tt>test/pybind/test_ceph_daemon.py</tt></li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The current and foremost task is to get the test suite to
	complete without errors.</task>

      <task>Build an automated test platform that will build
	<tt>ceph/master</tt> on &os; and report the results back to
	the Ceph developers.  This will increase the maintainability
	of the &os; side of things, as developers are signaled that
	they are using Linux-isms that will not compile or run on
	&os;.  Ceph has several projects that support this: Jenkins,
	teuthology, and palpito.  But even a
	<tt>while { compile }</tt> loop that reports the build data on
	a static webpage is a good start.</task>

      <task>Run integration tests to see if the &os; daemons will work
	with a Linux Ceph platform.</task>

      <task>Get the currently excluded Python tests to work.</task>

      <task>Compile and test the userspace RBD (Rados Block
	Device).</task>

      <task>Investigate if an in-kernel RBD device could be developed
	akin to <tt>ggate</tt>.</task>

      <task>Investigate the keystore which currently prevents the
	building of Cephfs and some other parts.</task>

      <task>Integrate the &os; <tt>/etc/rc.d</tt> init scripts in the
	Ceph stack for testing and for running Ceph on production
	machines.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Bringing GitLab into the Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Torsten</given>
	  <common>Zühlsdorff</common>
	</name>
	<email>tz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://freshports.org/www/gitlab">GitLab Port</url>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=208793">PR: Not Starting on Boot</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>After being in the &os; Ports Collection for three months,
	GitLab continues to mature and gain adoption.  Most of its
	initial problems have been resolved, with one known issue
	left: it does not start on boot.  Any help in solving this
	issue is welcome.</p>

      <p>Staying in sync with upstream is now easy for minor versions.
	But, some of the monthly major releases create a big workload
	by introducing a number of new dependencies.  This makes
	testing and updating an expensive process.</p>

      <p>The GitLab project itself now mentions native support on
	&os;, which is quite a commendation.</p>

      <p>Current work aims to fix the open problems, get the latest
	major version into the port, and create documentation for
	the update progress.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ASLR Interim State</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://kib.kiev.ua/kib/aslr">Patch Home</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This is an interim report on the technical state of my
	work towards ASLR support in the &os; base system.</p>

      <p>The <tt>proccontrol(1)</tt> utility was written to manage and
	query ASLR enforcement on a per-process basis.  It is required
	for analyzing ASLR failures in specific programs.  This
	utility leverages the <tt>procctl(2)</tt> interface which was
	added to the previous version of the patch, with some bug
	fixes.</p>

      <p>With r300792, ASLR settings are reset to system-wide defaults
	whenever a setuid binary is executed.</p>

      <p>The command's syntax is:</p>

      <p><tt>proccontrol -m (trace|aslr) [-q] [-s (enable|disable)]
	[-p pid | command]</tt></p>

      <p>with possible arguments</p>

      <p><tt>-m</tt> (specifies the trace mode to control debugger
	attachments)</p>

      <p><tt>-q</tt> (queries the state of the specified mode for the
	process with the PID specified by the <tt>-p</tt> option)</p>

      <p><tt>-s</tt> (toggles the feature on or off for the given
	process or itself)</p>

      <p>If a command is specified, it inherits the applied
	settings from <tt>proccontrol</tt>.  For instance, to start a
	build of a program with ASLR disabled, use
	<tt>proccontrol -m aslr -s disable make</tt>.</p>

      <p>A ports exp-run was done with ASLR tuned up to the most
	aggressive settings.  The results can be found in <a
	  href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=208580">PR 208580</a>.</p>

      <p>Case study: Lisp</p>

      <p>SBCL is an interesting case which illustrates several points.
	It is much smaller than JDK, and its build system is easier to
	work with.  The code provides a very non C-like language
	runtime which utilizes a lot of corner cases and makes non-standard
	uses of the VM system, at least from the point of view of a typical C
	programmer.</p>

      <p>SBCL compiles Lisp forms into the machine native code and
	manages its own arena for objects.  The precompiled Lisp
	runtime is mapped from a <tt>core</tt> file.  SBCL relies on
	the operating system's C runtime for the initial load of Lisp,
	and needs a functional <tt>libc</tt> to issue many system
	calls, including syscalls, as well as the dynamic loader.  The
	end result is that there are unfixed <tt>mmap(2)</tt> calls
	during both startup and runtime, interfering with other
	<tt>MAP_FIXED mmaps</tt>.  The loading of the core file
	and the private arenas are hard-coded to exist at fixed
	addresses.</p>

      <p>This happens to work on the default address map, which is not
	changed often, so the SBCL choices of the base addresses
	evolved to work.  But any significant distortion of the
	standard map results in <tt>SBCL mmap(MAP_FIXED)</tt> requests
	attempting to override memory from other allocators.</p>

      <p>&os; uses the <tt>MAP_EXCL</tt> flag to <tt>mmap(2)</tt>,
	which must be used in the form <tt>MAP_FIXED|MAP_EXCL</tt> to
	cause <tt>mmap(2)</tt> to fail if the requested range is
	already used.  I tried to force <tt>MAP_FIXED</tt> requests
	from SBCL to implicitly set <tt>MAP_EXCL</tt>, but this did
	not go well, since SBCL sometimes pre-allocates regions for
	later use with <tt>MAP_FIXED</tt>.  So, <tt>MAP_EXCL</tt>
	mappings failed, dumping the process into <tt>ldb</tt>.</p>

      <p>On Linux, if it is detected that the kernel is in AS-randomization mode,
	the initial SBCL runtime sets its personality to non-random and
	re-execs.  This might be a solution for &os; as well, after
	the ASLR patch is committed, so that the <tt>procctl(2)</tt>
	knob is officially available.</p>

      <p>SBCL still has issues on Linux, even with re-exec, when
	more aggressive randomization from the PaX patch is applied, as
	seen in <a
	  href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/sbcl/+bug/1523213">bug
	  1523213</a>.</p>

      <p>Case study: Emacs</p>

      <p>The Emacs build procedure involves loading the
	<tt>temacs</tt> image with the compiled Emacs Lisp files and
	then dumping its memory to create an image with the content
	preloaded, in order to reduce startup time.</p>

      <p>Recent Emacs sources seem to generally avoid
	<tt>MAP_FIXED</tt>, except in some situations.  When Emacs
	does use the flag, it carefully checks that the selected
	region is not busy.  In fact, Emacs would benefit from using
	<tt>MAP_EXCL</tt>.</p>

      <p>I tried several runs of building Emacs and running the dumped
	binary, but was not able to reproduce any issues.  It seems
	that the code improved enough to tolerate ASLR both in Linux
	and NetBSD without turning it off.</p>

      <p>In my opinion, it is not reasonable to fight the issues in
	the kernel as most of it is not fixable from the kernel side.
	The <tt>procctl(2)</tt> interface and <tt>proccontrol(1)</tt>
	utilities provide an override when needed, but are not
	automated.</p>

      <p>Conclusions</p>

      <p>The set of ports which cannot be built with ASLR turned on
	should be limited but fluid.  However, exp-runs may not
	reliably uncover all problems due to randomization, as seen in
	the Emacs example.  In the route to enable ASLR by default (with
	non-aggressive settings), the ports framework should provide an
	option like <tt>ASLR_UNSAFE=yes</tt> which spawns
	<tt>proccontrol -m aslr -s disable make</tt> for the build
	stages of the unsafe port.  Users would still need to be aware
	of <tt>proccontrol(1)</tt> in order to run the resulting
	binary or wrapper scripts provided to do so.</p>

      <p>A recommended approach is a flag in the ELF binary to mark
	it as not compatible with non-standard AS layouts.  This frees
	users from having to use <tt>proccontrol(1)</tt>, but still
	requires patching the application's build process and
	upstreaming the changes.  This approach is also
	useful outside the context of ASLR.  However, that
	mechanism is not yet ready, and developing it is a larger work
	than ASLR itself.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>The Graphics Stack on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Graphics team</name>
	<email>freebsd-x11@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Matthew</given>
	  <common>Macy</common>
	</name>
	<email>mmacy@nextbsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop/freebsd-base-graphics">GitHub Repository</url>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Graphics">Graphics Stack Roadmap and Supported Hardware Matrix</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/freebsd-ports-graphics">Ports Development Repository</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop/freebsd-base-graphics/tree/drm-next-4.6">DRM 4.6 Development Repository</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SummerOfCodeIdeas#Devices_management:_link_.2Fdev_entries_to_sysctl_nodes">GSoC 2016: Link <tt>/dev</tt> Entries to Sysctl Nodes</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SummerOfCode2016/RethinkLibdevq">GSoC 2016: Redesign libdevq </url>
      <url href="http://planet.FreeBSD.org/graphics">Graphics Team Blog</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the Ports tree, Mesa was updated to 11.2.2.  The next
	major release, 12.0.0 release candidate 4, is ready for
	testing in our development tree.</p>

      <p>The GSoC project about being able to connect a <tt>/dev</tt>
	entry to <tt>sysctl</tt> nodes is making progress.  After some
	fruitful discussons on the <a
	  href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-arch">freebsd-arch@
	  mailing-list</a>,
	Kiloreux finished the design and is now implementing the
	solution.  The GSoC project on <tt>libdevq</tt> was
	abandoned.</p>

      <p>All Intel GPUs up to and including the unreleased Kaby Lake
	are supported.  The <tt>xf86-video-intel</tt> driver will be
	updated soon.  Updating this driver requires updating
	<tt>Xorg</tt>, which in turn is blocked on Nvidia updates.</p>

      <p>Several problems remain to be solved:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>There are instances of visual artifacts that appear with
	  varying frequency, depending on workload.  Of particular
	  note is the lack of redraw when a Qt5 window is partially
	  covered by a menu and then uncovered.</li>

	<li>WebGL demos will sometimes fail due to a recoverable
	  render ring hang.</li>

	<li>There are still some known stability issues with
	  processors prior to Sandy Bridge (pre-2010).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Matt Macy is hoping to be able to diagnose the first two
	issues, along with others, by updating Linux support to the
	point where the Intel GPU Tools work on &os;.</p>

      <p>The Radeon AMD/ATI driver has been updated to GCN 1.0.  This has
	only been tested on an R7 240.  2D-accelerated X works.  Due
	to apparent issues with user library support, X does not
	recognize the KMS driver as being 3D-capable and reports it as
	&quot;not DRI2 capable&quot;.  The OpenCL benchmark <tt>clpeak</tt>
	fails in <tt>drm/ttm</tt>, so there may in fact be issues in
	the underlying 3D support.</p>

      <p>The Amdgpu AMD/ATI driver has been updated to GCN 1.1 and
	higher.  The KMS driver loads and attaches on discrete GPUs,
	though problems still exist on the Carizzo APU.  X will not
	start due to unimplemented functions in <tt>libdrm</tt>.  Koop
	Mast is actively working on this and should have it fixed
	soon.</p>

      <p>None of the required patches to <tt>src/sys</tt> were
	committed in time for &os; 11.  Although the plan is to
	ultimately make <tt>linuxkpi</tt>, <tt>drm</tt>,
	<tt>i915</tt>, <tt>radeon</tt>, and <tt>amdgpu</tt> updates
	available as ports, this will likely not happen until
	development has slowed to the point where it is economical to
	backport them to &os; in svn.  Until that time, modern GPU
	support will be available in PC-BSD snapshots and in the
	<tt>drm-next-4.6</tt> branch on GitHub.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; IRC Admin Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>IRC Admin Team</name>
	<email>irc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Eitan</given>
	  <common>Adler</common>
	</name>
	<email>eadler@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IRC/">&os; IRC Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; IRC Admin team manages the &os; Project's IRC
	presence on the freenode IRC network, looking after:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Registrations and ongoing management of channels within
	  the official namespace (<tt>#freebsd*</tt>).</li>

	<li>Liaising with freenode staff.</li>

	<li>Allocating freebsd hostmask cloaks for users.</li>

	<li>General user support.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>In order to facilitate a constructive and positive
	environment for all members of the &os; community, IRC Admin
	over the past 3-9 months has established and consolidated a
	consistent baseline with respect to the management of its
	channels on freenode.  This report is a summary of what has
	happened so far and things to come.</p>

      <p>These activities were completed over the last few
	quarters:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Registered &os; Group Contacts (GC) with freenode
	  staff.  For information on what this means, see <a
	    href="https://freenode.net/groupreg">the group
	    registration page</a>.</li>

	<li>Created a &os; NickServ account to assign as primary
	  owner/founder of the <tt>#freebsd*</tt> namespace
	  channels.</li>

	<li>The primary channels are owned/founded by a generic &os;
	  account that is owned and managed by the &os; Project.</li>

	<li>Created the <tt>Services::IRC</tt> component in Bugzilla
	  for change requests and issue reports.</li>

	<li>Obtained a report of all registered freenode channels
	  matching the <tt>#freebsd*</tt> namespace and assessed the
	  list for current ownership and activity status.</li>

	<li>Assigned <tt>freebsd/</tt> user cloaks to users requesting
	  them.  For more information, see <a
	    href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IRC/Cloaks">IRC
	    Cloaks</a>.</li>

	<li>Obtained a report on all nicknames and accounts with
	  existing <tt>freebsd/*</tt> user cloaks.</li>

	<li>Liaised with freenode staff on upcoming changes to freebsd
	  channels.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The goals for the next few quarters are to:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Complete the transfer of founder ownership for all
	  <tt>#freebsd*</tt> channels.  Existing channel creators,
	  some of whom are project members and others who are not,
	  will be contacted using known contact information or contact
	  information set in their registered NickServ account, in
	  order to initiate the transfer of the channel to the &os;
	  Project.  If the contact information of the existing channel
	  owner cannot be obtained, or if no response is received
	  after a suitable period of time has elapsed, IRC Admin will
	  complete the ownership transfer with freenode staff.</li>

	<li>Deregister defunct and inactive <tt>#freebsd*</tt>
	  channels.  Channels which have no visible signs of activity
	  based on last active time or registered owner last seen,
	  have been deprecated by alternative channels, or have no
	  other way of having ownership transferred will be
	  deregistered.  For channels where a sunset period may be
	  suitable, a channel topic will be set, and optionally a
	  forwarding channel, informing users of the changes,
	  including support and contact information.</li>

	<li>Create and document baseline procedures and guidelines.
	  These include: Community and User Guidelines, a Code of
	  Conduct, Operator and Moderator Guidelines and Expectations,
	  Abuse Reporting and Dispute Resolution Guidelines, and
	  procedures for delegation of channel management.</li>

	<li>Standardize and re-create channel access lists.
	  Existing access lists and user permissions for all
	  <tt>#freebsd*</tt> channels remain in their states prior to
	  &os; Group Registration.  Consolidation and reassignment to
	  the &os; Project is needed.  In order to ensure a consistent
	  user and community experience in official &os; channels
	  going forward, access lists for all channels will be created
	  from the ground up.  Users with existing access to channels
	  may, at the IRC Admin team's discretion, be provided with
	  the opportunity to re-apply for access subject to any
	  conditions, terms, or guidelines that may be
	  appropriate.</li>

	<li>Determine the methods for informing project members and
	  the community of future changes to IRC services, procedures,
	  and policies.</li>

	<li>Determine methods to designate existing channel founders
	  as channel managers or similar.</li>

	<li>Update the channels list on the Wiki to distinguish
	  official and unofficial channels.</li>

	<li>Establish consistent modes, entry messages, and topics for
	  all channels.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Users are invited to <tt>/join #freebsd-irc</tt> on the
	freenode IRC network.  The IRC Admin team welcomes ideas,
	contructive criticism, and feedback on how the &os; Project
	can improve the service and experience it provides to the
	community.</p>

      <p>While the vast majority of the broader community interacts on
	the freenode IRC network, the &os; developer presence there
	needs to be significantly improved.</p>

      <p>There are many opportunities to be had by increasing the
	amount and quality of interaction between &os; users and
	developers, both in terms of developers keeping their finger
	on the pulse of the community and in encouraging and
	cultivating greater contributions to the Project over the long
	term.</p>

      <p>It is critical to have a strong developer presence amongst
	users, and IRC Admin would like to call on all developers to
	join the &os; freenode channels to help support that
	presence.  We are the &os; giants on whose shoulders the
	future contributors stand.  It is important to be there, in
	force.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>GNOME on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; GNOME Team</name>
	<email>freebsd-gnome@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome">&os; GNOME Website</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD/freebsd-ports-gnome">Development Repository</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Jhbuild/FreeBSD">Upstream Build Bot</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook/using-gnome.html">USE_GNOME Porter's Handbook Chapter</url>
      <url href="https://bugs.FreeBSD.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=210272">GNOME/Gtk+ 3.20 Update Bug</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; GNOME Team maintains the GNOME, MATE, and CINNAMON
	desktop environments and graphical user interfaces for &os;.
	GNOME 3 is part of the GNU Project.  MATE is a fork of the
	GNOME 2 desktop.  CINNAMON is a desktop environment using
	GNOME 3 technologies, but with a GNOME 2 look and feel.</p>

      <p>GNOME 3.20 was ported with help from Ruslan Makhmatkhanov and
	Gustau Perez.  Work is being done on updating GDM from the old
	3.16 version to the 3.20 version.  For some reason, scrollbars
	in Firefox are no longer working, though this has not been
	investigated.</p>

      <p>With Gtk+ 3.20, theme support was again changed, and the
	changes are not backwards compatible.  If you have a theme
	update that requires the new Gtk+ version, feel free to add it
	as a blocker bug to the GNOME/Gtk+ 3.20 update bug.  This bug
	will be used for the exp-run of GNOME 3.20, when it is ready,
	and to track the theme-related ports.  Also, there is a
	problem with the open and save dialog content going
	invisible.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish GDM 3.20 porting.</task>

      <task>Investigate why the scrollbars in Firefox are missing and
	why the open/save dialog content is missing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The highlight of Core's second quarter has been the
	regular biennial election of a new Core team.  Core would like
	to thank Dag-Erling Sm&oslash;rgrav and Glen Barber for running
	the vote.  Despite an initially slow uptake on nominations,
	fourteen candidates eventually stood, including four incumbent
	members of core.  The ninth &os; Core team will be:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>John Baldwin</li>

	<li>Baptiste Daroussin</li>

	<li>Allan Jude</li>

	<li>Ed Maste</li>

	<li>Kris Moore</li>

	<li>George V. Neville-Neil</li>

	<li>Benedict Reuschling</li>

	<li>Benno Rice</li>

	<li>Hiroki Sato</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The new Core Team would like to thank the departing members
	for their many years of service.  Members stepping down
	are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Gavin Atkinson</li>

	<li>Gleb Smirnoff</li>

	<li>David Chisnall</li>

	<li>Robert Watson</li>

	<li>Peter Wemm</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The second most notable achievement this quarter was the
	successful conclusion of an issue that had been on Core's
	agenda for many years.  With the creation of <a
	  href="https://planet.FreeBSD.org/">planet.FreeBSD.org</a>,
	the &os; Project finally has an official blog aggregation
	service.</p>

      <p>Core spent a significant amount of time reviewing licensing
	and ensuring that the &os; source remains unencumbered by
	onerous license terms.  This quarter involved approving Adrian
	Chadd's plan to import GPLv2 licensed code, allowing
	<tt>bwn(4)</tt> to be built as a loadable module with support
	for 802.11n networking.  This required confirmation that the
	license terms on the latest dummynet AQM patches were
	acceptable and that its variant on the BSD 2-clause license is
	suitable for use in the &os; base system.</p>

      <p>Core applied for, and received, a project-wide license for
	the use of the JetBrains static analysis tool suite, at the
	behest of Mathieu Previot.</p>

      <p>Another of Core's important functions is to ensure good
	relations amongst developers.  To that end, members of Core
	provided oversight over the backing-out of disputed
	<tt>blacklistd</tt>-related patches to OpenSSH, and acted to
	smooth over ruffled tempers.</p>

      <p>This quarter saw the usual quota of gentle reminders to avoid
	intemperate language and other counter-productive behavior.
	Core had to take immediate action about death threats
	appearing on some of the mailing lists.  The culprit was
	immediately banned from the mailing lists and reported to
	their email service provider.  That person will be similarly
	removed should they be identified as having rejoined under a
	different alias.</p>

      <p>Other activities included:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Working with university authorities in an attempt to get
	  documentation certifying that a prospective GSoC student was
	  legally allowed to work on &os; code as a foreigner enrolled
	  at a USA university.  This issue was eventually solved by
	  the student returning home for the summer and working from
	  there.</li>

	<li>Issuing guidance on policy around forced commits, or
	  trivial changes used as a means of correcting a commit
	  message.  In these cases, the correct approach is to revert
	  the commit and re-commit with the correct message.  This
	  ensures the continuing usefulness of
	  <tt>svn blame</tt>.</li>

	<li>Approving a delay to the planned introduction of packaged
	  base and confirming that this did not require any change to
	  the new support policies to be introduced with
	  11.0-RELEASE.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>During this quarter, four new commit bits were awarded and
	none were taken in.  Please welcome Emmanuel Vadot, Landon
	Fuller, Mike Karels, and Eric Badger as new src committers.
	Yes, that is the same Mike Karels who was once a member of the
	CSRG at Berkeley and co-author of <i>The Design and
	  Implementation of the 4.3BSD UNIX Operating System</i>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Issue Triage Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Vladimir</given>
	  <common>Krstulja</common>
	</name>
	<email>vlad-fbsd@acheronmedia.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kubilay</given>
	  <common>Kocak</common>
	</name>
	<email>koobs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>Bugmeister</name>
	<email>bugmeister@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Since the Triage Team was introduced in the October&ndash;December
	2015 report, it has been working on the following three major
	aspects of issue triage:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Recruiting and educating more users to assist in issue
	  triage.</li>

	<li>Identifying problem areas, especially from the fresh eyes
	  perspective, revealing issues not immediately obvious to
	  contributors with experience.</li>

	<li>Proposing changes to improve the issue triage
	  process.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Our efforts have almost exclusively focused on issues in the
	&quot;Ports &amp; Packages&quot; component as that is the easiest
	starting point.  Other categories like &quot;Base System&quot; require
	more knowledge and experience with problem content and
	workflow.</p>

      <p>During this time, Rodrigo was inactive due to lack of
	available time, and Vladimir was unable to commit enough time
	during the first quarter of the year, but provided active
	contribution during the second.  It became obvious that the
	Issue Triage Team must concentrate on additional recruitment
	in the coming quarter.</p>

      <p>In the last two quarters, several problems were identified
	and the formulated solutions will be published on our upcoming
	Wiki page.  A summary of those issues is given here:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>Issue triage, defined as &quot;ensure that an issue is summarized,
	  classified, and assigned to appropriate people&quot;, is too time
	  consuming.  Bugzilla automation through auto-assign helps,
	  but is insufficient.  If the triage process is extended to
	  include &quot;track the issue through its entire life to
	  resolution&quot;, the time and effort required grows
	  exponentially.  Fortunately, there are many things the
	  community can do, with minimum effort, that help greatly.
	  Part of the recruitment and education process is educating
	  users on how to properly treat their own issues and issues
	  they interact with, in order to maximize the efficiency of
	  issue tracking and problem resolution.</li>

	<li>Various timeouts are inadequate.  For example, the
	  maintainer timeout is too long and does not differentiate
	  between classes of issues, such as a non-security and a
	  security timeout.  Other timeouts are not covered, such as
	  assignee timeouts, when an issue has been assigned with no
	  follow-up activity.  Another example is a timeout where
	  additional information was requested but never provided.
	  We will be recommending several changes and documenting
	  these in our Wiki.</li>

	<li>Partially as a consequence of inadequate timeouts and
	  inadequate ability to efficiently track issues through their
	  entire lifecycle, a great number of issues are open for too
	  long.   We have identified several classes of those issues
	  and will document the solutions to each in the near
	  future.</li>

	<li>Bugzilla is not perfect and at times it can hinder the
	  ability to properly track issues clearly and accurately, in
	  order to resolve them quickly.  However, changing bug
	  tracking software is a tremendous effort, so we will instead
	  recommend technical and workflow improvements in order to
	  improve the user experience as much as possible.  For
	  example, we identified additional saved searches to help
	  track and quickly find issue categories and, more
	  importantly, their <strong>states</strong>.  Another example
	  is ensuring that various flags and keywords are unambiguous
	  and well understood.  For instance, &quot;patch&quot; and
	  &quot;patch-ready&quot; can often be misunderstood or
	  misapplied.</li>

	<li>Issue statistics are lacking, and for the next quarter we
	  intend to change that.  Statistics help to provide insight
	  into potential bottlenecks and inform the prioritization of
	  improvements to the issue tracker and workflows.</li>
      </ol>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Recruit more suitable triagers into the team, both
	committers and community members.</task>

      <task>Gather and present some interesting statistics for the
	next report.</task>

      <task>Set up the Wiki page with identified problems and
	recommended guidelines and policies.</task>

      <task>Find common use patterns and add more saved searches to
	Bugzilla.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Using <tt>lld</tt>, the LLVM Linker, to Link &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafael</given>
	  <common>Espíndola</common>
	</name>
	<email>rafael.espindola@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Davide</given>
	  <common>Italiano</common>
	</name>
	<email>dccitaliano@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/LLD">&os; lld Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://lists.llvm.org/pipermail/llvm-dev/2016-March/096449.html">Status Report on Linking &os;/amd64 With lld</url>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2016/schedule/events/656.en.html">BSDCan 2016 Talk on lld for &os;</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><tt>lld</tt> is the linker in the LLVM family of projects.
	It is intended to be a high-performance linker and supports
	the <tt>ELF</tt>, <tt>COFF</tt>, and <tt>Mach-O</tt> object
	formats.  Where possible, <tt>lld</tt> maintains command-line
	and functional compatibility with the existing
	<tt>GNU BFD ld</tt> and <tt>gold</tt> linkers.  However, the
	authors of <tt>lld</tt> are not constrained by strict
	compatibility where it would hamper performance or desired
	functionality.</p>

      <p>Over the last quarter, the <tt>lld</tt> project implemented
	version script support sufficient to handle the &os; base
	system.  This is an important milestone on the path to having
	<tt>lld</tt> as a viable system linker.</p>

      <p><tt>lld</tt> still lacks comprehensive linker script
	expression evaluation support, and therefore cannot yet be
	used to link the &os; kernel.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Develop linker script expression improvements in the
	upstream <tt>lld</tt> project.</task>

      <task>Import a newer <tt>lld</tt> snapshot into the vendor
	area, add the build infrastructure, and connect it to the
	world build, installed as <tt>ld.lld</tt>.</task>

      <task>Request a ports exp-run with <tt>/usr/bin/ld</tt> a
	symlink to <tt>ld.lld</tt>.</task>

      <task>Extensive testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Reproducible Builds in &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/ReproducibleBuilds">Base System Reproducible Builds Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsReproducibleBuilds">Ports Reproducible Builds Wiki Page</url>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2016/schedule/events/714.en.html">BSDCan 2016 Reproducible Builds in &os; talk</url>
      <url href="https://reproducible-builds.org/">Reproducible Builds Website</url>
      <url href="https://diffoscope.org/">Diffoscope Home Page</url>
      <url href="https://people.FreeBSD.org/~emaste/reproducible-builds/iteration-1/diffoscope/">Diffoscope Results from the BSDCan Reproducible Builds Talk</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Reproducible builds are a set of software development
	practices which create a verifiable path from human-readable
	source code to the binary code used by computers.  In brief,
	the idea is that building the same binary, software package,
	document, or other binary artifact twice from the same source
	produces identical output.  The <a
	  href="https://reproducible-builds.org/">reproducible-builds.org
	  website</a>
	provides background information and documentation on making
	builds reproducible.</p>

      <p>Many folks have contributed to the reproducible build effort
	in &os; src and ports over the last decade.  There are many
	practical benefits of reproducible builds, such as bandwidth
	and storage savings.  However, there is a growing interest in
	the broad open source and free software communities,
	primarily from a software and toolchain integrity perspective.
	Over the last few years, some members of the Debian Project
	have led a comprehensive and structured reproducible builds
	effort.</p>

      <p>Baptiste Daroussin and Ed Maste attended the first
	Reproducible Builds Summit in Athens last year.  Since then,
	Ed investigated the state of build reproducibility
	in the ports tree, and presented
	<i>Reproducible Builds in &os;</i> at BSDCan 2016.  With
	some work-in-progress patches, over 80% of the &os; ports tree
	builds reproducibly.</p>

      <p>The Diffoscope tool performs in-depth comparison of files,
	archives, or directories to understand why a binary artifact
	does not build reproducibly.  Diffoscope results for the
	nonreproducible builds in Ed's talk are available at one of
	the links above.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Integrate &os; ports builds into the
	reproducible-builds.org continuous integration
	infrastructure.</task>

      <task>Integrate reproducible build patches into the ports
	tree.</task>

      <task>Investigate sources of nonreproducibility in individual
	ports.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE on &os;</title>

    <contact>
	<person>
	  <name>KDE on &os; team</name>
	  <email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
	</person>
    </contact>

    <links>
	<url href="https://freebsd.kde.org/">KDE on &os; Website</url>
	<url href="https://freebsd.kde.org/area51.php">KDE Ports Staging Area</url>
	<url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/KDE">KDE on &os; Wiki</url>
	<url href="https://mail.kde.org/mailman/listinfo/kde-freebsd">KDE/&os; Mailing List</url>
	<url href="http://src.mouf.net/area51/log/branches/plasma5">Development Repository for Integrating KDE 5</url>
	<url href="http://src.mouf.net/area51/log/branches/qt-5.6">Development Repository for Integrating Qt 5.6</url>
	<url href="http://src.mouf.net/area51/log/branches/qt-5.7">Development Repository for Integrating Qt 5.7</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE on &os; team focuses on packaging and improving the
	user experience of KDE and Qt on &os;.</p>

      <p>Many updates were committed to the ports tree this quarter,
	and even more were committed to our experimental ports
	repository.  Tobias Berner, Adriaan de Groot, and Ralf Nolden
	were responsible for most of the work.</p>

      <p>The following notable updates landed in the ports tree this
	quarter:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The CMake ports were updated to 3.5.1 and 3.5.2.</li>

	<li>The DigiKam ports were updated to 4.14.0.</li>

	<li>The KDevelop ports were updated to 4.7.3.</li>

	<li>The <tt>devel/qbs</tt> port was added for Qt's future
	  build system,
	  <a href="https://wiki.qt.io/Qt_Build_Suite">QBS</a>.</li>

	<li>Qt Creator was updated to 3.4.0, 3.5.0, 3.5.1, 3.6.0,
	  4.0.0, 4.0.1, and 4.0.2.</li>

	<li>A new port <tt>misc/qt5-examples</tt> was added for the
	  project examples provided by Qt.  This makes Qt Creator more
	  functional.</li>

	<li>A new port <tt>misc/qt5-doc</tt> was added for Qt's API
	  documentation, used by Qt Creator and other programs.</li>

	<li>The base KDE4 ports were updated to 4.14.10.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The following work occurred in our development
	repository:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Created ports for Qt 5.6.1-1
	  (<tt>branches/qt-5.6</tt>).</li>

	<li>Created ports for Qt 5.7.0
	  (<tt>branches/qt-5.7</tt>).</li>

	<li>The plasma5 branch is up-to-date with KDE's upstream and
	  contains ports for Frameworks 5.24.0, Plasma Desktop 5.7.0,
	  and Applications 16.04.2 (<tt>branches/plasma5</tt>).</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>René</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>&os; Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">&os; Ports Website</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">How to Contribute</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">Ports Monitoring Website</url>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team Website</url>
      <url href="https://twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/">Ports Management Team on Twitter</url>
      <url href="https://www.facebook.com/portmgr">Ports Management Team on Facebook</url>
      <url href="https://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383">Ports Management Team on Google+</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The 2016Q3 branch of the Ports Tree currently contains over
	26,100 ports, with the PR count around 2,000.  Of those,
	around 425 are unassigned.  The activity dropped somewhat,
	with 5,300 commits made by 125 active committers.  Almost
	1,760 PRs were closed in the last quarter.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter, we added two new committers: Ben Woods
	(<tt>woodsb02</tt>) and Torsten Zühlsdorff (<tt>tz</tt>).  No
	commit bits were taken in for safe keeping.</p>

      <p>On the management side, <tt>mat</tt> took over the role of
	cluster admin liaison from <tt>erwin</tt>, who decided to step
	down from portmgr.  <tt>rene</tt> took over the role of port
	manager secretary from <tt>culot</tt>.  No other changes were
	made.</p>

      <p>A lot of work was done on modernizing the infrastructure of
	the Ports Tree, by introducing 6 new <tt>USES</tt> knobs, one new
	keyword, and splitting out the larger targets of
	<tt>bsd.port.mk</tt> into separate scripts.  There were a
	total of 42 exp-runs to validate these and other
	infrastructure changes and package updates.  Furthermore,
	checks were added to the quality assurance phase of Poudriere
	to check for missing indirect dependencies, and advancements
	were made for reproducable package builds.</p>

      <p>Some noticeable package updates are: Firefox 47.0.1, Firefox
	ESR 45.2.0, Thunderbird 45.1.1, Chromium 51.0.2704.106, Ruby
	2.2.5, Ruby Gems 2.6.2, pkg 1.8.6, gmake 4.2.1, KDE 4.14.10,
	Python 2.7.12, libc++ 3.8.0, and binutils 2.26.</p>

      <p>Behind the scenes, <tt>antoine</tt> made sure that the
	exp-run- and package builders were kept up-to-date.
	<tt>bdrewery</tt> worked on further automating and hardening
	the package building infrastructure.</p>

      <p>During BSDCan, <tt>mat</tt> worked on various items,
	including updating the Porter's Handbook, and portmgr held a
	meeting to discuss various items.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/arm64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/arm64">&os;/arm64 Wiki Entry</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>arm64 pmap</tt> code has been updated to work with
	the full 4 pagetable levels.  This allows us to increase the
	user virtual address space to 256TB, with a concomittant increase of the
	kernel virtual address space.  It also allows an increase in
	the size of the physical memory &os; can handle to up to
	2TB.</p>

      <p>The interrupt framework has been replaced with
	<tt>intrng</tt> on <tt>arm64</tt>.  This allows both
	<tt>arm</tt> and <tt>arm64</tt> to share interrupt controller
	drivers, as is the case with the <tt>GICv2</tt> driver.  The
	<tt>GICv3 ITS</tt> driver has been rewritten to better
	integrate with <tt>intrng</tt>.</p>

      <p>Busdma was updated to handle the cache.  The updated code
	assumes that devices are non-coherent by default, unless the
	device driver marks the DMA tag as coherent when creating it.
	The generic and ThunderX PCIe drivers have been updated to
	create coherent mappings when the device tree marks the
	hardware as coherent.  This work also fixed issues found with
	the sync operation where it was missing memory barriers.</p>

      <p>A number of issues with <tt>hwpmc</tt> have been fixed.  This
	improves the stability of <tt>hwpmc</tt> on <tt>arm64</tt>,
	with no known software issues.  There is a single known issue
	which seems to be hardware-related, however, further testing is
	required.</p>

      <p><tt>NEW_PCIB</tt> has been enabled on <tt>arm64</tt>.  This
	includes handling the <tt>PCI_RES_BUS</tt> resource type.</p>

      <p>Old interfaces replaced before &os;-11 have been removed from the
	<tt>arm64</tt> kernel and libraries.  This includes support
	for compatibility with <tt>libc</tt> from releases prior to
	11.0.  The <tt>brk</tt> and <tt>sbrk</tt> functions have also
	been removed.  This allows a workaround for these functions in
	the <tt>arm64</tt> C runtime to be removed.</p>

      <p><tt>loader.efi</tt> has been updated to use an event timer to
	implement its internal time function.  This is needed, as many
	UEFI implementations do not handle the <tt>GetTime</tt>
	runtime service method.  This means that <tt>loader.efi</tt> will
	now correctly count down before automatically booting.</p>

      <p>Initial support for the ARM Juno reference platform has been
	added.  This hardware is common within ARM, and has been
	useful for finding assumptions on cpuids.  Booting on the Juno
	required fixing the kernel to remove the assumption that it is
	booting from CPU zero.  This included assigning cpuids and
	fixing assumptions within the <tt>GICv2</tt> driver that the
	cpuid is the same as the <tt>GIC</tt> cpuid.  &os; can now
	boot on the 4 Cortex-A53 CPUs of the Juno board.
	Further investigation is needed to track down why the boot
	fails when the 2 Cortex-A57 CPUs are enabled.</p>

      <p>Initial work has started on booting &os; on the Pine64 and
	Raspberry Pi 3 boards.  Both can boot to multiuser mode with
	out-of-tree patches.  Further work is needed to bring these
	patches into the tree, but it is expected this will happen
	soon after the end of the code freeze.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The FreeBSD Foundation</sponsor>

    <sponsor>ABT Systems Ltd</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/">FreeBSD Foundation Website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit
	organization dedicated to supporting and promoting the &os;
	Project and community worldwide.  Funding comes from individual and
	corporate donations and is used to fund and manage development
	projects, conferences and developer summits, and provide travel
	grants to &os; developers.  The Foundation purchases hardware to
	improve and maintain &os; infrastructure and publishes &os;
	white papers and marketing material to promote, educate, and
	advocate for the &os; Project.  The Foundation also represents
	the &os; Project in executing contracts, license agreements,
	and other legal arrangements that require a recognized legal
	entity.</p>

      <p>Here are some highlights of what we did to help &os;
	last quarter:</p>

      <p>Fundraising Efforts</p>

      <p>Our work is 100% funded by your donations.  Our spending
	budget for 2016 is $1,250,000 and we've raised $265,000 so far.
	Our Q1-Q2 financial reports will be posted by August 1.  As you can
	see, we need your donations to continue supporting &os; at our
	current level.  Please consider making a donation here:
	<a href="http://freebsdfoundation.org/donate">freebsdfoundation.org/donate</a>.</p>

      <p>OS Improvements</p>

      <p>The Foundation improves &os; by funding software
	development projects approved through our proposal submission
	process, and our internal software developer staff members.  Two
	Foundation-funded projects continued last quarter; one project is
	to improve the stability of the vnet network stack virtualization
	infrastructure, and the second is phase two of the &os;/arm64
	port project.</p>

      <p>Foundation staff members were responsible for many changes
	over the quarter.  Kostik Belousov accomplished the following work
	last quarter: implemented robust mutexes support, as part of
	ongoing efforts to bring our threading library into POSIX
	compliance and feature completeness; documented kernel interfaces
	used by the threading library and produced almost 30 pages of
	technical text; completed and committed the elimination of the
	pvh_global_lock from the amd64 pmap, which removed a hot contested
	lock; and fixed bugs that help keep &os; stable and
	reliable.</p>

      <p>Edward Napierala accomplished the following work last
	quarter: added filesystem thoughput limits to RCTL; committed iSER
	initiator support; added support for rerooting into NFS; and added
	<tt>iscsictl -e</tt>, which makes it possible to enable and disable
	iSCSI sessions.</p>

      <p>Ed Maste, our Project Development Director,  accomplished
	the following work last quarter: investigated the state of
	reproducible builds in the ports tree, with some work in progress
	to address issues; updated the ELF Tool Chain tools with bug fixes
	and improved handling of malformed input; investigated using
	<tt>lld</tt>, the linker from the LLVM family, to link the &os;
	base system; and reported on and tested patches for issues found.
	He also managed the <tt>arm64</tt> development project and
	investigated and fixed a number of bugs.  Lastly, he imported
	LLVM's <tt>libunwind</tt> and prepared it for use in &os; 11, and
	investigated and reviewed the <tt>blacklistd</tt> proposal and
	patches.</p>

      <p>George Neville-Neil continued hosting the bi-weekly Transport
	conference call (notes at <a
	  href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/TransportProtocols">https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/TransportProtocols</a>)
	and the bi-weekly DTrace conference call (notes at <a
	  href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DTrace">https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DTrace</a>.</p>

      <p>Ed continued facilitating the bi-weekly graphics call to
	coordinate efforts on the <tt>i915</tt> driver and other graphics
	stack work.</p>

      <p>Several of these projects are described elsewhere in this
	quarterly report.</p>

      <p>Release Engineering</p>

      <p>Foundation employee and release engineer Glen Barber worked
	closely with Marius Strobl on the 10.3-RELEASE, which was
	completed in April.  Glen also merged the release-pkg branch to
	11-CURRENT, though this will be a beta feature for 11.0-RELEASE.
	Lastly, with the Release Engineering Team, he started the
	11.0-RELEASE cycle.  Find out more in the Release Engineering Team
	status entry in this report.</p>

      <p>&quot;Getting Started with &os;&quot; Project</p>

      <p>We hired a summer intern, with no &os;, Linux, or any
	command line operating system experience, to figure out on his own
	how to install and use &os;.  He is writing easy-to-follow how-to
	guides to help make the new user experience straightforward and
	positive.  He's also been submitting bug reports and problems
	through the appropriate channels.  You can check out his first
	how-to guide at <a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/freebsd/how-to-guides/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/freebsd/how-to-guides/</a>.</p>

      <p>&os; Advocacy and Education</p>

      <p>A large part of our efforts are dedicated to advocating for
	the Project.  This includes promoting work being done by others
	with &os;; producing advocacy literature to teach people about
	&os; and help make the path to starting using &os; or
	contributing to the Project easier; and attending and getting
	other &os; contributors to volunteer to run &os; events,
  staff &os; tables, and give &os; presentations.</p>

      <p>Some of the work we did last quarter to support &os;
	advocacy included:  Creating a &os; page on our website to promote
	&os; derivative projects and showcase &os; users (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/freebsd/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/freebsd/</a>),
	and promoting &os; research by creating a Research page on our
	site and conference handout (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/what-we-do/research/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/what-we-do/research/</a>).</p>

      <p>We created guidelines and a repository for using the Project and
	Foundation logos (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/about/brand-assets/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/about/brand-assets/</a>).</p>

      <p>To help showcase &os; contributors, we published two new Faces
	of &os; stories, about Michael Lucas (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/faces-of-freebsd-2016-michael-lucas/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/faces-of-freebsd-2016-michael-lucas/</a>)
	and Kris Moore <a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/faces-of-freebsd-2016-kris-moore/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/faces-of-freebsd-2016-kris-moore/</a>).</p>

      <p>We published the March/April and May/June issues of the
	&os; Journal and participated in editorial board work.  Kirk
	McKusick wrote a feature article on the Fast Filesystem for the
	March/April issue, and other team members helped review and edit
	Journal articles.</p>

      <p>We also published monthly newsletters to highlight work being
	done to support &os;, tell you about upcoming events, and provide
	other information to keep you in the loop on what we're doing to
	support the &os; Project and community.</p>

      <p>George Neville-Neil and Robert Watson continued teaching
	and developing open source &os; teaching materials at
	<a href="http://teachbsd.org">teachbsd.org</a>.</p>

      <p>We launched the first Hosting Partner Spotlight to showcase
	the Project's partnership with NYI (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/hosting-partner-spotlight-nyi-at-the-heart-of-freebsd/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/hosting-partner-spotlight-nyi-at-the-heart-of-freebsd/</a>)</p>

      <p>We worked with Microsoft to get &os; onto Azure (<a
	  href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/more-from-the-freebsd-foundation-on-the-projects-partnership-with-microsoft/">https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/blog/more-from-the-freebsd-foundation-on-the-projects-partnership-with-microsoft/</a>).</p>

      <p>The Foundation was quoted in Cavium's Thunder X2 press release
	(<a href="http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/cavium-announces-thunderx2-300276536.html">http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/cavium-announces-thunderx2-300276536.html</a></p>

      <p>George worked with ARM to coordinate the upcoming ARM Partner
	Meeting in Cambridge.</p>

      <p>Conferences and Events</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation sponsors many conferences, events,
	and summits around the globe.  These events can be BSD-related,
	open source, or technology events geared towards underrepresented
	groups.</p>

      <p>We support the &os;-focused events to help provide a
	venue for sharing knowledge, to work together on projects, and to
	facilitate collaboration between developers and commercial users.
	This all helps provide a healthy ecosystem.  We support the
	non-&os; events to promote and raise awareness about &os;, to
	increase the use of &os; in different applications, and to recruit
	more contributors to the Project.</p>

      <p>In April, Benedict Reuschling helped organize and run a
	hackathon in Essen April 22-24.  He then attended the Open Source
	Datacenter conference in Berlin, with Allan Jude, to give a talk
	about &quot;Interesting things you can do with ZFS,&quot; which highlighted
	OpenZFS features and how well they work on &os;
	(<a href="https://www.netways.de/index.php?id=3445#c44065">https://www.netways.de/index.php?id=3445#c44065</a>).</p>

      <p>We promoted &os; at:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Flourish &mdash; April 1-2 in Chicago
	  (<a href="http://flourishconf.com/2016/">http://flourishconf.com/2016/</a>)</li>

	<li>LFNW &mdash; April 23-24 in Bellingham WA
	  (<a href="https://www.linuxfestnorthwest.org/2016">https://www.linuxfestnorthwest.org/2016</a>).</li>

	<li>OSCON &mdash; May 18-19 in Austin, TX
	  (<a href="http://conferences.oreilly.com/oscon/open-source-us">http://conferences.oreilly.com/oscon/open-source-us</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>Deb Goodkin and Dru Lavigne attended the Community
	Leadership Summit in Austin: May 14, 15
	(<a href="http://www.communityleadershipsummit.com/schedule/">http://www.communityleadershipsummit.com/schedule/</a>)</p>

      <p>Deb promoted &os; at USENIX ATC June 22-23 in Denver, CO.</p>

      <p>Our team attended BSDCan and the Ottawa Developer Summit.
	We held our annual board meeting to vote on officers, board
	members, and work on our strategic planning.  Most of us attended
	the developer/vendor summits.  Kirk McKusick presented &quot;A
	Brief History of the BSD Fast Filesystem&quot; (<a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2016/schedule/events/654.en.html">http://www.bsdcan.org/2016/schedule/events/654.en.html</a>).
	Ed Maste gave a presentation on &quot;Reproducible Builds in
	&os;&quot;.  George helped run the vendor summit.</p>

      <p>We sponsored five &os; contributors to attend BSDCan.</p>

      <p>Legal/&os; IP</p>

      <p>The Foundation owns the &os; trademarks, and it is our
	responsibility to protect them.  We continued to review requests
	and grant permission to use the trademarks.</p>

      <p>&os; Community Engagement</p>

      <p>We launched our first Community Survey.  The purpose was to get
	input from the community on why they use &os;, what they'd like to
	see the Foundation support, and other input to help us determine
	our direction and how we should support the Project.</p>

      <p>Anne Dickison, our Marketing Director,
	has been overseeing the efforts to rewrite the Project's Code of
	Conduct to help make this a safe, inclusive, and welcoming
	community.</p>

      <p>Other Stuff We Did</p>

      <p>Last quarter we purchased a server to reside at NYI to
	improve the continuous integration tools within the Project.</p>

      <p>We had two face-to-face board meetings last quarter to work
	on strategic planning and identify areas in the project we should
	support.</p>

      <p>We also held our first ever staff retreat in Boulder,
	Colorado to give our small team an opportunity to work together
	in person.</p>

      <p>We hired Sabine Percarpio as our Administration Manager.
	She is helping us manage donations, accounting, travel grant
	applications, handle questions that come in to the Foundation, and
	run our organization smoothly.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Intel Networking Tools</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sergey</given>
	  <common>Kozlov</common>
	</name>
	<email>sergey.kozlov@intel.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Several tools for Intel(R) Ethernet networking products are
	now available as ports and packages for &os;:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>sysutils/intel-nvmupdate</tt>: An application that is used
	  to update non-volatile memory on XL710- and X710-based network
	  devices.</li>

	<li><tt>sysutils/intel-qcu</tt>: An application used to switch
	  QSFP+ ports between 1x40Gbps and 4x10Gbps mode on XL710-based
	  network devices.</li>

	<li><tt>net/intel-ixl-kmod</tt>: An updated driver which enables
	  the tools support on &os;-10.x.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Intel Corporation
    </sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>&os; 11 support is under development and will be included in the
	next release.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
