<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status
Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2008-04-2008-06.xml,v 1.1 2008/08/19 23:04:12 brd Exp $ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>April - June</month>

    <year>2008</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This Status Report covers FreeBSD related projects between April
    and June 2008. During this period The FreeBSD Foundation has
    released their <a
    href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/press/2008Jul-newsletter.shtml">July
    Newsletter</a>.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
    enjoy reading.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>FreeBSD Architecture</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>The Ports Collection</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>ARM/Marvell port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Rafal</given>

          <common>Jaworowski</common>
        </name>

        <email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bartlomiej</given>

          <common>Sieka</common>
        </name>

        <email>tur@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/arm/src/sys/arm/orion/&amp;c=0h4@//depot/projects/arm/src/sys/arm/orion/?ac=83">Orion in Perforce</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>After the last couple of months of intensive development going
      on towards FreeBSD support for Marvell System-on-Chip devices, we
      have FreeBSD 8.0-CURRENT running on the following systems:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Orion (already available in Perforce):</li>
	<ul>
	  <li>88F5281</li>
	  <li>88F5181</li>
	  <li>88F5182</li>
        </ul>
	<li>Kirkwood - 88F6281</li>
	<li>Discovery - MV78100</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The above families of SOCs are built around CPU
      cores compliant with ARMv5TE instruction set architecture
      definition. They share a number of integrated peripherals, for most
      of which we already have operational and stable drivers:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>UART</li>
	<li>EHCI USB 2.0</li>
	<li>Ethernet</li>
	<li>IDMA (general purpose DMA engine)</li>
	<li>XOR</li>
	<li>TWSI (I2C)</li>
	<li>Timers, watchdog, RTC</li>
	<li>GPIO</li>
	<li>Interrupt controller</li>
	<li>L1, L2 cache</li>
      </ul>
      <p>High level functional summary:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Production Quality</li>
	<li>Error-free Operation</li>
	<li>Multiuser</li>
	<li>Self-hosted kernel/world builds</li>
	<li>NFS- or USB-mounted root filesystem</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The code is partially available (Orion in Perforce), other
        variants will also be integrated with Perforce/SVN soon.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Drivers that are In-progress: PCI and PCIE.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Graphics support for the boot loader</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Oliver</given>

          <common>Fromme</common>
        </name>

        <email>olli@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/OliverFromme/BootLoader" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project aims to implement graphics support for FreeBSD's
      boot loader. It will replace the existing ASCII menu. (Note that
      the ASCII menu will still be available when graphics mode cannot be
      used, such as on serial console or on unsupported hardware.)</p>

      <p>For a more detailed description and screen shots please refer to
      the project's Wiki URL above.</p>

      <p>Progress is slow (due to lack of time) but steady. The code
      currently lives in the Perforce repository. I'll try to prepare a
      first public CFT as soon as possible.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Implement a platform switch.</task>

      <task>Implement "themes" support (in FORTH).</task>

      <task>Documentation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeBSD Bugbusting Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ceri</given>

          <common>Davies</common>
        </name>

        <email>bugmeister@</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Remko</given>

          <common>Lodder</common>
        </name>

        <email>bugmeister@</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>bugmeister@</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/support.html#gnats">GNATS</url>
    <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/BugBusting">BugBusting</url>
    <url
    href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/pr_manpage_index.html">
    PRs indexed by manpage</url>
    <url
    href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/pr_tag_index.html">
    PRs indexed by tag</url>
    <url
    href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/prs_possibly_committed.html">
    PRs which may have already been committed</url>
    <url
    href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/well_known_prs.html">
    Well-Known PRs as determined by the bugbusting team</url>
    <url
    href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/JeremyChadwick/Commonly_reported_issues">
    Commonly Reported Issues</url>
    maintained by Jeremy Chadwick (includes commentary and
    analysis)</links>

    <body>
      <p>We have granted Bruce Cran (bruce@) direct access to GNATS and
      Volker Werth (vwe@) has been released from mentorship. We
      appreciate their help!</p>

      <p>We had a third bugathon in June, which resulted in the closing
      of a number of bugs and the investigation/classification of several
      others. We are still trying to find ways to get more committers
      helping us with closing PRs that the team has already analyzed.</p>

      <p>We continue to make good progress in categorizing PRs as they
      arrive with 'tags' that correspond to manpages. (Special thanks go
      to Dylan Cochran for the help.) As a result, we now have created
      some prototype reports that allow browsing the database 
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/pr_manpage_index.html">
      by manpage</url>.</p>

      <p>In addition, another new report, oriented towards PR submitters,
      summarizes the 
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~linimon/studies/prs/well_known_prs.html">
      most commonly reported issues</url>.
      Many of these issues persist because they are difficult to fix.
      Before filing a PR, you may want to check through this list.</p>

      <p>Mark Linimon summarized the good technical suggestions from the
      bugathons so far this year to the wiki. As a part of this, he
      rearranged the wiki pages, so if you have not seen them for a
      while, please see 
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/BugBusting">BugBusting</url>.
      In particular, the Resources page is much more complete.</p>

      <p>Jeremy Chadwick (koitsu@) is now maintaining a 
      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/JeremyChadwick/Commonly_reported_issues">
      page</url>

      that summarizes some of the commonly reported issues. This
      complements some of the reports, above, but includes a great deal
      more information, including how-tos.</p>

      <p>The overall PR count has been holding at around 5300 since the
      last release.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Think of some way for committers to only view PRs that have
      been in some way 'vetted' or 'confirmed'.</task>

      <task>Generate more publicity for what we've already got in place,
      and for what we intend to do next.</task>

      <task>Define new categories, classifications, and states for PRs,
      that will better match our workflow.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Build cluster</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kris</given>

          <common>Kennaway</common>
        </name>

        <email>kris@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>For the past couple of months I have been working on
      generalizing the package build cluster to allow it to host other
      batch and interactive jobs. Currently we make an inefficient use of
      build machines because various projects have dedicated machines
      that are either underloaded or overloaded for their particular
      tasks. The goal is to provide a framework for combining all of
      these machine resources into a single cluster that can be shared by
      many users, reducing dead time and allowing distributed build tasks
      to take advantage of extra build resources when available.
      Developers will be able to obtain on-demand interactive access to a
      jail running on any of the available architectures, with root
      access. Similarly, batch jobs will specify their resource
      requirements and be dispatched to run on a suitable machine in the
      cluster. Current status: The job queue manager is working and is
      now being used to map package builds to machines. Various package
      build scripts have been rewritten to use it instead of the previous
      build scheduler. The generic job dispatcher is being prototyped and
      will be validated with several existing services such as INDEX
      builds. Various support services like ZFS snapshot replication have
      been written.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Dutch Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Remko</given>

          <common>Lodder</common>
        </name>

        <email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Rene</given>

          <common>Ladan</common>
        </name>

        <email>r.c.ladan@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd-nl.org">Main documentation site</url>

      <url href="http://www.evilcoder.org/freebsd_nl/">Project site</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
        <p>The FreeBSD Dutch Documentation Project is an ongoing project
        to translate the FreeBSD Documentation resources to the Dutch
        language.</p>

        <p>The project is currently progressing very well in translating
        the FreeBSD Handbook to the Dutch language, the last chapter is
        being translated by the project members.</p>

        <p>Recent achievements include the translation of the Jails
        chapter, and the Virtualization chapter, as well as progression
        on the Advanced Networking chapter. Rene Ladan is a keyplayer in
        that region.</p>

        <p>We also started with the FAQ translation, which is another
        major target which we should be reaching at some point.</p>

        <p>If you care to helpout with the translation(s) and/or want to
        know something about it, please do not hesitate to contact us, we
        are glad to help where possible.</p>
      </p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish the Handbook translation.</task>

      <task>Finish the FAQ translation.</task>

      <task>Finish the Website translation.</task>

      <task>Keep the projects in sync with the English version(s).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>FreeBSD FAQ Renovation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Páli</common>
        </name>

        <email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Manolis</given>

          <common>Kiagias</common>
        </name>

        <email>manolis@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en/books/faq/">
      </url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/faq-renewal">FreeBSD FAQ Renewal
      Proposal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An extensive work on renovating the FreeBSD FAQ has been started
      to support its Greek and Hungarian translations. Further
      improvements and content changes are still possible, we hope other
      committers will help us to keep the FAQ updated and tuned
      further.</p>

      <p>We have launched a renewal proposal to collect and organize the
      ideas around a more interactive, accurate, open for comments,
      consistent across several views etc. FAQ document. We would like to
      experiment with methods to implement the goals mentioned before,
      and help is more than welcome.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Review the renovated FAQ.</task>

      <task>Add more question and answers to the FAQ.</task>

      <task>Refine the FAQ renewal proposal.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>finstall</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/finstall" />

      <url href="http://www.sf.net/projects/finstall" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Between the last report and this one, the project has yielded a
      LiveCD installer for i386 containing FreeBSD 7.0-RELEASE. The
      project was presented at BSDCan 2008. The development is
      progressing slowly due to the lack of free time. I'm looking for
      funding that will allow me more involvement in the project. The big
      item currently in development is documentation and description of
      the protocol used between the front-end and the back-end, which
      will result in more robustness in the implementation and could
      support third-party clients. This sub-project is near completion.
      The project is currently hosted at SourceForge to allow
      contribution from non-FreeBSD developers.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Partition editor.</task>

      <task>Package selection.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Hungarian Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Páli</common>
        </name>

        <email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.org/hu">Hungarian Web Site for
      FreeBSD</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/hu_HU.ISO8859-2/">Hungarian
      Documentation for FreeBSD</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HungarianDocumentationProject">
      The FreeBSD Hungarian Documentation Project's Wiki Page</url>

      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/docproj_hu/&amp;c=aXw@//depot/projects/docproj_hu/?ac=83">
      Perforce Depot for The FreeBSD Hungarian Documentation
      Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Hungarian translation of the 
      <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/hu/books/handbook">
      FreeBSD&nbsp;Handbook</a>

      has been finally committed to the doc repository. The translation
      of the 
      <em>FreeBSD&nbsp;FAQ</em>

      has also been started, however, the original document needed to be
      brought up to date first. Two other article translations has been
      added, 
      <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/hu/articles/compiz-fusion">
      compiz-fusion</a>

      and 
      <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/hu/articles/linux-users">
      linux-users</a>.</p>

      <p>Our Perforce depot was reorganized for the better layout, giving
      newcomers more space to play. The 
      <a
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/doc/el_GR.ISO8859-7/share/tools/checkupdate/checkupdate.py">
      checkupdate</a>

      script written by Giorgos&nbsp;Keramidas, a new tool for checking
      translations has been adopted to help the project's work.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Translate release notes for -CURRENT and 7.X.</task>

      <task>Translate more articles.</task>

      <task>Translate books/fdp-primer.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Qt/KDE4 Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Martin</given>

          <common>Wilke</common>
        </name>

        <email>miwi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeBSD KDE Team</given>
        </name>

        <email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://freebsd.kde.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Qt4 has been updated to 4.4.1 in our test repository. We ran
      into some runtime problems with Qt 4.4.0, so it was never committed
      it to the ports tree. Most of the problems have been fixed in 4.4.1
      and we plan to commit it in a few days.</p>

      <p>At the moment, the KDE 4.1 ports are ready for testing before
      they are committed to the FreeBSD ports tree. We have already had
      the first Call for Public Testing on July 17th, 2008 with KDE 4.1
      beta2. The feedback has been positive so far. If you want to help
      to test them to speed up the process, please visit the 
      <a href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/KDE4/install">Wiki page</a>

      and provide feedback.</p>

      <p>We plan to have it all committed by the middle of August.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Layer2 filtering</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gleb</given>

          <common>Kurtsou</common>
        </name>

        <email>gk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Thompson</common>
        </name>

        <email>thompsa@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/GlebKurtsov/Improving_layer2_filtering" />

      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/gleb/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Project aims to improve layer2 filtering in ipfw and pf. So far
      following project goals are achieved: pfil framework is extended to
      handle ethernet packets, ipfw layer2 filtering is greatly
      simplified, added l2filter and l2tag per interface flags. Both ipfw
      and pf firewalls support filtering by ethernet addresses, support
      stateful filtering with ethernet addresses and firewall's lookup
      tables are extended to contain ethernet addresses.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Implement ARP filtering options in IPFW.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/ports/">The FreeBSD Ports
      Collection</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">
      Contributing to the FreeBSD Ports Collection</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~fenner/portsurvey/">FreeBSD
      ports unfetchable distfile survey (Bill Fenner's report)</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">The FreeBSD
      Ports Management Team</url>

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com">marcuscom
      Tinderbox</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports count has jumped to over 19,000. The PR count has been
      holding steady at around 900.</p>

      <p>KDE has been updated to 4.1. Special thanks go to Martin Wilke
      for a great deal of pre-testing.</p>

      <p>GNOME has been updated three times, first to 2.22.1 and then to
      2.22.2 and 2.22.3.</p>

      <p>Other notable updates are automake, gettext, libtool, and
      m4.</p>

      <p>Florent Thoumie has been working on some updates to the pkg_*
      tools.</p>

      <p>Ion-Mihai Tetcu has set up a tinderbox with several purposes:
      first, to quickly try to build packages as changes are committed;
      secondly, to build them with a non-standard set of environment
      variables; and thirdly, to build older packages with the non-
      standard set of environment variables. As a result of all this
      work, and work by various committers, we are much closer to
      building packages corrected in the NOPORTDOCS case.</p>

      <p>Kris Kennaway has done a substantial rewrite of the package
      building tools, including moving as a default to ZFS, which allows
      quick cloning of src and ports directories. It is now much easier
      to manage and monitor the builds. Work on this is continuing. See
      the commits to 
      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/ports/Tools/portbuild/scripts/">
      Tools/portbuild/scripts</url>

      for more information. (Work is ongoing to update the Package
      Building article.) Related work has involved cleaning up some of
      the ports infrastructure; in particular, the INDEX builds are now
      much faster.</p>

      <p>We have been able to do many -exp runs since the last report,
      including those for bsd.cmake.mk, autotools update, CC environment
      passing, the KDE 4.1 pre-integration and post-integration checks,
      lockmgr changes, tty changes, and others.</p>

      <p>Although a number of PRs have been closed, we are still at 57
      portmgr PRs, the same as the last report.</p>

      <p>The following large changes are in the pipeline: 
      <ul>
        <li>Introduction of Perl 5.10</li>
      </ul>
      </p>

      <p>We are currently building packages for amd64-6, amd64-7,
      amd64-8, i386-6, i386-7, i386-8, sparc64-6, and sparc64-7. RELENG_5
      has reached the end of its supported life.</p>

      <p>We have added 4 new committers since the last report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Most of the remaining ports PRs are "existing port/PR
      assigned to committer". Although the maintainer-timeout policy is
      helping to keep the backlog down, we are going to need to do more
      to get the ports in the shape they really need to be in.</task>

      <task>Although we have added many maintainers, we still have over
      4,000 unmaintained ports (see, for instance, the list on portsmon).
      We are always looking for dedicated volunteers to adopt at least a
      few unmaintained ports. As well, the packages on amd64 and sparc64
      lag behind i386, and we need more testers for those.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Porting BSD-licensed text-processing tools from
    OpenBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/G%C3%A1borSoC2008">Wiki
      page</url>

      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//&amp;c=Kqj@//depot/projects/soc2008/gabor_textproc/?ac=83">
      Perforce depot</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The grep utility is ready for a thorough test on the portbuild
      cluster. It is almost compatible with GNU grep, but there are
      differences in the regex handling at the level of the regex
      libraries of GNU and the base system one, thus a better
      compatibility is very hard to implement.</p>

      <p>Some progress has been made on diff, but some important options
      are still missing. The sort utility seems to be very problematic in
      the aspect of the wide character support by design, thus it was
      given a lower priority.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish the incomplete options of diff and optimize it.</task>

      <task>Investigate about the opportunities to fix sort.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Spanish Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>José Vicente</given>

          <common>Carrasco Vayá</common>
        </name>

        <email>carvay@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.org/es">Spanish Web Site for
      FreeBSD</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/es_ES.ISO8859-1/">Spanish
      Documentation for FreeBSD</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SpanishDocumentationProject">The
      FreeBSD Spanish Documentation Project's Wiki Page</url>

      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/docproj_es/&amp;c=S1s@//depot/projects/docproj_es/?ac=83">
      Perforce Depot for The FreeBSD Spanish Documentation Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We have not made any significant progress in this period. We
      definitely need more active translators to progress with the
      translation project.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete renovation of the Spanish web site.</task>

      <task>Update Handbook translation.</task>

      <task>Translate release notes for -CURRENT and 7.X.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>USB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hans Petter</given>

          <common>Sirevaag Selasky</common>
        </name>

        <email>hselasky@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb2/&amp;c=oDu@//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb2/?ac=83">
      Current USB files</url>

      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//&amp;cdf=//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb2/core/README.TXT&amp;c=Vfw@//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb2/core/README.TXT?ac=64&amp;rev1=2">
      Current USB API README file</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the last three months there has been a number of changes.
      Most notably all global USB symbols have been renamed to "usb2_" to
      allow for co-existence with the old USB stack. Also there is now a
      completely new and reworked UGEN driver which allows multiple
      drivers to hook onto the same USB device. No more need to unload
      any kernel drivers. For example it is now possible to have a
      userland Mouse driver stealing half of the mouse events at the same
      time "ums" is loaded. The only disadvantage is that your mouse
      cursor will move slower on the screen. This is maybe not the most
      common use-case, but it illustrates that kernel USB drivers are no
      longer locking out other USB userland drivers. A new userland
      libusb is in the works for FreeBSD. The USB stack now also has
      support for independent USB BUS, USB Device, and USB Interface
      permissions. That means you can more easily give USB permissions to
      USB device drivers at either USB BUS, USB Device or USB Interface
      level. All USB modules have now been grouped into functional
      categories: usb2_bluetooth, usb2_ndis, usb2_controller, usb2_quirk,
      usb2_core, usb2_serial, usb2_ethernet, usb2_sound, usb2_image,
      usb2_storage, usb2_input, usb2_template, usb2_misc, and
      usb2_wlan.</p>

      <p>Ideas and comments with regard to the new USB API are welcome
      on the <a
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-usb">
      FreeBSD-USB Mailing List</a>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>

