<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status
Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2009-10-2009-12.xml,v 1.16 2011/06/02 12:05:56 uqs Exp $ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2009</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os; related projects between October and
    December 2009. This is the last of the four reports covering 2009,
    which has shown to be a very important year for the &os; Project. Besides
    other notable things, a new major version of &os;, 8.0-RELEASE, has been
    released, while the release process for 7.3-RELEASE is soon to begin.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
    enjoy reading. Let us also take this opportunity to wish you all a
    happy and successful new year for 2010.</p>

    <p>Please note that the deadline for submissions covering the
    period between January and March 2010 is April 15th, 2010.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>vendor</name>

    <description>Vendor / 3rd Party Software</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland utilities</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>DAHDI (Zaptel) support for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>

          <common>Khon</common>
        </name>

        <email>fjoe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://www.mail-archive.com/asterisk-dev@lists.digium.com/msg39598.html">
      Official Announcement</url>

      <url href="http://svn.digium.com/svn/dahdi/freebsd/trunk/">SVN
      repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A DAHDI support module for &os; has been created in the
      official Asterisk SVN repository.</p>

      <p>The following drivers are currently ported:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>main DAHDI driver</li>

        <li>all software echo cancellation drivers</li>

        <li>dahdi_dynamic</li>

        <li>dahdi_dynamic_loc</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The following HW drivers are currently ported and tested:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>wct4xxp, including HW echo cancellation support
        (Octasic)</li>

        <ul>
          <li>Digium TE205P/TE207P/TE210P/TE212P: PCI dual-port
          T1/E1/J1</li>

          <li>Digium TE405P/TE407P/TE410P/TE412P: PCI quad-port
          T1/E1/J1</li>

          <li>Digium TE220: PCI-Express dual-port T1/E1/J1</li>

          <li>Digium TE420: PCI-Express quad-port T1/E1/J1</li>
        </ul>

        <li>wcb4xxp</li>

        <ul>
          <li>Digium B410: PCI quad-port BRI</li>

          <li>Junghanns.NET HFC-2S/4S/8S duo/quad/octoBRI</li>

          <li>OpenVox B200P/B400P/B800P</li>

          <li>BeroNet BN2S0/BN4S0/BN8S0</li>
        </ul>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The port for dahdi_dynamic_eth and dahdi_dynamic_ethmf is
	underway.</task>

      <task>More HW drivers need to be ported.</task>

      <task>Please let me know if you can provide remote access with
        serial console to any box with ISDN/T1/E1 HW not currently
        supported by DAHDI for &os; but supported by DAHDI for Linux. I
        am also interested in porting drivers for FXO/FXS cards. Please
        let me know if you can provide a remote access or donate a
	card.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>CAM-based ATA implementation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Motin</common>
        </name>

        <email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>

          <common>Long</common>
        </name>

        <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Existing ata(4) infrastructure, which has been around many years,
      has various problems and limitations when compared to modern
      controllers/device support. Although the CAM subsystem (used for SCSI)
      is almost as old as ata(4), it is more eligible to solve the current
      problems. To reduce code duplication and better support border cases
      such as ATAPI and SAS, we have started to develop a new CAM based
      ATA implementation.</p>

      <p>As such, CAM infrastructure has been extended to support different
      transports. New transport has been implemented to support PATA/SATA
	buses. To support ATA disks, a new CAM driver (ada) has been written. ATAPI
      devices are supported by existing SCSI drivers cd, da, sa, etc. To
	support SATA port-multipliers another new CAM driver (pmp) has been written. To
      support most featured and widespread SATA controllers, new drivers
      ahci(4) and siis(4) have been developed.</p>

      <p>To support legacy ATA controllers, a kernel option ATA_CAM has been
      added. When used, it makes all ata(4) controllers directly
      available to CAM, deprecating ata(4) peripheral drivers and external
      APIs. To make this possible, ata(4) code has been heavily refactored,
      making controller driver API stricter.</p>

      <p>Command queuing support gives new ATA implementation up to
      double performance benefit on some workloads, with 20-30% improvement
      quite usual.</p>

      <p>SATA Port Multiplier support makes it easy to build fast and
	cheap storage with huge capacities, by using dozens of SATA drives
      in one system or external enclosures,</p>

      <p>Some of that code has been presented in the recently released &os; 8.0-RELEASE but
	8-STABLE now includes a much improved version.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Improve timeout and transport error recovery.</task>

      <task>Improve hot-plug support.</task>

      <task>Find and fix any show stoppers for legacy ata(4)
	deprecation.</task>

      <task>Write a new, more featured driver for Marvell SATA controllers
	(specifications desired).</task>

      <task>Write SAS-specific transport and drivers for SAS HBAs (specifications
        desired). SAS controllers can support SATA devices and
        multipliers, so it should fit nicely into the new
	infrastructure.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>Chromium web browser</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ben</given>

          <common>Laurie</common>
        </name>

        <email>ben@links.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://chromium.jaggeri.com">test builds and port
      progress</url>

      <url href="http://www.links.org/?p=724">first build
      information</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Chromium is a Webkit-based web browser that is largely BSD
      licensed. It has been ported from Linux to &os; in October and we have been
      posting patches and test builds periodically since then. Chromium
      works well on &os; &mdash; it is very fast and stable but there
      are a handful of rough edges that need to be polished up. Two
      remaining bugs should probably be fixed before releasing a
      chromium-devel port. We are looking for volunteers to test and
      maintain this port to make this BSD browser a viable option on
      &os; desktop systems.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix sporadic rendering freezes.</task>

      <task>Fix JavaScript interpreter, v8, on i386 architecture.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>SUJ &mdash; Journaled SoftUpdates</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jeff</given>

          <common>Roberson</common>
        </name>

        <email>jeff@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://jeffr_tech.livejournal.com/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I have been adding a small intent log to SoftUpdates to
      eliminate the requirement for fsck after an unclean shutdown. This
      work has been funded by Yahoo!, iXsystems, and Juniper. Kirk
      McKusick has been aiding me with design critiques and helping me
      better understand SoftUpdates.</p>

      <p>Extensive testing by myself and Peter Holm has yielded a stable
      patch. Current users are encouraged to follow the instructions
      posted to the current@FreeBSD.org mailing list to verify stability in your own workloads.
      Updates are forthcoming and it is expected to be merged to
      9.0-CURRENT before the end of January. Ports to older versions of &os;
      will be available in SVN under alternate branches. Official
      backports will be decided by re@ when 9.0-CURRENT is stable.</p>

      <p>The changes are fully backwards and forwards compatible as there
      are very few metadata changes to the filesystem. The journal may be
      enabled or disabled on existing FFS filesystems using tunefs(8).
      The log consumes 64 MB of space at maximum and fsck time is
      bounded by the size of the log rather than the size of the
      filesystem. Other details are available in my technical
      journal.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">The &os; Ports
      Collection</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">
      Contributing to the &os; Ports Collection</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">&os; ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html">The &os;
      Ports Management Team</url>

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com">marcuscom
      Tinderbox</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Most of the recent activity has been dealing with the 8.0-RELEASE
      process. As an experiment, we have tried to decouple the ports QA
      timeline as much as possible from the src QA timeline. Although
      this meant that the impact on people actively maintaining and using
      ports has been much less than in previous releases, it still has not
      solved the problem of the release going out with a stale set of
      packages. We are still trying to come up with a better solution for
      the problem.</p>

      <p>The ports count is over 21,000. The PR count jumped to over
      1,000 but is now back to around 950.</p>

      <p>We are currently building packages for amd64-6, amd64-7,
      amd64-8, i386-6, i386-7, i386-8, i386-9, ia64-8, sparc64-7, and
      sparc64-8. This represents the addition of i386-9 and ia64-8 since
      the last report.</p>

      <p>There has been some discussion of when to drop regular package
      builds for 6.X but no decision has been made yet. The cluster and
      the port managers are struggling to keep up with so many branches being
      active all at the same time.</p>

      <p>Mark Linimon continues to make progress on the cluster nodes.
      Almost every node that does not have a hard disk failure is now
      online. In addition, he continues to make progress debugging
      problems that occasionally take nodes offline.</p>

      <p>The next task is to characterize the overall performance of the
      build cluster. The question has been asked of us, "what would it
      take to speed up package builds?" There is no one simple answer. It
      is not merely a matter of having a larger number of package
      building machines, so before asking for funding we first need to
      identify the current bottlenecks. While we are starting to
      understand the problems on the nodes, the problems on the dispatch
      machine itself are much harder. Complicating the matter is that
      there are several periodic processes (ZFS backup, ZFS expiration,
      and errorlog compression, among others) that can combine to slow
      that machine significantly. The simultaneous interaction of all these
      is proving difficult to quantify.</p>

      <p>Between Pav Lucistnik and Martin Wilke, many more experimental ports runs have
      been completed and committed.</p>

      <p>We have added 3 new committers since the last report, and 1
      older one has rejoined us.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We are still trying to set up ports tinderboxes that can be
      made available to committers for pre-testing.</task>

      <task>Most of the remaining ports PRs are "existing port/PR
      assigned to committer". Although the maintainer-timeout policy is
      helping to keep the backlog down, we are going to need to do more
      to get the ports in the shape they really need to be in.</task>

      <task>Although we have added many maintainers, we still have more
      than 4,700 unmaintained ports. (See, for instance, the list on
      portsmon. The percentage remains steady at just over 22%.) We are
      always looking for dedicated volunteers to adopt at least a few
      unmaintained ports. As well, the packages on amd64 and especially
      sparc64 lag behind i386, and we need more testers for those.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/sparc64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Marius</given>

          <common>Strobl</common>
        </name>

        <email>marius@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The main thing that has taken place since the last Status Report
      is that I have gotten to the bottom of the remaining PCI problems
      with Sun Fire V215/V245 and support for these has been completed
      and since r202023 now is part of 9.0-CURRENT. With some luck it will also
      be part of the upcoming 7.3-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>Some other news:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Two bugs in the NFS server causing unaligned access and
        thus panics on sparc64 and all other architectures with strict
        alignment requirements (basically all Tier-2 ones) have been
        fixed. There likely will be a 8.0-RELEASE Erratum Notice released
        for these.</li>

        <li>&os; has been adopted to the changed firmware of newer Sun
        Fire V480 (those equipped with version 7 Schizo bridges) and has been
        reported to now run fine on these. The necessary change will be
        part of 7.3-RELEASE. Unfortunately, using the on-board NICs in
        older models of Sun Fire V480 (at least those equipped with
        version 4 Schizo bridges) under &os; still leads to the firmware
        issuing a FATAL RESET due to what appears to be a CPU bug, which
        needs to be worked around.</li>

        <li>Work on supporting Sun Fire V1280 has been started but still
        is in very early stages. Unfortunately, these are rather quirky
        machines. After solving two firmware specialties the loader now
        is able to boot the kernel but the latter currently still fails
        in early cycles as trying to take the trap table over from the
        firmware results in a solid hang.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="proj">
    <title>3G USB support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Thompson</common>
        </name>

        <email>thompsa@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Recently, a bunch of new device IDs have been added for the
	u3g(4) cellular wireless driver; the list should be comparable now with
      other operating systems around. A lot of these devices have a
      feature where the unit first attaches as a disk or CD-ROM that
      contains the Win/Mac drivers. This state should be detected by the
      u3g driver and the usb device is sent a command to switch to modem
      mode. This has been working for quite some time but as it is
      implemented differently for each vendor I am looking for feedback
      on any units where the auto switchover is not working (or the init
      is not recognized at all). Please ensure you are running an up to
      date kernel, like r201681 or later from 9.0-CURRENT, or 8-STABLE
      after the future merge of this revision.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="docs">
    <title>The &os; German Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Johann</given>

          <common>Kois</common>
        </name>

        <email>jkois@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Benedict</given>

          <common>Reuschling</common>
        </name>

        <email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Martin</given>

          <common>Wilke</common>
        </name>

        <email>miwi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://doc.bsdgroup.de">German Documentation Project
      Homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are happy to announce that Benedict Reuschling is now free
      from mentorship and can commit to the documentation tree on his own.</p>

      <p>Since the last status report, the German Documentation Team has
      chased updates to various sections of the &os; Handbook, FAQ and
      the German website. Many handbook pages have been updated to the latest
      version, including chapters about configuration, disks, kernel
      configuration, printing, multimedia and virtualization.</p>

      <p>We require help from volunteers that are willing to contribute
      bug fixes or translations. The following documents need active
      maintainership and are a good training ground for those willing to
      join the translation team:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>arch-handbook/jail/</li>

        <li>developers-handbook/I10n/</li>

        <li>developers-handbook/policies/</li>

        <li>developers-handbook/sockets/ (translation from scratch)</li>

        <li>handbook/firewalls/ (translation from scratch)</li>

        <li>handbook/security/</li>

        <li>porters-handbook/</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Read the translations and report bugs to
      de-bsd-translators@de.FreeBSD.org.</task>

      <task>Translate articles or missing sections listed above.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; Spanish Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
	</name>
	<email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/es/articles/fdp-es/">Introduction to the Spanish Documentation Project</url>

      <url href="https://listas.es.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/doc">Translators' Mailing List</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There is one article translation pending review.  Apart from this,
	neither translations nor maintenance work have been done.  We need
	more volunteers, mostly translators but we are glad to have
	more reviewers, as well.  One can join by simply subscribing to
	the translators' mailing list where all the work is done.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update Handbook translation.</task>

      <task>Update webpage translation.</task>

      <task>Add more article translations.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; Hungarian Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
	</name>
	<email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>P&aacute;li</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/hu/">Hungarian Web Page for &os;</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/hu/">Hungarian Documentation
	for &os;</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HungarianDocumentationProject">The
	&os; Hungarian Documentation Project's Wiki Page</url>

      <url href="http://p4web.FreeBSD.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/docproj_hu/&amp;c=aXw@//depot/projects/docproj_hu/?ac=83">Perforce
	Depot for the &os; Hungarian Documentation Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the last months, no new translation has been added.
	Lacking human resources, we can only manage to keep the existing
	documentation and web page translations up to date.  If you are interested
	in helping us, please contact us via the email addresses
	noted above.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Translate release notes.</task>

      <task>Add more article translations.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>The &os; Forums</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>&os; Forums</given>

          <common>Admins</common>
        </name>

        <email>forum-admins@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>&os; Forums</given>

          <common>Moderators</common>
        </name>

        <email>forum-moderators@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://forums.FreeBSD.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since the last report we have seen a growth of 2,000 users on our
      forums resulting in approximately 10,000 registered users at this time. The
      posts count is about to reach 60,000 soon, which are contained in
      almost 9,000 threads.</p>

      <p>The sign-up rate still hovers between 50-100 each week. The
      total number of visitors (including 'guests') is currently hard to
      gauge, but is likely to be a substantial multiple of the registered
      userbase.</p>

      <p>New topics and posts are actively 'pushed out' to search
      engines. This in turn makes the forums show up in search results
      more and more often, making it a valuable and very accessible
      source of information for the &os; community.</p>

      <p>One of the contributing factors to the forums' success is their
      'BSD-style' approach when it comes to administration and
      moderation. The forums have a strong and unified identity and are
      very actively moderated, spam-free, and with a core group of very
      active and helpful members, dispensing many combined decades' worth
      of knowledge to starting, intermediate and professional users of
      &os;.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>V4L support in Linux emulator</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>J.R.</given>

          <common>Oldroyd</common>
        </name>

        <email>fbsd@opal.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://opal.com/freebsd/sys/compat/linux/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>V4L video support in the Linux emulator is now available.</p>

      <p>This work allows Linux applications using V4L video calls to
      work with existing &os; video drivers that provide V4L interfaces.
      It is tested and working with the net/skype port and also with
      browser-based Flash applications that access webcams. An early version has been
      committed to 9.0-CURRENT and work is in progress to commit the latest
      version and then MFC. It is also tested on &os;-8.0/amd64 and
      &os;-7.2/i386.</p>

      <p>Note: to be clear, this does not add V4L support to all webcams.
      The &os; camera driver must already offer V4L support itself in
      order for a Linux application to be able to use that camera. The
      multimedia/pwcbsd port provides the pwc(4) driver that already has
      V4L support. If your camera is supported by a different driver, you
      will need to enhance that driver to add V4L support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>The webcamd deamon</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hans Petter</given>

          <common>Selasky</common>
        </name>

        <email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.selasky.org/hans_petter/video4bsd/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The webcamd daemon enables hundreds of different USB based
      webcam devices to be used under the &os;-8/9 operating system. The
      webcam daemon is basically an application, which is a port of
      Video4Linux USB webcam drivers into userspace on &os;. The daemon
      currently depends on libc, pthreads, libusb and the VIDEO4BSD
      kernel module.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Add support for the remaining Video4Linux USB devices.</task>

      <task>Make patches for increased buffer sizes, due to higher
      latency in userspace. Especially for High Speed USB.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Group Limit Increase</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brooks</given>
	  <common>Davis</common>
	</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Historically, &os; has limited the number of supplemental
	groups per process to 15 (NGROUPS_MAX was incorrectly declared to be
	16).  In &os; 8.0-RELEASE we raised the limit to 1023, which should be
	sufficient for most users and will be acceptably efficient for
	incorrectly written applications that statically allocate
	NGROUPS_MAX + 1 entries.</p>

      <p>Because some systems such as Linux 2.6 support a larger
	group limit, we have further relaxed this restriction in 9.0-CURRENT and
	made kern.ngroups a tunable value, which supports values between 1023
	and INT_MAX - 1.  We plan to merge this to 8-STABLE before
	8.1-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Syncing pf(4) with OpenBSD 4.5</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ermal</given>

          <common>Luçi</common>
        </name>

        <email>eri@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/viewvc/base/user/eri/pf45/">
      Viewing the changes.</url>

      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/base/user/eri/pf45/head/">The
      actual repo to build from.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This import is based on OpenBSD 4.5 state of pf(4). It includes
      many improvements over the code currently present in &os;. The
      actual new feature present in pf45 repository is support for
      divert(4), which should allow tools like snort_inline to work with
      pf(4) too.</p>

      <p>Currently, the pf(4) import is considered stable with normal
      kernel, as well as VIMAGE enabled kernels.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>pflow(4)/pflog(4)/pfsync(4) need to be made VIMAGE
      aware.</task>

      <task>More regression testing is needed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>NFSv4 ACL support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Edward Tomasz</given>

          <common>Napierala</common>
        </name>

        <email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/NFSv4_ACLs" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Native NFSv4 ACL support in ZFS and UFS has been committed into 9.0-CURRENT. It
      is expected to be MFCed in order to make it into &os; 8.1-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Support for NFSv4 ACLs in tar(1).</task>

      <task>MFC.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Ralink wireless RT2700U/2800U/3000U run(4) USB driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Akinori</given>

          <common>Furukoshi</common>
        </name>

        <email>moonlightakkiy@yahoo.ca</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://forums.FreeBSD.org/showthread.php?t=7562">
      Announcement on the &os; Forums</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The run(4) driver brings support for Ralink RT2700U/2800U/3000U
      USB wireless devices. For detailed information and list of all the
      supported devices, please see the above mentioned URL. The source
      code has been imported to the USB P4 repository on January 10, 2010
      (172906).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Solve USB_TIMEOUT problem when sending beacons, and/or
	confirm which chipsets supports AP mode if all of them do not
      support it.</task>

      <task>Read TX stats for AMRR on AP mode, and/or confirm which
	chipsets supports AP mode if all of them do not support
	it.</task>

      <task>Maintain the code.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/mips</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>The &os;/mips mailing list</given>
        </name>

        <email>mips@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

        <email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/mips/index.html" />

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/mips" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The base/projects/mips branch has been merged into 9.0-CURRENT.
      The merge is complete and the sanity tests have passed. The code
      has booted on both a Ubiquiti RouterStation (big endian) as well as
      in gxemul (little endian).</p>

      <p>The branch lived for one year, minus a day, and accumulated much
      work:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>A new port to the Atheros AR71xx series of processors. This
        port supports the RouterStation and RouterStation PRO boards from
        Ubiquiti. Other boards should work with minimal tweaking. This
        port should be considered as nearing production quality, and has
        been used extensively by the developers. The primary author of
        this port is Oleksandr Tymoshenko (gonzo@FreeBSD.org).</li>

        <li>A new port to the SiByte BCM1250 SoC on the BCM91250
        evaluation board (aka SWARM). This port is reported to be stable,
        but this hardware is a little old and not widely available. The
        primary author of this port is Neel Natu (neel@FreeBSD.org). Only
        one core is presently supported.</li>

        <li>A port, donated by Cavium, to their Octeon and Octeon plus
        series of SoC (CN3xxx and CN5xxx). This code is preliminary,
        supporting only a single core right now. It has been lightly
        tested on the CN3860 evaluation board only in 32-bit mode. Warner
        Losh (imp@FreeBSD.org) has been driving the efforts to get this
        code into the tree.</li>

        <li>A port, donated by RMI, to their XLR series of SoCs. This
        port is single core only, as well. The code reaches multi-user but
        should be considered beta quality for the moment. Randal Stewart
        (rrs@FreeBSD.org) has been driving the efforts to integrate this
        into the tree.</li>

        <li>Preliminary support for building a mips64 kernel from this
        source base. More work is needed here, but at least two kernels
        successfully build in 64-bit mode (OCTEON1 and MALTA64).</li>

        <li>Very early support for N32 and N64 ABIs</li>

        <li>Support for booting compressed kernels has been added
        (gonzo@).</li>

        <li>Improved support for debugging</li>

        <li>Improved busdma and bus_space support</li>

        <li>Many bug fixes</li>

        <li>More types of MIPS cores are recognized</li>

        <li>Expanded cache handling for newer processors</li>

        <li>Beginning of a port to the alchemy au1XXX cpus is present,
        but experimental.</li>

        <li>Work on SMP is underway to support multicore processors like
        the SiByte, Octeon and XLR processors.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The development branch had been updated incorrectly several times over the
	past year, and the damage was too much to repair. We have retired the
      branch and will do further mips development in 9.0-CURRENT for the time
      being. If you have a checked out tree, the suggested way to update
      the projects/mips tree you have is to do a "svn switch
      svn://svn.FreeBSD.org/base/head" in that tree.</p>

      <p>I would like to thank everybody that has contributed time, code
      or hardware to make &os;/mips better.</p>

      <p>As development proceeds, I will keep posting updates. In
      addition, I hope to have some mini "how-to" wiki pages done for
      people that want to try it out.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We are still investigating how feasible merging all this work
      into 8-STABLE will be, as it represents a huge leap forward in code
      stability and quality.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Flattened Device Tree for embedded &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafal</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FlattenedDeviceTree">Project wiki pages</url>

      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/changeList.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/fdt/...">Project P4 branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The purpose of this project is to provide &os; with support for the
	Flattened Device Tree (FDT) technology, the mechanism for describing
	computer hardware resources, which cannot be probed or self enumerated, in
	a uniform and portable way. The primary consumers of this technology are
	embedded &os; platforms (ARM, AVR32, MIPS, PowerPC), where a lot of
	designs are based on similar chips but have different assignment of pins,
	memory layout, addresses bindings, interrupts routing and other resources.</p>

      <p>Current state highlights:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Environment, supported tools</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Integrated device tree compiler (dtc) and libfdt into &os;
	    userspace, kernel and loader build</li>
	</ul>

	<li>loader(8)</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Full support for device tree blob handling</li>

	  <li>Load, traverse, modify (including add/remove) device tree
	    nodes and properties</li>

	  <li>Pass the device tree blob to the kernel</li>

	  <li>Both ARM and PowerPC loader(8) supported</li>
	</ul>

	<li>Kernel side FDT support (common)</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Developed OF interface for FDT-backed platforms</li>

	  <li>ofw_bus I/F (and /dev/openfirm) available with FDT</li>

	  <li>Integrated FDT resources representation with newbus (fdtbus
	    and simplebus drivers)</li>
	</ul>

	<li>PowerPC kernel (Freescale MPC85XX SOC)</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>MPC8555CDS and MPC8572DS successfully converted to FDT
	    conventions</li>
	</ul>

	<li>ARM kernel (Marvell Orion, Kirkwood and Discovery SOC)</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Work in progress on integrating FDT infrastructure with ARM
	    platform code</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>

      <p>Work on this project has been sponsored by the &os; Foundation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete missing pieces for PowerPC (PCI bridge driver conversion to
	FDT).</task>

      <task>Complete ARM support.</task>

      <task>Merge to SVN.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>HAST &mdash; Highly Available Storage</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Pawel Jakub</given>

          <common>Dawidek</common>
        </name>

        <email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-announce/2009-October/001279.html">
      Announcement</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>HAST software will provide synchronous replication of any GEOM
      provider (eg. disk, partition, mirror, etc.) or file from one &os;
      machine (primary node) to another one (secondary node).</p>

      <p>Because data is replicated at the block level neither applications, nor
      file systems have to be modified to take advantage of this
      functionality.</p>

      <p>The functionality that HAST software will provide is very similar
      to the functionality provided by the DRBD project for Linux.</p>

      <p>The HAST project is sponsored by the &os; Foundation.</p>

      <p>Work is progressing well; first milestone was reached in December
	2009 and the expected project completion date is January 31,
	2010.</p>

      <p>Check out &os; mailing lists for patches to test in February and
      wish me good luck!</p>

      <p>And by the way, do not forget to donate to the &os; Foundation, as your
      donations make projects like this possible.</p>

      <p>Thank you!</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Wireless mesh networking</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/WifiMesh"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Development of the &os; 802.11s stack continues.  The code in
	&os; HEAD has been updated to comply with draft 4.0.  Merge to
	&os; 8-STABLE will be done soon.</p>
         
      <p>The developer is looking for funding to be able to implement mesh
	link security algorithms and/or coordinated channel access
	(performance improvement).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>&os; TDM Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafal</given>
	  <common>Czubak</common>
	</name>
	<email>rcz@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Hajduk</common>
	</name>
	<email>mih@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Important changes regarding &os; TDM Framework since the last status
	report:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fully functional TDM controller driver for Marvell Kirkwood and
	  Discovery SoCs.</li>

	<li>Working voiceband channel character device driver.</li>

	<li>Working Si3215, Si3050 codec drivers on corresponding FXS, FXO
	  ports.</li>

	<li>Demo application, which is capable of manipulating voiceband
	  channel and codec state, starting/stopping channel transfers and
	  echoing on single channel.</li>

	<li>Preliminary version of driver bridging the voiceband
	  infrastructure with Zaptel/DAHDI.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Improve various issues regarding working drivers and demo
	application.</task>

      <task>Test Si3050 codec driver operation with PSTN.</task>

      <task>Fully integrate voiceband infrastructure with Zaptel/DAHDI telephony
	hardware drivers.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>POSIX utmpx for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2010-January/014893.html">Announcement</url>

      <url href="http://www.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/functions/endutxent.html">POSIX specification</url>

      <url href="http://cvsweb.netbsd.org/bsdweb.cgi/~checkout~/src/lib/libc/gen/utmpx.c">NetBSD's implementation</url>

      <url href="http://src.opensolaris.org/source/xref/onnv/onnv-gate/usr/src/lib/libc/port/gen/getutx.c">OpenSolaris' implementation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>On January 13, I removed the utmp user accounting database and
	replaced it with a new POSIX utmpx implementation. Unfortunately, the upgrade path is a bit
	complex, because the utmp interface provided almost no library
	interface to interact with the database files.</p>

      <p>This change may have caused some regressions. Some ports may fail
	to build, while there could also be bugs in the library
	functions.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Get a list of broken ports.</task>

      <task>Fix them to comply to standards.</task>

      <task>Send patches upstream.</task>
    </help>
  </project> 

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>BSD-licensed iconv</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
	</name>
	<email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/soc2009/gabor_iconv">Sources in the Perforce repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Good compatibility has been ensured and there are only few pending
	items that have to be reviewed/enhanced.  Recently, an enhancement
	has been completed, which makes it possible to accomplish better
	transliteration, just like in the GNU version.  An initial testing
	patch is expected at the beginning of February.</p>
     </body>

     <help>
      <task>Enhance conversion tables to make use of enhanced
	transliteration.</task>

      <task>A performance optimization might be done later.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>BSD-licensed text processing tools</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
	</name>
	<email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/soc2008/gabor_textproc">Perforce repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As 8.0-RELEASE is out, BSD bc/dc can be now committed to 9.0-CURRENT. We are
	only waiting for an experimental package building to make sure there are no
	regressions after this change.  BSD grep is complete but it cannot be integrated yet because of
	some regex library issues.  We need first a fast and modern regex
	library so that we can change to BSD grep.  BSD sort has few
	incomplete features and needs some performance review.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Commit BSD bc/dc.</task>

      <task>Implement remaining features for sort and optimize
	performance.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>NVIDIA amd64 driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Baldwin</common>
	</name>
	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.nvnews.net/vbulletin/showthread.php?t=142120">Release Announcement</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>NVIDIA has released the first BETA version of its graphics
	drivers for &os;/amd64.  Note that this driver will work on &os;
	versions 7.3-RELEASE or 8.0-RELEASE and later.  It also works on very recent
	versions of 7.2-STABLE.  More details are provided in the
	official release announcement.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Bugbusting Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Linimon</common>
	</name>
	<email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Remko</given>
	  <common>Lodder</common>
	</name>
	<email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Volker</given>
	  <common>Werth</common>
	</name>
	<email>vwe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/support.html#gnats">GNATS</url>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BugBusting">BugBusting</url>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~linimon/studies/prs/">Experimental
	  report pages</url>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~linimon/studies/prs/recommended_prs.html">PRs
	  recommended for committer evaluation by the bugbusting team</url>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~linimon/recommended_subscribers.txt">Subscription
	  list for the above report)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Bugmeister Gavin Atkinson has now been granted a src commit
	bit, and is now starting to work through some of our
	backlog.</p>

      <p>The list of PRs recommended for committer evaluation by the
	Bugbusting Team continues to receive new additions; however, it
	has not yet achieved high visibility.  (This list contains PRs,
	mostly with patches, that the Bugbusting Team consider potentially
	ready to be committed as-is, or are probably trivially resolved
	in the hands of a committer with knowledge of the particular
	subsystem.)  One of the suggestions at the Cambridge devsummit
	was to create a way for people to be emailed the weekly summary
	that is posted to freebsd-bugs@, and this has now been implemented.
	Please email linimon@FreeBSD.org to ask to be added to the
	recommended_subscribers.txt file (see above).</p>

      <p>We continue to classify PRs as they arrive, adding 'tags' to the
	subject lines corresponding to the kernel subsystem involved, or
	man page references for userland PRs.  These tags, in turn, produce
	lists of PRs sorted both by tag and by manpage.  At this point
	most of the PRs that refer to supported versions of &os; have
	been converted, and we are keeping up as new ones come in.  We
	hope that this is making it easier to browse the PR database.</p>
      
      <p>The overall PR count jumped to over 6,200 during the 8.0-RELEASE release
	cycle but seems to have stabilized at around 6,100.  As in the
	past, we have a fairly good clearance rate for ports PRs but
	much less so for other PRs.  (Partly this is due to the concept
	of individual ports having 'maintainers'.)</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Try to find ways to get more committers helping us with
	closing PRs that the team has already analyzed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
  
  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/ia64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcel</given>
	  <common>Moolenaar</common>
	</name>
	<email>marcel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work continues on our ia64 port.  Many recent commits to
	help improve stability have been made to 9.0-CURRENT and MFCed
	to 8-STABLE.</p>

      <p>Due to interest from a very motivated user, package builds
	have been restarted for ia64-8.  This is primarily intended as
	a QA step to discover and fix bugs on ia64, rather than to
	create packages for upload.</p>

      <p>Based on the above, Mark Linimon documented how to add more
	architectures to the package cluster scheduler.  (This work will
	also be of use in an upcoming effort to start powerpc package
	builds.)</p>

      <p>There are currently 3 ia64 machines online and building
	packages.  The machines seem stable as long as multiple
	simultaneous package builds are not attempted, in which case
	they get machine checks.  This is puzzling, since other heavy
	workloads seem stable on the same machines.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Continue to try to understand why multiple simultaneous
	package builds bring the machines down.</task>
	
      <task>Upgrade the firmware on the two machines at Yahoo! to
	see if that helps the problem.</task>

      <task>Configure a fourth machine that has been made available
	to us.</task>

      <task>Figure out the problems with the latest GCC port on
	ia64.</task>

      <task>We can use some help with reviewing the ia64 platform pages
	and bringing them up-to-date.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>bwn(4) &mdash; Broadcom Wireless driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Weongyo</given>
	  <common>Jeong</common>
	</name>
	<email>weongyo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/weongyo/wireless/src/sys/dev/bwn&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">bwn(4)
	  sources in P4</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>bwn(4) is replacing bwi(4) driver for to the following
	reasons:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Uses latest v4 firmware image instead of using the much older v3
	  firmware. In this way, we have some great benefits, such as
	  support for N-PHYs and the fixes of various earlier firmware bugs.</li>

	<li>Supports PIO mode. This is important because &mdash; as you might
	  know &mdash; the Broadcom Wireless Driver is created by
	  reverse-engineering so some pieces of hardware might not
	  work with DMA operations.</li>

	<li>Supports 64 bit DMA operations.</li>

	<li>Separates bwi(4) driver into two parts; siba(4) driver and
	  bwn(4) driver.  Many Broadcom wireless and NIC devices
	  are based on Silicon Sonics Backplane, such as bwi(4), which
	  implemented the SIBA operations internally. This resulted in
	  code duplication as other drivers had to implement their
	  own routines to deal with SIBA.  In the case of bwn(4),
	  these two parts have been separated and implemented in their
	  own kernel modules to avoid this problem and help further
	  development by providing a standalone siba(4) driver.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Currently, it is tested on big/little endian machines and 32/64-bit
	DMA operation with STA mode.  A major patch for siba(4)
	is being reviewed before committing into 9.0-CURRENT.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>MESH/IBSS/HOSTAP mode is not supported.</task>

      <task>LP/N PHYs are not supported.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Release Engineering Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Release Engineering Team announced &os; 8.0-RELEASE on
	November 26th, 2009.  With 8.0-RELEASE completed planning has
	begun for 7.3-RELEASE.  The schedule has been set with the
	release date planned for early March 2010.</p>
  
      <p>The Release Engineering Team would like to thank George
	Neville-Neil (gnn@) for his service on the team.  George
	continues to work with the &os; Project but has stepped down
	from the Release Engineering Team to focus on other
	activities.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>IP Payload Compression Protocol support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern A.</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>One of the longer outstanding feature problems with the &os;
	IP security stack, broken IP Payload Compression Protocol
	(IPcomp) support, has been fixed.</p>

      <p>While working on the fix, various problems had been
	identified:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Problems with the IPcomp packet handling in IPsec.</li>

	<li>opencrypto compression handling and deflate implementation
	  limitations.  These were debugged using DTrace SDT
	  probes.</li>

	<li>Problems due to an outdated version of zlib used in some
	  parts of the network stack and by the opencrypto
	  framework.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Patches for all but the zlib support have been committed to
	9.0-RELEASE and merged to all supported stable branches including
	6-STABLE.  Special thanks to Eugene Grosbein for helping with
	testing.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix ng_deflate so that we can make use of Kip Macy's work
	on an up-to-date unified zlib version in the kernel, which
	would also fix the last occasional IPcomp hiccups.</task>
    </help>
  </project> 

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Foundation Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/">The &os; Foundation</url>
      <url href="https://twitter.com/freebsdfndation">Follow us on Twitter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Despite a difficult economy, we more than doubled our number
	of donors, we raised $269K towards our goal of $300K, and with
	an improved economy hope to surpass that this year.</p>

      <p>We have funded two new projects.  One is the Flattened Device Tree by
	Rafal Jaworowski.  And, the second one is Highly Available Storage
	by Pawel Jakub Dawidek.  We continued supporting the New Console
	Driver by Ed Schouten and Improvements to the &os; TCP Stack by
	Lawrence Stewart.  We also purchased equipment for several
	projects.</p>

      <p>We have big plans for the new year!  We are going to significantly
	increase our project development and equipment spending.  Stay
	tuned for a project proposal submission announcement soon.  We
	just announced that we are accepting travel grant applications
	for AsiaBSDCon and will be accepting them soon for BSDCan.  And,
	we are working on infrastructure projects to beef up hardware
	for package-building, network-testing, etc.</p>

      <p>Read more about how we supported the project and community by
	reading our end-of-year newsletter available at <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/press/2009Dec-newsletter.shtml">http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/press/2009Dec-newsletter.shtml</a>.</p>

      <p>We are fund-raising for 2010 now!  Find out more at <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/">http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/</a>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>VirtualBox on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Beat</given>
	  <common>Gaetzi</common>
	</name>
	<email>beat@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bernhard</given>
	  <common>Froehlich</common>
	</name>
	<email>decke@bluelife.at</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juergen</given>
	  <common>Lock</common>
	</name>
	<email>nox@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Martin</given>
	  <common>Wilke</common>
	</name>
	<email>miwi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/VirtualBox" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>VirtualBox 3.1.2 has been committed to the ports tree.</p>

      <p>Several changes to the port have been performed with this
	update including:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Port has been renamed to virtualbox-ose to reflect that we
	  are now using the OSE version.</li>

	<li>A separate port for the kernel modules has been created
	  &mdash; virtualbox-ose-kmod.</li>

	<li>A separate port for guest additions for &os; guests has
	  been created &mdash; virtualbox-ose-additions.</li>

	<li>Proper &os; support for PulseAudio has been added.</li>

	<li>Procfs is not required anymore because vbox uses sysctl(3)
	  now.</li>

	<li>Juergen Lock's &os; host networking patches have been added.  They
	  are now also in the upstream vbox SVN (modulo vbox variable
	  naming style adjustments).</li>

	<li>Allow direct tap networking again (for users that need the
	  best network performance and/or need more complex network
	  setups, like when they want to use routing instead of bridging
	  to e.g. protect guests from messing with the lan's ARP tables;
	  a tap + routing + proxy arp example is in the above
	  freebsd-emulation@ posting.)</li>
	
	<li>Enable vbox's shared MAC feature when using bridged mode on
	  a Wifi interface, together with the virtualbox-ose-kmod
	  change this should fix bridged mode for Wifi users.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We would like to say thanks to all the people that helped us
	by reporting bugs and submitting fixes.  We also thank the
	VirtualBox developers for their help with the ongoing effort
	to port VirtualBox to &os;</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSDCan 2010 &mdash; The BSD Conference</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>BSDCan Information</given>
	</name>
	<email>info@BSDCan.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.BSDCan.org/2010/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>BSDCan, a BSD conference held in Ottawa, Canada, has quickly
	established itself as the technical conference for people
	working on and with 4.4BSD based operating systems and related
	projects.  The organizers have found a fantastic formula that
	appeals to a wide range of people from extreme novices to
	advanced developers.</p>

      <p>BSDCan 2010 will be held on 13-14 May 2010 at the University of
	Ottawa, and will be preceded by two days of Tutorials on 11-12
	May 2010.</p>

      <p>There will be related events (of a social nature, for the most
	part) on the day before and after the conference.</p>

      <p>Please check the conference web site for more information.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>AsiaBSDCon 2010 &mdash; The BSD Conference</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>AsiaBSDCon Information</given>
	</name>
	<email>secretary@AsiaBSDCon.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://2010.AsiaBSDCon.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>AsiaBSDCon is a conference for users and developers on BSD
	based systems.  AsiaBSDCon is a technical conference and aims
	to collect the best technical papers and presentations
	available to ensure that the latest developments in our open
	source community are shared with the widest possible audience.
	The conference is for anyone developing, deploying and using
	systems based on FreeBSD, NetBSD, OpenBSD, DragonFlyBSD, Darwin
	and MacOS X.</p>

      <p>The next conference will be held at the Tokyo University of
	Science, Tokyo, Japan, on 11th to 14th March, 2010.</p>

      <p>For more detailed information, please check the conference
	web site.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>meetBSD 2010 &mdash; The BSD Conference</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>meetBSD</given>
	  <common>Information</common>
	</name>
	<email>info@meetBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.meetBSD.org"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The meetBSD conference is an annual event gathering users and
	developers of the BSD operating system family, mostly &os;,
	NetBSD and OpenBSD.  Afer the special California edition,
	meetBSD Wintercamp in Livigno, this year we are back to
	Krakow, Poland.</p>
         
      <p>In 2010, meetBSD will be held on 2-3 July at the Jagiellonian
	University.</p>
         
      <p>See the conference main web site for more details.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Clang replacing GCC in the base system</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Roman</given>
	  <common>Divacky</common>
	</name>
	<email>rdivacky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brooks</given>
	  <common>Davis</common>
	</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel</given>
	  <common>Worach</common>
	</name>
	<email>pawel.worach@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BuildingFreeBSDWithClang" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are again able to build bootable i386/amd64 kernel.  Nathan
	Whitehorn committed a fix to &os;, which enabled LLVM/clang to
	work mostly fine on PowerPC.  There is some preliminary testing
	of LLVM/clang on ARM and MIPS being done.  We have some ideas
	about sparc64 support which are currently being investigated.
	You are welcome to contact us if you want to help.</p>

      <p>Since the last report, a lot has happened mostly in the area of
	C++; clang is currently able to build working groff, gperf and
	devd, i.e. all of the C++ apps we have in base.  Unfortunately,
	it still cannot build any of the C++ libraries &mdash; two of
	them are missing builtins and libstdc++ is broken for other
	reasons.</p>

      <p>Not much happened in the clangbsd branch as we cannot
	upgrade the clang/llvm there because we are blocked by a bug
	that requires using newer assembler than we can ship.  This
	might be solved by either fixing this (short term) or using
	llvm-mc instead of GNU as for assembling (longer term).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Help with ARM/MIPS/sparc64.</task>
      
      <task>More testing of clang on 3rd party apps (ports).</task>
      
      <task>Discussion on integrating LLVM/clang into &os;.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Intel XScale hwpmc(9) support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Preliminary Hardware Performance Counter support for Intel
	XScale ARM processors was committed to &os; 9.0-CURRENT
	in December.  This adds another supported architecture to hwpmc(9).
	The system works for basic performance counter usage but more
	advanced usage scenarios, namely callchain support, are not
	yet implemented.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
