<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-October</month>

    <year>2005</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>After a long, exhausting, yet very productive third quarter of 2005
    FreeBSD 6.0 has been released. Many activities were put into the
    background in order to make this release the success it has
    become.</p>

    <p>Nonetheless, we received a tremendous amount of reports covering
    various projects that either found their way into FreeBSD 6.0 already
    or have started to develop in, what is now known as 7-CURRENT. The
    EuroBSDCon and the Developer Summit in Basel next week will be a good
    opportunity to help some of the ideas herein to take off.</p>

    <p>Last round we had the pleasure to introduce our accepted Google
    Summer of Code projects. Now, that the summer is over, we are even
    more pleased to include reports about the outcome of these projects.
    Some already found their way into the tree or the general public
    otherwise - most ocularly the new webdesign.</p>

    <p>Unfortunately, this publication has been delayed for various
    reasons - the before mentioned release of 6.0 being one of them.
    Thus, some of the reports might no longer be as up to date as they
    were when we received them and we encourage you - even more this time
    - to also visit the weblinks to get more recent information.</p>

    <p>Thanks again to everyone who submitted reports, and our sincere
    apologies for running late this time.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google summer of code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network infrastructure</description>
  </category>

<!--
  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland programs</description>
  </category>
-->
  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>vendor</name>

    <description>Vendor / 3rd Party Software</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>Cronyx/Asterisk</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Roman</given>

          <common>Kurakin</common>
        </name>

        <email>rik@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.cronyx.ru/hardware/wan.html">Cronyx WAN
      Adapters</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/~rik">rik's Home Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A new netgraph-to-zaptel module that allows to use E1(ISDN PRI)
      WAN adapters as an interface card for open source PBX - Asterisk.
      All you need is an adapter that able to work in raw phone mode
      (like Cronyx Tau-PCI/2E1), eq. without HDLC-like framing and that
      has support of Netgraph.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSDCan</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>

          <common>Langille</common>
        </name>

        <email>dan@langille.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/">BSDCan</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are in the process of recruiting new members for the program
      committee. If you would like to volunteer before you are recruited,
      please contact me.</p>

      <p>The dates for 2006 have been announced: May 12-13, 2006. The
      venue will be the same as previous events: University of Ottawa.
      The prices will not increase from 2005.</p>

      <p>Please start thinking about your papers. The call for papers
      will go out soon.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/ports/">The FreeBSD ports
      collection</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~fenner/portsurvey/">FreeBSD
      ports unfetchable distfile survey (Bill Fenner's report)</url>

      <url href="http://edwin.adsl.barnet.com.au/~edwin/ports/">FreeBSD
      ports updated distfile survey (Edwin Groothius' report)</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">The FreeBSD
      Ports Management Team</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A great deal of work has gone into the Ports Collection since
      the last report in April, much of it behind-the-scenes.</p>

      <p>As this report was being written, the 6.0 release was ongoing.
      Due to the amount of time that it has taken to get 6.0 through the
      beta process and into RC, we have been in ports freeze or slush for
      more than two months. Unfortunately this has held back needed work
      on the ports infrastructure.</p>

      <p>The last major update to bsd.port.mk, in early May, was
      coordinated by Kirill Ponomarew added a number of new features and
      closed 15 PRs. Another similar set of changes has been tested and
      is ready for commit after release.</p>

      <p>portmgr welcomed two new members to its team: Erwin Lansing (who
      had previously served as secretary, a role in which he is
      continuing) and Clement Laforet. Clement is interested in speeding
      up the adoption of new changes into the infrastructure, an item I'm
      sure that that everyone can support. He promises to bring some
      fresh ideas to bear on this, including the revitalization of
      devel/portmk as a testing ground for new changes to bsd.port.mk in
      which the larger community can help test changes.</p>

      <p>The unfetchable distfile survey, which had been non-functional
      for quite some time, was revitalized by Bill Fenner, with many new
      pages of analysis added to it. Work is still ongoing. As a result
      of this analysis, Bill and Mark Linimon eliminated nearly 100 lines
      of bogus or outdated sites from bsd.sites.mk alone. They are
      continuing to work through many other sites and ports as successive
      iterations of the survey reveal more dimensions to the problem. We
      still need more help from the larger community (see below).</p>

      <p>Edwin Groothius has instituted a similar but slightly different
      survey. His program attempts to visit each listed mastersite for
      each distfile and determine whether or not a newer version might be
      available. The results are stored in a database. This is helping to
      automate a function that had been left up to individual maintainers
      to look through numerous websites to try to find these updates. The
      survey has been hugely (if not universally) popular. Already,
      dozens of port updates have been committed as a direct result of
      this service.</p>

      <p>In addition, portsmon, which had been down due to a machine
      change, was moved to portsmon.FreeBSD.org and updated during this
      time. Many thanks to Erwin Lansing for providing the loan of this
      machine, and Will Andrews for having provided the loan of the
      previous incarnation.</p>

      <p>Both of the above surveys are now generating periodic email to
      ports maintainers advising them of problems. This is in addition to
      recurring email from portsmon. The surveys allow individual
      maintainers to ask to receive no further email. portsmon does not
      currently have this but it needs to be added. Although we have no
      doubt the mail can in some cases be annoying (especially given the
      fact that there will inevitably be some false positives), the fact
      is that these emails have had a direct impact on the quality on the
      ports. We ask for patience from the community while each of us
      continues to fine-tune the algorithms controlling what email is
      generated. (Because of the number of emails these systems generate,
      it is impossible to go over every one individually for a sanity
      check).</p>

      <p>As a result of bounces from the above email, we have also been
      resetting maintainers who have become unreachable.</p>

      <p>Pav Lucistnik has done a great deal of work on the Porter's
      Handbook, including some much needed reshuffling and cleanup.
      Expanded sections include Apache and PHP; Configure Scripts;
      Dealing With Shared Libraries; Dealing With User Configuration
      Files; Handling Empty Directories; Python; and Ruby. In addition,
      Edwin Groothius has contributed a section on OPTIONS, and numerous
      other sections have been improved by good suggestions from various
      other contributors.</p>

      <p>A new article, "Maintaining and contributing to the FreeBSD
      Ports Collection", has been prepared by Sam Lawrance and has been
      reviewed and is ready for commit. This document attempts to codify
      the rights and responsibilities of ports maintainers, which until
      now had merely been "community lore" as discussed on various
      mailing lists.</p>

      <p>We continue to add new committers regularly, 8 since the last
      report.</p>

      <p>The ports collection now contains over 13,500 ports. This is an
      increase of over 750 since the last report in April.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>portmgr would like to ask maintainers and committers alike to
      go through the status of their ports on the two distfile surveys,
      both the one that shows unfetchable current distfiles and the one
      that shows possibly updated distfiles. This is an effective way to
      quickly help improve our user's perception of the state of the
      ports.</task>

      <task>A great deal of progress has been made in cracking down on
      ports that install files outside the approved directories and/or do
      not deinstall cleanly (see "Extra files not listed in PLIST" on 
      <a href="http://pointyhat.freebsd.org/errorlogs/">pointyhat</a>

      ). These ports are now a small minority thanks to the dedicated
      efforts of a large number of individuals.</task>

      <task>We still have a large number of PRs that have been assigned
      to committers for some time (in fact, they constitute the
      majority). portmgr members are now going through this list and
      asking each committer to either commit them or release them to the
      general pool so that someone else may work on them. In addition,
      the existing policies for inactive maintainers (two weeks for
      maintainer- timeout on PRs; three months for maintainer reset if no
      activity) are going to be much more actively pursued than in the
      past, where the policies were more honored in the breach than in
      the observance. The goal is to try to bring the Ports Collection as
      up-to-date as possible. (While there has been progress on many
      fronts, there are still areas where ports are suffering from
      bit-rot.)</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Improve Libalias</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Paolo</given>

          <common>Pisati</common>
        </name>

        <email>p.pisati@oltrelinux.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/PaoloPisati">
      Wiki/Official project site</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/PaoloPisati" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project met all the scheduled goals, and following are the
      new features implemented in libalias: 
      <ul>
        <li>integration with IPFW in kernel land</li>

        <li>support for 4.x and 5.x as kld</li>

        <li>converted from a monolithic to a modular architecture, added
        the ability to load/unload at runtime support for new protocols
        (modules work both in kernel and user land)</li>

        <li>added logging support in kernel land</li>
      </ul>

      <br />

      Fell free to suggest other improvements.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test and feedback are welcome</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>FreshPorts</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>

          <common>Langille</common>
        </name>

        <email>dan@langille.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freshports.org/">FreshPorts</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I'm in the process of adding personalized newsfeeds to the
      website. For each of your Watch Lists, you will also have a news
      feed just for that watch list. Any commit to any port in your watch
      list will turn up on your newsfeed. This fantastic new feature is
      available now for your RSS pleasure at 
      <a href="http://beta.freshports.org/">the BETA site</a>

      . I've also been doing some work in the area of supporting multiple
      platforms and architectures. This will allow FreshPorts to
      correctly report that a port is broken, for example, on i386, but
      not the other platforms. This feature will take note of BROKEN,
      FORBIDDEN, and IGNORE for the following architectures: 
      <ul>
        <li>alpha</li>

        <li>amd64</li>

        <li>i386</li>

        <li>ia64</li>

        <li>sparc64</li>
      </ul>

      And the following OSVERSIONS (subject to upgrade as new releases
      come along): 
      <ul>
        <li>492100</li>

        <li>504102</li>

        <li>600033</li>

        <li>700001</li>
      </ul>

      Upcoming changes, in addition to the above, include: 
      <ol>
        <li>NOT_FOR_ARCHS</li>

        <li>ONLY_FOR_ARCHS</li>

        <li>IS_INTERACTIVE</li>
      </ol>

      I've been getting useful help from those on IRC. Thanks.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete the above.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Fuse for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Csaba</given>

          <common>Henk</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-chenk@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://fuse4bsd.creo.hu/">New home page</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/FuseFilesystem">
      FreeBSD wiki page</url>

      <url href="http://creo.hu/~csaba/projects/fuse4bsd/downloads/">
      Download location</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Fuse for FreeBSD is the outcome of my "ssh based networking
      filesystem for FreeBSD" SoC project.</p>

      <p>The kernel interface for the comprehensive userspace filesystem
      API provided by the ( 
      <a href="http://fuse.sourceforge.net">Fuse project</a>

      ) has been implemented for FreeBSD (6.x and 7.x), under the BSD
      license. This has the benefit of opening up the possibility of
      porting the rich collection of Fuse based filesystems to
      FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>Now it's ready for consumption by a broader audience. The 
      <tt>sysutils/fusefs-kmod</tt>

      , 
      <tt>sysutils/fusefs-libs</tt>

      , 
      <tt>sysutils/fusefs-sshfs</tt>

      ports can be expected to be integrated into the FreeBSD ports tree
      in the next few days (the ports were created and are maintained by
      Anish Mistry, and Simon Barner's careful review also helps a
      lot).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Implement missing features like extended attributes and
      attribute/name caching (with timeout).</task>

      <task>Resolve problems with autotools and integrate userspace
      modifications into the Fuse codebase.</task>

      <task>Port Fuse based filesystems and language bindings to
      FreeBSD.</task>

      <task>Create sysfs (Fuse based filesystem interface to
      sysctl).</task>

      <task>Test, test, test among a broad variety of
      circumstances.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>gvinum 'move', 'rename' support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Chris</given>

          <common>Jones</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-cjones@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/GvinumMoveRename">
      gvinum 'move', 'rename' wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Support for moving and renaming objects in gvinum was completed
      at the end of August 2005. All gvinum objects (drives, subdisks,
      plexes, and volumes) can be renamed, and subdisks can be moved from
      drive to drive. Also, a man page for gvinum was created.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update FreeBSD Handbook chapter on vinum to reflect gvinum.
      Slowly in progress, but hopefully done by the end of the year,
      workload permitting.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Integrated SNMP monitoring</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Philip</given>

          <common>Paeps</common>
        </name>

        <email>philip@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Shteryana</given>

          <common>Shopova</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-shteryana@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~harti/bsnmp/index.html" />

      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/ShteryanaShopova" />

      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/SnmpMonitoringModulesStatus" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This summer, we've had the pleasure of having two Google Summer
      of Code students hacking on our SNMP monitoring machinery. Victor
      worked on implementing the Host Resources, TCP and UDP MIBs in
      bsnmpd while Shteryana started on client-side SNMP tools.</p>

      <p>With these modules and tools, a FreeBSD installation can be
      monitored without having to install any (heavy!) third-party
      tools.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
        <p>While the modules and the tools currently in Perforce are
        generally functional, they still need some tidying up (style(9))
        and testing before they can be committed to CVS.</p>

        <p>At the time of this writing, the Hostres MIB is pretty much
        commit-ready in Perforce (//depot/user/philip/bsnmp/...), the
        other modules and tools live in
        //depot/projects/soc2005/bsnmp/... They'll be branched for
        tidying up and committing "Real Soon Now"[tm]</p>
      </task>

      <task>Testers are very welcome. :-) Please let us know about any
      bugs!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Interface Cleanup</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Anders</given>

          <common>Persson</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-anders@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/CleanupOfNetworkInterfaceApisProposal">
      SoC Proposal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The dependencies to kernel-only datastructures in netstat
      (ifnet, etc.) have been removed almost completely (AppleTalk and
      IPX still needs work). In order to remove the dependencies, the
      debugging features of netstat had to be removed. However, a project
      to create a generic, modular 'data structure' examination tool is
      ongoing, and the debugging features factor out of netstat have been
      migrated to this tool.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Refactoring of the netstat code, create a modular version in
      the spirit of ifconfig.</task>

      <task>Data structure examination tool needs to be completed,
      current state is more that of a prototype.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>UFS Journaling</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brian</given>

          <common>Wilson</common>
        </name>

        <email>polytopes@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>

          <common>Long</common>
        </name>

        <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Scott has been working on inserting journalling hooks into the
      ufs and ffs filesystem code. Brian has been balancing school and
      redesigning various things that were deemed necessary to update
      during the end of the actual SoC project.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish the redesign of the internal block management
      code.</task>

      <task>Integration and test of the ffs/ufs hooks and the journaling
      code.</task>

      <task>Updating userland tools to be aware of and use the
      journal.</task>

      <task>Journal buffer management wiring to VM subsystem a la
      XFS.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>pfSense</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>

          <common>Ullrich</common>
        </name>

        <email>sullrich@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.pfsense.com" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pfSense is a m0n0wall derived operating system platform with
      radically different goals such as using Packet Filter, FreeBSD 6,
      ALTQ for excellent packet queueing and finally an integrated
      package management system for extending the environment with new
      features.</p>

      <p>Work continues to stabilize pfSense in preparation for the
      FreeBSD 6 release. Once FreeBSD 6 is released pfSense will enter
      the final beta and release candidate phases in preparation for the
      1.0 release.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Stabilize installer (cannot load kernel errors after
      install)</task>

      <task>Finish outgoing load balancing monitoring</task>

      <task>Fix last minute bugs that turn up</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>launchd(8) for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>R. Tyler</given>

          <common>Ballance</common>
        </name>

        <email>tyler@tamu.edu</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/launchd">Project
      Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In short, launchd can run perfectly fine on FreeBSD, and
      combined with launchctl, it can be used to manage daemons through
      the launchctl(1) interface. Jobs can be added and managed two ways
      as of yet from launchctl(1). Using zarzycki@'s experimental
      "submit" command within launchctl(1) or by using my
      lame/rudimentary/etc "launcher" format (launchd/launchers/*.launch)
      which uses property(3) to parse out three simple, and important
      details. The program label, path, and any program flags. Using the
      "load" command, one can load the data into launchctl(1) and then
      start the processes with the..."start" command. Jobs can be
      removed/stopped with the "remove" command. The "limit" command
      still throws launchctl(1) into an infinite loop, and yes, I plan on
      fixing this.</p>

      <p>There are some things that need to be fixed, first off, some
      sort of boot time integration, whether as an init-replacement (i.e.
      PID 1, a la Mac OS X) or as the first thing started from init, that
      kicks all rcng things off. Along with, more importantly, a plist
      parser, so we can have full compatibility with Mac OS X's launchd
      via Core Foundation.</p>

      <p>I'm also trying to get launchd(8) relicensed with the BSD
      license, as opposed to the APSL, anybody with tips, or methods for
      achieving this goal, contact me at tyler@tamu.edu</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Writing a light-weight plist (non-XML) parser with lex and
      yacc.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Porting FreeBSD to the Xbox</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Rink</given>

          <common>Springer</common>
        </name>

        <email>rink@rink.nu</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ed</given>

          <common>Schouten</common>
        </name>

        <email>ed@fxq.nl</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.xbox-bsd.nl" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As of 26th July 2005, it is possible to run FreeBSD on your Xbox
      with minor patching effort. The framebuffer has initial support;
      The USB ports, IDE- and audio controllers are fully supported; the
      only part severely lacking now is the lack of support for the
      NForce Ethernet controller.</p>

      <p>Currently, efforts are focussing on eliminating the XBOX kernel
      option and make the port self-detecting; this means the x86 and
      xbox kernels will be identical. The goal is to provide native xbox
      support in 7-CURRENT.</p>

      <p>Furthermore, a porting effort is planned from Linux' GPL-ed
      forcedeth.c; not only the Xbox port will benefit from this but also
      all NForce motherboard owners. The resulting driver could be
      kldload-ed to keep the kernel GPL-free.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The xbox framebuffer driver should be merged in the VESA
      framework, so it can use syscons(4). Assistance on this would be
      very welcome!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ggtrace</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@yahoo.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://ivoras.sharanet.org/projects/ggtrace.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Ggtrace is "GEOM gate tracer", utility to track I/O requests on
      a storage device on FreeBSD. It uses the ggate facility of FreeBSD
      to attach to a file or device and produces a device that can be
      used for any I/O, including hosting filesystems.</p>

      <p>I/O requests are presented in the form of a moving histogram
      that can be used to discern which parts of the storage device are
      used most often. One use of ggtrace is to analyze how filesystems
      arrange and access data on storage devices.</p>

      <p>The project is working and usable only on the RELENG_6
      branch.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>gjournal</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@yahoo.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/gjournal">gjournal
      wiki page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Gjournal provides GEOM-level journaling and COW capabilities to
      storage devices. Unfortunately, it cannot be used as a substitute
      for filesystem journaling (fsck is still needed when gjournal
      device is used to host filesystems). Development has slowed down,
      and the existing code needs much more testing. If there is
      continued interest in it, I'll probably split the functionalities
      into two projects, one handling COW and one handling the
      journaling, in order to make the code cleaner.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More testing is needed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>TCP &amp; IP Routing Optimization Fundraise</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>

          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>

        <email>andre@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~andre/tcpoptimization.html" />

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/news/status/report-mar-2005-june-2005.html#Fundraising---TCP-&amp;-IP-Routing-Optimization" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The fundraise has been very successful and I want to thank
      everyone who has pledged their support and tipped the jar. The full
      amount plus a little bit more has been raised in a very short
      timeframe. More information on the exact amounts and their sponsors
      can be found at the first link.</p>

      <p>Due to the extended (and unexpected long) code freeze for the
      release process of FreeBSD 6.0 (which is very high quality btw.)
      I've decided to push back on working full time until the freeze is
      lifted. So far I've done some work in the mbuf handling area and
      some other netinet cleanups in my local repository.</p>

      <p>Once FreeBSD 6.0 is released I resume my work on this project
      and many changes and optimizations, as described in the first and
      second link, will go into into FreeBSD-current.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>TODO list for volunteers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The TODO list for volunteers (see the last report for more) is
      now under review by some doc@ people.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>bridge.c retired</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>

          <common>Laier</common>
        </name>

        <email>mlaier@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Thompson</common>
        </name>

        <email>thompsa@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As of September 27, the old bridge(4) implementation has been
      removed from HEAD and will not be part of FreeBSD 7 and later.
      FreeBSD 6 will serve as transition period. The full functional
      replacement if_bridge(4) is now available in FreeBSD 5 (not yet
      part of 5.4 however), FreeBSD 6 and -CURRENT. Any problems should
      be reported to Andrew Thompson, who is maintaining if_bridge in
      FreeBSD.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Document the change in the handbook and other reference
      material.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Problem Report Database</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>bugmeister_at_freebsd_dot_org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/support.html#gnats">GNATS</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Due to some good recent commit and cleanup work by both
      Alexander Leidinger and Craig Rodrigues, the number of base-system
      PRs has stabilized somewhat. The number of incoming ports PRs
      continues to accelerate but except during freezes the ports
      committers have been battling to commit them as quickly as they
      come in. (The graphs very clearly show where the freezes are.) The
      net result is that we are holding our own but it takes a great deal
      of (mostly unheralded) effort to do so. Thanks are due to a large
      number of individuals who are doing this ongoing work.</p>

      <p>There is ongoing work to ask committers who have had PRs
      assigned to them for a significant period of time, whether they are
      still interested in pursuing them or whether they should instead be
      reassigned to the pool. This is being done to try to get as many
      PRs 'unstuck' as possible to try to help improve our users'
      perceptions of the project.</p>

      <p>As an experiment, Mark Linimon has been adding 'tags' to many of
      the kern and bin PRs, including such things as '[nfs]', '[if_em]',
      and so forth. The idea is to try allow searching and browsing based
      on these terms so that committers will find it easier to work with
      our current PR database. At the moment this is in the experimental
      stage, although it is possible for committers to work with them
      from the command line on systems with a database installed via
      query-pr(1).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Removable interface improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~brooks/pubs/eurobsdcon2004/" />

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/dingo/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project is an attempt to clean up handling of network
      interfaces in order to allow interfaces to be removed reliably.
      Current problems include panics if Dummynet is delaying packets to
      an interface when it is removed.</p>

      <p>I have removed struct ifnet's and layer two common structures
      from device driver structures. This will eventually allow them to
      be managed properly upon device removal. This code has been
      committed and will appear in 6.0. Popular drivers continue to
      be fixed. jhb's locking work has identified and corrected many
      issues. rwatson has also committed cleanups to the multicast code
      which fixed some issues in this area.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>OpenBSD dhclient import</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Sam</given>

          <common>Leffler</common>
        </name>

        <email>sam@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The OpenBSD rewrite of dhclient has been imported, replacing the
      ISC dhclient. The OpenBSD client provides better support for
      roaming on wireless networks and a simpler model of operation.
      Instead of a single dhclient process per system, there is one per
      network interface. This instance automatically goes away in the
      even of link loss and is restarted via devd when link is
      reacquired. To support this change, many aspects of the network
      interface configuration process were overhauled.</p>

      <p>The current code works well in most circumstances, but more
      testing and polishing is needed. A few bugs are being tracked, but
      most of them are edge cases.</p>

      <p>Work on further interface configuration enhancements is underway
      for FreeBSD 7.0.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>EuroBSDCon 2005 - Basel</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Information</given>
        </name>

        <email>info@eurobsdcon.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The fourth European BSD conference in Basel, Switzerland is a
      great opportunity to present new ideas to the community and to meet
      some of the developers behind the different BSDs.</p>

      <p>The two day conference program (Nov 26 and 27) will be
      complemented by a tutorial day preceding the conference (Nov
      25).</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD developers will hold a DevSummit on Nov 24 and 25,
      so several developers will be at the conference.</p>

      <p>The program is available for 
      <a
      href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/conference-schedule-saturday.php">
      Saturday</a>

      and 
      <a href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/conference-schedule-sunday.php">
      Sunday</a>

      providing very interesting FreeBSD talks and topics.</p>

      <p>Today more than 160 people from 25 countries have registered for
      the conference.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>FreeBSD GNOME Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joe Marcus</given>

          <common>Clarke</common>
        </name>

        <email>marcus@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeBSD GNOME</given>

          <common>Team</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnome@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/">FreeBSD GNOME Project
      Homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since our last status report, we have added a new member to the
      team: Jean-Yves Lefort (jylefort). We have even spiced up our 
      <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/contact.html">contact
      page</a>

      with pictures of ourselves and in some cases, a cute hippo. And our
      very own Adam Weinberger (adamw) has been made a GNOME Project
      committer heading up the Canadian English translation project.</p>

      <p>We have finished the port GNOME 2.12 to FreeBSD. However, due to
      the ports slush in preparation for 6.0-RELEASE, the update has not
      been merged into the official ports tree. If people are eager to
      try out GNOME 2.12 while waiting for the ports tree to fully thaw,
      we have 
      <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html">
      instructions</a>

      on our website. GNOME 2.12 will be the first FreeBSD GNOME release 
      <em>not</em>

      to include support for FreeBSD 4.X. While 4.X is still a very
      viable release for servers, it lacks many of the features needed
      for a Desktop Environment such as GNOME. We do plan to continue
      support of the GNOME development platform on 4.X, however. This
      includes Glib, GTK+, libgnome, etc. A new porting component will be
      introduced with GNOME 2.12 called, ``ltverhack''. This will help
      with future upgrades by keeping shared library versions from
      needlessly changing.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD GNOME Project is also committed to providing our
      users with a solid package experience. To that end, we have
      extended our 
      <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/faq2.html#q21">
      Tinderbox</a>

      to build amd64 packages for all supported versions of FreeBSD for
      both the production and development releases of the GNOME Desktop.
      The development packages are even built with debugging symbols to
      better help with reporting problems.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>FreeBSD needs a 
      <a href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software_2fhal">HAL</a>

      port. HAL will be vital for both GNOME and KDE in providing FreeBSD
      users with a smooth, elegant desktop experience. Once GNOME 2.12
      has been merged into the ports tree, work will begin on making HAL
      on FreeBSD a reality. Contact 
      <a href="mailto:gnome@FreeBSD.org">gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

      if you are interested in helping.</task>

      <task>We need help with project documentation. In particular, we
      need help auditing the 
      <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/docs/faq.html">FAQ</a>

      to make sure the content is still relevant, and we are not missing
      any key items. If you're interested, please contact 
      <a href="mailto:gnome@FreeBSD.org">gnome@FreeBSD.org</a>

      .</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>PowerPC Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Peter</given>

          <common>Grehan</common>
        </name>

        <email>grehan@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/platforms/ppc.html">FreeBSD/PPC
      Platform page.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project has been following the 6.0 release schedule by
      producing BETA-* builds and is now up to the RC1 build.</p>

      <p>Dario Freni successfully built a FreeSBIE/ppc iso for his
      Summer-of-code project.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>iSCSI Initiator</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Daniel</given>

          <common>Braniss</common>
        </name>

        <email>danny@cs.huji.ac.il</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="ftp://ftp.cs.huji.ac.il/users/danny/freebsd/iscsi-12.tar.bz2" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This iSCSI kernel module and its companion control program, are
      still under development, but the main parts seem to be working. A
      second round of public tests has started.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>login chap authentication</task>

      <task>digest</task>

      <task>network disconnect recovery</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>The Kernel Stress Test Suite</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Peter</given>

          <common>Holm</common>
        </name>

        <email>pho@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~pho/stress/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The current version of the test suite took form in the beginning
      of the year after discussions with Jeff Roberson, during a long
      period of testing Jeff's VFS SMP work.</p>

      <p>At that time, Daniel Seuffert donated a Thunder 7500
      motherboard complete with CPUs, RAM and coolers.  This allowed me
		to do some serious SMP testing.</p>

      <p>Mid July Murray Stokely suggested adding a link from the 6.0
      todo web page to the Stress Test Status Page. At that time there
      were a few reoccurring panics that made it hard to test the kernel
      for other problems. Numerous people put a lot of hard work in
      fixing the panics and livelocks found during the next months. At
      the same time others stepped in and ran the test suite on their own
      hardware, thus increasing the focus on kernel stability.</p>

      <p>As of 6.0, the kernel stress test suite cannot panic the
      kernel.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Nsswitch / Caching daemon</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Michael</given>

          <common>Bushkov</common>
        </name>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/NsswitchAndCachingFinalReport" />

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/MichaelBushkov" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The nsswitch / caching daemon project was developed within the
      Google's Summer Of Code program. Almost all goals of the project
      were achieved. Thanks to Brooks Davis and Jacques Vidrine, who were
      my mentors and greatly helped me.</p>

      <p>Nsswitch subsystem was extended to support new sources
      (services, protocols, rpc, openssh and GT4). The testing of the
      Globus Grid Toolkit 4 patch (which adds support for nsswitch to
      GT4) is still to be done. For nsswitch to support caching, the
      caching daemon was implemented on top of the caching library, which
      was also developed during the SoC. The current version of the
      daemon uses simple nscd-like configuration file and seems to be
      stable. To complete the SoC project, the experimental version of
      libc with in-process caching enabled was made. It's benchmarking
      will be done in the nearest future.</p>

      <p>There were some requests for caching daemon to be able to act
      like NSCD (to perform the actual nsswitch lookups by itself), so it
      was modified to support this feature. But current implementation
      has some restrictions and requires a lot of testing. Right now the
      final polishing is being made to the project's sources, so that
      they could be added to the CURRENT</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Extend caching daemon to support NSCD functionality</task>

      <task>Test Globus Grid Toolkit 4 patch</task>

      <task>Add support for MAC and audit related configuration files to
      the nsswitch</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>FreeBSD Web Site Redesign</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Emily</given>

          <common>Boyd</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-emily@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Murray</given>

          <common>Stokely</common>
        </name>

        <email>murray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Web</given>

          <common>Team</common>
        </name>

        <email>freebsd-www@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/old">Archived copy of old
      site.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The new website has gone live! Thanks to Emily Boyd for all her
      hard work. We still have a lot of work to do to integrate
      suggestions that have been made by users since we went live. The
      new CSS design makes it much easier to rapidly change the look and
      feel of the site, so it is easy to experiment. We're still looking
      for more HTML/CSS designers to help us improve the site.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>NEWCARD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

        <email>imp@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Due to an email snafu, the June report was not submitted, so
      this report covers since the last 6 months.</p>

      <p>Summary: The 16-bit part of NEWCARD has been greatly enhanced.
      In addition, power control has become interrupt driven. Some
      drivers make use of the new functionality.</p>

      <p>The pccard layer now exports the CIS for each device that is
      present, even if there's no driver for the card or parts of the
      card.</p>

      <p>The power up and reset sequence is now interrupt driven. This
      has eliminated many of the long pauses that the system used to
      experience after a card insertion. We can not play glitch-free
      audio while inserting or removing a card.</p>

      <p>A number of additional cards are recognized by PC Card. In
      addition, drivers now can read the CIS for more information about
      the card. Drivers have been enhanced to read the CIS for MAC
      addresses and the like where appropriate.</p>

      <p>The ed driver now attaches the mii bus of the AX88190 and
      AX88790 fast ethernet PC Card chips. This allows better status
      reporting and increased functionality for PHY chips that need some
      help. The ed driver also supports the Tamarack TC5299J chipset
      (including attaching its MII bus) now, the only open source OS that
      does so (TC5299J cards will work with other open source OS, but
      they won't report their status or attach a mii bus).</p>

      <p>A number of bugs have been fixed in the pccard or cardbus
      drivers. Most of these changes have been merged into the
      forthcoming 6.0. Others will be merged after the release.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>ExpressCard laptops have arrived with ExpressCard/54 and
      ExpressCard/34 slots. It is unknown the extent of the work
      necessary to support them.</task>

      <task>The ISA attachment of cbb needs work to make it fully
      functional.</task>

      <task>A CIS parser in userland needs to be written. The pccardc
      based CIS parser is OK, but it doesn't handle MFC cards too well.
      Ideally the parser would produce output that is compatible with the
      linux tool.</task>

      <task>A mechanism for CIS override is needed. We need a tool that
      will take an ascii representation of the CIS and produce a binary.
      We need a tool that will install the binary into the kernel and
      kernel modifications to switch from the CIS that's in the card to
      the faked up CIS.</task>

      <task>We need a mechanism for creating pseudo multi-function cards.
      Initially, it seems that all we really need is the ability for an
      arbitrary driver to add a sio companion, since that covers all the
      cases I'm aware of. Resources would need to be 'donated' from the
      creating driver to the sio card.</task>

      <task>It would be nice if we could move to a more common CIS
      parsing and dispatch. The CardBus side is wide open at the moment
      since none of the pci drivers use the CIS information outside of a
      few that get their MAC address via a standard interface.</task>

      <task>The ep driver needs work to make the newer ep cards that have
      mii bus on them actually probe and attach it. It needs to gain
      media support for the non-mii based cards. The 3C1 still needs
      work.</task>

      <task>The sn driver needs work to support many of the SMC91Cxxx PC
      Card devices. These are typically combination cards that need
      special, non-standard initialization.</task>

      <task>Power savings for 16-bit cards can be realized if we power
      them up at 3.3V rather than at 5.0V. Not all cards can support
      this, but many can and indicate this support in the CIS. Windows
      tries the 3.3V configuration entries before the 5.0V ones. We
      should do the same.</task>

      <task>Most of the changes that have been made to the pccard and
      cardbus layers can be merged back into RELENG_5.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>OpenBSD packet filter - pf</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>

          <common>Laier</common>
        </name>

        <email>mlaier@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Further improvements have been made to pfsync to make it behave
      well in SMP scenarios. All bug fixes have been MFCed to RELENG_5
      where applicable. A couple of bugfixes and feature improvements
      have been imported via OpenBSD (originally suggested by FreeBSD
      users).</p>

      <p>As described in the last report, FreeBSD 6.0 and future RELENG_6
      releases will be based on OpenBSD 3.7. Newer code will be imported
      as soon as 6.0 has settled down a bit.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>BSD Installer</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Turner</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdinstaller.org/" />

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/BSDInstaller" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>By the end of August I managed to modify the release building
      process to build a live CD that loads the front and backends. It
      could install all the distfiles, install the ports tree and had
      minimal support to install and uninstall packages.</p>

      <p>Since the end of the Summer of Code I have worked to integrate
      the new Lua backend. This has been successful, with it now past the
      point of the BSDINSTALLER-BETA-1 release. It can install the
      distfiles but not the ports tree or packages yet.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Low-overhead performance monitoring for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joseph</given>

          <common>Koshy</common>
        </name>

        <email>jkoshy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~jkoshy/projects/perf-measurement">
      Project home page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This projects implements a kernel module (hwpmc(4)), an
      application programming interface (pmc(3)) and a few simple
      applications (pmcstat(8) and pmccontrol(8)) for measuring system
      performance using event monitoring hardware in modern CPUs.</p>

      <p>The last three months have been spent in bug fixing and in
      tweaking the code. A few more minor features and loose ends remain
      to be taken care of. Once these are done, I hope to get started on
      a graphical performance analyser.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Realtime POSIX signal</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>David</given>

          <common>Xu</common>
        </name>

        <email>davidxu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD kernel is powerful, but it still lacks some realtime
      POSIX facilities, for example, sigqueue. Most of the code is ready,
      and I am testing it.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>POSIX timer, timer_xxx syscalls</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>SNMP Monitoring</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Harti</given>

          <common>Brandt</common>
        </name>

        <email>harti@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Philip</given>

          <common>Paeps</common>
        </name>

        <email>philip@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Victor</given>

          <common>Cruceru</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-victor@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/VictorCruceru">
      FreeBSD wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>New MIBs are implmented for the BSNMP agent:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>
        <strong>HOST-RESOURCES-MIB</strong>

        ( 
        <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2790.txt">
        http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2790.txt</a>

        ). Philip is going to submit the code into the CVS
        repository.</li>

        <li>
        <strong>TCP-MIB with combined IPv4 &amp; IPv6 support</strong>

        ( 
        <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4022.txt">
        http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4022.txt</a>

        ). This new TCP-MIB is 100% backward compatible with the old one
        (v4 only). It adds a clear distinction between active and passive
        tcp endpoints and for each endpoint info about the process it
        belongs to.</li>

        <li>
        <strong>UDP-MIB with combined IPv4 &amp; IPv6 support</strong>

        ( 
        <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4113.txt">
        http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4113.txt</a>

        ). This new UDP-MIB is 100% backward compatible with the old one
        (v4 only) and it adds multiple instances support for the UDP
        endpoints and for each endpoint info about the processes using
        it.</li>
      </ol>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>For HOST-RESOURCES-MIB we are going to add support for more
      detailed memory stats based of libmemstat(3)</task>

      <task>The rest of the IPv6 MIBs.</task>

      <task>FreeBSD enterprise MIBs for supporting SNMP configuration
      (via SNMP SETs) for FreeBSD.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>csup: cvs mode support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Christoph</given>

          <common>Mathys</common>
        </name>

        <email>cmathys@bluewin.ch</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/ChristophMathys">
      The wikipage with details about my SoC-project</url>

      <url href="http://mu.org/~mux/csup.html">csup project page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the "Summer of Code" I worked on csup (a rewrite of CVSup
      in C). It already supported checkout-mode, so my task was to
      implement support for cvs-mode. The biggest part of the project was
      to implement support for rcs-files. As "byproducts" I also wrote
      the necessary code to create nodes/hardlinks and to update files
      using the rsync-algorithm. For what I know, the code works fine,
      but errorhandling is practically inexistent.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Errors should be properly handled</task>

      <task>Support to get fixups</task>

      <task>The hard part to support rcs file updates is done, but there
      is no checksum, some options are not honored and the performance
      could be improved</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Sound subsystem improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Multimedia</given>

          <common>Mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>multimedia@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ariff</given>

          <common>Abdullah</common>
        </name>

        <email>skywizard@MyBSD.org.my</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Recently a lot of fixes, specially in handling format / rate
      conversion and general stability was committed to -current. This
      include fixes for most LOR's and new features (software volume
      handling for soundcards without volume handling in hardware and the
      possibility to switch to spdif).</p>

      <p>A lot of effort was expended by Ariff (and other people) to come up
      with those improvements. For this reason Ariff was "punished" with a
      commit bit, so he is able to commit further improvements on his
      own.</p>

      <p>This work is not integrated into 6.0-RELEASE because of some
      lose ends (see 'sndctl' below).</p>

      <p>You can help by looking at 
      <a
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/query-pr-summary.cgi?category=&amp;severity=&amp;priority=&amp;class=&amp;state=&amp;sort=none&amp;text=sound&amp;responsible=&amp;multitext=&amp;originator=&amp;release=">
      sound related PR's in GNATS</a>

      and making follow-up's which tell us if a problem still persists or
      if a PR can be closed because the bug is fixed. Also feel free to
      submit patches for anything on the TODO list below.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update manual pages to reflect new features.</task>

      <task>Fix driver specific issues (via, t4dwave, maestro).</task>

      <task>Make all drivers MPSAFE.</task>

      <task>Rewrite some parts (e.g. a new mixer subsystem with OSS
      compatibility).</task>

      <task>sndctl(1): tool to control non-mixer parts of the sound
      system (e.g. spdif switching, virtual-3D effects) by an user
      (instead of the sysctl approach in -current); pcmplay(1),
      pcmrec(1), pcmutil(1).</task>

      <task>Plugable FEEDER infrastructure. For ease of debugging various
      feeder stuff and/or as userland library and test suite.</task>

      <task>Support for new hardware (envy24, Intel HDA).</task>

      <task>Performance enhancement (via 'slave'-channels, changes are
      under review)?</task>

      <task>Closer compatibility with OSS, especially for the upcoming
      OSS v4.</task>

      <task>Close a lot of PR's.</task>

      <task>Document the sound system in the 
      <a
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/arch-handbook/index.html">
      FreeBSD Architecture Handbook</a>

      .</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Tinderbox</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joe Marcus</given>

          <common>Clarke</common>
        </name>

        <email>marcus@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Tinderbox</given>

          <common>List</common>
        </name>

        <email>tinderbox-list@marcuscom.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com">Tinderbox Homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Ports Tinderbox is a packaged system for building FreeBSD
      ports in a clean environment. It can be used to test new ports,
      updates to existing ports, or simply as a package building engine.
      Tinderbox uses the same underlying code that the official FreeBSD
      package build cluster, pointyhat, uses. So if a port builds under
      Tinderbox, it is guaranteed to build on pointyhat.</p>

      <p>More and more FreeBSD committers and ports maintainers are
      starting to use Tinderbox. We just released version 2.1.0 which
      added much-requested PostgreSQL support as well as fixed many bugs.
      We expect a 2.1.1 release soon with some additional bug fixes.</p>

      <p>With the 2.1.0 release of Tinderbox, we have branched the code
      base so that we can focus on larger features in our HEAD branch
      while still producing stable releases on a more frequent basis. The
      biggest new feature planned for Tinderbox 3.0 is clustering support
      which is being spearheaded by Ade Lovett (ade).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>At this point, we really need help with documentation. Work
      has begun on creating man pages for the various Tinderbox commands,
      but we need help to churn them out at as faster rate. If you have
      strong mdoc fu, and interested in helping us out, please contact 
      <a href="mailto:marcus@marcuscom.com">marcus@marcuscom.com</a>

      .</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>

