<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<!-- This file was generated with https://github.com/trasz/md2docbook -->
<!--
     Variables to replace:
     %%START%%     - report month start
     %%STOP%%      - report month end
     %%YEAR%%      - report year
     %%NUM%%       - report issue (first, second, third, fourth)
     %%STARTNEXT%% - report month start
     %%STOPNEXT%%  - report month end
     %%YEARNEXT%%  - next report due year (if different than %%YEAR%%)
     %%DUENEXT%%   - next report due date (i.e., June 6)
-->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>April-June</month>

    <year>2019</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This quarter our report includes
    some interesting topics easily accessible to anyone, even if
    you are not a programmer: we report the link to a presentation
    of the 2019 FreeBSD survey results at BSDCan 2019 and describe
    an interesting experience of a 3-person hackaton, which might
    encourage you to host one yourself, possibly with more participants.
    We also provide some up to date information about the status
    of our IRC channels.</p>

  <p>For those who have some more technical skills, we give some
      news about the role of git in the FreeBSD project, describe
      the status of some tools to hunt bugs or enhance security and
      announce a clone of sysctl.</p>

    <p>Finally, those who are more experienced with programming will
      probably be interested in the great work that has been done
      with drivers: in particular, an aknowledgement is due to Alan
      Somers for having started to bring up to date our FUSE
      implementation, which was about 11 years behind. Other important
      improvements include a more user-friendly experience with
      trackpoints and touchpads enabled by default, much low level
      work on graphics, many new bhyve features, updates to the
      linux compatibility layer, various kernel improvements.</p>

    <p>Have a nice read!<br/>
      
      -- Lorenzo Salvadore</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>

    <p>Entries from the various official and semi-official teams,
      as found in the <a href="&enbase;/administration.html">Administration
        Page</a>.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>

    <p>Projects that span multiple categories, from the kernel and userspace
      to the Ports Collection or external projects.</p>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>

    <p>Updating platform-specific features and bringing in support
      for new hardware platforms.</p>.
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>third</name>

    <description>Third-Party Projects</description>

    <p>Many projects build upon &os; or incorporate components of
      &os; into their project.  As these projects may be of interest
      to the broader &os; community, we sometimes include brief
      updates submitted by these projects in our quarterly report.
      The &os; project makes no representation as to the accuracy or
      veracity of any claims in these submissions.</p>
  </category>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/releases/11.3R/schedule.html">FreeBSD 11.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/releases/11.3R/announce.html">FreeBSD 11.3-RELEASE announcement</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/releases/12.1R/schedule.html">FreeBSD 12.1-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="https://download.freebsd.org/ftp/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">FreeBSD development snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Release Engineering Team is responsible for
	setting
	and publishing release schedules for official project
	releases
	of FreeBSD, announcing code freezes and maintaining the
	respective branches, among other things.</p>

      <p>During the second quarter of 2019, the FreeBSD Release
	Engineering team
	started the 11.3-RELEASE cycle, with the code slush
	starting May 3rd.
	Throughout the cycle, there were three BETA builds and
	three RC builds,
	all of which in line with the originally-published
	schedule. The final RC
	build started June 28th, with the final release build
	targeted for July 5th.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD 11.3-RELEASE will be the fourth release from the
	<tt>stable/11</tt>
	branch, building on the stability and reliability of
	11.2-RELEASE.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Release Engineering Team also published the
	schedule for the
	12.1-RELEASE, targeted to start September 6th. One
	important thing to note
	regarding the published schedule is it excludes a hard
	freeze on the
	<tt>stable/12</tt> branch, as a test run for eliminating
	code freezes entirely during
	a release cycle. Commits to what will be the
	<tt>releng/12.1</tt> branch will still
	require explicit approval from the Release Engineering
	Team, however.</p>

      <p>Additionally throughout the quarter, several development
	snapshots builds
	were released for the <tt>head</tt>, <tt>stable/12</tt>,
	and <tt>stable/11</tt> branches.</p>

      <p>Much of this work was sponsored by the FreeBSD Foundation
	and Rubicon
	Communications, LLC (Netgate).</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>René Ladan</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Ports Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/">About FreeBSD Ports</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">Contributing to Ports</url>
      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/index.html">FreeBSD Ports Monitoring</url>
      <url href="https://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">Ports Management Team</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The following was done during the last quarter by portmgr
	to keep things in
	the Ports Tree going:</p>

      <p>During the last quarter the number of ports rose to just
	under 37,000. At the
	end of the quarter, there were 2146 open PRs and 7837
	commits (excluding 499 on
	the quarterly branch) from 172 committers. This shows a
	slight decrease in
	activity compared to previous quarter.</p>

      <p>People come and go, last quarter we welcomed Pedro Giffuni
	(pfg@), Piotr Kubaj
	(pkubaj@) and Hans Petter Selasky (hselasky@). Pedro and
	Hans Petter were
	already active as src committers. We said goodbye to
	gordon@, kan@, tobez@,
	and wosch@.</p>

      <p>On the infrastructure side, a new USES=cabal was
	introduced and various default
	versions were updated: MySQL to 5.7, Python to 3.6, Ruby
	to 2.5, Samba to 4.8
	and Julia gained a default version of 1.0. The web
	browsers were also updated:
	Firefox to 68.0 and Chromium to 75.0.3770.100</p>

      <p>During the last quarter, antoine@ ran a total of 41
	exp-runs to test various
	package updates, bump the stack protector level to
	"strong", switch the default
	Python version to 3.6 as opposed to 2.7, remove sys/dir.h
	from base which has
	been deprecated for over 20 years, and convert all Go
	ports to USES=go.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>FreeBSD Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Core Team is the governing body of FreeBSD.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Core approved source commit bits for Doug Moore (dougm),
	Chuck Silvers
	(chs), Brandon Bergren (bdragon), and a vendor commit bit
	for Scott
	Phillips (scottph).</li>
      </ul>

      <ul>
	<li>The annual developer survey closed on 2019-04-02. Of the
	397
	developers, 243 took the survey with an average completion
	time of 12
	minutes. The public survey closed on 2019-05-13. It was
	taken by
	3637 users and had a 79% completion rate.
	<a
	href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9nc8N6GtAPg&amp;t=549">A
	presentation of the survey results</a>
	took place at BSDCan 2019.</li>
      </ul>

      <ul>
	<li>The core team voted to appoint a working group to explore
	transitioning our source code 'source of truth' from
	Subversion to
	Git. Core asked Ed Maste to chair the group as Ed has been
	researching this topic for some time. For example, Ed gave
	<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G8wQ88d85s4">a
	MeetBSD 2018 talk on the topic</a>.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	There is a variety of viewpoints within core regarding
	where and how
	to host a Git repository, however core feels that Git is
	the prudent
	path forward.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The project received many Season of Docs submissions and
	picked a top
	candidate. Google will announce the accepted technical
	writer
	projects on 2019-08-06. We are hoping for lots of new and
	refreshed
	man pages.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Continuous Integration</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Jenkins Admin</name>
	<email>jenkins-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Li-Wen Hsu</name>
	<email>lwhsu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://ci.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD Jenkins Instance</url>
      <url href="https://artifact.ci.FreeBSD.org/">FreeBSD CI artifact archive</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Jenkins">FreeBSD Jenkins wiki</url>
      <url href="https://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-testing">freebsd-testing Mailing List</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ci">freebsd-ci Repository</url>
      <url href="https://preview.tinyurl.com/y9maauwg">Tickets related to freebsd-testing@</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/HostedCI">Hosted CI wiki</url>
      <url href="https://hackfoldr.org/freebsd-ci-report/">FreeBSD CI weekly report</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD CI team maintains continuous integration
	system and related tasks
	for the FreeBSD project. The CI system regularly checks
	the committed changes
	can be successfully built, then performs various tests and
	analysis of the
	results. The results from build jobs are archived in an
	artifact server, for
	the further testing and debugging needs. The CI team
	members examine the
	failing builds and unstable tests, and work with the
	experts in that area to
	fix the code or adjust test infrastructure. The details
	are of these efforts
	are available in the weekly CI reports.</p>

      <p>The
	<a
	href="https://github.com/freebsd/fcp/blob/master/fcp-20190401-ci_policy.md">FCP
	for CI policy</a>
	is in "feedback" state, please provide any comments to
	freebsd-testing@ or
	other suitable lists.</p>

      <p>We had a testing working group in <a
	href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/DevSummit/201905/TestingCI">201905
	DevSummit</a></p>

      <p>Please see freebsd-testing@ related tickets for more
	information.</p>

      <p>Work in progress:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fixing the failing test cases and builds</li>

	<li>Adding drm ports building test against -CURRENT</li>

	<li>Adding powerpc64 tests job: <a
	href="https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ci/pull/33">https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ci/pull/33</a></li>

	<li>Implementing automatic tests on bare metal hardware</li>

	<li>Extending and publishing the embedded testbed</li>

	<li>Planning for running ztest and network stack tests</li>

	<li>Help more 3rd software get CI on FreeBSD through a hosted
	CI solution</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>FreeBSD Graphics Team status report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>FreeBSD Graphics Team</name>
	<email>x11@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Niclas Zeising</name>
	<email>zeising@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop">Project GitHub page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD X11/Graphics team maintains the lower levels
	of the FreeBSD graphics
	stack.
	This includes graphics drivers, graphics libraries such as
	the
	MESA OpenGL implementation, the X.org xserver with related
	libraries and
	applications, and Wayland with related libraries and
	applications.</p>

      <p>In the last report, half a year ago, several updates and
	changes had been made
	to the FreeBSD graphics stack.</p>

      <p>To further improve the user experience, and to improve
	input device handling,
	evdev was enabled in the default configuration in late
	2018. Building on that,
	we have enabled IBM/Lenovo trackpoints and elantech and
	synaptics touchpads by
	default as well.</p>

      <p>The input device library libinput has been updated as the
	last in a series of
	updates bringing the userland input stack up to date.
	This is work that was started in 2018.</p>

      <p>We have made several improvements to the drm kernel
	drivers.
	A long-standing memory leak in the Intel (i915) driver has
	been fixed, and
	several other updates and improvements have been made to
	the various drm
	kernel driver components.</p>

      <p>A port of the drm kernel drivers using the 5.0 Linux
	kernel sources has been
	created and committed to FreeBSD ports as
	<tt>graphics/drm-devel-kmod</tt>.
	This driver requires a recent Linux KPI and is only
	available on recent
	versions of FreeBSD CURRENT.</p>

      <p>This version of the driver contains several development
	improvements.
	The generic drm (drm.ko) driver as well as the i915
	(i915kms.ko) driver
	can now be unloaded and reloaded to ease in development
	and testing.
	This causes issues with the virtual consoles, however, so
	an SSH connection is
	recommended.
	To aid debugging <tt>i915kms.ko</tt> use of debugfs has
	been improved, but there are
	still limitations preventing it from being fully
	functional.
	Since debugfs is based on pseudofs it is possible that
	this will prevent a fully
	functional debugfs in its current state, so we might have
	to look into adding
	the required functionality to pseudofs or use another
	framework.</p>

      <p>The new in-kernel drm driver for VirtualBox,
	<tt>vboxvideo.ko</tt> has been ported from
	Linux.
	Support is currently an experimental work in progress.
	For example the virtual console won't update after loading
	the driver, but X-
	and Wayland-based compositors are working.</p>

      <p>Mesa has been updated to 18.3.2 and switched from using
	<tt>devel/llvm60</tt> to use
	the Ports default version of llvm, currently
	<tt>devel/llvm80</tt>.</p>

      <p>Several userland Xorg drivers, applications, and libraries
	have been updated,
	and other improvements to the various userland components
	that make up the
	Graphics Stack have been made.</p>

      <p>We have also continued our regularly scheduled bi-weekly
	meetings, although work
	remains in sending out timely meeting minutes afterwards.</p>

      <p>People who are interested in helping out can find us on
	the x11@FreeBSD.org
	mailing list, or on our gitter chat: <a
	href="https://gitter.im/FreeBSDDesktop/Lobby">https://gitter.im/FreeBSDDesktop/Lobby</a>.
	We are also available in #freebsd-xorg on EFNet.</p>

      <p>We also have a team area on GitHub where our work
	repositories can be found:
	<a
	href="https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop">https://github.com/FreeBSDDesktop</a></p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>IRC Admin</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>IRC Admin</name>
	<email>irc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD IRC Admin team manages the FreeBSD Project's
	presence
	and activity on the freenode IRC network, looking after:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Registration and management of channels within the
	official namespace (#freebsd*)</li>

	<li>Channel moderation</li>

	<li>Liaising with freenode staff</li>

	<li>Allocating <tt>freebsd/*</tt> hostmask cloaks for users</li>

	<li>General user support relating to channel management</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	While the FreeBSD Project does not <tt>currently</tt>
	endorse IRC as an
	official support channel (see
	<a
	href="https://www.freebsd.org/community/irc.html">here</a>
	and <a
	href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/faq/support.html#irc">here</a>),
	as it has not been able to guarantee
	a consistent or positive user experience, IRC Admin has
	been working
	toward creating a high quality experience, by
	standardising channel
	administration and moderation expectations, and ensuring
	the projects
	ability to manage all channels within its namespace.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter, IRC Admin:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Cleaned up (deregistered) registrations for channels that
	were defunct,
	stale, out of date, or had founders that were inactive
	(not seen for &gt; 1
	year). Channels that were found to be otherwise active
	have been retained.
	FreeBSD now has ~40 channels registered from a previous
	total of over 150.</li>

	<li>Documented baseline configuration settings in the Wiki for
	channels,
	including ChanServ settings, channel modes, registration
	policy, etc.</li>

	<li>Established multiple documented methods for reporting user
	abuse
	or other channel issues to IRC Admin for resolution</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Upcoming changes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Work with existing <tt>#freebsd*</tt> channels to
	standardise channel management,
	settings and access.</li>

	<li>Migrate, forward and/or consolidate existing or duplicate
	<tt>#freebsd*</tt>
	channels to channels with a standard naming convention.</li>

	<li>Work with unofficial <tt>##freebsd*</tt> channels to
	migrate them to the official
	<tt>#freebsd*</tt> channels if suitable</li>

	<li>Update existing IRC-related website and documentation
	sources the describe
	the official state of project managed IRC presence on
	freenode.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Lastly, and to repeat a previous call, while the vast
	majority of
	the broader user community interacts on the freenode IRC
	network,
	the FreeBSD developer presence still needs to be
	significantly
	improved on freenode.</p>

      <p>There are many opportunities to be had by increasing the
	amount and
	quality of interaction between FreeBSD users and
	developers, both
	in terms of developers keeping their finger on the pulse
	of the
	community and in encouraging and cultivating greater
	contributions
	to the Project over the long term.</p>

      <p>It is critical to have a strong developer presence amongst
	users,
	and IRC Admin would like again to call on all developers
	to join
	the FreeBSD freenode channels to increase that presence.</p>

      <p>Users are invited to <tt>/join #freebsd-irc</tt> on the
	freenode IRC network
	if they have questions, ideas, constructive criticism, and
	feedback
	on how the FreeBSD Project can improve the service and
	experience
	it provides to the community on IRC.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>FreeBSD Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Deb Goodkin</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit
	organization dedicated to supporting and promoting
	the FreeBSD Project and community worldwide.
	Funding comes from individual and corporate
	donations and is used to fund and manage software
	development projects, conferences and developer
	summits, and provide travel grants to FreeBSD
	contributors. The Foundation purchases and
	supports hardware to improve and maintain FreeBSD
	infrastructure and provides resources to improve
	security, quality assurance, and release
	engineering efforts; publishes marketing material
	to promote, educate, and advocate for the FreeBSD
	Project; facilitates collaboration between
	commercial vendors and FreeBSD developers; and
	finally, represents the FreeBSD Project in
	executing contracts, license agreements, and other
	legal arrangements that require a recognized legal
	entity.</p>

      <p>Here are some highlights of what we did to help FreeBSD
	last quarter:</p>

      <p>We held our annual board meeting in Ottawa on May 14.
	Board Director and Officer elections take place
	each year at this meeting. Justin Gibbs was
	elected as the new President of the Board of
	Directors. The new FreeBSD Foundation Board of
	Directors includes President and Founder Justin T.
	Gibbs, Vice President Benedict Reuschling,
	Secretary Philip Paeps, Treasurer Marshall Kirk
	McKusick, and Directors Hiroki Sato, George
	Neville-Neil and Robert N. M. Watson. You can read
        <a href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/latest-news/freebsd-foundation-names-justin-gibbs-as-new-board-president/">more
        about the elections</a>.</p>

      <p>After the elections, our management team gave updates to
	the board on their respective areas. We then
	discussed the key areas of the Project that need
	help, and where we can step in to fill those
	holes. We reviewed and updated our 12 month goals,
	and identified projects we should support. We then
	discussed conferences we are likely to attend, and
	went over the latest on our fundraising efforts.
	We followed that up with a discussion on how to
	get more users to contribute back to the Project.
	While discussing how to increase the number of
	users and contributors, we talked about methods
	for making for more training material available.</p>

      <p>
	Partnerships and Commercial User Support</p>
      <p>
	We help facilitate collaboration between commercial users
	and FreeBSD developers. We also meet with
	companies to discuss their needs and bring that
	information back to the Project. In Q2, Ed Maste
	and Deb Goodkin met with a few commercial users in
	Germany. It’s not only beneficial for the above,
	but it also helps us understand some of the
	applications where FreeBSD is used. Because BSDCan
	brings in a high number of commercial users, we
	have an excellent opportunity to have similar
	discussions about their needs during the four-day
	FreeBSD Summit and BSDCan.</p>

      <p>
	Fundraising Efforts</p>
      <p>
	Our work is 100% funded by your donations. We are grateful
	for the generous donations from Intel, NetApp,
	VMware and Stormshield last quarter. We are
	working hard to get more commercial users to give
	back to help us continue our work supporting
	FreeBSD. More importantly, we’d like to thank
	our individual donors, for making $10-$1,000
	donations last quarter, for a total of $16,000!</p>

      <p>Please consider making a donation to help us
	<a href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/donate/">continue and
	increase our support for FreeBSD</a>.</p>

      <p>We also have the
	<a href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/FreeBSD-foundation-partnership-program/">Partnership
	Program</a> to provide more
	benefits for our larger commercial donors.
	Find out more information at the link and share with your
	companies!</p>

      <p>OS Improvements</p>
      <p>
	The Foundation improves the FreeBSD operating system by
	employing our technical staff to maintain and
	improve critical kernel subsystems, add features
	and functionality, and fix problems. The
	Foundation also provides grants to fund individual
	projects.</p>

      <p>There were 243 commits to the FreeBSD base system
	repository sponsored by the Foundation during the
	quarter. These include improvements to the tmpfs
	in-memory, MSDOS, and UFS filesystems, device
	driver and hardware compatibility fixes, virtual
	memory (VM), tool chain, documentation, and
	testing and continuous integration improvements.</p>

      <p>We fixed a number of race conditions and security issues
	found by Syzkaller, Google’s
	code-coverage-guided system call fuzzer.</p>

      <p>Alan Somers’ work on updating FreeBSD’s support for
	FUSE (userspace filesystems) continued during the
	quarter; the full details are elsewhere in this
	quarterly report. At this point most of the work
	has been committed to the project branch but some
	bug fixes and improvements have been committed
	directly to the FreeBSD development branch.</p>

      <p>Edward Napierala’s Linuxulator project continued through
	the quarter, resulting in a number of improvements
	to the Linuxulator and linux-specific
	functionality such as linsysfs. This work is part
	of the path to supporting the Linux strace
	debugging tool in order to facilitate debugging
	failures of other Linux binaries under the
	Linuxulator. Mateusz Guzik continued with
	scalability and performance improvements during
	the quarter, and Bjoern Zeeb integrated the SDIO
	stack (with details elsewhere in the quarterly
	report).</p>

      <p>Progress was made on the online RAID-Z expansion project
	over the quarter. Matt Ahrens posted an <a
	href="https://github.com/zfsonlinux/zfs/pull/8853">alpha
	preview</a> of the feature for further
	experimentation and review, and the FreeBSD
	Foundation will make an alpha release image
	available for testing in the near future.</p>

      <p>Foundation staff contributed to nine FreeBSD security
	advisories and errata updates over the quarter,
	including CPU vulnerability workarounds. Related
	work included improving Intel microcode update
	loading.</p>

      <p>Continuous Integration and Quality Assurance</p>
      <p>
	The Foundation provides a full-time staff member who is
	working on improving our automated testing,
	continuous integration, and overall quality
	assurance efforts.</p>

      <p>During the second quarter of 2019, Foundation staff
	continued to improve the project's CI
	infrastructure, worked with contributors to fix
	the failing build and test cases, and worked with
	other teams in the Project for their testing
	needs. We hosted a CI-focused working group at
	BSDcan and continue to publish the CI weekly
	report at <a
	href="https://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-testing">freebsd-testing@</a>
	mailing list.</p>

      <p>See the FreeBSD CI section of this report for more
	information.</p>

      <p>
	Supporting FreeBSD Infrastructure</p>
      <p>
	The Foundation provides hardware and support to improve
	the FreeBSD infrastructure. Last quarter, we
	continued supporting FreeBSD hardware located
	around the world.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD Advocacy and Education</p>
      <p>
	A large part of our efforts are dedicated to advocating
	for the Project. This includes promoting work
	being done by others with FreeBSD; producing
	advocacy literature to teach people about FreeBSD
	and help make the path to starting using FreeBSD
	or contributing to the Project easier; and
	attending and getting other FreeBSD contributors
	to volunteer to run FreeBSD events, staff FreeBSD
	tables, and give FreeBSD presentations.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation sponsors many conferences, events,
	and summits around the globe. These events can be
	BSD-related, open source, or technology events
	geared towards underrepresented groups. We support
	the FreeBSD-focused events to help provide a venue
	for sharing knowledge, to work together on
	projects, and to facilitate collaboration between
	developers and commercial users. This all helps
	provide a healthy ecosystem. We support the
	non-FreeBSD events to promote and raise awareness
	of FreeBSD, to increase the use of FreeBSD in
	different applications, and to recruit more
	contributors to the Project.</p>

      <p>Check out some of the advocacy and education work we did
	last quarter:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Represented FreeBSD at LinuxFest Northwest In Bellingham,
	Washington</li>

	<li>Sponsored and helped organize the FreeBSD Developers
	Summit at BSDCan, in Ottawa, Canada</li>

	<li>Sponsored and attended BSDCan 2019</li>

	<li>Set up registration and attended the Vienna FreeBSD
	Security Hackathon in Vienna, Austria</li>

	<li>Represented FreeBSD at HKOSCON</li>

	<li>Attended the Berlin FreeBSD Developers Summit</li>

	<li>Presented at 2019 Comcast Labs Connect Open Source
	Conference</li>

	<li>Sponsored, presented and represented FreeBSD at RootConf
	2019 in Bangalore, India</li>

	<li>Committed to attend OSCON, and All Things Open</li>

	<li>Committed to sponsor and help organize a Bay Area
	Developers Summit</li>

	<li>Provided FreeBSD advocacy material</li>

	<li>Provided travel grants to FreeBSD contributors to attend
	many of the above events</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	We continued producing FreeBSD advocacy material to help
	people promote FreeBSD around the world.</p>

      <p>Read more about our conference adventures in the
	conference recaps and trip reports in our
	<a href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/news-and-events/newsletter/">monthly
	newsletters</a>.</p>

      <p>We help educate the world about FreeBSD by publishing the
	professionally produced FreeBSD Journal. As we
	mentioned previously, the FreeBSD Journal is now a
	free publication. Find out more and access the
	latest issues at
	<a href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/journal/">https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/journal/</a>.</p>

      <p>You can find out more about
	<a href="https://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/news-and-events/">events
	we attended and upcoming events</a>.</p>

      <p>We have continued our work with a new website developer to
	help us improve our website. Work has begun to
	make it easier for community members to find
	information more easily and to make the site more
	efficient.</p>

      <p>Legal/FreeBSD IP</p>
      <p>
	The Foundation owns the FreeBSD trademarks, and it is our
	responsibility to protect them. We also provide
	legal support for the core team to investigate
	questions that arise.</p>

      <p>Go to http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org to find out how we
	support FreeBSD and how we can help you!</p>
    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>bhyve - Live Migration</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Elena Mihailescu</name>
	<email>elenamihailescu22@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Darius Mihai</name>
	<email>dariusmihaim@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mihai Carabas</name>
	<email>mihai@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Virtual-Machine-Migration-using-bhyve">Github wiki - How to Live and Warm Migrate a bhyve guest</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/tree/projects/bhyve_migration">Github - Warm Migration branch</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/tree/projects/bhyve_migration_dev">Github - Live Migration branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Migration feature uses the Save/Restore feature to
	migrate a bhyve guest
	from a FreeBSD host to another FreeBSD host. To migrate a
	bhyve guest,
	one needs to start an empty guest on the destination host
	from a shared guest
	image using the bhyve tool with the <tt>-R</tt> option
	followed by the source host
	IP and the port to listen to migration request. On the
	source host, the
	migration is started by executing the bhyvectl command
	with the <tt>--migrate</tt>
	or <tt>--migrate-live</tt> option, followed by the
	destination host IP and the
	port to send to the messages.</p>

      <p>New features added:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Clear the dirty bit after each migration round</li>

	<li>Extend live migration to highmem segment</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Future tasks:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Refactor live migration branch</li>

	<li>Rebase live migration</li>

	<li>Extend live migration to unwired memory</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Matthew Grooms
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>bhyve - Save/Restore</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Elena Mihailescu</name>
	<email>elenamihailescu22@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Darius Mihai</name>
	<email>dariusmihaim@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mihai Carabas</name>
	<email>mihai@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/tree/projects/bhyve_snapshot">Github repository for the snapshot feature for bhyve</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Save-and-Restore-a-virtual-machine-using-bhyve">Github wiki - How to Save and Restore a bhyve guest</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/FreeBSD-UPB/freebsd/wiki/Suspend-Resume-test-matrix">Github wiki - Suspend/resume test matrix</url>
      <url href="https://reviews.freebsd.org/D19495">Phabricator review - bhyve Snapshot Save and Restore</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Save/Restore for bhyve feature is a suspend and resume
	facility added to the
	FreeBSD/amd64's hypervisor, bhyve. The bhyvectl tool is
	used to save the guest
	state in three files (a file for the guest memory, a file
	for the states of
	various devices and the state of the CPU, and another one
	for some metadata that
	is used in the restore process).
	To suspend a bhyve guest, the bhyvectl tool must be run
	with the <tt>--suspend
	&lt;state_file_name&gt;</tt>
	option followed by the guest name.</p>

      <p>To restore a bhyve guest from a checkpoint, one simply has
	to add the <tt>-r</tt> option
	followed by the main state file (the same file that was
	given to the <tt>--suspend</tt>
	option for bhyvectl) when starting the VM.</p>

      <p>New features added:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Open ticket on Phabricator</li>

	<li>Apply feedback received from community</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Future tasks:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Add suspend/resume support for nvme</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for virtio-console</li>

	<li>Add suspend/resume support for virtio-scsi</li>

	<li>Add TSC offsetting for restore for AMD CPUs</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Matthew Grooms
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ENA FreeBSD Driver Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Michal Krawczyk</name>
	<email>mk@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Maciej Bielski</name>
	<email>mba@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Marcin Wojtas</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/amzn/amzn-drivers/blob/master/kernel/fbsd/ena/README">ENA README</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ENA (Elastic Network Adapter) is the smart NIC available
	in the
	virtualized environment of Amazon Web Services (AWS). The
	ENA
	driver supports multiple transmit and receive queues and
	can handle
	up to 100 Gb/s of network traffic, depending on the
	instance type
	on which it is used.</p>

      <p>ENAv2 has been under development for FreeBSD, similar to
	Linux
	and DPDK. Since the last update internal review and
	improvements
	of the patches were done, followed by validation on
	various AWS
	instances.</p>

      <p>Completed since the last update:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Upstream of the ENAv2 patches - revisions
	<a
	href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=348383">r348383</a>
	-
	<a
	href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=348416">r348416</a>
	introduce a major driver upgrade to version v2.0.0. Along
	with various fixes
	and improvements, the most significant features are LLQ
	(Low Latency Queues)
	and independent queues reconfiguration using sysctl
	commands.</li>

	<li>Implement NETMAP support for ENA</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Todo:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Internal review and upstream of NETMAP support</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Amazon.com Inc
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FUSE</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Alan Somers</name>
	<email>asomers@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>FUSE (File system in USErspace) allows a userspace program
	to
	implement a file system. It is widely used to support
	out-of-tree file
	systems like NTFS, as well as for exotic pseudo file
	systems like
	sshfs. FreeBSD's fuse driver was added as a GSoC project
	in 2012.
	Since that time, it has been largely neglected. The FUSE
	software is
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/buglist.cgi?bug_status=__open__&amp;known_name=fusefs&amp;list_id=289348&amp;query_based_on=fusefs&amp;query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc=%5Bfusefs%5D%20sysutils%2Ffusefs-&amp;short_desc_type=anywordssubstr">buggy</a>
	and out-of-date. Our implementation is about 11 years
	behind.</p>

      <p>During Q2 I nearly finished the FUSE overhaul that I
	begain in Q1. I raised
	the protocol level from 7.8 to 7.23, fixed many bugs (see
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=199934">199934</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=216391">216391</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=233783">233783</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=234581">234581</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=235773">235773</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=235774">235774</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=235775">235775</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236226">236226</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236231">236231</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236236">236236</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=239291">239291</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236329">236329</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236379">236379</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236381">236381</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236405">236405</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236327">236327</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236466">236466</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236472">236472</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236473">236473</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236474">236474</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236530">236530</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236557">236557</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236560">236560</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236647">236647</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=236844">236844</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=237052">237052</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=237181">237181</a>,
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=237588">237588</a>,
	and
	<a
	href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=238565">238565</a>),
	and added
	the following features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Optional kernel-side permissions checks (`-o
	default_permissions`)</li>

	<li>Implement <tt>VOP_MKNOD</tt>, <tt>VOP_BMAP</tt>, and
	<tt>VOP_ADVLOCK</tt></li>

	<li>Allow interrupting FUSE operations</li>

	<li>Support named pipes and unix-domain sockets in fusefs file
	systems</li>

	<li>Forward <tt>UTIME_NOW</tt> during <tt>utimensat(2)</tt> to
	the daemon</li>

	<li><tt>kqueue</tt> support for <tt>/dev/fuse</tt></li>

	<li>Allow updating mounts with <tt>mount -u</tt></li>

	<li>Allow exporting fusefs file systems over NFS</li>

	<li>Server-initiated invalidation of the name cache or data
	cache</li>

	<li>Respect <tt>RLIMIT_FSIZE</tt></li>

	<li>Try to support servers as old as protocol 7.4</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	I also added the following performance enhancements:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Implement FUSE's <tt>FOPEN_KEEP_CACHE</tt> and
	<tt>FUSE_ASYNC_READ</tt> flags</li>

	<li>Cache file attributes</li>

	<li>Cache lookup entries, both positive and negative</li>

	<li>Server-selectable cache modes: writethrough, writeback, or
	uncached</li>

	<li>Write clustering</li>

	<li>Readahead</li>

	<li>Use <tt>counter(9)</tt> for statistical reporting</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	All that remains is to finish merging the branch, and deal
	with any newly
	introduced bugs.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Kernel ZLIB Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Yoshihiro Ota</name>
	<email>ota@j.email.ne.jp</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://reviews.freebsd.org/D19706">Review D19706</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Kernel zlib upgrade is in progress.</p>

      <p>Xin (delphij@) and I have been working closely for zlib
	upgrade.
	We relocated contrib/zlib to sys/contrib/zlib in order for
	kernel
	code to access zlib in the tree. We also deleted dead code
	that
	depended on zlib and inflate - inflate is a fork of unzip
	to
	uncompress gzip files. We also renamed crc.h to avoid
	conflicts
	with zlib/crc.h.</p>

      <p>Next goal is to compile both old zlib and new zlib into
	the kernel
	allowing to switch each zlib user independently.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Linux compatibility layer update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Edward Tomasz Napierala</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The project aims to improve the Linux compatibility layer,
	to make
	it more compatible with recent Linux releases, and also to
	lower
	the bar for potential developers who want to start
	contributing to it.</p>

      <p>The initial effort focused on tooling, to make it easier
	to debug
	problems and to prevent future regressions. The first part
	involved
	making it possible to use Linux strace(1) utility and
	providing it
	as <tt>linux-c7-strace</tt> package. The reason is that
	while FreeBSD
	<tt>truss(1)</tt> and <tt>ktrace(1)</tt> can trace Linux
	binaries, they cannot
	decode Linux-specific flags and structures.</p>

      <p>The second part involved providing Linux Test Project
	binaries as
	<tt>linux-ltp</tt> package. There is ongoing work to hook
	it up to the
	FreeBSD CI infrastructure <a
	href="http://ci.FreeBSD.org">http://ci.FreeBSD.org</a>.</p>

      <p>There was also a number of improvements and fixes to bugs
	discovered
	in the process. One of them (not yet committed) fixes
	binaries
	linked against newer version of libc, effectively
	unbreaking binaries
	from recent Ubuntu releases.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Lock-less delayed invalidation for amd64 pmap</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Virtual Memory machine-dependent layer (pmap) on amd64
	needs to
	track all mappings for the managed physical memory pages,
	to be able
	to either destroy all of them (for page-out), or change
	them from
	writeable to read-only (e.g. to sync the page content to
	file, without
	racing with modifications through user writes). The
	mappings are
	accounted by creating pv_entry which records the address
	space
	(implicitly, by linking the pv entry to pmap) and the
	virtual address
	of the mapping.</p>

      <p>Previous work split the lock protecting the pv entries
	lists from
	other VM locks into the pvh_global_lock lock, which was
	global for all
	address spaces. You can see it in i386 pmap.c still.
	Later, hashed
	per-page pv lists locks were introduced, which would
	reduce contention
	on pv lists maninulations for different pages, but
	unfortunately the
	pvh_global_lock was still needed to guarantee the safety
	of some
	operations.</p>

      <p>Problem arises because amd64 pmap uses pmap lock to
	protect page
	tables and TLB consistency, which is per-pmap locks
	different from pv
	lists locks. When updating page table entry, we never drop
	pmap lock
	until the necessary TLB invalidation is done globally,
	including
	signalling other CPUs with IPI. But pv list locks can be
	unlocked
	before the necessary invalidation is done. So for instance
	when pmap
	is asked to remove all mappings of the specific page
	(pmap_remove_all(9)), it checks pv list of the page to
	find the
	mappings. The list might appear empty despite other CPUs
	TLB were not
	yet invalidated. If such page is reused, other CPUs might
	change its
	content using cached TLB entries. Allowing that means
	allowing both
	silent data corruption and opening security hole.</p>

      <p>So the global pvh lock was held until all pmaps
	invalidated their
	TLBs. This mechanism has obvious scalability issues, and
	instead a
	generation-count based scheme for handling delayed
	invalidation (DI)
	was developed, where each thread that might remove entry
	from pv list
	acquired a generation number and marked the page with it,
	see
	pmap_delayed_invl_page(9). Then, on e.g.
	pmap_remove_all(9) or
	pmap_remove_write(9), pmap code waits for the maximum
	current thread's
	invalidation generation number to pass the page's
	generation, which
	guarantees that all required TLB invalidations are done.</p>

      <p>Original implementation of DI allowed to get rid of
	pvh_global_lock,
	and only used a private mutex to handle sequential
	queueing of the
	coming and leaving threads, protecting a bounded region. A
	problem
	with that appeared e.g. in scalability benchmarks which
	did massive
	parallel unmaps, causing most of the threads to contend on
	DI
	queueing.</p>

      <p>Current implementation of DI switched to lock-less queue
	algorithm
	using the approach proposed by T.L. Harris and relying on
	double-CAS
	to coalesce generation count and queueing. It uses ifuncs
	to select
	either previous locked DI or current lock-less
	implementation, only
	old AMD Athlons which did not implemented the CMPXCHG16B
	instruction
	falls to the locked implementation by default. Lock-less
	implementation still blocks the waiting thread on
	turnstile to avoid
	priority-inversion issues, but practically the wait occur
	very rare,
	typical parallel buildworld generates single-digit number
	of the
	events.</p>

      <p>The patch got a lot of testing from Peter Holm, continuous
	reviews by
	Mark Johnston while I worked out bugs and live-lock
	problems in the
	implementation, and additional testing by Mateusz Guzik
	who helped to
	identify a priority inversion bug with the wait.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Mellanox Drivers Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Slava Shwartsman Hans Petter Selasky Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>freebsd-drivers@mellanox.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mellanox.com/page/products_dyn?product_family=193&amp;mtag=freebsd_driver">Mellanox OFED for FreeBSD Documentation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The mlx5 driver provides support for ConnectX-4 [Lx],
	ConnectX-5 [Ex] and
	ConnectX-6 [Dx] adapter cards. The mlx5en driver provides
	support for Ethernet
	adapter cards, whereas mlx5ib driver provides support for
	InfiniBand adapters
	and RDMA over Converged Ethernet (RoCE).</p>

      <p>Following updates done in mlx5 drivers:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>200Gb/s ConnectX-6 Ethernet:
	Added support for <a
	href="http://www.mellanox.com/page/products_dyn?product_family=285&amp;amp;mtag=socketdc">Mellanox
	Socket Direct Adapters</a>
	which allows, among the rest of the capabilities, to run
	up to 200Gb/s on a
	PCIe Gen 3.0 on a LAG interface.</li>

	<li>Support for "BlueField" - Multicore System On A Chip:
	Added support for RShim driver for <a
	href="http://www.mellanox.com/products/bluefield-overview/">BlueField
	Multicore System On A Chip(SOC)</a>.
	The RShim driver provides access to the RShim resources on
	the BlueField
	target accessible from an external host machine. The
	current RShim version
	provides device files for boot image push and virtual
	console access. It
	also creates virtual network interface to connect to the
	BlueField target
	and provides access to internal RShim registers.</li>

	<li>Firmware Burning and Diagnostics Tools:
	Added MSTFLINT to ports, this package contains a burning
	and diagnostic
	tools for Mellanox NICs.
	This package contains following tools:
	mstflint - Tools which allows to query and burn firmware.
	mstconfig - This tool queries and sets non-volatile
	configurable options for
	Mellanox HCAs.
	mstregdump - This utility dumps hardware registers from
	Mellanox hardware.
	mstmcra - This debug utility reads/writes a to/from the
	device
	configuration register space.
	mstvpd - This utility dumps the on-card VPD.
	and more.</li>

	<li>OFED-FreeBSD-v3.5.1 Upstream:
	Pushed upstream and MFCed OFED-FreeBSD-v3.5.1 driver -
	more details
	on the content of this update can be found in <a
	href="http://www.mellanox.com/page/products_dyn?product_family=193&amp;amp;mtag=freebsd_driver">Mellanox
	OFED for FreeBSD documentation</a> page.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	General updates:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Submitted papers for EuroBSDcon for a joint talk with
	Netflix titled
	"Kernel TLS and TLS Hardware Offload". The papers were
	accepted.</li>

	<li>Mellanox is intensively working to improve its cooperation
	with the FreeBSD
	community. As part of this effort, FreeBSD users are
	invited to propose
	features and enhancements to further develop and enrich
	the end-user
	experience. In addition, Mellanox continues to identify
	and present the
	right solutions to meet customers' needs.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Mellanox Technologies
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>NFSv4.2 client/server implementation for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Rick Macklem</name>
	<email>rmacklem@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/projects/nfsv42">current sources</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>NFSv4.2 is a newer minor version of NFSv4, made up of a
	set of optional
	operations/features. A majority of these operations are
	related to
	the POSIX operations posix_fadvise(2), posix_fallocate(2)
	and lseek(2)'s
	support for SEEKHOLE/SEEKDATA. There is also a Copy
	operation that allows
	a byte range of a file to be copied to another file
	locally on the NFS
	server, avoiding data transfer over the wire in both
	directions.
	FreeBSD-current now has a Linux compatible
	copy_file_range(2) syscall
	that will invoke this Copy operation on NFSv4.2 mounts.
	There is also support for MAC labelling, but it requires
	changes to the
	RPCSEC_GSS implementation to add V3 support and, as such,
	may not happen
	soon.</p>

      <p>The implementation of NFSv4.2 (RFC-7862) is progressing
	nicely.
	At this time, the LayoutError, IOAdvise, Allocate and Copy
	operations
	have been implemented. There is still work to be done on
	Copy, to add
	asynchronous support, so that large copies do not result
	in a long delay
	for the RPC's reply.</p>

      <p>The major operation that will be implemented next is Seek,
	so that
	lseek(SEEKHOLE/SEEKDATA) will work for the NFSv4.2 mounts.</p>

      <p>It is hoped that this implementation will be ready for
	FreeBSD-current/head
	in time for the FreeBSD-13 release.</p>

      <p>Testing is always appreciated and can be done by
	downloading the modified
	kernel from the svn repository in base/rojects/nfsv42 and
	then building
	and testing it on a couple of recent FreeBSD-current
	systems.</p>

      <p>If anyone is conversant with Kerberos and wants to take on
	the challenge
	of adding RPCSEC_GSS_V3 support to the kernel RPC, a patch
	that does
	that would also be greatly appreciated.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>NUMA awareness in the FreeBSD kernel</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Jeff Roberson</name>
	<email>jeff@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Andrew Gallatin</name>
	<email>gallatin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mark Johnston</name>
	<email>markj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A set of patches to improve the state of NUMA awareness in
	the FreeBSD
	kernel are being developed and refined. This work also
	aims to
	generally improve the performance of FreeBSD's memory
	management
	subsystem on systems with many CPUs.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD 12.0 featured a number of large changes which
	improve its
	performance on systems with a non-uniform memory
	architecture. That is,
	systems in which memory access latency for a given address
	varies
	depending on the CPU. Another round of improvements is
	being developed
	and will soon be available in FreeBSD-CURRENT. Short
	descriptions of
	some of these patches follow; a few have already been
	committed to
	FreeBSD-CURRENT.</p>

      <p>In FreeBSD terminology, a memory page whose contents may
	not be evicted
	is referred to as "wired." Pages may be wired under
	different
	circumstances: for instance, all kernel memory is wired,
	and userland
	applications may request that ranges of memory be wired
	using the
	mlock(2) and mlockall(2) system calls. FreeBSD has
	historically defined
	a system-wide limit on the number of wired pages so as to
	avoid
	deadlocks that may arise when too much of a system's
	memory cannot be
	reclaimed to satisfy new memory allocations. This limit
	was applied
	only to userland wiring requests, but kernel wirings were
	counted
	against the limit, so a large source of kernel wirings
	could cause
	mlock(2) failures. This occurs frequently with a large ZFS
	ARC, for
	example. In FreeBSD-CURRENT this limit has been changed
	such that only
	userland wirings are counted against the limit; the kernel
	contains a
	number of mechanisms to apply back-pressure to kernel
	memory usage, so
	the use of a global limit on all wirings did not provide
	much benefit.
	This fixes a common problem on large ZFS systems, and
	helps enable some
	other architectural improvements to the code which manages
	page wirings.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD has historically maintained two separate reference
	counters in
	the structure which describes a single physical page of
	memory. These
	counters initially had quite different properties, but
	have over time
	become more and more similar. Some work to merge the two
	counters has
	landed in FreeBSD-CURRENT. This does not have any
	user-visible effects,
	but it simplifies the page management code and removes a
	large amount of
	code which existed solely to transform references of one
	type to the
	other. Such code also made use of heavily contended locks,
	so the
	simplification improved kernel scalability for some
	workloads and has
	enabled further scalability improvements.</p>

      <p>UMA is the slab allocator used in FreeBSD's kernel. It is
	the backend
	which services virtually all dynamic memory allocations
	performed in the
	kernel. The first round of NUMA improvements added NUMA
	awareness to
	the "keg" layer of UMA, which allocates and manages slabs.
	However, the
	frontend of UMA, which provides several layers of caching
	for objects,
	did not provide domain-aware caching, so over time the
	caches would
	become "polluted" with objects from different memory
	domains. However,
	this caching layer is being modified to ensure that
	objects from
	different memory domains are partitioned, helping ensure
	that consumers
	can perform domain-local allocations and frees
	efficiently. This will
	enable a global "first-touch" allocation policy for
	UMA-managed objects.</p>

      <p>During boot, the FreeBSD kernel allocates a number of
	static data
	structures to track physical memory. These structures have
	historically
	lived in the lowest available range of physical memory, so
	they many not
	inhabit the same NUMA domain as the memory that they
	track. This is
	suboptimal when one tries to affinitize a workload to a
	particular NUMA
	domain: if while executing the workload the kernel
	frequently accesses
	page structures for local memory, and the page structures
	themselves
	are not placed in local memory, the kernel will perform
	many remote
	memory accesses. Some in-progress work for the amd64
	platform creates
	multiple arrays of page tracking structures, one per NUMA
	domain, and
	ensures that each array is local to its domain. This
	complicates the
	task of initializing kernel data structures during boot,
	but can
	substantially reduce the amount of cross-domain
	communication that
	occurs while the kernel is performing useful work.
	Similarly, some
	patches to affinitize per-CPU structures are being
	developed; while
	most per-CPU memory allocations already return CPU-local
	memory, some
	structures allocated during boot are not yet properly
	placed with
	respect to the accessing CPU's memory domain.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Netflix
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeBSD SDIO and Broadcom FullMAC WiFi Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Bjoern Zeeb</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.ORG</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/SDIO">FreeBSD Wiki SDIO page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>SDIO is an interface designed as an extension to SD Cards
	to allow attachments of various other peripherals, e.g.,
	WiFi or Bluetooth.</p>

      <p>Work has been ongoing by Ilya Bakulin on the MMCCAM stack
	to provide the infrastructure to be able to have SD cards
	and SDIO devices attached side-by-side facilitating
	FreeBSD's CAM framework.
	Based on this excellent work over the last years,
	SDIO support was finished earlier this year and committed
	to FreeBSD HEAD with the intention to merge to 12 at a
	later time.</p>

      <p>Facilitating the newly available SDIO bus, work started to
	port Broadcom's FullMAC WiFi driver. This work is still
	in progress and expected to complete later this year.
	With this WiFi support for the Raspberry Pi and other
	embedded boards will become available.
	Likewise drivers for other SDIO devices can be developed
	now.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BIO_DELETE support for the swap pager</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Doug Moore</name>
	<email>dougm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Alan Cox</name>
	<email>alc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mark Johnston</name>
	<email>markj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>An ongoing project aims to teach the swap pager to send
	SCSI UNMAP or
	ATA TRIM commands to the swap device when a block of swap
	space has been
	freed, for example when the application owning that block
	is exiting.</p>

      <p>SSDs have become commonplace and feature low latency for
	random I/O
	requests. This makes them appealing for use as swap
	devices, since
	lower latencies mean that applications spend less time
	blocked while
	waiting for a page-in from the swap device. To maximize
	write
	performance, some SSDs require the operating system to
	send a
	notification to the disk when a sector is no longer in
	use; this helps
	the disk optimize their usage of NAND flash cells. In
	FreeBSD such a
	notification is called a BIO_DELETE.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD's UFS and ZFS filesystems have for a long time
	been able to
	transmit BIO_DELETE requests to the devices backing the
	filesystem. For
	example, for UFS this support is enabled by specifying -t
	in newfs(8) or
	tunefs(8)'s parameters. However, FreeBSD has historically
	not had a
	corresponding implementation for swap devices.</p>

      <p>Thanks to Doug Moore, as of r349286 in -CURRENT and
	r349930 in stable/12
	swapon(8) can send BIO_DELETE to all blocks on the
	specified device
	immediately prior to configuring it as a swap device. This
	is enabled
	by specifying -E in the swapon(8) parameters, or by adding
	the
	"trimonce" option to the swap device's /etc/fstab entry.
	Some
	in-progress work on the swap pager implements online block
	deletion, in
	which BIO_DELETE is transmitted for blocks as they are
	freed by
	applications; this will hopefully be implemented in
	FreeBSD 13.0.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Fuzzing FreeBSD with syzkaller</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Mark Johnston</name>
	<email>markj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Andrew Turner</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Michael Tuexen</name>
	<email>tuexen@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Ed Maste</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/google/syzkaller">syzkaller</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>See the syzkaller entry in the 2019q1 quarterly report for
	an
	introduction to syzkaller.</p>

      <p>syzkaller continues to find FreeBSD kernel bugs. A number
	of
	such bugs have been fixed in the past quarter, and we
	continue
	to investigate and fix bug reports from syzkaller. Work to
	extend syzkaller's capabilites has progressed: Andrew
	Turner
	has implemented support for fuzzing the 32-bit
	compatibility
	layer in amd64 kernels, helping illuminate some of the
	darker
	corners of the kernel, and it is now possible to use bhyve
	as
	a VM backend to syzkaller, so it is now efficient and
	convenient
	to fuzz FreeBSD on FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>Some planned work includes: enabling the use of ZFS as the
	base filesystem for fuzzer VMs; extending the range of
	system
	calls and ioctls covered by syzkaller; enabling LLVM
	sanitizers
	in the kernel so as to catch more issues; and making use
	of
	netdump(4) to capture kernel dumps for panics found by
	syzkaller,
	making it much easier to diagnose bugs for which syzkaller
	was
	unable to find a reproducible test case.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Locking changes for vnodes during execve(2)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Konstantin Belousov</name>
	<email>kib@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The execve(2) family of syscalls replaces the executing
	image in the
	current process. The file containing the program text,
	data, and
	arbitrary other pre-initialized segments for the newly
	activated image
	is usually called the text file. FreeBSD marks the text
	file as such,
	the mark is mutually exclusive with any opening of the
	file for write.
	In other words, file opened for write cannot be executed,
	and text
	file cannot be opened for write.</p>

      <p>During the execve(2) syscall processing, kernel needs to
	lock the text
	file' vnode. This is done both to satisfy the VFS calls
	protocol, and
	to ensure that there is no incompatible parallel changes
	occuring to
	the text vnode. A vnode can be locked either in exclusive
	mode, which
	is mutually incompatible with any other lock acquisition,
	or in shared
	mode, which is only incompatible with exclusive requests,
	but allows
	other shared owners.</p>

      <p>In principle, there is no reason why would execve(2) need
	an exclusive
	vnode lock, since it does not modify neither content nor
	metadata for
	the text vnode. The only exception is the marking of the
	vnode as
	text, which was done using VV_TEXT flag in v_vflag and
	protected by
	the vnode lock. Since we modify v_vflag, the vnode lock
	protecting
	the modification should be taken exclusive.</p>

      <p>The end result is that execve(2)'s of the same file are
	serialized. For
	instance, if user runs parallel build, which executes more
	than one
	job for compiling, all invocation of the compiler are
	serialized
	during execve(2).</p>

      <p>The count of opens for write is contained in other struct
	vnode member
	named v_writecount, which was protected by the vnode lock
	as well.
	Since text is mutually exclusive with an open for write, I
	reused
	v_writecount to indicate text references. Now, negative
	v_writecount
	counts the number of text references. The v_writecount
	content is
	literally protected by the vnode interlock, but normally
	all mutators
	also own vnode lock at least in the shared mode.</p>

      <p>This way, we no longer need to acquire exclusive text
	vnode lock
	during execve(2), removing the serializing point.
	Additional positive
	effect is that we started to account the precise number of
	text
	references on the vnode. Before, we cleared VV_TEXT on the
	last unmap
	of the text vnode, potentially allowing obscure DoS where
	mapping the
	text file while it is executed prevented writes until the
	mapping is
	destroyed. Now we mark the mappings for text explicitly in
	the
	vm_map_entry and dereference v_writecount by +1 when such
	entry is
	unmapped.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Broadcom ARM64 SoC support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Michal Stanek</name>
	<email>mst@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Kornel Duleba</name>
	<email>mindal@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Marcin Wojtas</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Semihalf team continued working on FreeBSD support for
	the
	<a
	href="https://www.broadcom.com/products/embedded-and-networking-processors/communications/bcm58712/">Broadcom
	BCM5871X SoC series</a></p>

      <p>BCM5871X are quad-core 64-bit ARMv8 Cortex-A57
	communication
	processors targeted for networking applications such as
	10G routers,
	gateways, control plane processing and NAS.</p>

      <p>Completed since the last update:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>iProc PCIe root complex (internal and external buses):
	fixes and improvements,
	including adding a BCM58712 quirk to GICv2m driver</li>

	<li>BNXT Ethernet support: sys/dev/bnxt.c driver has been
	extended to support
	the BCM58700 variant, and the iflib was made to work
	without IO cache coherency</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	In progress:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Crypto engine acceleration for IPsec offloading.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Todo:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Upstreaming of work. This work is expected to be
	submitted/merged
	to HEAD in the second half of 2019.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Juniper Networks, Inc
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>NXP ARM64 SoC support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Marcin Wojtas</name>
	<email>mw@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Artur Rojek</name>
	<email>ar@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The Semihalf team initiated working on FreeBSD support for
	the
	<a
	href="https://www.nxp.com/products/processors-and-microcontrollers/arm-based-processors-and-mcus/qoriq-layerscape-arm-processors/qoriq-layerscape-1046a-and-1026a-multicore-communications-processors:LS1046A">NXP
	LS1046A SoC</a></p>

      <p>LS1046A are quad-core 64-bit ARMv8 Cortex-A72 processors
	with
	integrated packet processing acceleration and high speed
	peripherals
	including 10 Gb Ethernet, PCIe 3.0, SATA 3.0 and USB 3.0
	for a wide
	range of networking, storage, security and industrial
	applications.</p>

      <p>Already completed:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Platform base support (ramp-up multi-user SMP operation
	with UART)</li>

	<li>SATA 3.0</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	In progress:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>USB3.0</li>

	<li>SD/MMC</li>

	<li>I2C</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Todo:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Ethernet support</li>

	<li>GPIO</li>

	<li>QSPI</li>

	<li>Upstreaming of developed features. This work is expected
	to
	be submitted/merged to HEAD in the Q4 of 2019.</li>
      </ul>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      Alstom Group
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='third'>
    <title>Aberdeen Hackathon</title>

    <body>
      <p>At BSDCam in Cambridge last year we had a discussion to
	create a template
	Hackathon in the same way we have a template for
	Devsummits. To test out the
	idea I was convinced (I swear tricked is the correct word)
	to host a Hackathon
	in Aberdeen.</p>

      <p>As a project I think we benefit a lot from hackathons, but
	they do take a
	little organisation. The worst part of this is dealing
	with getting money from
	attendees so you can pay for events. I spoke with Deb
	Goodkin from the
	foundation at BSDCam and we arranged to use their new
	EventBrite based system
	to handle ticketing.</p>

      <p>Overall this system made it straight forward for attendees
	to register and get
	me their details and requirements. After the event the
	expenses were then
	recouped from the foundation. This was much easier than me
	putting together a
	custom system or even setting up and using EventBrite
	myself.</p>

      <p>The hackathon went well, you can read in Benedict and
	Kristof's reports that
	follow, but it was less well attended than I originally
	expected.</p>

      <p>For hackers planning future hackathons remember to take
	heed of common national
	holidays (we could have planned the event to not land at
	Easter) and expect
	major geopolitical events to make things unpredictable (we
	knew Brexit would do
	something, but not when).</p>

      <p>I need to thank the University of Aberdeen for providing
	the location for the
	Hackathon and to encourage you to run a hackathon where
	you are. The next one
	should be in your home town.</p>

      <p>Benedict Reuschling</p>

      <p>The hackathon in Aberdeen was happening in the week of
	Easter at the University
	of Aberdeen. Although only Kristof Provost (kp@) and
	myself joined our host Tom
	Jones, I still consider it a productive week for us. The
	overall theme of the
	hackathon was networking and each of us provided something
	towards that goal
	(be it PRs, submitting unfinished work, or other bits and
	pieces). We got
	together the night of Tuesday, April 16 over dinner and
	talked about what our
	plans were for the week.</p>

      <p>Kristof and I had talked at AsiaBSDcon when I took his
	tutorial about Testing
	in FreeBSD that we should add a chapter about it in the
	developers handbook. We
	also used our first meeting to synchronize each other
	about the latest news in
	FreeBSD from our developers viewpoint.</p>

      <p>The next day, we met up at the Frazer Noble building where
	the hackathon was
	taking place. It was one of the newer buildings on campus,
	nicely integrated
	into the older houses of the city. Since we were only a
	handful, we sat in
	Tom's office for the hackathon, which had plenty of room.
	He also showed us the
	room where we are supposed to be having the hackathon if
	we were more people
	and Tom gave us a little tour. Working in a university
	myself, I'm always
	interested in how other education organizations are
	structured and the rooms
	and equipment they provide for learning. Overall, my
	impression was that there
	is a good amount of space and equipment available, which
	we could have used in
	the hackathon.</p>

      <p>After returning, we decided to use a special tag in the
	commits we would be
	doing to identify them as coming from this hackathon. We
	chose "Event:" for it
	as it is a general enough term to be used at other events
	like conferences,
	too. The "Sponsored by:" line we used in the past is more
	for companies or
	individuals sponsoring certain features, so I created a
	review to add this line
	to the committers guide.</p>

      <p>Kristof had a couple of changes to the pf chapter in the
	FreeBSD handbook for
	me, so I started going through those. I created a review
	for him and the commit
	was made there and then, making use of the short feedback
	cycle. Originally, we
	thought about bringing in people via hangouts, but then
	resolved to contact
	people via our usual IRC channel if we needed their input.</p>

      <p>Kristof and Tom worked on some network specific stuff,
	whereas I started work
	on creating an initial draft for the testing chapter. We
	would occasionally
	start talking about something and then return to our work
	in silence. If we
	needed to coordinate or had questions, we simply asked and
	could continue once
	we got our answer. This provided a nice atmosphere to work
	in. I tackled some
	doc PRs while Kristof found a bug in pf and fixed it.</p>

      <p>The afternoons were spent at different locations within
	walking distance. Tom
	made sure we got a good impression on how it is to be a
	student and that there
	is both taste and variety of food available. In the
	evenings, Tom drove us into
	town to have dinner at various restaurants over the week.</p>

      <p>Aberdeen has a lot to offer as a city. Starting from the
	second day, Kristof
	and I would meet up at my hotel, which was close to the
	Aberdeen beach and walk
	along it to the University. According to Tom, it is
	possible to see Dolphins
	when the weather is right and the gulf stream provides the
	city with enough
	warmth that the winters aren't as bad as you'd think this
	far up north.</p>

      <p>Tom also gave us a tour of the zoological department of
	the university, which
	offered a beautiful garden with various plants and trees,
	as well as a museum
	with zoological specimen. This offered a great spot for
	photographs and to
	unwind a bit from the technical discussions we've had. Tom
	also had t-shirts
	made for the event, which are already rare collectors
	items.</p>

      <p>I had to return on Sunday, so Tom took us on a tour of the
	Scottish highlands
	in his car the day before. We stopped at a couple of
	places to take pictures
	and Tom would explain at lot to us having lived there all
	his life. We came to
	Stonehaven and had fish and chips there from a take-out
	restaurant that had a
	lot of awards for sustainable fishing. This was certainly
	a highlight for the
	week and even then, we couldn't stop talking about FreeBSD
	and networking.</p>

      <p>Although more people would maybe have produced more
	output, the three of us
	were certainly productive as a small group. It also made
	planning and
	coordination easier and more flexible. Tom Jones had done
	a lot of preparation
	and was an excellent guide. I would encourage him to host
	another such
	hackathon in the future and hope that next time, more
	people will take a trip
	to Aberdeen to spend some time hacking on FreeBSD</p>

      <p>Kristof Provost</p>

      <p>While I’d been to Scotland before I’d never seen Aberdeen.
	It’s a charming
	city, and I enthusiastically recommend visiting.</p>

      <p>I arrived a little while after Benedict, but made it to my
	hotel easily, and
	turned up in time to join Benedict and Tom for dinner.</p>

      <p>Despite being small (or perhaps because of it), the
	hackathon was remarkably
	productive. Benedict and I went through the pf
	documentation in the handbook,
	so that Benedict could rework and improve it. (Benedict’s
	doing the work, but
	I’m going to take credit anyway.)</p>

      <p>Tom and I looked at the GSoC proposals and tried to find
	potential mentors for
	two promising proposals. Both of us are candidate mentors
	as well. We should
	know soon if our students are awarded slots.</p>

      <p>Tom also proposed a patch to eliminate RFC 2675 IPv6
	Jumbograms. It has my
	enthusiastic support.</p>

      <p>I managed to look at a couple of open pf issues:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>pfctl’s interface_group() function checks if a name is an
	interface or an interface group. It still thought
	that interface names always ended with a number,
	but this assumption has been wrong for several
	years now. That’s fixed in <a
	href="https://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/346370">r346370</a>.</li>

	<li>The DIOCRSETTFLAGS ioctl() misused copyin() (It held a
	lock calling it), which could result in panics.</li>

	<li>That previous issue was actually discovered by my local
	instance of syzcaller, which I’d set up to add pf
	support to it. That support has now been merged,
	so we may see more issues detected by syzcaller
	soon.</li>

	<li>Also for the DIOCRSETTFLAGS problem I extended the pf
	tests to check for this issue.</li>

	<li>The pf tests will now fail if the pft_set_rules call fails
	to set the rules. That didn’t actually cause
	issues yet, but it’ll make debugging tests
	slightly easier, and they may catch more problems
	now.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	On Saturday Tom took us out to discover some of the pretty
	bits of Scotland. It
	turns out there are a lot of them. I can’t really do it
	justice, but Tom has a
	promising career at the Scottish tourism board when this
	computers fad blows
	over.</p>

      <p>On my way home I passed through Oslo, and took the
	opportunity to meet with
	(have lunch with) two of the EuroBSDCon local organisers.
	EuroBSDCon is filling
	up fast, make sure to register now to secure your place!</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='third'>
    <title>Bring more Security Intelligence to FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Michael Muenz</name>
	<email>m.muenz@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/stamparm/maltrail">Maltrail - distributed Malware detection</url>
      <url href="https://wazuh.com/">Wazuh - thread detection and incident response</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>To bring more Security Intelligence we maintain the
	FreeBSD port
	of <tt>zmaltail</tt>. This open source project based on
	Python can act
	as a sensor and/or as a central server. It listens in
	defined ports
	or protocols and compares IP addresses and domains against
	static
	and dynamic feeds, contributed by the community.</p>

      <p>As you can install this piece of software on multiple
	firewalls
	and let them send to a central server, you are able to
	detect attacks
	and compromises very fast. Within Q2 we updated the port
	to the latest
	version and are constantly in contact with the core
	developer
	(also co-author of <tt>SQLmap</tt>) to bring out new
	features.</p>

      <p>The second project we are currently trying to add as a
	port is <tt>Wazuh</tt>.
	Wazuh is a fork of <tt>Ossec</tt> which is already in the
	ports tree.
	Compared to Ossec, Wazuh has some intelligent addition
	like full
	<tt>ELK-Stack</tt> integration with own apps and
	dashboards.</p>

      <p>With Wazuh installed on your webserver, or even on your
	windows desktop
	you can monitor file integrity or log files for most kind
	of attacks.
	Active response features let you e.g. send API calls to
	your firewalls
	to dynamically block this offender.</p>

      <p>As Wazuh offers a complete ELK-Stack you can use it also
	as a central
	logging solution for better security insights into your
	network.</p>

    </body>

    <sponsor>
      m.a.x. Informationstechnologie AG
    </sponsor>

  </project>

  <project cat='third'>
    <title>nsysctl 1.0</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Alfonso Sabato Siciliano</name>
	<email>alfonso.siciliano@email.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://gitlab.com/alfix/nsysctl">gitlab.com/alfix/nsysctl</url>
      <url href="https://www.freshports.org/sysutils/nsysctl/">sysutils/nsysctl port</url>
      <url href="https://alfix.gitlab.io/bsd/2019/02/19/nsysctl-tutorial.html">Tutorial</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>nsysctl</tt> utility is a <tt>/sbin/sysctl</tt>
	clone, to get or set the kernel
	state, supporting <tt>libxo</tt> and extra options.</p>

      <p><programlisting>
	  nsysctl [--libxo=opts [-r tagname]]<br/>
	  [-DdFGgIilmNpqTt[V|v[h[b|o|x]]]Wy]<br/>
	  [-e sep] [-B &lt;bufsize&gt;] [-f filename]<br/>
	  name[=value[,value]] ...<br/>
	  nsysctl [--libxo=opts [-r tagname]]<br/>
	  [-DdFGgIlmNpqTt[V|v[h[b|o|x]]]Wy]<br/>
	  [-e sep] [-B &lt;bufsize&gt;] -A|a|X<br/>
</programlisting></p>

      <p>You could use <tt>nsysctl</tt> to explore the sysctl MIB
	showing the value and the
	info of an object. The output is explicitly indicated by
	the options and is
	printed via <tt>libxo</tt> in human and machine readable
	formats, moreover some value
	is parsed to display it in a structured mode (e.g.,
	<tt>vm.phys_free</tt>).
	The support for <tt>efi_map_header</tt> was added but it
	is untested, someone could
	help by trying it via <tt>machdep.efi_map</tt>.</p>

      <p>Please refer to the tutorial for a more thorough
	description.</p>

    </body>

  </project>

  <project cat='third'>
    <title>libvdsk - QCOW2 implementation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Sergiu Weisz</name>
	<email>sergiu121@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Marcel Molenaar</name>
	<email>marcel@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Marcelo Araujo</name>
	<email>araujo@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>Mihai Carabas</name>
	<email>mihai@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/xcllnt/libvdsk">Github - libvdsk repo</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Add support for using QCOW in bhyve using the libvdsk
	library. Libvdsk was used
	to substitute the regular disk operations from bhyve with
	a call to libvdsk
	which will in turn call the disk-specific handler for the
	operation.</p>

      <p>To use this feature one has to install the libvdsk-enabled
	bhyve version along
	with libvdsk from the libvdsk repo linked above.</p>

      <p>New features added:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Extend libvdsk to make it easier to implement new formats</li>

	<li>Improve read/write performance and stability</li>

	<li>Add support for Copy-On-Write</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	Future tasks:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Integrate libvdsk in bhyve</li>
      </ul>

    <sponsor>
      Matthew Grooms
    </sponsor>

    </body>

  </project>

</report>
