<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>January-March</month>

    <year>2013</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between January and
      March 2013. This is the first of four reports planned for 2013.</p>

    <p>Highlights from this status report include the busy preparations
      of 8.4-RELEASE, restoration of binary package building, steady
      progress of several porting efforts, like work on the &os; ports
      of xorg, GNOME, KDE, and Xfce, bringing &os; to Cubieboard and
      Hackberry boards, development of ARM and AMD GPU support,
      improving performance of UFS/FFS and callouts, and introducing a
      multipath TCP implementation for the network stack.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 31 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period between April
      and June 2013 is July 7th, 2013.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Core Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>At the end of 2012, the Core Team approved using Google
	Analytics on the Project web site to enable the Documentation
	Engineering Team to collect statistics on its usage for better
	profiling.  In the first quarter of 2013, the Core Team worked
	with the Documentation Engineering Team to finalize the
	associated policies.</p>

      <p>Due to some debates around the political correctness of quotes
	added for the fortune(6) utility, the corresponding data file
	has been removed from the base system in -CURRENT.</p>

      <p>In light of the security incident, the liaison role between the
	Core Team and the Security Team has been restored, with Gavin
	Atkinson assuming this role.  The Core Team work hard on
	resolving the current situation of the binary package building
	cluster and the associated security problems in tight
	cooperation with the Ports Management Team, Cluster
	Administators, and the &os; Foundation Board.  The <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/news/2012-compromise.html">compromise page</a>
	is kept updated on the results.</p>

      <p>The &os; Project submitted an application for Google Summer of
	Code this year again.</p>

      <p>There was access granted for 2 new committers and 1 commit bit
	was taken for safekeeping in this quarter.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Port Managers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Port</given>
	  <common>Management Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en/articles/contributing-ports/"/>
      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/"/>
      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/portmgr/"/>
      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/"/>
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree contains approximately 24,300 ports, while the
	PR count still is close to 1600.</p>

      <p>In the first quarter we added 4 new committers, took in 1
	commit bit for safe keeping, and re-instated 1 commit bit.</p>

      <p>In February, Mark Linimon (linimon) stepped down from his
	duties in the team.  Mark had been the second longest serving member of
	the team.  Mark had spent many long hours refactoring and
	documenting the portbuild software to ensure that pointyhat
	services could be restored.</p>

      <p>After a security review, redports.org was turned back on,
	restoring Tinderbox services to contributors, along with post
	commit QATs.  In addition, pointyhat infrastructure had also
	undergone a review and work begain on restoring the package
	build system.</p>

      <p>Erwin Lansing (erwin) and Martin Wilke (miwi) took on the
	principle roles of getting the portbuild software installed and
	running on pointyhat.  As a result of all their hard work,
	portmgr@ was finally able to resume doing -exp runs, preparing
	packages for the upcoming 8.4 release, as well as getting a set
	of 9.1 packages retroactively prepared.</p>

      <p>After many long years of being the defacto standard for the
	Project, CVS support for the ports tree officially ended on
	February 28.</p>

      <p>The ports tree was tagged with <tt>RELEASE_7_EOL</tt>, to
	coincide with the end of life for &os;&nbsp;7.X.</p>

      <p>Beat Gaetzi (beat) stepped down from his duties on portmgr@ in
	March.  Among his notable contributions was the task of migrating
	the Ports Tree from the old CVS repo to Subversion.</p>

      <p>Bryan Drewery (bdrewery) joined the Ports Management team in
	March, bringing with him his wealth of knowledge and skill from
	maintaining portupgrade, portmaster, assisting with pkgng, as
	well as co-developing poudriere.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Most ports PRs are assigned, we now need to focus on
	testing, committing and closing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; Japanese Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hiroki</given>
	  <common>Sato</common>
	</name>
	<email>hrs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ryusuke</given>
	  <common>Suzuki</common>
	</name>
	<email>ryusuke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ja/">Japanese &os; Web Page</url>
      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/doc-jp/">The &os; Japanese Documentation Project Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Web page (<tt>htdocs</tt>): Newsflash and some other updates in
	the English version have been translated to keep them up-to-date.
	Specifically, the release related contents were updated in this
	period.</p>

      <p>Books: &os; Handbook has constantly been updated since the last
	report; particularly, "ports", "desktop" section were largely
	updated.  Some progress has been made in the
	"advanced-networking" section, contributed by a new
	translator.</p>

      <p><q>Writing &os; Problem Reports</q> article is now in sync with
	the English version.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Further translation work of outdated documents in
	ja_JP.eucJP subtree.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Cubieboard</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ganbold</given>
	  <common>Tsagaankhuu</common>
	</name>
	<email>ganbold@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>Initial support of Allwinner A10 SoC is committed to -CURRENT.
	&os; is now running on boards such as Cubieboard, Hackberry and
	it supports following peripherals:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>USB EHCI</li>
	<li>GPIO</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Get EMAC Ethernet driver working.  Need more help from
	network driver experts.</task>
      <task>Implement more drivers.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Multipath TCP (MPTCP) for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nigel</given>
	  <common>Williams</common>
	</name>
	<email>njwilliams@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Lawrence</given>
	  <common>Stewart</common>
	</name>
	<email>lastewart@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/mptcp/tools.html"/>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/newtcp/mptcp/"/>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/reports/130424A/CAIA-TR-130424A.pdf"/>
      <url href="https://pub.allbsd.org/FreeBSD-snapshots/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We have been working to create a BSD-licensed implementation of
	Multipath TCP &mdash; a set of TCP extensions that allow for
	transparent multipath operation with multiple IP addresses as
	specified in experimental RFC6824.</p>

      <p>We made our first v0.1 public release on 2013-03-11 and
	recently released v0.3 on 2013-04-16.  The code is currently
	considered to be of alpha quality.  We are working towards
	pushing the code into a &os; Subversion repository project
	branch to continue the on-going development effort in a more
	publicly accessible location.  As part of this move, we hope to
	begin releasing regular snapshot installer ISOs of the MPTCP
	project branch courtesy of Hiroki Sato and the allbsd.org daily
	snapshot infrastructure.</p>

      <p>We are about to release a CAIA technical report 130424A
	entitled <q>Design Overview of Multipath TCP version 0.3 for
	&os;&nbsp;10</q> on 2013-04-24 which provides a high-level
	design and architecture overview of the v0.3 code release.</p>

      <p>Going forward, we expect to continue development and release
	additional technical reports and academic papers covering topics
	such as performance analysis and multipath congestion
	control/scheduling.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The code is currently of alpha quality so we welcome all
	testing feedback, but please familiarize yourself with the README
	file and "Known Limitations" section in particular before
	jumping in.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>TCP-AO Authentication Option</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andr&eacute;</given>
	  <common>Oppermann</common>
	</name>
	<email>andre@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/user/andre/tcp-ao/">SVN branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work is under way to implement TCP-AO (TCP Authentication
	Option) according to RFC5925 and RFC5926.  TCP-AO is an
	extension to TCP-MD5 signatures commonly used in routers to
	secure BGP routing protocol sessions against spoofing attacks.
	The work is under contract and sponsored by Juniper
	Networks.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Atomic "close-on-exec"</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jilles</given>
	  <common>Tjoelker</common>
	</name>
	<email>jilles@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/AtomicCloseOnExec"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>If threads or signal handlers call <tt>fork()</tt> and
	<tt>exec()</tt>, file descriptors may be passed undesirably to
	child processes, which may lead to hangs (if a pipe is not
	closed), exceeding the file descriptor limit and security
	problems (if the child process has lower privilege).  One
	solution is various new APIs that set the <q>close-on-exec</q>
	flag atomically with allocating a file descriptor.  Some
	existing software will use the new features if present or will
	even refuse to compile without them.</p>

      <p>Various parts have been present for some time.</p>

      <p>In first quarter of 2013, extensions to <tt>recvmsg()</tt>,
	<tt>socket()</tt>, <tt>socketpair()</tt> and
	<tt>posix_openpt()</tt> have been added.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BXR.SU &mdash; Super User's BSD Cross Reference</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Constantine A.</given>
	  <common>Murenin</common>
	</name>
	<email>cnst++@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://bxr.su/">BXR.SU &mdash; Super User's BSD Cross Reference</url>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-hackers/2013-April/042334.html"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Super User's BSD Cross Reference (BXR.SU) is a new source-code
	search engine that covers the complete kernel and non-GNU
	userland source trees of &os;, NetBSD, OpenBSD, and DragonFly
	BSD.</p>

      <p>BXR.SU is optimised to be very fast, has daily updates of all
	the trees, and also acts as a deterministic URL shortener.</p>

      <p>BXR.SU is based on an OpenGrok fork, but it is more than just
	OpenGrok.  We have fixed a number of annoyances, eliminated
	features that just never worked right from the outright, and
	provided integration with tools like CVSweb (including great
	mirrors like allbsd.org), &os;'s ViewVC (SVN), as well as GitHub
	and Gitweb from <tt>git.freebsd.your.org</tt>, plus a tad of
	other improvements, including a complete rewrite of an mdoc
	parser.  Last, but definitely not least, is an extensive set of
	nginx rewrite rules that makes it a breeze to use BXR.SU as a
	deterministic URL compactor for referencing BSD source code.
	For example, the <tt>http://bxr.su/f/kern/sched_ule.c</tt> URL
	will automatically redirect to
	<tt>http://bxr.su/FreeBSD/sys/kern/sched_ule.c</tt> through
	nginx.</p>

      <p>Note that according to the release schedule of BXR.SU, there is
	no IPv4 glue until 2013-04-24; otherwise, the service is available
	via both IPv4 and IPv6.  See the 2013-04-01 announcement on the
	freebsd-hackers mailing list for more details.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Find up-to-date git repositories (served with Gitweb) of
	NetBSD and OpenBSD.</task>
      <task>Find a Gitweb mirror of &os; that is faster than GitHub and
	Gitorious.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Postmaster Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Wolfskill</common>
	</name>
	<email>postmaster@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>In the first quarter of 2013, the &os; Postmaster Team has
	implemented the following items that may be interest of the
	general public:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Changes in configuration of Mailman-managed lists: allow to
	  accept the <tt>application/pkcs7-signature</tt> MIME type (in
	  addition to the <tt>application/x-pkcs7-signature</tt> MIME
	  type), thus permitting S/MIME signatures on list mail.</li>

	<li>New lists: <tt>freebsd-ops-announce</tt> &mdash;
	  announcements of infrastructure issues, and <tt>freebsd-pkg</tt>
	  &mdash; discussion of binary package management and package
	  tools.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Bugmeister Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Eitan</given>
	  <common>Adler</common>
	</name>
	<email>eadler@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

  <links/>

  <body>
    <p>The &os; Bugmeister Team are continuing to evaluate options for
	alternate bug trackers and have narrowed their choices to two
	possibilities: Bugzilla and roundup.</p>

    <p>The number of non-ports PRs have remained relatively static over
	the last three months, with as many coming in as being closed.
	The number of ports PRs have increased recently, largely due to
	the ports freeze for the upcoming 8.4-RELEASE.</p>

    <p>The Bugmeister team continue work on trying to make the contents
	of the GNATS PR database cleaner, more accessible and easier for
	committers to find and resolve PRs, by tagging PRs to indicate
	the areas involved, and by ensuring that there is sufficient
	info within each PR to resolve each issue.</p>

    <p>As always, anybody interested in helping out with the PR queue is
	welcome to join us in <tt>#freebsd-bugbusters</tt> on EFnet.  We
	are always looking for additional help, whether your interests
	lie in triaging incoming PRs, generating patches to resolve
	existing problems, or simply helping with the database
	housekeeping (identifying duplicate PRs, ones that have already
	been resolved, etc).  This is a great way of getting more
	involved with &os;!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finalize the decision of which new bug tracker to
	use.</task>

      <task>Get more users involved with triaging PRs as they come
	in.</task>

      <task>Assist committers with closing PRs.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>callout(9) Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Davide</given>
	  <common>Italiano</common>
	</name>
	<email>davide@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~davide/asia/callout_paper.pdf"/>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~davide/asia/calloutng.pdf"/>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=247777"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In &os;, timers are provided by the callout facility, which
	allows to register a function with an argument to be called at
	specified future time.  The subsystem suffered of some problems,
	such as the impossibility of handling high-resolution events or
	its inherent periodic structure, which may lead to spurious
	wakeups and higher power consumption.  Some consumers, such as
	high-speed networking, VoIP and other real-time applications
	need a better precision than the one currently allowed.  Also,
	especially with the ubiquity of laptops in the last years, the
	energy wasted by interrupts waking CPUs from sleep may be a
	sensitive factor.  Recent changes in the subsystem addressed
	those long-standing issues as well as introduced a new
	programming interface to take advantage of the new features.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Evaluating if it is worthwhile to migrate any of the other
	callout(9) consumers to the new interface.</task>
      <task>Move callout consumers still using the legacy
	timeout()/untimeout() interface to callout_*() in order to get
	rid of redundant code and clean up KPI.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Haskell Ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>P&aacute;li</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ashish</given>
	  <common>Shukla</common>
	</name>
	<email>ashish@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/Haskell">&os; Haskell wiki page</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd-haskell/freebsd-haskell/">&os; Haskell ports repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are proud to announce &os; Haskell Team has updated existing
	ports to their latest stable versions.  We also added number of
	new ports, which brings the count of Haskell ports in &os; ports
	tree to more than 400, featuring many popular software, e.g.
	<tt>xmonad</tt>, <tt>git-annex</tt>, <tt>pandoc</tt> or various
	web framework implementations.  All of these updates will be
	available as part of the upcoming 8.4-RELEASE.  We also came to
	know that Haskell ports are also being used successfully on
	DragonFlyBSD's dports tree.</p>

      <p>In our development repository, there was some optional support
	added for LLVM-based code generation using the GHC LLVM backend.
	This works mostly on &os; too, though some of the ports would
	need fixing so it is still considered experimental.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Try to build GHC with clang (as system compiler).</task>
      <task>Commit pending Haskell ports to the &os; ports tree.</task>
      <task>Add more ports to the Ports Collection.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeNAS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alfred</given>
	  <common>Perlstein</common>
	</name>
	<email>alfred@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Josh</given>
	  <common>Paetzel</common>
	</name>
	<email>jpaetzel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeNAS.org/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>FreeNAS 8.3.1-RELEASE-p2 will hit Sourceforge the second week
	of April, and should end up as the last FreeNAS release based on
	&os;&nbsp;8.X.  It is currently the only Free Open Source NAS
	product available with any form of ZFS encryption (provided by
	GELI).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The team is hard at work on getting a &os;&nbsp;9.X-based
	release of FreeNAS ready.  Currently there are several nightly
	snapshots available.</task>

      <task>Add HAST to the webinterface.</task>

      <task>Migrate to NFSv4.</task>

      <task>Integrate foundation sponsored kernel iSCSI target.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>Improving the Documentation Project Infrastructre</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
	</name>
	<email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/doc/projects/xml-tools/">The xml-tools branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There is an on-going work to improve the documentation
	infrastructure and modernize our documentation toolchain.  The
	work can be found in the <tt>xml-tools</tt> branch and is very
	near to completion.  The improvements include the following:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Upgrade to DocBook 4.5.</li>
	<li>Use XSLT instead of DSSSL to render XHTML-based output.</li>
	<li>Generate PDF from PS and simplify image processing.</li>
	<li>Fix <tt>make lint</tt> and validate the whole documentation
	  set.</li>
	<li>Fix rendering of TOC elements.</li>
	<li>Fix misused link elements that resulted in a corrupt
	  rendering.</li>
	<li>Use more human-friendly publication data and release info
	  rendering.</li>
	<li>Add support for XInclude in DocBook documents.</li>
	<li>Add support for profiling with attributes.</li>
	<li>Add support for Schematron constraints.</li>
	<li>Add experimental epub support.</li>
	<li>Add experimental support for XSL-FO-based printed
	  output.</li>
	<li>Clean up obsolete SGML constructs.</li>
	<li>Clean up catalogs.</li>
	<li>Drop HTML Tidy since it is not needed any more.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The changes eliminate some dependencies and switch the doc
	repository to a real XML toolchain with proper validation and
	more advanced rendering tools.  The only exceptions are Jade and
	the DSSSL stylesheets, which are still needed for printed
	output.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix rendering problems with images in printed
	formats.</task>

      <task>Update the Documentation Primer to reflect changes.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>GNOME/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os; GNOME team</given>
	</name>
	<email>gnome@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/gnome/docs/develfaq.html"/>
      <url href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/viewvc/viewvc.cgi/marcuscom"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/jlmess77/mate-ports"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The GNOME/&os; Team has recently merged Glib 2.34, Gtk+ 2.24.17
	and Gtk+ 3.6.4 into ports, the C++ bindings also have got
	updates.  In additional "low-level" GNOME ports received
	updates, like libsoup, gobject-introspection, atk and vala for
	example.  The telepathy stack and empathy where also
	updated.</p>

      <p>The <tt>USE_GNOME</tt> macro has received support for
	<tt>:run</tt> and <tt>:build</tt> targets thanks to Jeremy
	Messenger (mezz).  Currently only libxml2 and libxslt support
	these targets.</p>

      <p><tt>USE_GNOME=pkgconfig</tt> is being deprecated in favor of
	<tt>USE_PKGCONFIG=build</tt>.  The former also adds a run
	dependency on pkg-config, which is not required.  A first pass
	was done to get rid of this in the Glib update to 2.34.  In
	cooperation with the X11 Team, the usage of
	<tt>USE_GNOME=pkgconfig</tt> in X components will be removed.
	After the fallout from this is handled and stragglers are
	converted, the <tt>USE_GNOME</tt> option will be removed.</p>

      <p>In addition <tt>USE_GNOME=gnomehack</tt> is deprecated and
	should not be used.  Please replace it with
	<tt>USES=pathfix</tt>.</p>

      <p>The GNOME development repository has switched from CVS to SVN.
	CVS will not get any more updates.  Uses can get a new version
	of the <a
	  href="http://marcuscom.com/downloads/marcusmerge">marcusmerge</a>
	script that supports SVN from its home page, and should remove
	the old CVS checkout "ports" dir.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>SVN anonymous root: <a href="svn://creme-brulee.marcuscom.com/">svn://creme-brulee.marcuscom.com/</a>
	  or <a href="svn://sushi.marcuscom.com/">svn://sushi.marcuscom.com/</a> (IPv6)</li>
	<li>ViewVC: <a href="http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/viewvc/viewvc.cgi/marcuscom">http://www.marcuscom.com:8080/viewvc/viewvc.cgi/marcuscom</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>Ongoing efforts:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>glib</tt> 2.36, <tt>pango</tt> 1.34.0, <tt>gtk</tt>
	  3.8.0 and <tt>gobject-introspection</tt> 1.36.0 where updated in
	  the GNOME development repository.</li>

	<li>Gustau Perez i Querol stepped up and started work on
	  updating the old GNOME 3.4 ports to 3.6.  At the moment of
	  writing these are not available in the GNOME development
	  repository just yet.  For his efforts, he was awarded a &os;
	  GNOME team membership.</li>

	<li>Jeremy Messenger (mezz) has completed Mate 1.6 which will be arriving in
	  ports near you when deemed stable enough.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>If you want to help with keeping the documentation updated or
	helping out in other ways, even if it only parts for the
	Glib/Gtk/GNOME stack you are interested in, please contact
	us!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update the FreeBSD.org/gnome website, in particular the
	developer information about USE_GNOME, maybe put that section in
	the Porter's Handbook instead.</task>

      <task>Merge more updated ports from MC to ports.</task>

      <task>Testing latest Glib/Gtk releases with existing ports, and import
	it into ports when it is ready.</task>

      <task>After porting GNOME 3.6 run tests and fix bugs.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	<given>KDE</given>
	<common>&os;</common>
	</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">KDE/&os; home page</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">area51</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE/&os; Team is very proud to have Schaich Alonso (aschai)
	joining the team.  Welcome!</p>

      <p>The KDE/&os; Team have continued to improve the experience of
	KDE software and Qt under &os;.  The latest round of improvements
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Fix problems establishing UDP connections.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The Team have also made many releases and upstreamed many fixes
	and patches.  The latest round of releases include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>KDE SC: 4.9.5, 4.10.1 (ports)</li>
	<li>Qt: 5.0.0 (area51) and 4.8.4 (ports)</li>
	<li>PyQt: 4.9.6 (ports); QScintilla 2.7 (ports); SIP: 4.14.2 (area51) and 4.14.3 (ports)</li>
	<li>KDevelop: 4.4.1 (ports); KDevPlatform: 1.4.1 (ports)</li>
	<li>Calligra: 2.5.5, 2.6.2 (ports)</li>
	<li>Amarok: 2.7.0</li>
	<li>CMake: 2.8.10.2</li>
	<li>Digikam (and KIPI-plugins): 3.1.0 (area51)</li>
	<li>QtCreator: 4.6.1 (ports)</li>
	<li>KDE Telepathy 0.6.0 (area51)</li>
	<li>many smaller ports</li>
      </ul>

      <p>As a result &mdash; according to PortScout &mdash; we have 431
	ports, of which 93.5% (from 91%) are up-to-date.</p>

      <p>The Team are always looking for more testers and porters so
	please contact us and visit our home page.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Updating out-of-date ports, see PortScout for a list.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>UFS/FFS Performance Work</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kirk</given>
	  <common>McKusick</common>
	</name>
	<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mckusick.com/publications/faster_fsck.pdf">Paper describing this work</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Some work on the performance of UFS/FFS has been recently
	committed to HEAD.  The purpose of the corresponding change to
	the FFS layout policy is to reduce the running time for a full
	file system check.  It also reduces the random access time for
	large files and speeds up the traversal time for directory tree
	walks.</p>

      <p>The key idea is to reserve a small area in each cylinder group
	immediately following the inode blocks for the use of metadata,
	specifically indirect blocks and directory contents.  The new
	policy is to preferentially place metadata in the metadata area
	and everything else in the blocks that follow the metadata
	area.</p>

      <p>The size of this area can be set when creating a filesystem
	using <tt>newfs(8)</tt> or changed in an existing filesystem using
	<tt>tunefs(8)</tt>.  Both utilities use the <tt>-k
	held-for-metadata-blocks</tt> option to specify the amount of
	space to be held for metadata blocks in each cylinder group.  By
	default, <tt>newfs(8)</tt> sets this area to half of minfree
	(typically 4% of the data area).</p>

      <p>As with all layout policies, it only affects layouts of things
	allocated after it is put in place.  So these changes will
	primarily be noticable on newly created file systems.</p>

      <p>File system checks have been sped up by caching the cylinder
	group maps in pass1 so that they do not need to be read again in
	pass5.  As this nearly doubles the memory requirement for
	<tt>fsck(8)</tt>, the cache is thrown away if other memory needs
	in <tt>fsck(8)</tt> would otherwise fail.  Thus, the memory
	footprint of <tt>fsck(8)</tt> remains unchanged in memory
	constrained environments.  This optimization will be evident on
	all UFS/FFS filesystems.</p>

      <p>This work was inspired by a <a
	  href="http://www.usenix.org/conference/fast13/ffsck-fast-file-system-checker">paper</a>
	presented at Usenix's FAST '13.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>MFC to 9-STABLE and possibly 8-STABLE should happen by May
	unless problems arise with these changes in HEAD.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Kernel Information in Process Core Dumps</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mikolaj</given>
	  <common>Golub</common>
	</name>
	<email>trociny@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>When doing postmortem analysis of a crashed process it is
	sometimes very useful to have kernel information about the process
	at the moment of the crash, like open file descriptors or resource
	limits.  For a live process this information can be obtained via
	<tt>sysctl(3)</tt> interface e.g. using <tt>procstat(1)</tt>.</p>

      <p>The aim of the project is to add additional notes to a process
	core dump, which include process information from the kernel at
	the moment of the process crash, teach <tt>libprocstat(3)</tt>
	to extract this information and make <tt>procstat(1)</tt> use
	this functionality.</p>

      <p>At the moment all necessary code changes are committed to HEAD
	and are going to be merge to stable/9 in 1 month.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/8.4R/schedule.html"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; 8.4-RC1 just got out the door and we are planning RC2.  A
	couple of critical fixes have come in that will be included in
	RC2.  The schedule has slipped about 10 days so far.  We are
	expecting the final release by the end of April.  Packages for 8.4
	have been provided by a fully operational package building
	cluster.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>AMD GPU Kernel Mode-Setting (KMS) Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jean-S&eacute;bastien</given>
	  <common>P&eacute;dron</common>
	</name>
	<email>dumbbell@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>J.R.</given>
	  <common>Oldroyd</common>
	</name>
	<email>jr@opal.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/AMD_GPU">Project status on the wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project progressed well since February:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Konstantin committed his TTM port to 10-CURRENT.</li>

	<li>With the help of John Baldwin (jhb) and Andriy Gapon (avg),
	  the Video BIOS situation greatly improved: the
	  <tt>radeonkms</tt> driver reads the BIOS shadow copy if the
	  video card is the primary one, or query the PCI expansion ROM
	  otherwise.  In the end, this code will be probably committed
	  to the PCI driver so that other video drivers benefit from
	  it.</li>

	<li>Andriy also reported several problems with the I2C code.
	  Now that they are fixed, the monitors plugged into DVI and
	  HDMI connectors are detected and their EDID is read correctly.
	  VGA connector is not tested so far.</li>

	<li>There is a locking problem in either TTM or the Radeon
	  driver which prevents OpenGL from working properly.
	  Jean-S&eacute;bastien is currently tracking this down.</li>

	<li>J.R. Oldroyd started to work on a 9-STABLE backport of the
	 driver which is now working quite well.  He had to backport
	 some features from the VM which may need further refinement by
	 the VM folks.</li>
      </ul>

      <p><a href="http://www.yakaz.com/">Yakaz</a> loaned
	Jean-S&eacute;bastien a computer which allows him to test a
	RV630-based discrete card and, in the future, other PCIe cards.
	Several users already kindly tested the driver.  Big thanks to
	all those contributors!</p>

      <p>In its current state, the driver allows a simple X
	session (no OpenGL), run common applications, watch movies,
	change the resolution and enable additional monitors with
	<tt>xrandr(1)</tt>.  The most blocking issue now is the OpenGL
	deadlock which prevents running modern compositors/desktop
	environment, games and WebGL demos.  We are not ready for a
	"Call For Testers" yet.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test multiple cards configurations for Video BIOS issues,
	especially Intel integrated card + Radeon discrete card, and AMD
	integrated card (IGP) + Radeon discrete card.  No need to check
	configurations with one shared connector though, it is not
	supported right now.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The <tt>entities</tt> Documentation Branch</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ren&eacute;</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>rene@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/doc/projects/entities/">Subversion repository link</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The entities branch was created to reduce duplication of
	committer entities.  Currently there is one in
	<tt>authors.ent</tt> (with email addresses) and another one in
	developers.ent (without email addresses).  This seems to be a
	leftover from the doc/www split in earlier times.  To remedy
	this, <tt>developers.ent</tt> is merged into
	<tt>authors.ent</tt> and entities with email addresses are
	postfixed as such.  Apart from the instructions for the initial
	commit, there should be little user-visible changes.  Some
	related cleanups, like cleaning up team definitions, replacing
	literal names by entities from <tt>authors.ent</tt>, and adding
	missing names to <tt>authors.ent</tt> are also made.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish processing of the &lt;email&gt; tag.</task>
      <task>Send out a CFT.</task>
      <task>Merge back into head branch.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/arm Superpages for ARMv7</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zbigniew</given>
	  <common>Bodek</common>
	</name>
	<email>zbb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grzegorz</given>
	  <common>Bernacki</common>
	</name>
	<email>gjb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafa&#322;</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://static.usenix.org/events/osdi02/tech/full_papers/navarro/navarro.pdf">Paper</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/ARMSuperpages">Wiki page</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/semihalf-bodek-zbigniew/freebsd-arm-superpages.git">Project's GitHub repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ARM architecture is more and more prevalent, not only in the
	mobile and embedded space.  Among the more interesting industry
	trends emerging in the recent months has been the "ARM server"
	concept.  Some top-tier companies have started developing systems
	like this already (Dell, HP).</p>

      <p>Key to &os; success in these new areas are sophisticated
	features, among them are superpages.</p>

      <p>The objective of this project is to provide &os;/arm with the
	superpages support, which will allow for efficient use of TLB
	translations (enlarge TLB coverage), leading to improved
	performance in many applications and scalability.  Indicated
	functionality is intended to work on ARMv7-based processors,
	however compatibility with ARMv6 will be preserved.</p>

      <p>Current support status:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Port of the pv_entry allocator.</li>
	<li>Switch to "AP[2:1]" access permissions model.</li>
	<li>PTE-based, page-referenced/modified emulation.</li>
	<li>Fixes regarding page replacement strategy.</li>
	<li>Code optimizations and bug fixes.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Next steps:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Dirty pages management.</li>
	<li>Gradual integration to &os; -CURRENT.</li>
	<li>Further pmap optimizations.</li>
	<li>Fragmentation control management.</li>
	<li>Testing and benchmarking.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Support for multiple page sizes.</task>
      <task>Implementation of page promotion, demotion and eviction
	mechanisms.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>xorg on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; X11 Team</name>
	<email>x11@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Niclas</given>
	  <common>Zeising</common>
	</name>
	<email>zeising@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Koop</given>
	  <common>Mast</common>
	</name>
	<email>kwm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/Xorg"/>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~zeising/xorg-7.7.diff"/>
      <url href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/ports/browser/trunk"/>
      <url href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/ports/browser/branches/xorg-7.7"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Most of the work during this period has been in updating,
	testing and stabilizing the development repository.  A number of
	xorg applications and various other leaf ports has been
	committed as part of this effort.  After this a CFT was sent out
	asking for help in testing the remaining bits in development,
	including updates to all major libraries and xorg-server.</p>

      <p>Currently, the CFT patch has been submitted for an exp-run to
	iron out any final bugs.  The plan is to merge it sometime after
	FreeBSD 8.4 is released and the ports tree is reopened for
	commits.</p>

      <p>Work is also ongoing to port new versions of MESA and OpenGL,
	as well as a new version of xorg-server, and perhaps in the
	future, Wayland.  These are considered more long-term goals and
	are not targeted for the current update.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Decide how to handle the new and old xorg distributions.  In
	recent xorg, a lot of legacy driver support has been dropped,
	therefore we need to maintain two xorg distributions to not
	lose a lot of hardware drivers.  Currently, this is done by
	setting the flag WITH_NEW_XORG in /etc/make.conf, but a more
	practical solution is needed.  This is especially important
	since the flag is not very user-friendly, and since there
	currently will be no official packages for the new
	distribution.</task>

      <task>Continue to test and update xorg related ports.  There are
	new versions of xserver, as well as MESA and related OpenGL
	libraries which needs to be ported and eventually integrated
	into the ports tree.</task>

      <task>Port Wayland.  The future of graphical environments in open
	source operating systems seems to be Wayland.  This needs to be
	ported to &os; so that a wider audience can test it, and so that
	it eventually can be integrated into the ports tree, perhaps as
	a replacement for the current xorg.</task>

      <task>Look into replacements for HAL.  HAL is used for
	hot-plugging of devices, but it has been long abandoned by Linux.
	A replacement, perhaps built on top of devd would be nice to
	have.  This work should be coordinated with the &os; GNOME and
	KDE teams.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>racct: Block IO Accounting</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rudolf</given>
	  <common>Tomori</common>
	</name>
	<email>rudot@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/RudolfTomori/IOLimits"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project adds the block IO access accounting to the
	racct/rctl resource limiting framework; a working prototype
	implementation is available.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/ARM Toolchain Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Turner</common>
	</name>
	<email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>Clang has been made the default compiler on ARM.  A number of
	issues with LLVM and clang have been found, reported, and fixed
	upstream.</p>

      <p>An issue where some ARM EABI applications compiled with clang
	crash has been reported upstream with a patch and will be
	brought into the &os; tree when it is accepted.  The only other
	issue blocking moving to the ARM EABI is C++ exceptions fail to
	work correctly with shared objects.  This will need us to either
	import libunwind or implement the functions libgcc_s requires to
	find the correct unwind table.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix exception handling for EABI.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Native iSCSI Stack</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napiera&#322;a</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Native%20iSCSI%20target"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Focus of the project was extended to also include a new iSCSI
	initiator.  Compared to the old one, it is more reliable, much
	more user-friendly, and somewhat faster.  It uses exactly the
	same configuration file format as the old one to make migration
	easier.</p>

      <p>As for the target side, it was verified to work properly
	against major initiators (&os;, Linux, Solaris, Windows and VMWare
	ESX).</p>

      <p>This project is being sponsored by &os; Foundation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>RDMA support, for both the target and the initiator.</task>
      <task>Performance optimization.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Read-only Port of NetBSD's UDF File System</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Will</given>
	  <common>DeVries</common>
	</name>
	<email>william.devries@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/williamdevries/UDF">Github Repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An initial read-only port of NetBSD's UDF file system has been
	largely completed.  (The UDF file system is often used on CD, DVD
	and Blu-Ray discs.) This port provides a number of advantages
	over &os;'s current UDF implementation, which include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Support for version 2.60 of the UDF file system
	  specification.  &os;'s current implementation only partially
	  supports version 1.5 of the standard, which was released in
	  1997.  Since Windows and other systems support newer version
	  of this file system, our users are left without the ability to
	  read some media written by these systems.  In addition,
	  Blu-Ray discs are commonly written using version 2.50 or
	  2.60.</li>

	<li>The ability to override the owner and group for all the
	  files and directories on a UDF volume using mount options.</li>

	<li>The ability to set the owner and group for files and
	  directories that lack defined owner or group information using
	  mount options.  (The UDF specification allows for files and
	  directories without owners or groups.)</li>

	<li>The ability to override the mode for all directories and
	  files on a volume using mount options.</li>

	<li>Support for mounting previous versions of incrementally
	  recorded media, like CD-Rs.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Xfce/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Xfce Team</name>
	<email>xfce@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Xfce"/>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~olivierd/patches/midori-0.4.9_0.5.0.diff">Midori 0.5 patches</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Xfce &os; Team has updated many ports, especially:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>tumbler: 0.1.27 (add new option, COVER)</li>
	<li>Parole: 0.5.0</li>
	<li>xfdesktop: 4.10.2</li>
	<li>Midori: 0.4.9 (fully compatible with Vala 0.18), 0.5.0 is available
	  (see links)</li>
	<li>Orage: 4.8.4</li>
	<li>xfce4-terminal: 0.6.1 (renamed by upstream, previous name
	 was Terminal)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>This last application contains drop-down functionality: new
	window slides down from the top of the screen when key (we can
	define keyboard shortcut) is pressed.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Replace libxfce4gui (deprecated and not maintained by
	upstream) by libxfce4ui in order to enhance support panel plugins
	for Xfce >= 4.10.</task>

      <task>Work on Midori Gtk3 port.</task>

      <task>Fix gtk-xfce-engine with Gtk+ >=3.6.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Wine32 on &os;/amd64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Naylor</common>
	</name>
	<email>dbn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/i386-Wine">Wine32 on &os;/amd64 Project page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The i386-wine port (formally wine-fbsd64) has been added to the
	ports collection (as emulators/i386-wine-devel).  Although the
	port can only be compiled under a x86 32-bit system the
	resulting package can be installed on a x86 64-bit system and
	enable running of 32-bit Microsoft Windows programs.</p>

      <p>Packages for the port are in development and should be
	announced shortly on the freebsd-questions and freebsd-emulation
	mailing lists.</p>

      <p>There are some issues with Wine32 on &os;/amd64 &mdash;
	possibly related to <tt>FREEBSD32_COMPAT</tt>, or other general
	32/64-bit issues &mdash; that could do with some focus.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Port wine64 to &os;.</task>
      <task>Port WoW64 (wine32 and wine64 together) to &os;.</task>
      <task>Fix 32- and 64-bit issues (such as Intel graphics not
	accelerating).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>PyPy</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Naylor</common>
	</name>
	<email>dbn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PyPy">&os;-PyPy Project page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>PyPy has been successfully updated to 2.0-beta1 with 2.0-beta2
	finishing translating and other tests.  Many major changes were
	made to the PyPy port from the 2.0-beta1 release, these
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Reworking the build script.</li>
	<li>Optionally use <tt>pypy</tt> (when available) for self-translating.</li>
	<li>Refine memory checks.</li>
	<li>Fix the test target.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Although the port is in a healthy state, PyPy on &os; has some
	rough edges (see <tt>make test</tt> for examples of
	roughness).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix failed unit tests.</task>
      <task>Integrate PyPy into bsd.python.mk.</task>
      <task>See the project page for more items.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>mdoc.su &mdash; Short Manual Page URLs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Constantine A.</given>
	  <common>Murenin</common>
	</name>
	<email>cnst++@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://mdoc.su/">mdoc.su &mdash; Short Manual Page URLs for &os;, NetBSD, OpenBSD and DragonFly BSD</url>
      <url href="http://nginx.conf.mdoc.su/mdoc.su.nginx.conf">nginx.conf for mdoc.su</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/cnst/mdoc.su" />
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-doc/2013-February/021465.html"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><a href="http://mdoc.su/">mdoc.su</a> is a deterministic URL
	shortener for BSD manual pages, written entirely in
	<tt>nginx.conf</tt>.</p>

      <p>Since the original announcement, OS version support has been
	added (e.g. <tt>/f91/</tt> and <tt>/FreeBSD-9.1/</tt> etc.), as
	well as dynamic multi-flavour web-pages with multiple links
	(e.g. <tt>http://mdoc.su/f,d/ifnet.9</tt> and
	<tt>http://mdoc.su/-/mdoc</tt>), which even let you specify the
	versions too (e.g. <tt>http://mdoc.su/f91,n60,o52,d/mdoc</tt>).</p>

      <p>The source code for the whole site is available under a BSD
	licence.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fork it on GitHub (see links)!</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
