<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>January-March</month>

    <year>2017</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p><strong>This is a draft of the January&ndash;March 2017
      status report.  Please check back after it is finalized, and
      an announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
      list.</strong></p>

    <?ignore
    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between January and
      March 2017.  This is the first of four reports planned for
      2017.</p>

    <p>The first quarter of 2017 was another productive quarter for
      the &os; project and community. [...]</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from April
      to June 2017 is July 7, 2017.</p>
     ?>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>The &os; Dutch Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rene</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>rene@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Remko</given>
	  <common>Lodder</common>
	</name>
	<email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://www.FreeBSD.org/docproj/translations.html#dutch">The Dutch Translation Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work has started on an initial translation of the &os;
	Handbook to the Dutch language via the 'po' system.  While we
	have an (outdated) version of the Handbook available via the
	older XML files, we are now trying to get back into shape with
	the po file.</p>

      <p>Rene started working on 2 articles already and did some
	translation strings for the FDP-Primer, while Remko had started
	working on the Handbook.  If you think you can assist with that,
	please let Rene and Remko know on their email addresses so that
	we can start coordinating work.</p>

      <p>In addition, since we have a translation set already from the
	XML files, it would be interesting to see and know whether we
	can merge them easily into the po structure.  If you have ideas
	on that, contact us a.s.a.p.</p>

      <p>Part of this work is facilitated by Remko's employer:
	Snow&nbsp;B.V.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>Snow&nbsp;B.V.</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Identify a way to merge the current XML translations into
	the nl_NL.po files.</task>

      <task>Merge the translations into the .po files.</task>

      <task>Update the remaining/open items into the po files.</task>

      <task>Remove the old/outdated translation files from the main
	repo and use the po and book.xml files to generate the dutch
	handbook and other files.</task>

      <task>Identify whether we can also translate the htdocs pages
	via the po system.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; s390x attempt III</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern A.</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A long time ago, in the &os; 5 times, there was an initial
	port of &os; to s390 (32bit) and s390x (64bit)
	which booted past init on good days in an emulator.</p>

      <p>As an attempt to revive the s390x/systemz efforts I started
	to get &os; s390x to build with clang/llvm 3.90.
	At this time it is possible to build world and a GENERIC kernel
	skeleton (not doing anything yet) using external binutils.</p>

      <p>The primary idea of this initial work was to allow to
	incrementally add the neccessary architecture-specific code.
	Having the build framework done will allow third-party
	developers to simply type <tt>make</tt>, as they are willing
	to contribute to the port without having to know &os; build
	specifics.  After some cleanup and further updates to a more
	recent HEAD I am planning to push the current work to a public
	repo to allow collaboration.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Write a wiki page with per-architecture specific tasks
	that need to be done based on the current work and the experience
	from arm64 and riscv.</task>

      <task>Implement both the user space and kernel per-architecture
	gaps.</task>

      <task>Figure out a way to get access to IBM's zPDT or better
	emulators to ease implementation, testing, and debugging.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
