<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2012</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between July and
      September 2012. This is the third of the four reports planned for
      2012.</p>

    <p>Highlights from this quarter include successful participation in
      Google Summer of Code, major work in areas of the source and
      ports trees, and a Developer Summit attended by over 30
      developers.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! This report
      contains 12 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>&os; in Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>&os; on Altera FPGAs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brooks</given>
	  <common>Davis</common>
	</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/ctsrd/">
	CTSRD Project</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/ctsrd/cheri.html">
	CHERI</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the course of developing the <a
	  href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/ctsrd/cheri.html">
	    CHERI processor</a> as part of the <a
	  href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/ctsrd/">CTSRD
	    project</a> SRI International's Computer Science Laboratory and
	the University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory have developed
	support for a number of general purpose IP cores for Altera FPGAs
	including the Altera Triple Speed Ethernet (ATSE) MAC core, the
	Altera University Program SD Card core, and the Altera JTAG UART.
	We have also added support for general access to memory mapped
	devices on the Avalon bus via the avgen bus. We have implemented
	both nexus and flattened device tree (FDT) attachments for these
	devices.</p>

      <p>In addition to these softcore we have developed support for
	the Terasic multi-touch LCD and are working to provide support
	for the Terasic HDMI Transmitter Daughter Card. Both of these
	work with common development and/or reference boards for Altera
	FPGAs. They do require additional IP cores which we plan to
	release to the open source community in the near future.</p>

      <p>With exception of the ATSE and HDMI drivers we have merged all
	of these changes to &os;-CURRENT. We anticipate that these
	drivers will be useful for users who with to run &os; on either
	hard or soft core CPUs on Altera FPGAs.</p>

      <p>This work has been sponsored by DARPA, AFRL, and Google.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Native iSCSI Target</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napiera&#322;a</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the July-September time period, the Native iSCSI Target
	project was officially started under sponsorship from the &os;
	Foundation. Before the end of September I've written ctld(8), the
	userspace part of the target, responsible for handling
	configuration, accepting incoming connections, performing
	authentication and iSCSI parameter negotiation, and handing off
	connections to the kernel. For the time being, I've reused some
	parts of protocol-handling code from the istgt project; since
	ctld(8) only handles the Login phase, the code can be rewritten
	in a much simpler and shorter way in the future.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Parallel rc.d execution</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kuan-Chung</given>
	  <common>Chiu</common>
	</name>
	<email>buganini@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kilian</given>
	</name>
	<email>kklimek@uos.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/buganini/rcexecr" />
      <url href="https://github.com/kil/rcorder" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are two implementations to make rc.d execution parallel.
	Compared to Kil's rcorder, rcexecr brings more concurrence and
	provides more flexibility than older "early_late_divider"
	mechanism but require more invasive /etc patch. Both
	implementations have switch to toggle parallel execution. Further
	modification/integration needs more discussion.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Refine /etc/rc.d/* to eliminate unnecessary waiting.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Bugbusting Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Eitan</given>
	  <common>Adler</common>
	</name>
	<email>eadler@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleksandr</given>
	  <common>Tymoshenko</common>
	</name>
	<email>gonzo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/support.html#gnats" />
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/BugBusting" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In August, Eitan Adler (eadler@) and Oleksandr Tymoshenko
	(gonzo@) joined the Bugmeister team. At the same time, Remko
	Lodder and Volker Werth stepped down. We extend our thanks to
	Volker and Remko for their work in the past, and welcome
	Oleksandr and Eitan. Eitan and Oleksandr have been working hard
	on migrating from GNATS, and have made significant progress on
	evaluating new software, and creating scripts to export data
	from GNATS.</p>

      <p>The bugbusting team continue work on trying to make the
	contents of the GNATS PR database cleaner, more accessible and
	easier for committers to find and resolve PRs, by tagging PRs
	to indicate the areas involved, and by ensuring that there is
	sufficient info within each PR to resolve each issue.</p>

      <p>As always, anybody interested in helping out with the PR
	queue is welcome to join us in #freebsd-bugbusters on EFnet. We
	are always looking for additional help, whether your interests
	lie in triaging incoming PRs, generating patches to resolve
	existing problems, or simply helping with the database
	housekeeping (identifying duplicate PRs, ones that have already
	been resolved, etc). This is a great way of getting more
	involved with &os;!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Further research into tools suitable to replace
	GNATS.</task>

      <task>Get more users involved with triaging PRs as they come
	in.</task>

      <task>Assist committers with closing PRs.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Core Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Along with the change in the Core Team membership, several
	related roles changed hands. Gabor Pali assumed the role of core
	secretary from Gavin Atkinson, and David Chisnall replaced Robert
	Watson as liaison to the &os; Foundation. The Core Team felt
	there was no longer a need for a formal security team liaison, so
	that role was retired.</p>

      <p>In the third quarter, the Core Team granted access for 2 new
	committers and took 2 commit bits into safekeeping.</p>

      <p>The Core Team worked with the Port Management Team and Cluster
	Administrators to set a date to stop providing CVS exports for
	the ports repository, which is February 28, 2013. In the
	meantime, the CVS export for 9.1-RELEASE was restored.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/press/2012Jul-newsletter.shtml">
	Semi-annual newsletter</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Foundation hosted and sponsored the Cambridge &os;
	developer summit in August 2012.</p>

      <p>We were represented at the following conferences: OSCON July
	2012, Texas LinuxFest, and Ohio LinuxFest.</p>

      <p>We negotiated/supervised Foundation funded projects:
	Distributed Security Audit Logging, Capsicum Component
	Framework, Native iSCSI Target Scoping, and Growing UFS
	Filesystems Online.</p>

      <p>We negotiated, supervised, and funded hardware needs for
	&os; co-location centers.</p>

      <p>We welcomed Kirk McKusick to our board of directors. He took
	over the responsibility of managing our investments.</p>

      <p>We visited companies to discuss their &os; use and to help
	facilitate collaboration with the Project.</p>

      <p>We managed &os; vendor community mailing list and
	meetings.</p>

      <p>We created a high quality &os; 9 brochure to help promote
	&os;.</p>

      <p>Published our <a
	  href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/press/2012Jul-newsletter.shtml">
	    semi-annual newsletter</a> that highlighted Foundation
	  funded projects, travel grants for
	  developers, conferences sponsored and other ways the Foundation
	  supported the &os; Project.</p>

      <p>We hired a technical writer to help with &os;
	marketing/promotional material.</p>

      <p>We began work on redesigning our website.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>&os; on ARMv6/ARMv7</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>freebsd-arm mailing list</given>
	</name>
	<email>freebsd-arm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Support for ARMv6 and ARMv7 architecture has been merged from
	project branch to HEAD.  This code covers the following parts:
	<ul>
	  <li>General ARMv6/ARMv7 kernel bits (pmap, cache, assembler
	    routines, etc...)</li>
	  <li>ARM Generic Interrupt Controller driver</li>
	  <li>Improved thread-local storage for cpus &gt;=ARMv6</li>
	  <li>Driver for SMSC LAN95XX and LAN8710A ethernet controllers</li>
	  <li>Marvell MV78x60 support (multiuser, ARMADA XP kernel config)</li>
	  <li>TI OMAP4 and AM335x support (multiuser, no GPU or graphics
	    support, kernel configs for Pandaboard and Beaglebone)</li>
	  <li>LPC32x0 support (multiuser, frame buffer works with SSD1289
	    LCD controller.  Embedded Artists EA3250 kernel config)</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <p>This work was a result of a joint effort by many people,
	including but not limited to: Grzegorz Bernacki (gber@),
	Aleksander Dutkowski, Ben R. Gray (bgray@), Olivier Houchard
	(cognet@), Rafal Jaworowski (raj@) and Semihalf team, Tim
	Kientzle (kientzle@), Jakub Wojciech Klama (jceel@), Ian Lepore
	(ian@), Warner Losh (imp@), Damjan Marion (dmarion@), Lukasz
	Plachno, Stanislav Sedov (stas@), Mark Tinguely and Andrew
	Turner (andrew@).  Thanks to all, who contributed by
	submitting code, testing and giving valuable advice.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More hardware bring-ups and more drivers</task>

      <task>Finish SMP support</task>

      <task>VFP/NEON support</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; Japanese Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hiroki</given>
	  <common>Sato</common>
	</name>
	<email>hrs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ryusuke</given>
	  <common>Suzuki</common>
	</name>
	<email>ryusuke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ja/">Japanese &os; Web
	Page</url>

      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/doc-jp/">The &os; Japanese
	Documentation Project Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Web page (htdocs): Newsflash and some other updates in the
	English version were translated to keep them up-to-date.
	Especially "security incident on &os; infrastructure" was
	translated and published in a timely manner.</p>

      <p>&os; Handbook: Big update in the "advanced-networking". With
	this update, merging translation results from the handbook in the
	local repository of Japanese documentation project into the main
	repository was completed. This chapter is still outdated and
	needs more work. The other sections have also constantly been
	updated. Especially, new subsection "Using pkgng for Binary
	Package Management" was added to "ports" section and "Using
	subversion" subsection was added to "mirrors" section.</p>

      <p>Article: Some progress was made in "Writing &os; Problem
	Reports" and "Writing &os; Problem Reports" articles.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Further translation work of outdated documents in the 
	<tt>ja_JP.eucJP</tt> subtree.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>KDE</given>
	  <common>FreeBSD</common>
	</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">KDE/&os; home page</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">area51</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE/&os; team have continued to improve the experience of
	KDE software and Qt under &os;. The latest round of improvements
	include: 
	<ul>
	  <li>Fixes for building Qt with libc++ and C++11</li>

	  <li>Fixes for Solid-related crashes</li>

	  <li>Fix battery detection in battery monitor plasmoid</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <p>The team has also made many releases and upstreamed many fixes
	and patches. The latest round of releases include: 
	<ul>
	  <li>KDE SC: 4.9.1 (area51) and 4.8.4 (ports)</li>

	  <li>Qt: 4.8.3 (area51)</li>

	  <li>PyQt: 4.9.4 (area51); QScintilla 2.6.2 (area51); SIP:
	    4.13.3 (area51)</li>

	  <li>Calligra: 2.4.3, 2.5-RC2, 2.5.0. 2.5.1, 2.5.2 (area51) and
	    2.4.3, 2.5.0, 2.5.1 (ports)</li>

	  <li>Amarok: 2.6.0 (area51)</li>

	  <li>CMake: 2.8.9 (ports)</li>

	  <li>Digikam (and KIPI-plugins): 2.7.0, 2.8.0, 2.9.0 (area51)
	    and 2.7.0, 2.9.0 (ports)</li>

	  <li>QtCreator: 2.6.0-beta (area51)</li>

	  <li>many smaller ports</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <p>The team is always looking for more testers and porters so
	please contact us at kde@FreeBSD.org and visit our home page at 
	<a href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">http://FreeBSD.kde.org</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Please see 2012 Q4 Status Report</task>

      <task>Updating out-of-date ports, see 
	<a href="http://portscout.FreeBSD.org/kde@freebsd.org.html">PortScout</a>
	for a list</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Port</given>
	  <common>Management Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/" />

      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/index.html" />

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html" />

      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree approaches 24,000 ports, while the PR count
	still is above 1000.</p>

      <p>In Q3 we added 2 new committers and took in two commits bit
	for safe keeping.</p>

      <p>The Ports Management team had performed multiple -exp runs,
	verifying how base system updates may affect the ports tree,
	as well as providing QA runs for major ports updates.</p>

      <p>Beat Gaetzi took over the role of sending out fail mails, a
	role that Pav Lucistnik had previously held. Beat also undertook
	the task of converting the Ports tree from CVS to Subversion.</p>

      <p>Florent Thoumie stepped down from his role on portmgr, he was
	instrumental in maintaining the legacy pkg_* code.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Most ports PRs are assigned, we now need to focus on
	testing, committing and closing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>&os; Developer Summit, Cambridge, UK</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/201208DevSummit">Developer
	Summit Home Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the end of August, there was an "off-season" Developer
	Summit held in Cambridge, UK at the University of Cambridge
	Computer Laboratory. This was a three-day event, with a
	documentation summit scheduled for the day before.  The three
	days of the main event were split into three sessions, with two
	tracks in each.  Some of them even involved ARM developers from
	the neighborhoods which proven to be productive, and led to
	further engagement between the &os; community and ARM.</p>

      <p>The schedule was finalized on the first day, spawning a
	plethora of topics to discuss, followed by splitting into groups.
	A short summary from each of the groups was presented in the
	final session and then published at the event's home page on the
	&os; wiki. This summit contributed greatly to arriving to a
	tentative plan for throwing the switch to make clang the default
	compiler on HEAD. This was further discussed on the mailing list,
	and has now happened, bringing us one big step closer to a
	GPL-free &os; 10. As part of the program, an afternoon of short
	talks from researchers in the Cambridge Computer Laboratory
	involved either operating systems work in general or &os; in
	particular. Robert Watson showed off a tablet running &os; on a
	MIPS-compatible soft-core processor running on an Altera
	FPGA.</p>

      <p>In association with the event, a dinner was hosted by St. John's
	college and co-sponsored by Google and the &os; Foundation. The
	day after the conference, a trip was organized to Bletchley Park,
	which was celebrating Turing's centenary in 2012.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Google Summer of Code 2012</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>
	  </given>
	  <common>&os; Summer of Code Administrators</common>
	</name>
	<email>soc-admins@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/summerofcode.html">
	FreeBSD Summer of Code page</url>

      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2012">Summer of
	Code 2012 projects</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Over the Summer of 2012, &os; were once again granted a
	place to participate in the Google Summer of Code program. We
	received a total of 32 project proposals, and were ultimately
	given 15 slots for university students to work on open source
	projects mentored by existing &os; developers.</p>

      <p>We were able to accept a wide spread of proposals, covering
	both the base system and the ports infrastructure. We had
	students working on file systems, file integrity checking, and
	parallelization in the ports collection. Students worked on
	kernel infrastructure, including one project to support CPU
	resource limits on users, processes and jails, and one student
	improving the BSD callout(9) and timer facilities. Two students
	worked on the ARM platform, widely used in embedded systems and
	smart phones; one student worked on a significant cleanup and
	improvements to the Flattened Device Tree implementation code,
	while the other ported &os; to the OMAP3-based BeagleBoard-xM
	device. One student worked on improving IPv6 support in
	userland tools, whilst another worked on BIOS emulation for the
	BHyVE BSD-licensed hypervisor, new in &os; 10. Other students
	worked on EFI boot support, userland lock profiling and an
	automated kernel crash reporting system.</p>

      <p>Overall, a significant proportion of the code produced has
	or will be integrated into &os; in one form or another. All of
	the work is available in our Summer Of Code Subversion
	repository, and some of the work has already been merged back
	into the main repositories.</p>

      <p>&os; is once again grateful to Google for being selected to
	participate in Summer of Code 2012.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
