<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status
Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2006-06-2006-10.xml,v 1.6 2008/08/16 21:55:59 pgj Exp $ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2006</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers FreeBSD related projects between June and
    October 2006. This includes the conclusion of this year's Google
    Summer of Code with 13 successful students. Some of last year's and
    the current SoC participants have meanwhile joined the committer
    ranks, kept working on their projects, and improving FreeBSD in
    general.</p>

    <p>This year's 
    <a href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/">EuroBSDCon</a>

    in Milan, Italy has meanwhile published an exciting program. Many
    developers will be there to discuss these current and future projects
    at the Developer Summit prior the conference. Next year's
    conference calendar has a new entry - in addition to the now well
    established 
    <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/">BSDCan</a>

    in Ottawa - 
    <a href="http://www.asiabsdcon.org/">AsiaBSDCon</a>

    will take place in Tokyo at the beginning of March.</p>

    <p>As we are closing in on FreeBSD 6.2 release many bugs are being
    fixed and new features have been MFCed. On the other hand a lot of
    the projects below already are focusing on FreeBSD 7.0 and promise
    a lot of exciting news and features to come.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
    enjoy reading.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>FreeBSD Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>OpenBSD dhclient</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Most dhclient changes in HEAD have been merged to 6-STABLE for
      6.2-RELEASE. The highlight of these changes is a fix for runaway
      dhclient processes when packets are not 4 byte aligned. Further
      changes including always sending client identifiers are scheduled
      for merge before the release. Work is ongoing to improve dhclient's
      interaction with alternate methods of setting interface
      addresses.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>FreeBSD/arm on Atmel AT91RM9200</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

        <email>imp@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Olivier</given>

          <common>Houchard</common>
        </name>

        <email>cognet@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD/arm port has grown support for the Atmel AT91RM9200.
      Boards based on this machine are booting to multiuser off either
      NFS or an SD card. The onboard serial ports, PIO, ethernet and
      SD/MMC card controllers are well supported. Support for the SSC,
      IIC and SPI flash parts in the kernel will be forthcoming
      shortly.</p>

      <p>In addition to normal kernel support, the port includes a boot
      loader that can initialize memory and boot off IIC eeprom, SPI
      DataFlash, BOOTP/TFTP and SD memory cards.</p>

      <p>The port will be included in forthcoming commercial
      products.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Add support for other members of the AT91 family of arm9
      processors.</task>

      <task>Finish support for AT45D* flash parts.</task>

      <task>Finish support for USB ports</task>

      <task>Write support for USB Device functionality</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc' summary='t'>
    <title>Summer of Code Summary</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Murray</given>

          <common>Stokely</common>
        </name>

        <email>murray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/summerofcode-2006.html">
      FreeBSD Summer of Code 2006</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2006">SoC 2006
      Student wiki</url>

      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/soc2006/">
      SoC 2006 Perforce trees</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We had another successful summer taking part in the Google
      Summer of Code. By all accounts, the FreeBSD participation in this
      program was an unqualified success. We received over 150
      applications for student projects, amongst which 13 were selected
      for funding. All successful students received the full $4,500.</p>

      <p>These student projects included security research, improved
      installation tools, new utilities, and more. Many of the students
      have continued working on their FreeBSD projects even after the
      official close of the program. At least 2 of our FreeBSD mentors
      will be meeting with Google organizers in Mountain View this month
      to discuss the program at the Mentor Summit.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Release Engineering</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <common>Release Engineering Team</common>
        </name>

        <email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/snapshots/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Release Engineering team is currently working on
      FreeBSD 6.2-RELEASE, which is scheduled for release in early
      November 2006. Some notable features of this release include the
      debut of security event auditing as an experimental feature, Xbox
      support, the FreeBSD Update binary updating utility, and of course
      many fixes and updates for existing programs. Pre-release images
      for all Tier-1 architectures are available for testing now;
      feedback on these builds is greatly appreciated. More information
      about release engineering activities can be found at the links
      above.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>IPv6 Stack Vulnerabilities</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Clement</given>

          <common>Lecigne</common>
        </name>

        <email>clem1@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/ClementLecigne">SoC Student
      Wiki</url>

      <url href="http://pcs.sf.net">PCS Library</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The focus of this project was to review past vulnerabilities,
      create vulnerability testing tools and to discover new
      vulnerabilities in the FreeBSD IPv6 stack which is derived from the
      KAME project code. During the summer Clement took two libraries,
      the popular libnet, and his mentor's Packet Construction Set (PCS)
      and created tools to find security problems in the IPv6 code.
      Several issues were found, bugs filed, and patches created. At the
      moment Clement and George are editing a 50 page paper that
      describes the project which will be submitted for conference
      publication.</p>

      <p>All of the code from the project, including the tools, is
      online and is described in the paper.</p>

      <p>By all measures, this was a successful project. Both student and
      mentor gained valuable insight into a previously externally
      maintained set of code. In addition to the new tools development in
      this effort, the FreeBSD Project has gained a new developer to help
      work on the code.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Analyze and Improve the Interrupt Handling
    Infrastructure</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Paolo</given>

          <common>Pisati</common>
        </name>

        <email>pisati@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>

          <common>Baldwin</common>
        </name>

        <email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/Interrupts">SoC Student
      Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project consisted in the improvement of the Interrupt
      Handling System in FreeBSD: while retaining backward compatibility
      with the previous models (FAST and ITHREAD), a new method called
      'Interrupt filtering' was added. With interrupt filtering, the
      interrupt handler is divided into 2 parts: the filter (that checks
      if the actual interrupt belong to this device) and the ithread
      (that is scheduled in case some blocking work has to be done). The
      main benefits of interrupt filtering are:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Feedback from filters (the system finally knows if any
        handler has serviced an interrupt or not, and can react
        consequently).</li>

        <li>Lower latency/overhead for shared interrupt line.</li>

        <li>Previous experiments with interrupt filtering showed an
        increase in performance against the plain ithread model</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Moreover, during the development of interrupt filtering, some MD
      dependent code was converted into MI code, PPC was fixed to support
      multiple FAST handlers per line and an interrupt stray storm
      detection logic was added. While the framework is done, there are
      still machine dependent bits to be written (the support for ppc,
      sparc64, arm and itanium has to be written/reviewed) and a serious
      analysis of the performance of this model against the previous one
      is a work-in-progress</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Jail Resource Limits</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Chris</given>

          <common>Jones</common>
        </name>

        <email>cdjones@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kip</given>

          <common>Macy</common>
        </name>

        <email>kmacy@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/JailResourceLimits">SoC
      Student Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We now have support for limiting CPU and memory use in jails.
      This allows fairer sharing of a systems' resources between divergent
      uses by preventing one jail from monopolizing the available memory
      and CPU time, if other users and jails have processes to run.</p>

      <p>The code is currently available as patches against RELENG_6, and
      Chris is in the process of applying it to -CURRENT. More details
      can be found at JailResourceLimits on the wiki.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Port patches against -CURRENT.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Bundled PXE Installer</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Markus</given>

          <common>Boelter</common>
        </name>

        <email>m@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Paul</given>

          <common>Saab</common>
        </name>

        <email>ps@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/MarkusBoelter">SoC Student
      Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>For me, the Google Summer of Code was a new and very exciting
      experience. I got actively involved in doing Open Source Software
      and giving something back to the community. Facing some
      challenges within the project forced me to look behind the scenery
      of FreeBSD. The result was a better understanding of the overall
      project. Working with a lot of developers directly also
      gave a very special spirit to the Google Summer of Code.</p>

      <p>I really enjoyed the time and will continue to work on the
      project after the deadline. For me, it was a great chance to get
      involved in active development and not just some scripts and hacks
      at home. Getting paid for the work was just a small part of the
      overall feeling.</p>

      <p>Thanks to the people at the FreeBSD Project and Google for the
      really, really great time!</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Nss-LDAP importing and nsswitch subsystem improvement</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Michael</given>

          <common>Bushkov</common>
        </name>

        <email>bushman@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hajimu</given>

          <common>UMEMOTO</common>
        </name>

        <email>ume@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/MichaelBushkov">SoC Student
      Wiki</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/LdapCachedOriginalProposal">
      Original Project Proposal</url>

      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/LdapCachedDetailedDescription">
      Detailed Description of the Completed Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Project consisted of five parts:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Nsswitch modules and libc separation. The idea was to move
        the source code for different nsswitch sources (such as "files",
        "dns", "nis") out of the libc into the separate shared libraries.
        This task was successfully finished and the patch is
        available.</li>

        <li>Regression tests for nsswitch. A set of regression tests to
        test the correctness of all nsswitch-related functions and the
        invariance of their behavior between system upgrades. The task
        can be considered successfully completed, the patch is
        available.</li>

        <li>Rewriting nss_ldap. Though, this task was not clearly
        mentioned in the original proposal, during the SoC we found
        it would be easier, not to simply import PADL's nss_ldap, but
	to rewrite it from scratch (licensing issues were among the
	basic reasons for this). The resulting module behaves similarly
	to PADL's module, but has a different architecture that is more
	flexible.  Though it's basically finished, several useful
	features from the PADL's nss_ldap still need to be implemented.
	Despite the lack of some features, this task can be considered
	successfully completed. Missing features will be implemented as
	soon as possible, hopefully during September.</li>

        <li>Importing nss_ldap into the Base System. The task was to
        prepare a patch, that will allow users to use nss_ldap from the
        base system. The task was successfully completed (the patch is
        available), but required importing OpenLDAP into the base in
        order for nss_ldap to work properly, and it had led to a long
        discussion in the mailing list. This discussion, however, have
        concluded with mostly positive opinions about nss_ldap and
        OpenLDAP importing.</li>

        <li>Cached performance optimization. The caching daemon
        performance needs to be as high as possible in order for cached
        to be as close (in terms of speed) to "files" nsswitch source as
        possible. Cached's performance analysis was made and nsswitch
        database pre-caching was introduced as the optimization. This
        task was completed (the patch is available). However there is
        room for improvement. More precise and extensive performance
        analysis should be made and more optimizations need to be
        introduces. This will be done in the near future.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>Though none of the code was committed yet into the official
      FreeBSD tree, my experience from the previous year makes me think
      that this situation is normal. I hope, that the code will be
      reviewed and committed in the coming months.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Porting the seref policy and setools to SEBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dongmei</given>

          <common>Liu</common>
        </name>

        <email>dongmei@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Christian</given>

          <common>Peron</common>
        </name>

        <email>csjp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/DongmeiLiu">SoC Student
      Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Dongmei Liu spent the summer working on the basic footwork
      required to port the SEREF policy to SEBSD. This work has been
      submitted and can be viewed in the soc2006/dongmei_sebsd Perforce
      branch. This work was originated from the SEBSD branch:
      //depot/projects/trustedbsd/sebsd. Additionally setools-2.3 was
      ported from Linux and can be found in contrib/sebsd/setools
      directory. It is hoped that this work will be merged into the main
      SEBSD development branch.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>SCTP Integration</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Randall</given>

          <common>Stewart</common>
        </name>

        <email>randall@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.sctp.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There are currently patches available for testing. A planned
      integration to HEAD is set to happen in October.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The code still needs plenty of testing. See patches on 
      <a href="http://www.sctp.org/">sctp.org</a>

      and in -CURRENT soon.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Embedded FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.embeddedfreebsd.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Moved the HTML pages into the project CVS tree.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Setup the web site to be served from projects CVS so that it
      can be updated by others.</task>

      <task>Complete the ARM port.</task>

      <task>Work on the MIPS port.</task>

      <task>Update the documentation to include common tasks for embedded
      engineers.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>FAST_IPSEC Upgrade</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bjoern</given>

          <common>Zeeb</common>
        </name>

        <email>bz@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="www.freebsd.org/~gnn/fast_ipv6.patch">CURRENT patch to
      enable FAST_IPSEC and IPv6</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>First working version of code. Does not pass all TAHI tests, but
      does pass packets correctly and does not panic.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More testing of the patch needed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>USB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hans Petter</given>

          <common>Sirevaag Selasky</common>
        </name>

        <email>hselasky@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
      Current USB files</url>

      <url href="http://www.turbocat.net/~hselasky/usb4bsd">My USB
      homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the last three months I have finished reworking nearly
      all USB device drivers found in FreeBSD-7-CURRENT. Only two USB
      drivers are left and that is ubser(4) and slhci. Some still use
      Giant, but most have been brought out of Giant. At the moment I am
      looking for testers that can test the various USB device drivers.
      Some have already been tested, and confirmed to work, while others
      have problems which need to be fixed. If you want to test, checkout
      the USB perforce tree or download the SVN version of the USB driver
      that is available on my homepage. At the moment the tarballs are a
      little out of date.</p>

      <p>Ideas and comments with regard to the new USB API are welcome
      at:
      
      <a href="mailto:freebsd-usb@freebsd.org">
      freebsd-usb@freebsd.org</a>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>iSCSI Initiator</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Damiel</given>

          <common>Braniss</common>
        </name>

        <email>danny@cs.huji.ac.il</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="ftp://ftp.cs.huji.ac.il/users/danny/freebsd/iscsi-17.5.tar.bz2 " />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This iSCSI initiator kernel module and its companion control
      program are still under development, but the main parts are
      working.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Network Disconnect Recovery.</task>

      <task>Sysctl Interface and Instrumentation.</task>

      <task>Rewrite the userland side of iscontrol.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>GJournal</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Pawel Jakub</given>

          <common>Dawidek</common>
        </name>

        <email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~pjd/patches/gjournal_20060930.patch">
      Patches against HEAD.</url>

      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~pjd/patches/gjournal6_20060930.patch">
      Patches against RELENG_6.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>GJournal seems to be finished. I fixed the last serious bug and
      it is now stable and reliable in our tests. I'm planning to commit
      it really soon now.</p>

      <p>The work was sponsored by home.pl</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>AsiaBSDCon 2007</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hiroki</given>

          <common>Sato</common>
        </name>

        <email>hrs@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <email>secretary@asiabsdcon.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.asiabsdcon.org/">Conference Web Site</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Web site is up and we're soliciting papers and presentations.
      Some tutorials are already scheduled. Email 
      <a href="mailto:secretary@asiabsdcon.org">
      secretary@asiabsdcon.org</a>

      if you have questions or submissions.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Send in more papers!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>Chinese (Simplified) Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Xin</given>

          <common>LI</common>
        </name>

        <email>delphij@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://cnsnap.cn.FreeBSD.org/zh_CN/">Latest snapshot for
      translated website</url>

      <url href="http://cnsnap.cn.FreeBSD.org/doc/zh_CN.GB2312/">Latest
      snapshot for translated documentation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
        <p>In the previous quarter we primarily focused on overall
        quality of the translation rather than just increasing the number
        of translations, and we have strived to make sure that these
        translated stuff are up-to-date with their English revisions.
        Also, we have merged the translated website into the central
        repository.</p>

        <p>In the next quarter we will focus on developing
        documentation that will help to attract more developers.</p>
      </p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Translate more development related documentation.</task>

      <task>Review more of the currently translated documentation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>EuroBSDCon 2006</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>EuroBSDCon Organizing Committee</given>

          <common>
          </common>
        </name>

        <email>info@eurobsdcon.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/">EuroBSDCon Home Page</url>

      <url href="http://www.eurobsdcon.org/register/">Registration
      Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>EuroBSDCon 2006 is taking place in Milan (Italy), from the 10th
      to the 12th of November.</p>

      <p>EuroBSDCon represents the biggest gathering for BSD developers
      from the old continent, as well as users and passionates from
      around the World. It is also a chance to share experiences,
      know-how, and cultures.</p>

      <p>The program is rich in talks about FreeBSD, with topics ranging
      from "How the FreeBSD ports collection works" to "Interrupt
      Filtering in FreeBSD". This means that both the novice and the
      hacker can enjoy the conference.</p>

      <p>Registration is open. The EuroBSDCon Organizing Committee hopes
      to see you in Milan.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>Hungarian translation of the webpages</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://gabor.t-hosting.hu/data/hu/">Snapshot</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since the last status report, there has been a lot of progress.
      I investigated a lot of charset issues and found out that HTML tidy
      breaks some entities when using iso-8859-2, so HTML tidy had to be
      disabled for Hungarian pages.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Translate 4 pages.</task>

      <task>Review, fix typos and improve the wording where
      necessary.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>FreeBSD Security Officer and Security Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Security</given>

          <common>Officer</common>
        </name>

        <email>security-officer@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Security</given>

          <common>Team</common>
        </name>

        <email>security-team@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/security/" />

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/administration.html#t-secteam" />

      <url href="http://vuxml.freebsd.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the time since the last status report, six security
      advisories have been issued concerning problems in the base system
      of FreeBSD; of these, five problems were in "contributed" code,
      while one was in code maintained within FreeBSD. The
      Vulnerabilities and Exposures Markup Language (VuXML) document has
      continued to be updated by the Security Team and Ports Committers
      documenting new vulnerabilities in the FreeBSD Ports Collection;
      since the last status report, 57 new entries have been added,
      bringing the total up to 814.</p>

      <p>The following FreeBSD releases are supported by the FreeBSD
      Security Team: FreeBSD 4.11, FreeBSD 5.3, FreeBSD 5.4, FreeBSD 5.5,
      FreeBSD 6.0, and FreeBSD 6.1. The respective End of Life dates of
      supported releases are listed on the web site; of particular note,
      FreeBSD 5.3 and FreeBSD 5.4 will cease to be supported at the end
      of October 2006, while FreeBSD 6.0 will cease to be supported at
      the end of November 2006 (or possibly a short time thereafter in
      order to allow time for upgrades to the upcoming FreeBSD 6.2).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Summer of FreeBSD security development</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Colin</given>

          <common>Percival</common>
        </name>

        <email>cperciva@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~cperciva/funding.html" />

      <url
      href="http://www.daemonology.net/freebsd-upgrade-6.0-to-6.1/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I spent the months of May through August working on improving
      Portsnap, FreeBSD Update, and devoting more time to my (continuing)
      role as Security Officer. FreeBSD Update is now part of the FreeBSD
      base system and is fully supported by the FreeBSD Security Team;
      updates are currently only being built for the i386 architecture,
      but AMD64 updates will become available soon.</p>

      <p>In an attempt to reduce the number of people running out of date
      (and unsupported) FreeBSD releases, I wrote an automatic binary
      upgrade script for upgrading systems from FreeBSD 6.0 to FreeBSD
      6.1; I will be releasing a new script for upgrading to FreeBSD
      6.2-(RC*|RELEASE) soon (possibly before this status report is
      published).</p>

      <p>Further improvements to Portsnap are still ongoing.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Porting ZFS to FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Pawel Jakub</given>

          <common>Dawidek</common>
        </name>

        <email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/pjd/zfs">
      Source code.</url>

      <url href="http://www.opensolaris.org/os/community/zfs/porting/">
      ZFS porting site.</url>

      <url
      href="http://docs.freebsd.org/cgi/mid.cgi?20060822104516.GB16033">
      ZFS port announce.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>My work is moving slowly forward. ZVOL is, I believe, fully
      functional (I recently fixed snapshots and clones on zvols), which
      means you can put UFS on top of RAID-Z volume, take a snapshot of
      the volume, clone it if needed, etc. Very cool. The hardest part is
      the ZPL layer, I'm still working on it. Most file system methods
      work, but probably need detailed review and many fixes. Most of the
      time these days I'm spending on implementing mmap(2) correctly. It
      works more or less in simple tests but fails under fsx program. On
      the other hand, 'fsx -RW' works very stable and reliable. Other
      test programs (those that don't use mmap(2)) also work quite well.
      There is still a lot of work to do, mostly in ZPL area, many
      clean-ups, etc. Some functionality (like ACLs) I haven't even tried
      to touch yet.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>TSO - TCP Segmentation Offload committed</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>

          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>

        <email>andre@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/cvs-src/2006-September/068524.html">
      TSO commit to tcp_output.c</url>

      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/cvs-src/2006-September/068610.html">
      TSO em(4) hardware support</url>

      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/cvs-src/2006-September/069493.html">
      Enhanced em(4) TSO hw setup for IPv6 and future protocols</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>TSO - TCP Segmentation Offload support has been committed to the
      network stack of FreeBSD-current in September 2006. With TSO, TCP
      can send data in the send socket buffer in bulk down to the network
      card which then does the splitting into MTU sized packets. On bulk
      high speed sending the performance is increased by 25% (normal
      writes) to 108% (sendfile). Jack Vogel and Prafulla Deuskar of
      Intel committed the driver changes for TSO hardware support of
      em(4) based network cards.</p>

      <p>These changes are scheduled to be backported to FreeBSD 6-STABLE
      shortly after FreeBSD 6.2-RELEASE is published to appear in
      upcoming FreeBSD 6.3 early next year.</p>

      <p>This work was sponsored by the TCP/IP Optimization Fundraiser
      2005.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Highly improved implementations of sendfile(2), sosend_*() and
    soreceive_stream()</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>

          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>

        <email>andre@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2006-September/065997.html">
      sendfile(2) patch with detailed performance figures</url>

      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2006-September/066199.html">
      sosend_*() patch with detailed performance figures</url>

      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~andre/sendfile+sosend+soreceive-20061006.diff">
      Combined sendfile(2), sosend_*() and soreceive_stream() patch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The addition of TSO (TCP Segmentation Offload) has highlighted
      some shortcomings in the sendfile(2) and sosend_*() kernel
      implementations.</p>

      <p>The current sendfile(2) code simply loops over the file, turns
      each 4K page into an mbuf and sends it off. This has the effect
      that TSO can only generate 2 packets per send instead of up to 44
      at its maximum of 64K. kern_sendfile() has been rewritten to work
      in two loops, the inner which turns as many pages into mbufs as it
      can -- up to the free send socket buffer space. The outer loop then
      drops the whole mbuf chain into the send socket buffer, calls
      tcp_output() on it and then waits until 50% of the socket buffer
      are free again to repeat the cycle. This way tcp_output() gets the
      full amount of data to work with and can issue up to 64K sends for
      TSO to chop up in the network adapter without using any CPU cycles.
      Thus it gets very efficient especially with the readahead the VM
      and I/O system do.</p>

      <p>Looking at the benchmarks we see some very nice improvements:
      181% faster with new sendfile vs. old sendfile (non-TSO), 570%
      faster with new sendfile vs. old sendfile (TSO).</p>

      <p>The current sosend_*() code uses a sosend_copyin() function that
      loops over the supplied struct uio and does interleaved mbuf
      allocations and uiomove() calls. m_getm() has been rewritten to be
      simpler and to allocate PAGE_SIZE sized jumbo mbuf clusters (4k on
      most architectures). m_uiotombuf() has been rewritten to use the
      new m_getm() to obtain all mbuf space in one go. It then loops over
      it and copies the data into the mbufs by using uiomove().
      sosend_dgram() and sosend_generic() have been changed to use
      m_uiotombuf() instead of sosend_copyin().</p>

      <p>Looking at the benchmarks we see some very nice improvements:
      290% faster with new sosend vs. old sosend (non-TSO), 280% faster
      with new sosend vs. old sosend (TSO).</p>

      <p>Newly written is a specific soreceive_stream() function for
      stream protocols (primarily TCP) that does only one socket buffer
      lock per socket read instead of one per data mbuf copied to
      userland. When doing netperf tests with WITNESS (full lock tracking
      and validation enabled) the receive performance increases from
      ~360Mbit/s to ~520Mbit/s. Without WITNESS I could not measure any
      statistically significant improvement on a otherwise unloaded
      machine. The reason is two-fold: 1) per packet we do a wakeup and
      readv() is pretty much as many times as packets come it, thus the
      general overhead dominates; 2) the packet input path has a pretty
      high overhead too. On heavily loaded machines which do a lot of
      high speed receives a performance increase should be
      measureable.</p>

      <p>The patches are scheduled to be committed to FreeBSD-current at
      end of October or early November 2006.</p>

      <p>This work was sponsored by the TCP/IP Optimization Fundraiser
      2005.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Porting Xen to FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jue</given>

          <common>Yuan</common>
        </name>

        <email>yuanjue@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.yuanjue.net/xen/howto.html">Step-by-step
      tutorial for installing and using FreeBSD as domU</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/YuanJue">Wiki page for this
      project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>As a participant of Google's Summer of Code 2006, I am focusing
      on porting 
      <a href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/Research/SRG/netos/xen/"
      target="_blank">Xen</a>

      to FreeBSD these months. The result of this summer's work include a
      domU kernel that could be used for installation, a
      <a href="http://www.yuanjue.net/xen/howto.html" target="_blank">
      guide</a>

      for getting started with FreeBSD on Xen, and some other trivial
      improvements. But there are still a lot of work needing to be done
      in this area, e.g, the long-expeted dom0 support. So I will
      continue my work here and try to keep up with the update of Xen
      itself.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>dom0 support is the most urgent</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Gvirstor</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/gvirstor">gvirstor home
      page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Gvirstor is a GEOM class providing virtual ("overcommit")
      storage devices larger than physical available storage, with
      possibility to add physical storage on-line when the need arises.
      Current status is that it's done and waiting commit to HEAD,
      scheduled for some time after 6.2 is released.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The project is in need of testing! If you have the equipment
      and time, please give it a try so possible bugs can be fixed before
      it goes into -CURRENT.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/ports/">The FreeBSD Ports
      Collection</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">
      Contributing to the FreeBSD Ports Collection</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~fenner/portsurvey/">FreeBSD
      ports unfetchable distfile survey (Bill Fenner's report)</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">The FreeBSD
      Ports Management Team</url>

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com/">marcuscom
      tinderbox</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports PRs surged (especially due to a large number of new
      port submissions), but with some hard work we have been able to get
      back down to around 900. We are rapidly approaching 16,000
      ports.</p>

      <p>Due to this acceleration in adding new ports, portmgr is now
      very concerned that we are outstripping the capacity of both the
      build infrastructure and our volunteers to keep up with build
      errors and port updates. Accordingly, we've added a guideline (not
      a rule) that ports should be of more than just theoretical use to
      be added to the Ports Collection (e.g. we can't support all of CPAN
      + all of Sourceforge + everything else). Basically, use common
      sense as a guideline; certainly no one wants to see any kind of
      "gateway" procedure to get incoming ports approved.</p>

      <p>Seven sets of changes have been added to the infrastructure,
      mostly refactoring and bugfixing.</p>

      <p>As part of a Summer of Code project, we have also incorporated
      some of gabor@'s changes to incorporate better DESTDIR support.
      However, due to some unanticipated side-effects, more work is going
      to be needed in this area. gabor@ is continuing to work on the
      changes.</p>

      <p>netchild@ and bsam@ have been doing a great deal of work to
      bring the linux emulator ports closer to sanity, including bringing
      up a regression-test suite.</p>

      <p>The long-anticipated import of X.Org 7 has stalled due to
      developer time, mostly to deal with documentation and upgrade
      instructions. Hopefully this can get done in the early 6.3
      development cycle. See the wiki for more information.</p>

      <p>As a part of that work, the decision has been made to move away
      from using X11BASE and just put everything into LOCALBASE;
      /usr/X11R6 is simply an artifact at this point. A plan for a
      transition process is underway; a great deal of testing will need
      to be done, but in the end the ports tree will be much cleaner. The
      GNOME team has already done the work to move all of their ports
      over, and it will be incorporated after the 6.2 release is
      shipped.</p>

      <p>tmclaugh@ is looking for someone to take over the C# ports. He
      has maintained them for over a year and wants more time to be able
      to work on other projects.</p>

      <p>Some work has been done to get rid of FreeBSD 2.X cruft in
      ports. Further work is needed to get the 3.X cruft removed.</p>

      <p>linimon@ did another pass through resetting inactive
      maintainers. Another list is waiting in the wings.</p>

      <p>linimon@ is also working on adding the ability for portsmon to
      analyze successful packages (not just failed ones), so that queries
      such as "show me packages that build on i386 but not amd64" and
      "show me why dependent package foo was not built on bar". This is
      currently in alpha testing.</p>

      <p>We have added 4 new committers since the last report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We still need help getting back to our modern low of 500
      PRs.</task>

      <task>We have nearly 4400 unmaintained ports (see, for instance, 
      <url
      href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/portsconcordanceformaintainer.py?maintainer=ports@FreeBSD.org">
      the list on portsmon</url>

      ). Although there has been a welcome upsurge in new maintainers
      recently which has dropped the percentage down below 28%, we still
      need much more help.</task>

      <task>A test run of gcc4.1 on the ports tree showed around 1000 new
      build errors. Kris@ has posted some results so that people can
      start working on the problems now. In particular, it seems that
      certain older versions of GCC cannot be built with GCC 4.1, so
      ports that depend on those older versions are going to have to be
      fixed as well. Although the import of GCC 4.1 to -CURRENT is not
      imminent, the time to start planning is now.</task>

      <task>The state of the packages on AMD64 and sparc64 significantly
      lags that of i386. In many of these cases, packages are not
      attempted because NOT_FOR_ARCH is used instead of more accurately
      only setting BROKEN based on ARCH. (pointyhat can be forced to
      build packages that are marked BROKEN, but not NOT_FOR_ARCH).
      NOT_FOR_ARCH is supposed to denote only "will never work on this
      ARCH". Although we have volunteers who have expressed interest in
      sparc64 (and ia64), we need more people who are running amd64
      (especially as a desktop) to help us get more packages
      working.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>CScout on the FreeBSD Source Code Base</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Diomidis</given>

          <common>Spinellis</common>
        </name>

        <email>dds@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/CScout">The CScout project
      page on the FreeBSD wiki.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>CScout is a refactoring editor and source code browser for
      collections of C code. The aim of the project is to make it easy
      for FreeBSD developers to use CScout and to improve the FreeBSD
      source code quality through CScout-based queries and
      refactorings.</p>

      <p>CScout was first applied to the FreeBSD kernel in 2003. Its
      application at that point involved substantial tinkering with the
      build system. The version released in October 2006 makes the
      running of CScout on the three Tier-1 architectures a fairly
      straightforward procedure. The current version can also draw a
      number of call graphs; this might help developers better understand
      foreign code.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Use CScout to locate problematic code areas (for example
      unused or too liberaly visible objects).</task>

      <task>Use CScout to globaly rename identifiers in a more consistent
      fashion.</task>

      <task>Apply CScout to the userland code.</task>

      <task>Identify CScout extensions that would help us improve the
      quality of our code.</task>

      <task>Arrange for the continuous availability of a live CScout
      kernel session on the current version of the source code.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Libelf</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joseph</given>

          <common>Koshy</common>
        </name>

        <email>jkoshy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/LibElf">Wiki page tracking
      LibELF</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/PmcTools">Wiki page for
      PmcTools</url>

      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~jkoshy/projects/perf-measurement/">
      PMC Tools Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Libelf is a BSD-licensed library for ELF parsing &amp;
      manipulation implementing the SysV/SVR4 (g)ELF[3] API.</p>

      <p>Current status: Implementation of the library is nearly
      complete. A TET-based test suite for the API is being worked
      on.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Reviewers are needed for the code and the test suite. If you
      have extensions to the stock SysV/SVR4 ELF(3) API that you would
      like to see in -lelf, please send Joseph an email.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>DTrace</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>

          <common>Birrell</common>
        </name>

        <email>jb@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Progress this month has been limited due to my sea-change,
      moving house to the country.</p>

      <p>Sun's OpenSolaris developers have followed through and released
      the DTrace test suite as part of the OpenSolaris distribution.</p>

      <p>jkoshy@'s work on libbsdelf is nearing feature completion for
      DTrace and will make life easier in FreeBSD for DTrace, given that
      we have more architectures to support than Sun has.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD project has made available a dual processor AMD64
      machine for DTrace porting.</p>

      <p>I am currently working through the diffs between the DTrace
      project in P4 and -current, committing files to -current if they
      are ready.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>TrustedBSD Audit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Christian</given>

          <common>Peron</common>
        </name>

        <email>csjp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Wayne</given>

          <common>Salamon</common>
        </name>

        <email>wsalamon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/audit.html">TrustedBSD Audit
      Page</url>

      <url href="http://www.OpenBSM.org/">OpenBSM Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
        <p>The TrustedBSD audit implementation provides fine-grained
        security event logging throughout the FreeBSD operating system.
        The big news for the last quarter is that the TrustedBSD audit
        implementation has been merged into RELENG_6 branch, and appeared
        in 6.2-BETA2. Over the past few months, work has also occurred in
        the following areas:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>OpenBSM 1.0 alpha 8 through alpha 12 have been released and
          merged into FreeBSD CVS. Changes include significant numbers of
          bug fixes, documentation improvements, and feature
          enhancements. These include regular expression based matching
          for auditreduce, auditd management of kernel audit policy (such
          as maximum trail file size), improvements in printing support
          for a variety of tokens including execve argument support.</li>

          <li>Significant enhancements to the FreeBSD Handbook chapter on
          Audit.</li>

          <li>Full audit support for execve events, including optional
          auditing of command line arguments and environmental variables,
          as well as audit support for a broad range of other additional
          kernel events.</li>

          <li>Kqueue support for audit pipes.</li>

          <li>Robustness improvements in the presence of low disk space
          conditions.</li>

          <li>Support for system call capture on additional platforms,
          such as ppc and ia64.</li>

          <li>Improved support for very large audit record sizes (as
          required for extensive execve support).</li>

          <li>id(1) now supports a -A argument to query audit state for
          the process.</li>

          <li>An audit_warn(5) event for trail rotation, which can be
          used for archiving, reduction, and other administrative
          activities.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Lots of testing as part of the 6.2-BETA cycle would be much
        appreciated. Audit support will be considered an experimental
        feature in FreeBSD 6.2-RELEASE, but we hope that it will be a
        production feature in 6.3-RELEASE.</p>
      </p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Continue expanding auditing of syscall arguments.</task>

      <task>Continue expanding auditing of administrative tools.</task>

      <task>More testing!</task>

      <task>Continue to explore improvements of the administrative model
      for audit trails, etc.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>MMC/SD Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

        <email>imp@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bernd</given>

          <common>Walter</common>
        </name>

        <email>tisco@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The MMC/SD stack got a significant boost this quarter. Warner
      Losh and Bernd Walter have written a generic MMC/SD flash card
      stack for FreeBSD, and have implemented a host controller for the
      AT91RM9200 embedded ARM controller they are each using in separate
      projects.</p>

      <p>The stack is presently experimental in quality. It is being used
      as the root file system for these embedded projects. There's been
      no work done to support hot insertion and removal of cards (neither
      board wires up the pins necessary, and besides, / disappearing is
      very bad). There are still many rough edges.</p>

      <p>This is a freshly written stack. It has been written using the
      SD 1.0 (and recently 2.0) simplified specification, with the
      SanDisk MMC application notes supplementing. The Linux stack looks
      good, although not entirely standards conforming (there's work in
      progress that I've not seen that is supposed to fix this) and it
      is contaminated with the GPL. The OpenBSD stack also looks
      interesting, but Warner's experience porting NEWCARD over from
      NetBSD suggested that a fresh rewrite may be faster, at least for
      the bus and driver level. Since MMC is fairly simple, a port of the
      sdhci driver might be possible.</p>

      <p>Please see the open tasks list.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Write sdhci driver, and integrate it into the current
      stack.</task>

      <task>Add support for hot plugging of cards.</task>

      <task>Add support for MMC cards (SD cards were the first
      target).</task>

      <task>Expand SD support to include SDIO cards as well as the new
      SDHC standard cards.</task>

      <task>Export stats via sysctl for each of the cards that are found
      as a debugging and usage monitoring aid.</task>

      <task>Add support for reading/writing multiple blocks at a time to
      improve performance.</task>

      <task>Implement any other host controller.</task>

      <task>Add proper support for timeouts.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Sun Niagara port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kip</given>

          <common>Macy</common>
        </name>

        <email>kmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for the UltraSparc T1 (Niagara) continues to improve.
      The code has recently been checked into public CVS under
      sys/sun4v.</p>

      <p>It isn't clear whether or not I will have time to implement full
      logical domaining support before the APIs become publicly
      available. Testing indicates that substantial work will be needed
      before FreeBSD can take full advantage of all 32 threads.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Random testing and bug fixes.</task>

      <task>Import and extend improved mutex profiling support.</task>

      <task>Virtual network and virtual disk device drivers for logical
      domains.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Xen Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kip</given>

          <common>Macy</common>
        </name>

        <email>kmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work on Xen support has slowly been continuing in perforce. The
      SOC student fixed several bugs and is continuing to work on it.
      Someone is needed who has the time to complete dom0 support and
      shepherd it production level stability.</p>

      <p>Sufficient interest has been expressed in it that it probably
      makes sense to check it in to public CVS so that more people can
      try it out. Time permitting, I will bring it up to date and check
      it in the next month.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>dom0 support.</task>

      <task>General testing and bug fixing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeSBIE</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeSBIE</given>

          <common>Staff</common>
        </name>

        <email>staff@FreeSBIE.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Matteo</given>

          <common>Riondato</common>
        </name>

        <email>matteo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeSBIE.org">FreeSBIE Website</url>

      <url href="http://liste.gufi.org/mailman/listinfo/freesbie">
      FreeSBIE ML Subscription Form</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~matteo/GMV/GMVAnnounce.txt">
      FreeSBIE GMV Announcement</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>FreeSBIE is a FreeBSD based LiveCD.</p>

      <p>On August 19th, Matteo Riondato, a member of the FreeSBIE staff,
      released an unofficial ISO, codename FreeSBIE GMV, based on FreeBSD
      -CURRENT (read the Announcement to download it). This is supposed
      to be the first in a series of four ISOs that will end up with the
      release of FreeSBIE 2.0. Matteo is now working on another ISO,
      codename FreeSBIE LVC, which is scheduled to be released October 12th.</p>

      <p>FreeSBIE 2.0 will be based on FreeBSD 6.2-RELEASE and will
      hopefully be released at EuroBSDCon 2006 in Milan. It will be
      available for the i386 and AMD64 platforms.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test the released ISO in preparation for the release.</task>

      <task>Suggest software to include in the ISO.</task>

      <task>Submit a simple and clear but complete fluxbox
      configuration.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Update of the Linux compatibility environment in the
    kernel</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Roman</given>

          <common>Divacky</common>
        </name>

        <email>rdivacky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Emulation</given>

          <common>Mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>emulation@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/linux-kernel">Wiki page about
      the linux compatibility environment.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Roman Divacky participated in the Google Summer of Code 2006 and
      implemented a major part of the syscall compatibility to the 2.6.16
      Linux kernel. The work has been committed to -CURRENT (the default
      compatibility still being a 2.4.2 Linux kernel) and we are working
      on fixing the remaining bugs as time permits.</p>

      <p>"Intron" submitted an implementation for the linux aio syscalls.
      His work has been committed to the Perforce repository.</p>

      <p>We also started to consolidate a list of known bugs, open issues
      and helpful stuff (e.g. regression tests and their status) in
      -CURRENT on a page in the FreeBSD wiki (see the links-section). It
      also contains a link to a more or less up-to-date patch with stuff
      we have in the Perforce repository so that interested people can
      help with testing. Thanks to the help of Marcin Cieslak we already
      fixed some bugs (some of the fixes are already MFCed to
      -STABLE).</p>

      <p>Thanks to the nice regression tests of the Linux Test Project
      (LTP) we have a list of small (and not so small) things which need
      to be looked at. This list makes up for a quick start into kernel
      hacking. So if you have a little bit of knowledge about C
      programming, and if you want to help us a little bit in improving
      FreeBSD, feel free to have a look at the list and to try to fix a
      problem or two. Sometimes it is as easy as "if (error condition)
      return Esomething;" (but you should coordinate with the emulation
      mailinglist, so that nobody does some work someone else just did
      too). Even if you do not know how to program, you can help. Have a
      look at the wiki page and tell us about things which should get
      mentioned there too. Or download the patch and test it.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Sound Subsystem Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ariff</given>

          <common>Abdullah</common>
        </name>

        <email>ariff@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ryan</given>

          <common>Beasley</common>
        </name>

        <email>ryanb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Multimedia</given>

          <common>Mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>multimedia@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~ariff/">Some patches.</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/ideas/">The FreeBSD
      Project Ideas List.</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/soundsystem">Wiki page about the
      sound system.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since the last status report we added basic support for envy24ht
      chips, imported the emu10kx driver into the base system and added
      support for High Definition Audio (HDA) compatible chips.</p>

      <p>Additionally the work of Ryan Beasley as part of his Google
      Summer of Code 2006 participation is committed. It adds
      compatibility to the Open Sound System (OSS) v4 API as far as this
      was possible. This allows for more sophisticated programs to be
      written. For example it is now possible to synchronize the start of
      multiple sound channels. It is also possible for a driver to
      support more than the AC97 mixer devices, but so far no driver has
      been extended to support this yet. More about it can be found in
      the wiki and in the official OSS documentation.</p>

      <p>The wiki page about the sound system was started to describe
      the current status of the sound system and to provide some
      information about where we are heading. But more work needs to be
      done to reach this goal. So far we collected some information about
      the status of the most recent work in the soundsystem. So if you
      have a look at it and you think that something important is
      missing, just tell us about it. While fully prepared content is
      very welcome, we are even happy about some ideas what we should
      list on the wiki page.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Have a look at the sound related entries on the ideas
      list.</task>

      <task>sndctl(1): tool to control non-mixer parts of the sound
      system (e.g. spdif switching, virtual-3D effects) by an user
      (instead of the sysctl approach in -current); pcmplay(1),
      pcmrec(1), pcmutil(1).</task>

      <task>Plugable FEEDER infrastructure. For ease of debugging various
      feeder stuff and/or as userland library and test suite.</task>

      <task>Extend the wiki page.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Bridge Spanning Tree Protocol Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Thompson</common>
        </name>

        <email>thompsa@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work is almost finished to implement the Rapid Spanning Tree
      Protocol (RSTP) which supersedes Spanning Tree Protocol (STP).
      RSTP has a much faster link failover time of around one second
      compared to 30-60 seconds for STP, this is very important on
      modern networks. The code will be posted shortly for testing and
      feedback.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>OCaml language support in ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stanislav</given>

          <common>Sedov</common>
        </name>

        <email>stas@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/~checkout~/ports/lang/ocaml/bsd.ocaml.mk?rev=1.3&amp;content-type=text/plain">
      Framework include file</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>There were a number of OCaml ports in our tree, and each of them
      was doing the same work by maintaining OCaml ld.conf in the correct
      state, installing/removing their files/entries etc. To simplify the
      task of OCaml-language ports creation, the special framework
      (bsd.ocamk.mk) was developed and most of the ports were converted to
      use this framework. This allowed a lot of duplicate code to be
      removed. This new framework handles all the things required to
      install an OCaml-language library and properly register it.
      bsd.ocaml.mk also contains knobs to deal with findlib-powered
      libraries, modify ld.conf in the proper way, etc. Also, a lot of
      new Ocaml-related ports were added.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Enlightenment DR17 support in the ports tree</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stanislav</given>

          <common>Sedov</common>
        </name>

        <email>stas@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Integration of the new innovative e17 window manager into the
      ports tree is almost completed. A lot of new e17-related
      applications was ported, all old ports were updated to the latest
      stable cvs snapshot. The special framework (bsd.efl.mk) was created
      to support the whole thing and simplify the creation of dependent
      ports. I'll commit the changes in the days before the ports
      freeze.</p>

      <p>Thanks to Sergey Matveychuk (sem@) for providing a machine to
      place CVS snapshots on. Without his help it will be impossible.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Port Entrance (xdm-like app, but very appealing).</task>

      <task>Port Net and Wlan e17 module.</task>

      <task>Develop FreeBSD-specific e17 apps/modules to use The
      Ports Collection, system configs, etc.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>CPU Microcode Update Software</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stanislav</given>

          <common>Sedov</common>
        </name>

        <email>stas@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Last month I was working on a driver/module to update the
      microcode of Intel or AMD CPUs that support having their
      microcode updated. As you might know these processors are
      microcode-driven and this firmware can be updated. Intel(R)
      often releases microcode updates, and AMD(R) updates can be
      found in BIOS programs. The work is almost finished now, I just
      need to find a bit of time to test it on AMD64 systems and
      perform some code cleanup. The driver also provide a way for
      userland programs to access the Machine Specific Registers (MSR)
      and CPUID info for a certain cpu. This will allow some programs
      like x86info to provide more accurate information about cpus in
      SMP systems and make assumptions based on the contents of the
      MSR.</p>

      <p>Thanks to John Baldwin, Kostik Belousov, John-Mark Gurney and
      Divacky Roman for helping during development.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Perform testing on the AMD64-based systems.</task>

      <task>Write manpage.</task>

      <task>Code cleanup/checks.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Improving FreeBSD Ports Collection Infrastructure</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Erwin</given>

          <common>Lansing</common>
        </name>

        <email>erwin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/G%C3%A1borK%C3%B6vesd%C3%A1n">
      Gábors wiki page.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the Google Summer of Code 2006, Gábor worked on several
      ideas to improve the ports infrastructure:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>New handling for i386 binary ports.</li>

        <li>Cleanup: use ECHO_CMD and ECHO_MSG in bsd.port.mk
        properly.</li>

        <li>Add basic infrastructure support for debugging.</li>

        <li>Installing ports with different destination (DESTDIR
        macro).</li>

        <li>Cleanup: Move fetch shell scripts out of bsd.port.mk.</li>

        <li>Make ports respect CC and CFLAGS.</li>

        <li>Cross-compiling Ports.</li>

        <li>Plist generator tool.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>The first three items have been completed and the next two
      items are being worked on. The DESTDIR support was more
      complicated than presumed and took more time than expected to
      complete.  Gábor will continue working to finish these tasks and
      other ports related tasks. FreeBSD is happy to have interested
      him to keep working on ports and ports infrastructure.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Gvinum improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ulf</given>

          <common>Lilleengen</common>
        </name>

        <email>lulf@pvv.ntnu.no</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://folk.ntnu.no/lulf/patches/freebsd/gvinum/gvinum_all_current.diff" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I thought that since I sent a status report the last time, I
      might as well send one now.</p>

      <p>Since the last status report I have done work on several of the
      remaining commands as attach, detach, and finally the concat
      command to be able to create concatenated volumes with one easy
      command. The mirror and stripe commands are the next step after
      this.</p>

      <p>The most important thing I've been working on is maybe the
      implementation of drivegroups. I have posted a bit information on
      this mailinglists, but basically, it's a way to group drives with
      the same configuration. This way, you can make many commands
      operate on groups instead of drives, and the group-abstraction will
      handle how the underlying subdisks are created on the drives.
      In the future one will be able to move groups to different
      machines, etc.</p>

      <p>I've created a patch of all my work that is not in HEAD yet here
      (this is a snapshot of my development branch, so how thing's are
      done might be changed quite fast): 
      <a
      href="http://folk.ntnu.no/lulf/patches/freebsd/gvinum/gvinum_all_current.diff">
      http://folk.ntnu.no/lulf/patches/freebsd/gvinum/gvinum_all_current.diff</a>
      </p>

      <p>Be aware that a there will probably be bugs in the code,
      so don't use it in production yet!</p>

      <p>Thanks to Greg Lehey for offering to help me on getting this
      into CVS, and all feedback on this has been good.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Remaining components, mirror, stripe and some info
      commands.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>FreeBSD Multimedia Resources List</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Edwin</given>

          <common>Groothuis</common>
        </name>

        <email>edwin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mavetju.org/unix/multimedia.php" />

      <url href="http://www.mavetju.org/unix/multimedia-rss.php">RSS
      version</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I have setup the FreeBSD Multimedia Resources List, a
      one-stop-shop for FreeBSD related podcasts, vodcasts and
      audio/video resources. Hopefully this list will make it easier for
      people to find and keep up to date with these recordings. The
      overview is available as a normal HTML page and as an XML/RSS
      feed.</p>

      <p>The ultimate goal is to have this list to reside under the
      www.FreeBSD.org umbrella.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>SNMP monitoring (BSNMP)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Shteryana</given>

          <common>Shopova</common>
        </name>

        <email>shteryana@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bjoern A.</given>

          <common>Zeeb</common>
        </name>

        <email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/soc%2dshteryana/bsnmp&amp;HIDEDEL=NOe">
      P4 workspace</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/CategorySNMP">SNMP-related
      pages on FreeBSD Wiki</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/SnmpBridgeModule">A wiki page on
      if_bridge(4) monitoring module</url>

      <url href="http://www.freshports.org/net-mgmt/bsnmptools/">
      bsnmptools port</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A BRIDGE monitoring module for FreeBSD's BSNMP daemon has been
      implemented. In addition to RFC 4188 single bridge support and
      extending the kernel to get access to all the information, a
      private MIB was designed in order to be able to monitor multiple
      bridges supported by FreeBSD. The kernel part has already been
      committed to -CURRENT (thanks to thompsa@), for -STABLE a patch is
      available (see the wiki), code has already been reviewed.</p>

      <p>SoC 2005 work on SNMP client tools is now available too via port
      (net-mgmt/bsnmptools), thanks to Andrew Pantyukhin for the port.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More testing is very welcome.</task>

      <task>if_vlan(4) monitoring module.</task>

      <task>jail(8) monitoring module.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSDCan 2007</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>

          <common>Langille</common>
        </name>

        <email>dan@langille.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The dates for 
      <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2007/">BSDCan 2007</a>
      have been set: 11-12 May 2007. As is usual, BSDCan will be held at
      University of Ottawa, with two days of tutorials prior to the
      conference starting.</p>

      <p>The 
      <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2007/papers.php">call for papers</a>

      will go out in mid December. Start thinking about your submissions
      now!</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>FreshPorts</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>

          <common>Langille</common>
        </name>

        <email>dan@langille.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freshports.org/">FreshPorts - The Place For
      Ports</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The new 2U server mentioned in the last report now has a
      collection of Raptor drives in a RAID-10 configuration. Thanks to
      very generous donations from the community, I purchased eight of
      these drives at very good prices. The server will be deployed in
      the next few weeks.</p>

      <p>There has been quite a bit of work since the last report in
      June. Some highlights include:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>New news feed 
        <a href="http://www.freshports.org/backend/">formats</a>,

        including newsfeeds for your watch list.</li>

        <li>Better pages caching for faster response.</li>

        <li>Sanity Test Failures now available 
        <a
        href="http://news.freshports.org/2006/10/11/sanity-test-failures/">
        online.</a>
        </li>

        <li>Ability to 
        <a
        href="http://news.freshports.org/2006/10/15/all-commits-under-a-point- in-the-tree/">
        search for all commits</a>

        (ports, doc, src, etc) under a given point in the tree.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>For more detail, please review the 
      <a href="http://news.freshports.org/">FreshPorts Blog</a>

      .</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="team">
    <title>The FreeBSD Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Deb</given>

          <common>Goodkin</common>
        </name>

        <email>deb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation continued to support the FreeBSD project
      and community through various activities. These activities include
      creating strategies for fund development and actively seeking
      funding for the FreeBSD community, coordinating a new IBM
      Bladeserver project, and protecting the image and integrity of
      FreeBSD by governing the use of the trademarks. We are pleased to
      be a sponsor of EuroBSDCon and will be sponsoring a few developers
      to attend the conference through our travel grant program. And
      finally, we have secured funds for a major project that will be
      announced later this month.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>

