<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status
Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2007-07-2007-10.xml,v 1.3 2008/01/27 18:30:01 gabor Exp $ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-October</month>

    <year>2007</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers FreeBSD related projects between July and
    October 2007. The sixth EuroBSDCon was held in Denmark in September.
    The Google Summer of Code project came to a close and lots of
    participants are working getting their code merged back into
    FreeBSD.</p>

    <p>The bugs in the FreeBSD HEAD branch are being shaked out and it is
    being prepared for the FreeBSD 7 branching. If your are curious about
    what's new in FreeBSD 7.0 we suggest reading Ivan Voras' excellent
    summary 
    <a href="http://ivoras.sharanet.org/freebsd/freebsd7.html">here</a>

    .</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
    enjoy reading.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>FreeBSD Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>MTund - Magic Tunnel Daemon</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Matus</given>

          <common>Harvan</common>
        </name>

        <email>mharvan@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/MTund">mtund Wiki Page</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.inf.ethz.ch/personal/mharvan/docs/eurobsdcon.pdf">
      MTund Poster</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>IP can easily be tunneled over a plethora of network protocols
      at various layers, such as IP, ICMP, UDP, TCP, DNS, HTTP, SSH.
      While a direct connection may not always be possible due to a
      firewall, the IP packets could be encapsulated as payload in other
      protocols, which would get through. However, each such
      encapsulation requires the setup of a different program and the
      user has to manually probe different encapsulations to find out
      which of them works in a given environment.</p>

      <p>MTund is a tunneling daemon using run-time loadable plugins for
      the different encapsulations. It automagically selects the best
      encapsulation in each environment and can fail over to another
      encapsulation. Several plugins have been implemented and the daemon
      supports multiple concurrent clients.</p>

      <p>Note that the project originally started under the name of Super
      Tunnel Daemon, but was later renamed to Magic Tunnel Daemon
      (MTund).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Config file format and parser.</task>

      <task>More plugins (http, ssh, ...).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The Spanish Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>J. Vicente</given>

          <common>Carrasco Vay&aacute;</common>
        </name>

        <email>carvay@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>G&aacute;bor</given>

          <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/es_ES.ISO8859-1/articles/fdp-es/">
      Info for volunteers</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>After a long break in this project, we started reviewing and
      refreshing our translations. We have to update the content to
      reflect the current state of the English version. There are a few
      parts written in a poor style, another task is to improve these a
      bit. Any kind of help is highly welcome.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Sync the website with the English version.</task>

      <task>Sync the documentation with the English version.</task>

      <task>Review the quality of poorly translated parts.</task>

      <task>Add more translations.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The Hungarian Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>G&aacute;bor</given>

          <common>K&ouml;vesd&aacute;n</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>G&aacute;bor</given>

          <common>P&aacute;li</common>
        </name>

        <email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/hu/docproj/hungarian.html">Info
      for volunteers</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/hu/">Hungarian website</url>

      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/docproj%5fhu&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
      Perforce repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We have a new volunteer, G&aacute;bor P&aacute;li, who provided us
      some high-quality contributions. As a result, we have been able to add 5
      new articles since the last status report.</p>

      <p>There is also an ongoing effort in the Perforce repository to
      translate the FreeBSD Handbook to Hungarian. Any kind of support is
      highly welcome.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Translate the Handbook.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>EuroBSDcon 2007</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <common>EuroBSDCon 2007 Organizing Committee</common>
        </name>

        <email>info@EuroBSDCon.dk</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://2007.EuroBSDCon.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The sixth EuroBSDCon went well. 215 people attended the
      conference. Feedback has been very positive.</p>

      <p>At the conference we had a Best Talk contest. Steven Murdoch,
      Isaac Levy and Pawel Jakub "zfs-man" Dawidek each received a prize
      for their fantastic talks.</p>

      <p>Also over 300 pictures from the conference has been uploaded to
      Flickr with the tag 
      <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/eurobsdcon2007/">
      EuroBSDCon2007</a>
      </p>

      <p>Videos and slides from the talks are now online at the
      conference website.</p>

      <p>We thank our speakers for graciously having permitted recording
      and publication of their talks</p>

      <p>EuroBSDCon 2008 will take place in Strassbourg.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>finstall</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/finstall" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The "finstall" project is about the new graphical installer for
      FreeBSD. The basic frameworks (both client-side and server-side)
      are done during the SoC 2007 and it's ready for major new features
      to be implemented. This project should yield an usable installer
      for 7.0-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>- There are several patches needed for finstall's operation
      that are still waiting on re@'s approval (unionfs, pwd, kbdmap).
      Finstall will be late or unusable until these patches are
      committed.</task>

      <task>- After the patches are committed, there are several exciting
      features to be implemented, among others ZFS and GEOM RAID
      support.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>GNATS graphs</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Edwin</given>

          <common>Groothuis</common>
        </name>

        <email>edwin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~edwin/gnats/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>With the leaving of bsd@, we lost the GNATS statistics webpages.
      On this URL I generate a new set of graphs, right now a subset of
      what bsd@ had, hopefully a superset of that in the future.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc' summary='t'>
    <title>Summer of Code</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Murray</given>

          <common>Stokely</common>
        </name>

        <email>murray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/summerofcode-2007.html">
      Official FreeBSD Summer of Code 2007 Final Status Update</url>

      <url
      href="http://googlesummerofcode.blogspot.com/2007/09/updates-from-freebsd.html">
      Google Blog Post About FreeBSD</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2007">FreeBSD Summer
      of Code Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We're happy to report the successful conclusion of our third
      consecutive Google Summer of Code. By all accounts, the FreeBSD
      participation in this program was an unqualified success. We
      narrowed down the many impressive applications to 25 that were
      selected for funding and 92% of these completed successfully and
      were awarded the full $4,500 stipend. The FreeBSD Foundation was
      also granted $500 per student from Google for a total of
      $12,500.</p>

      <p>These student projects included security research, improved
      installation tools, new utilities, and more. Many of the students
      have continued working on their FreeBSD projects even after the
      official close of the program. Three students have already been
      granted full src/ commit access to CVS and more are expected. At
      least 2 of our FreeBSD mentors will be meeting with Google
      organizers in Mountain View this month to discuss the program at
      the Mentor Summit.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Integration of student projects into FreeBSD -CURRENT.
      Several are currently blocked on the FreeBSD 7.0 code freeze, but
      we hope to see these contributions included in a future
      release.</task>

      <task>Updating the ideas list. Many of the items listed there have
      been completed and we could always use new projects for next year's
      students and for others to work on throughout the year.
      http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/ideas</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>gvirstor</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ivan</given>

          <common>Voras</common>
        </name>

        <email>ivoras@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/gvirstor" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>GEOM_VIRSTOR (virtual disk space / over-commit GEOM class) has
      been committed to 7-CURRENT and will ship in 7.0-RELEASE. Thanks to
      Pawel Jakub Dawidek and others who have made this possible.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>It needs wider exposure and testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>USB</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Hans Petter</given>

          <common>Sirevaag Selasky</common>
        </name>

        <email>hselasky@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
      Current USB files</url>

      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/fileLogView.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/usb/src/sys/dev/usb/README">
      Current USB API README file</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the last three months there has been a flush of changes
      going into the FreeBSD USB P4 project. The changes mainly concern
      the ability to support the USB device side and multi frame USB
      transfers. Up to date the FreeBSD USB stack has only supported the
      USB Host Side. Before Christmas 2007 the P4 USB project will offer
      USB device support and some simple USB device side implementations.
      Technically an USB device side driver will look very similar to an
      USB host side driver. Infact there will be very few differences.
      Support for multi frame USB transfers opens up the possibility to
      transfer multiple short-packet terminated USB frames to/from
      different memory locations resulting in only one interrupt on the
      USB Host Controller. More specific: I have implemented support for
      the "alt_next" pointer in the EHCI Transfer Descriptor. This should
      give a noticeable increase in the maximum number of short-packet
      terminated BULK frames that can be transferred per second.</p>

      <p>I regularly get questions from people asking about when the USB
      P4 project will be merged into FreeBSD-current. The answer is not
      simple, but probably something like another year. The reason is not
      that the current code in the USB P4 project is not usable, but
      rather that the quality needs to be raised in means of making
      already good solutions more technically excellent, writing more
      documentation and styling the code.</p>

      <p>Ideas and comments with regard to the new USB API are welcome at
      freebsd-usb@freebsd.org.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Porting Linux KVM to FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Fabio</given>

          <common>Checconi</common>
        </name>

        <email>fabio@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Luigi</given>

          <common>Rizzo</common>
        </name>

        <email>luigi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://feanor.sssup.it/~fabio/freebsd/lkvm/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
        <p>Linux KVM (Kernel-based Virtual Machine) is a software package
        that can be used to create virtual machines fully emulating x86
        hardware on top of machines supporting Intel VT-x or AMD-V
        virtualization extensions, available on newer AMD and Intel
        processors, e.g., recent Athlon64, Core 2 Duo, Xeon and so
        on.</p>

        <p>Linux KVM has been ported to FreeBSD as a loadable kernel
        module, using the linux-kmod-compat port (in /usr/ports/devel/)
        to reuse as much as possible of the original source code, plus an
        userspace client consisting in a modified version of qemu, that
        uses KVM for the execution of its guests.</p>

        <p>The porting has been completed, many of the limitations
        present at the end of the Summer of Code have been removed and
        the known bugs have been fixed. Some configurations have been
        tested, FreeBSD-CURRENT i386 guests have been booted on Intel and
        AMD processors, both in i386 and amd64 (host) installations. Only
        one client at a time is supported by now and performance is not
        that exciting, but the project seems to be ready to receive wider
        testing.</p>
      </p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Apple's MacBook on FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Rui</given>

          <common>Paulo</common>
        </name>

        <email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/AppleMacbook" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Summer of Code project went well and we reached interesting
      results. At least the Mac Mini should be fully supported by now.
      Regarding the other Apple systems, we still need to polish some
      edges.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Integrate rpaulo-macbook p4 branch into CVS.</task>

      <task>Continue the work on the remaining issues.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Multicast DNS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Fredrik</given>

          <common>Lindberg</common>
        </name>

        <email>fli@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/MulticastDNS" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project (started out as a GSoC 2007 project) aims to provide
      a complete Multicast DNS and Service Discovery suite. Much progress
      have been made since the last status report and the project is
      slowly reaching a usable state. Most features are complete and the
      current focus is on fixing outstanding bugs, fine tuning and
      testing. However, there are still a few open tasks (see below).
      More information and snapshots can be found at the wiki page.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Avahi library wrapper.</task>

      <task>dns_sd (Apple) library wrapper.</task>

      <task>Testing (always welcome).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Multi-link PPP daemon (MPD) 5.x</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Motin</common>
        </name>

        <email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/mpd/">Project home</url>

      <url href="http://mpd.sourceforge.net/doc5/mpd5.html">
      ChangeLog</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>New mpd-5.x branch has been started and first public release is
      planned soon. The main goal of the new branch is to implement new
      operation principles based on dynamic on-demand links/bundles
      creation. There are several benefits received from new design:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Significantly simplified server configuration - no more tons
        of predefined links/bundles,</li>

        <li>New multilink implementation - no more predefined link-bundle
        relations,</li>

        <li>Call forwarding (LAC, PAC, TSA) like in Cisco VPDN setups can
        now be enabled/configured depending on peer auth
        name/domain.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>L2TP auth proxying support.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Network Stack Virtualization</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Marko</given>

          <common>Zec</common>
        </name>

        <email>zec@fer.hr</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://imunes.tel.fer.hr/virtnet/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The network stack virtualization project aims at extending the
      FreeBSD kernel to maintain multiple independent instances of
      networking state. This allows for networking independence between
      jail-like environmens, each maintaining its private network
      interface set, IPv4 and IPv6 network and port address space,
      routing tables, IPSec configuration, firewalls, and more.</p>

      <p>The prototype, which is kept in sync with FreeBSD -CURRENT,
      should be sufficiently stable for testing and experimental use. The
      project's web page includes weekly code snapshots, as well as a
      virtualized FreeBSD system installed on a VMWare disk image
      available for download.</p>

      <p>The short-term goal is to deliver production-grade kernel
      support for virtualized networking for FreeBSD 7.0-RELEASE (as a
      snap-in kernel replacement), while continuing to keep the code in
      sync with -CURRENT for possible merging at a later date.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Porting OpenBSD's sysctl Hardware Sensors Framework to
    FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Constantine A.</given>

          <common>Murenin</common>
        </name>

        <email>cnst@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Shteryana</given>

          <common>Shopova</common>
        </name>

        <email>syrinx@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/GSoC2007/cnst-sensors">Port
      OpenBSD's sysctl hw.sensors framework to FreeBSD, a Google Summer
      of Code 2007 project</url>

      <url href="http://cnst.livejournal.com/tag/GSoC2007">cnst's
      GSoC2007 blog</url>

      <url href="http://cnst.livejournal.com/data/atom?tag=GSoC2007">
      cnst's GSoC2007 atom feed</url>

      <url
      href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-hackers/2007-September/021722.html">
      Project completion announcement from 2007-09-13</url>

      <url
      href="http://p4web.freebsd.org//depot/projects/soc2007/cnst-sensors/?ac=83" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The 
      <strong>GSoC2007/cnst-sensors</strong>

      project was about porting the 
      <em>sysctl hw.sensors</em>

      framework from OpenBSD to FreeBSD. The project was 
      <a
      href='http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-hackers/2007-September/021722.html'>
      successfully completed</a>,

      <a
      href='http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/commits/2007-10/msg00015.html'>
		committed into DragonFly BSD</a>, and is now pending final review and integration
		into the FreeBSD's CVS tree (subject to the tree being unfrozen).</p>

  <p>The <em>sensors framework</em> provides a unified interface for
		storing, registering and accessing information about hardware
		monitoring sensors. Sensor types include, but are not limited to,
		temperature, voltage, fan RPM, time offset and logical drive
		status. In the OpenBSD base system, the framework spans 
		<em>sensor_attach(9)</em>, <em>sysctl(3)</em>, <em>sysctl(8)</em>,
		<em>systat(1)</em>, <em>sensorsd(8)</em>, <em>ntpd(8)</em> and
		more than 50 drivers, ranging from I2C temperature sensors and
      Super I/O hardware monitors to IPMI and RAID controllers. Several
      third-party tools are also available, for example, a plug-in for
      Nagios and ports/sysutils/symon.</p>

      <p>As a part of this Google Summer of Code project, all core
      components of the framework were ported, including sysctl, systat
      and sensorsd. Some drivers for the most popular Super I/O Hardware
		Monitors were ported, too: <em>it(4)</em>, supporting most
		contemporary ITE Tech Super I/O, and <em>lm(4)</em>, supporting
		most contemporary Winbond Super I/O. Moreover, some existing
		FreeBSD drivers were converted to utilise the framework, for
		example, <em>coretemp(4)</em>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Final Review and Commit</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>PC-BSD Handbook</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Murray</given>

          <common>Stokely</common>
        </name>

        <email>murray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Matt</given>

          <common>Olander</common>
        </name>

        <email>matt@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Fukang</given>

          <common>Chen</common>
        </name>

        <email>loader@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.pcbsd.org">PC-BSD Web Page</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/handbook">FreeBSD Handbook</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The PC-BSD derivative of FreeBSD is becoming increasingly
      popular for new users of BSD. Much of the content in the existing
      FreeBSD Handbook is directly applicable to PC-BSD. We are writing
      PC-BSD specific installation and port/packages chapters (PBI).
      These chapters will be checked into
      docs/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/pcbsd-handbook and will include some of
      the same chapters as the Handbook does, but with a different
      &amp;os entity and possibly with some conditional changes in those
      chapter files.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More work is needed on a PC-BSD ports/packages chapter.
      Fukang may already have some work in this area so coordinate with
      him first.</task>

      <task>More text is needed for the PC-BSD installation chapter to
      augment the screenshots that Fukang has collected. Contact him to
      coordinate.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/ports/">The FreeBSD Ports
      Collection</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">
      Contributing to the FreeBSD Ports Collection</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~fenner/portsurvey/">FreeBSD
      ports unfetchable distfile survey (Bill Fenner's report)</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">The FreeBSD
      Ports Management Team</url>

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com">The Marcuscom
      Tinderbox</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/gcc4">GCC4 Status Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports count is over 17,700. The PR count has decreased a bit
      to just over 700.</p>

      <p>There have been 6 experimental runs on the build cluster. The
      resulting commits include the fixup of last year's DESTDIR changes,
      the refactoring of perl bits into bsd.perl.mk, the update of xorg
      from 7.2 to 7.3, the upgrade of all of the autoconf dependencies to
      the latest version (wherever possible), and the upgrade of Python
      to 2.5. This effort has resulted in the fewest number of 'open'
      portmgr PRs in quite some time. portmgr appreciates all the people
      who worked with us on these patches, and people's patience as we
      catch up.</p>

      <p>As well, lofi@ committed the upgrade of QT to 4.3.1.</p>

      <p>We have added 3 new committers since the last report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>GCC4.2 has been imported to the base for 7.0. Unfortunately,
      this broke a large number of ports. The ones that have not yet been
      fixed have now been flagged as 'broken' for both i386 and amd64, as
      appropriate. Please see the GCC4 status page (above) if you are
      able to help.</task>

      <task>Most of the remaining ports PRs are "existing port/PR
      assigned to committer". Although the maintainer-timeout policy is
      helping to keep the backlog down, we are going to need to do more
      to get the ports in the shape they really need to be in.</task>

      <task>Although we have added many maintainers, we still have many
      unmaintained ports. The packages on amd64 are lagging behind a bit;
      those on sparc64 require even more work.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>FreeBSD-update Front End</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Turner</common>
        </name>

        <email>andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://developer.berlios.de/projects/facund/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The freebsd-update front end is able to wait for freebsd-update
      to download a new set of patches to apply. It can then install and
      rollback the patches on either the local computer or over a SSH
      tunnel.</p>

      <p>Since the end of the Summer of Code work has moved to BerliOS.
      The focus has been on writing tests for the front end, back end and
      communication library. The library has had tests written for most
      of it while the front and back ends have none.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Write more tests.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Ports Collection infrastructure improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gábor</given>

          <common>Kövesdán</common>
        </name>

        <email>gabor@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/G%C3%A1borSoC2007">Wiki
      page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The two most important parts of this Summer of Code projects
      have been accomplished.</p>

      <p>The DESTDIR support for the Ports Collection has been rewritten
      to use a chrooted install. Now it is much more lightweight and
      easier to understand, but it works well for the most common cases,
      where it is supposed to be useful.</p>

      <p>The Perl parts of the Ports Collection infrastructure have been
      extracted into an own module. At the same time, a new version
      handling has been invented. You can find more info on the Wiki.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="team">
    <title>FreeBSD.org Admins Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeBSD.org</given>

          <common>Admins Team</common>

          <email>admins@FreeBSD.org</email>
        </name>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Over the last couple of months several FreeBSD.org systems have
      been experiencing hardware issues. This included the main
      web-server www.FreeBSD.org which had a bad fan. The bad fan has
      been replaced so it should hopefully be stable again. In general we
      are working on replacing older hardware with newer systems and
      consolidating machine functions in the process.</p>

      <p>Since August most FreeBSD.org services have been available via
      IPv6 with connectivity provided from ISC using a tunnel.</p>

      <p>To honor the "Eat your own dog-food" principle the first two
      FreeBSD.org infrastructure systems have been upgraded to FreeBSD 7
      and more are being upgraded as time permit.</p>

      <p>Due to heavy load on the project's Perforce and CVS server the
      two services are being moved to separate systems to improve
      performance of both CVS and Perforce.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>

