<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2013</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between October and
      December 2013.  This is the fourth of four reports planned for
      2013.</p>

    <!-- XXX: Add introduction -->

    <!-- XXX: Keep updating the number of entries -->
    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 2 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering between January and
      March 2014 is April 7th, 2014.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>CBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleg</given>
	  <common>Ginzburg</common>
	</name>
	<email>olevole@olevole.ru</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdstore.ru"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/olevole/cbsd"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>CBSD is another &os; jail management solution, aimed at
	combining various features, such as <tt>racct(8)</tt>,
	<tt>vnet</tt>, <tt>zfs(8)</tt>, <tt>carp(4)</tt>,
	<tt>hastd(8)</tt>, into a single tool.  This provides a more
	comprehensive way for building application servers using
	pre-installed jails with a typical set of software, and requires
	a minimal effort to configure.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Proper English translation of the website and the
	documentation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>&os; Test Suite</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Julio</given>
	  <common>Merino</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmmv@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/TestSuite">Project page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Test Suite project aims to equip &os; with a
	comprehensive test suite that is easy to run out of the box and
	during the development of the system.  The test suite is
	installed into <tt>/usr/tests/</tt> and the <tt>kyua(1)</tt>
	command-line tool (<tt>devel/kyua</tt> in the Ports Collection)
	is used to run them.</p>

      <p>The benefits of having a test suite that is easy to use and
	continuously run are obvious: regressions can be caught sooner
	rather than later and the Release Engineering Team can better
	assess the quality of the tree before deciding to cut a release.
	Additionally, and because we choose to install the tests, we
	also allow any end user to perform sanity checks on new
	installations of the system on his or her particular hardware
	configuration &mdash; a very attractive thing to do when
	deploying production servers.</p>

      <p>During the last few months, we have added the necessary pieces to
	the build system to support building and installing test programs of
	various kinds. To demonstrate the functionality of these, some test
	programs were added and others were migrated from the old testing tree
	in <tt>tools/regression/</tt> to the new layout for tests.</p>

      <p>The current test suite should be seen as a proof of concept at this
	point: it is only composed of a small set of test programs and the goal
	is to get the infrastructure in place before mass-migrating existing
	test code and/or importing external tests.</p>

      <p>As part of this work, two new releases of Kyua were published.
	Of special interest is the addition of a TAP-compliant backend so
	that existing tests from <tt>tools/regression/</tt> can be
	plugged into the test suite with minimum effort.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We have got three machines in which to set up a continuous
	testing system.  This work is in progress.  Once done, periodic
	test reports will be available online.</task>

      <task>Related to the above, the Kyua reporting engine needs
	significant tuning to make the reports nice and clean.  These
	changes will come after the basic infrastructure is in
	place.</task>

      <task>A tutorial on writing tests for &os; has been proposed for
	AsiaBSDCon&nbsp;2014.  The outcome of the proposal is still
	unknown, but stay tuned!</task>

      <task>Port, port, and port more tests to the new test suite.  A
	test suite is worthless if it does not validate stuff!  Stay tuned
	for a request for help when we have put all basic pieces in
	place and have streamlined the migration process.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
