<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2013</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between July and
      September 2013.  This is the third of four reports planned for
      2013.</p>

    <!-- XXX: introduction goes here -->

    <!-- XXX: keep updating the number of entries -->
    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 5 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <!-- XXX: set date for the next set of submissions -->
    <p>The deadline for submissions covering between October and
      December 2013 is not yet decided.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>AES-NI Improvements for GELI</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John-Mark</given>
	  <common>Gurney</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;revision=255187"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An enhancement to the AES-NI implementation for OpenCrypto has
	been committed that significantly improves AES-XTS and AES-CBC
	decryption performance.  This gives <tt>geli(8)</tt> around a
	three times performance boost on <tt>gnop(8)</tt> using AES-XTS
	compared to the old code.</p>

      <p>These improvements are available to users of the OpenCrypto
	framework and <tt>crypto(4)</tt>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Static Code Analysis</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ulrich</given>
	  <common>Spoerlein</common>
	</name>
	<email>uqs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://scan.coverity.com/">Coverity Scan</url>
      <url href="http://scan.freebsd.your.org/">Clang Static Analyzer Scan for &os;</url>
      <url href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/">Clang Static Analyzer Home Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>With our own (old and unstable) instance of Coverity Prevent
	gone, we have now fully transitioned to the Scan project run by
	Coverity (see links), which Open Source projects can use to
	learn about possible defects in their source code.</p>

      <p>We also continue to run our code base through the Static
	Analyzer that is shipped with Clang/LLVM.  It cannot track the
	state of the code over time, but has the benefit that everyone
	can use it without any special setup.  See the home page at the
	links section for more information on the Clang Static Analyzer
	project in general, and head over to the &os; Clang Static
	Analyzer Scan page (see links) to see those possible defects (no
	signup required).</p>

      <p>We are looking for a co-admin for both of these projects to
	increase the bus-factor and the chance of survival for these
	services.  Fame and fortune await!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Maybe turn on email reports for new defects to the internal
	list of &os; developers.</task>

      <task>Find co-admin.</task>

      <task>Fix the defects reported by Coverity and Clang.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>GEOM Direct Dispatch and Fine-Grained CAM Locking</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/projects/camlock/">Project SVN branch</url>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~mav/camlock_patches/">Project patches</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Last year's high-performance storage vendors reported a
	performance bottleneck in the &os; block storage subsystem,
	limiting peak performance around 300-500K IOPS.  While that is
	still more than enough for average systems, detailed
	investigation has shown a number of places that require radical
	improvement.  Unmapped I/O support implemented early this year
	already improved I/O performance by about 30% and moved more
	accents toward GEOM and CAM subsystems scalability.  Fixing
	these issues was the goal of this project.</p>

      <p>The existing GEOM design assumed most I/O handling to be done
	by only two kernel threads (<tt>g_up()</tt> and
	<tt>g_down()</tt>).  That simplified locking in some cases, but
	limited potential SMP scalability and created additional
	scheduler overhead.  This project introduces the concept of
	direct I/O dispatch into GEOM for cases where it is known to be
	safe and efficient.  That implies marking some GEOM consumers
	and providers with one or two new flags, declaring situations
	when a direct function call can be used instead of normal request
	queuing.  That allows avoiding any context switches inside GEOM
	for the most widely used topologies, simultaneously processing
	multiple I/Os from multiple calling threads.</p>

      <p>Having GEOM passing through multiple concurrent calls down to
	the underlying layers exposed major lock congestion in CAM.  In
	the existing CAM design all devices connected to the same ATA/SCSI
	controller are sharing a single lock, which can be quite busy due
	to multiple controller hardware accesses and/or code logic.
	Experiments have shown that applying only the above GEOM direct
	dispatch changes burns up to 60% of system CPU time or even more
	in attempts to obtain these locks by multiple callers, killing
	any benefits of GEOM direct dispatch.  To overcome that, new
	fine-grained CAM locking design was implemented.  It implies
	splitting big per-SIM locks into several smaller ones: per-LUN
	locks, per-bus locks, queue locks, etc.  After these changes,
	the remaining per-SIM lock protects only the controller driver
	internals, reducing lock congestion down to an acceptable level
	and keeping keep compatibility with existing drivers.</p>

      <p>Together, GEOM and CAM changes double the peak I/O rate,
	reaching up to 1,000,000 IOPS on contemporary hardware.</p>

      <p>The changes were tested by a number of people and will be
	committed into &os; <tt>head</tt> and merged to
	<tt>stable/10</tt> after the end of the &os; 10.0 release
	cycle.</p>

      <p>The project is sponsored by iXsystems, Inc.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More reviews, more stability and performance tests.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>VMware VMXNET3 Driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>Venteicher</common>
	</name>
	<email>bryanv@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2013-August/043494.html"/>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/head/sys/dev/vmware/vmxnet3/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A port of the OpenBSD <tt>vmx(4)</tt> ethernet driver has been
	committed.  The driver can be used in place of the VMware Tools
	<tt>vmxnet3</tt> driver, which currently does not support
	10.0-RELEASE (or anything past 9.1-RELEASE).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Performance improvements, multiqueue support.</task>
      <task>Merge to <tt>stable/9</tt>.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>VirtIO Network Multiqueue</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>Venteicher</common>
	</name>
	<email>bryanv@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/255112"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The VirtIO network driver, <tt>vtnet(4)</tt>, recently gained
	support for multiple queues, along with a significant cleanup
	and support for a few additional features.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
