<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
  Status Report//EN"
  "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2014</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

<!-- <?ignore -->
    <p><strong>This is a draft of the July-September 2014 status
	report.	 Please check back after it is finalized, and an
	announcement email is sent to the &os;-Announce mailing
	list.</strong></p>
<!-- ?> -->

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between July and
      September 2014.  This is the third of four reports planned for
      2014.</p>

    <p>The third quarter of 2014... was a very busy and productive
      time</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This
      report contains 0 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering the period from October
      to December 2014 is January 7th, 2015.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <?ignore
  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>
  ?>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

<project cat='proj'>
  <title>New Automounter</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
        <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
        <common>Napiera&#322;a</common>
      </name>
      <email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Automounter" />
    <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~trasz/autofs.pdf" />
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>
         Deficiencies in the current automounter, amd(8), are a recurring problem reported by many FreeBSD users. A new automounter is being developed to address these concerns.

         The automounter is a cleanroom implementation of functionality available in most other Unix systems, using proper kernel support implemented via an autofs filesystem. The automounter supports a standard map format, and will integrate with the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) service.

         The code is ready to use - it has been committed to 11-CURRENT and 10-STABLE, and will ship as part of 10.1-RELEASE.  There is ongoing work on improving performance and fixing possible bugs.
    </p>
  </body>

  <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
  </sponsor>

  <help></help>
</project>

<project cat='proj'>
  <title>Chelsio iSCSI Offload Support</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
        <given>Sreenivasa</given>
        <common>Honnur</common>
      </name>
      <email>shonnur@chelsio.com</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
        <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
        <common>Napiera&#322;a</common>
      </name>
      <email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links></links>

  <body>
    <p>
         Building on the new in-kernel iSCSI target and initiator stack released in FreeBSD 10.0, Chelsio Communications has begun developing an offload interface to take advantage of the hardware offload capabilities of Chelsio T4 and T5 10 and 40 gigabit Ethernet adapters.

         The code implements hardware PDU offload for both target and initiator.  The iSCSI stack has been modified to provide hardware-independent offload API, allowing offload drivers to be loaded as kernel modules, and to provide mechanisms for the system administrator to configure this feature.  The project is entering a testing phase.  The code will be released under the BSD license and is expected to be completed later in the year and ship in FreeBSD 10.2-RELEASE.
    </p>
  </body>

  <sponsor>
      Chelsio Communications
  </sponsor>
  <sponsor>
      The FreeBSD Foundation
  </sponsor>

  <help>
    <task>
         Complete testing
    </task>
  </help>
</project>


</report>
