<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd">

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>February - April</month>
    <year>2002</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This report covers FreeBSD development activities from February,
	2002 through April, 2002.  It's been a busy few months -- BSDCon
	in San Francisco, the FreeBSD Developer Summit, a first development
	preview of 5.0-CURRENT, not to mention lots of progress on the
	5.0 feature set (SMPng, sparc64, GEOM, ... the list goes on).</p>
      <p>In the next two months, the USENIX ATC occurs (highly recommended
	event for both developers and users), and a number of new software
	components will hit the tree, including UFS2 and the TrustedBSD
	MAC framework.  We'll also complete the elections for the FreeBSD
	Core Team, and should have the next Core Team online by the time
	the next report rolls around.  Stay tuned for more!</p>
      <p>Robert Watson</p>
  </section>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD Package-building Cluster</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kris</given>
	  <common>Kennaway</common>
	</name>
	<email>kris@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Packages are built from the FreeBSD Ports Collection on a
	cluster of i386 and alpha machines using scripts available in
	/usr/ports/Tools/portbuild/.  Over the past few months I have
	been cleaning up and extending these scripts to improve
	efficiency and allow for greater flexibility in how package
	builds are performed.  Major improvements so far have been:
	cleaning up and modularizing the scripts to avoid code
	duplication and reduce the need for ongoing maintenance;
	optimizing the build process and making it much more robust
	against client machine failure; and allowing package builds to
	be restarted if they are interrupted.  The i386 package
	cluster is currently running FreeBSD 5.0-CURRENT, and it has
	proven to be a useful testing ground for exposing kernel bugs,
	especially those which only manifest under system load.</p>

      <p>Future plans include the ability to perform incremental
	package rebuilds which only build packages that have changed
	since the last run.  This will allow packages to be made
	available on the FTP site within an hour or two of the CVS
	commit to the ports collection.  We also hope to set up a
	sparc64 package cluster in the near future, but this is
	contingent on suitable hardware.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>UMA</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	 <name>
	  <given>Jeff</given>
	  <common>Roberson</common>
	</name>

	<email>jeff@FreeBSD.org</email>
     </person>
   </contact>

    <body>
      <p>FreeBSD's new kernel memory allocator has been committed to
	5.0.  UMA is a slabs derived allocator that supports memory
	reclaiming, object caching, type stable storage, and per CPU
	free lists for optimal SMP performance.  It has both a
	malloc(9) interface and a zone style interface for specific
	object types. uma(9) will be available shortly.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Universal Disk Filesystem for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>
          <common>Long</common>
        </name>
        <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jeroen</given>
          <common>Ruigrok</common>
        </name>
        <email>asmodai@wxs.nl</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~scottl/udf">UDF Homepage.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Read-only support for UDF filesystems was checked into the 5-CURRENT
        branch in April.  Backporting for 4-STABLE is being conducted by
        Jeroen.  The next phase is to write a newfs_udf, then move on to
        adding write support to the filesystem.  I'm still looking for a
        volunteer to handle read and write support for write-once media
        (e.g. CD-R).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Zero Copy Sockets</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ken</given>

          <common>Merry</common>
        </name>

        <email>ken@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~ken/zero_copy/">Zero copy patches
        and information. </url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> I have released a new zero copy sockets snapshot, the first since
        November, 2000.  The code has been ported up to the latest
        -current, and the jumbo code now has mutex protection.  Also, zero
        copy send and receive can be selectively turned on and off via sysctl
        to make it easier to compare performance with and without zero copy.
        Reviews and comments are welcome.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Bluetooth stack for FreeBSD (Netgraph implementation)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Maksim</given>
          <common>Yevmenkin</common>
        </name>

        <email>m_evmenkin@yahoo.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>

      <p>I'm slowly making progress. The second engineering release is
        available for download at
        http://www.geocities.com/m_evmenkin/ngbt-fbsd-20020506.tar.gz</p>

      <p>This release includes support for H4 UART transport layer, Host
        Controller Interface (HCI), Link Layer Control and Adaptation
        Protocol (L2CAP) and Bluetooth sockets layer. It also comes
        with several user space utilities that can be used to configure
        and test Bluetooth devices.</p>

      <p>I'm currently working on RFCOMM protocol implementation (Serial
        port emulation over Bluetooth link). My next goal is to port
        Service Discovery Protocol (SDP) implementation from BlueZ
        (http://bluez.sf.net). I'm also thinking about adding USB device
        support (as soon as i find/buy hardware).</p>

      <p>Issues: 1) Bluetooth hardware; I have couple PC-CARDs that i use
        for development and testing purposes, but i'd love to have more.
        2) Time; My regular day job kicked in, so i will be spending more
        time doing stuff i'm getting paid for.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD C99 &amp; POSIX Conformance Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mike</given>

          <common>Barcroft</common>
        </name>

        <email>mike@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <common>FreeBSD-Standards Mailing List</common>
        </name>

        <email>standards@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/c99/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since the last status report, two developers working on utility
        conformance were given commit access to the FreeBSD CVS repository
        to help expedite development.  As a result, the following utilities
        have been brought up to conformance, they include: csplit(1),
        env(1), expr(1), fold(1), join(1), m4(1), mesg(1), paste(1),
        patch(1), pr(1), uuencode(1), uuexpand(1), and xargs(1).  The
        printf(1) utility was brought up to conformance with the 1992
        edition of POSIX.2, with further development planned.</p>

      <p>On the header front, much progress has been made.  Specifically,
        infrastructure to control visibility of components of a header, based
        on the standard requested by an application, has been added to
        &lt;sys/cdefs.h&gt;.  Some work has been completed on renovating the
        way types are defined.  This has lead to the creation of
        &lt;sys/_types.h&gt;.  Further improvements such as the merger of
        &lt;machine/ansi.h&gt; and &lt;machine/types.h&gt; are planned.
        Additionally, the headers: &lt;strings.h&gt;, &lt;string.h&gt;, and
        &lt;sys/un.h&gt; have been made to conform to POSIX.1-2001.</p>

      <p>On the API front, scanf(3) has received support for 5 new length
        modifiers (hh, j, ll, t, and z).  A patch to implement two
        additional conversion specifiers (j and z) has been developed for
        printf(9) and is expected to be committed soon.</p>

      <p>In other news, the project's web site has been moved to the main
        FreeBSD site.  It is now available at the URL at the top of this
        status report.  Please update your bookmarks.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Netgraph ATM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Harti</given>

          <common>Brandt</common>
        </name>

        <email>brandt@fokus.fhg.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>

      <url href="http://www.fokus.fhg.de/research/cc/cats/employees/hartmut.brandt/ngatm/index.html">Introduction to NgAtm</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Version 1.1 for FreeBSD-current is now available. It includes
        the SNMP-daemon package bsnmp, the driver package ngatmbase,
        the UNI4.0 signaling package ngatmsig and the network emulation
        package ngatmnet. NgAtm allows both to build applications running
        directly on top of ATM and to use ATM-Forum LAN emulation to
        use IP over ATM. Currently we are working on a simple switch module,
        that implements the network side signaling and ILMI as well as
        simple routing and call admission control.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>GNOME Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joe</given>

          <common>Marcus</common>
        </name>

        <email>marcus@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome">FreeBSD GNOME Project
      homepage.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The GNOME project has seen quite a few changes lately.  For one,
        the author of this update has recently been given "The Bit."
        Joe Marcus Clarke now has CVS access, and is working primarily
        on the GNOME project.  Joe has been closing a good deal of GNOME
        PRs, as well as patching some of the existing GNOME 1.4
        components.</p>

      <p>The GNOME 2 porting effort continues on.  We have completed porting
        of the GNOME 2.0 API, and are 75% complete on porting the full
        GNOME 2.0 desktop.  When complete, GNOME 1.4 and GNOME 2.0 will
        be co-resident in the ports tree.  Both APIs can be installed
        concurrently in the same PREFIX, but the respective desktops
        will remain mutually independent.  Maxim Sobolev is working
        on adapting bsd.gnome.mk to handle both versions of the desktop
        in an elegant fashion.</p>

      <p>Not to be left out, the existing GNOME 1.4 components have received
        numerous updates to keep them in sync with the stable distfiles
        on gnome.org.  We have seen many "1.0" milestone releases including
        the most recent AbiWord 1.0.0.  In the next few weeks, we will be
        making sure all the GNOME 1.4 components build correct packages
        on bento so that GNOME 1.4 will be on the 4.6-RELEASE CD.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD/KGI</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Nicholas</given>

          <common>Souchu</common>
        </name>

	<email>nsouch@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~nsouch/ggiport.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> FreeBSD/KGI started last year after the port of GGI to VGL.
        KGI (Kernel Graphic Interface) is a kernel infrastructure providing user
        applications with access to hardware graphic resources (dma,
        irqs, mmio). KGI is already available under Linux as a separate
        project. The FreeBSD/KGI project aims at integrating KGI
        in the FreeBSD kernel. Mostly a port for now, but optimized for
        FreeBSD in the future. Currently FreeBSD/KGI is under development
        and the code is only available for reading, compiling but not running.
        More interesting are design hints found at the project URL.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Libh</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Antoine</given>
          <common>Beaupr&#351;</common>
        </name>

	<email>anarcat@anarcat.ath.cx</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>
          <common>Langer</common>
        </name>

	<email>alex@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Nathan</given>
          <common>Ahlstrom</common>
        </name>

	<email>nra@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/libh.html">Main project page.</url>

    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We now have a loadable mfsroot floppy. It contains just the
	diskeditor (which is really a disk partitioner) which has been
	enhanced and is probably in its final form. It's been geared
	towards making the newfs(1) and mount(1) steps separate dialogs, so
	it reduceed its complexity. A basic fstab class has been
	implemented to manipulate /etc/fstab and mountpoint. This might
	find a use outside libh, by the way. Libh package format is still
	incomplete and somehow buggy, so it's my next target.</p>

      <p>There is a API documentation effort underway with the help of
	doxygen(1), so there's now more documentation for people that want
	to get started with libh.</p>

      <p>All this lead me to prepare the release of another alpha
	preview of libh that will shortly be available in the ports
	collection (0.2.2). Also, a new committer (okumoto) has joined the
	project (as well as I) and he is currently working on cleaning up
	the build system. It's been a few months without news, so this
	probably seemed a bit long, but don't worry, we still need your
	help to really get this going!</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>jp.FreeBSD.org daily SNAPSHOTs project</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Makoto</given>
          <common>Matsushita</common>
        </name>
	<email>matusita@jp.FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://snapshots.jp.FreeBSD.org/">Project Webpage</url>
      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/snapshots/">Project Webpage (in Japanese)</url>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>There are several new topics, including: Source Code Tour is now
	separated into kernel part and userland part, yet another snapshots
	from RELENG_4_x branch (currently 4.5-RELEASE-p4), add several
	packages including XFree86 4.x to installation CD-ROM, new
	cdboot-only ISO image, fix breakage of duplex.iso, etc.  See also
	the project webpage for more detail.  Also, I have a plan to add
	FreeBSD/alpha distribution to this project -- stay tuned.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>KAME</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Shinsuke</given>
          <common>SUZUKI</common>
        </name>

	<email>suz@kame.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.kame.net/">KAME Project Home Page</url>
      <url href="http://www.kame.net/roadmap-2002.html">KAME Project Roadmap</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p> KAME Project has been extended until March 2004, and we decided the project
	roadmap for these two years.  The first one year is for implementation, and the
	remaining year is for feedback of our results into other BSD projects (please refer
	to the above URL for further detail).
	Great change is lack of NAT-PT support due to a lack of human resource, although
	KAME snap still contains it as it is.</p>

      <p> SUZUKI Shinsuke (suz@kame.net) has begun working for KAME and FreeBSD merge task in
	cooperation with Umemoto-san (ume@FreeBSD.org).
	Some of KAME stuff (critical bug fix, newest ports for pim6sd and racoon, etc)
	has been merged into 4-stable in this April.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Audit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Reiter</common>
        </name>
	<email>arr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>TrustedBSD Audit Mailing List</given>
	</name>
	<email>trustedbsd-audit@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD
main web page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Over the past couple of months, progress has pretty much stopped
	until very recently.  The past few changes to the audit code were
	update the usage of zones to UMA zones, cleanup some old cruft,
	and start toying with the idea of having an audit write thread
	implemented as an ithd.  The next step is to decide two realistic
	approaches to the where the records will be dumped -- whether that
	is to a local disk or fed up to userland and then dealt with.
	After that, the goal will be to expand the number of events that
	are being audited, while also working in some performance testing
	procedures.  I will be posting to trustedbsd-audit about the recent
	changes shortly.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD MAC</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>TrustedBSD Discussion Mailing List</given>
	</name>
	<email>trustedbsd-discuss@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD main web page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Over the last three months, there has been a lot of activity
	in the TrustedBSD MAC tree.  An initial commit of the SEBSD
	code (NSA FLASK and SELinux implementation) was made; many
	MAC policies previously linked directly to the kernel via
	kernel options were moved to kernel modules; the flexibility
	of the framework was improved relating to the life cycle of
	object labels; additional labeling and access control hooks
	were introduced; new policies were introduced to demonstrate
	the flexibility of the framework (including a cleanup of
	inter-process authorization, additional VFS hooks, improved
	support for multilabel filesystems, network booting, IPv6,
	IPsec, support for "peer" labels on stream sockets).
	Current modules include Biba integrity policy, MLS
	confidentiality policy, Type Enforcement, "BSD Extended"
	(permitting firewall-like rulesets for filesystem protection),
	"ifoff" (limit interface communication by policy),
	mac_seeotheruids (limit visibility of processes/etc of other
	users), "babyaudit" (a simple audit implementation), and
	SEBSD (FLASK/SELinux port).</p>
      <p>Over the next month, a final move to completely dynamic
	labeling will be made, permitting policies to introduce new
	state relating to process credentials, vnodes, sockets,
	mounts, interfaces, and mbufs at run-time, allowing a broad
	range of flexible label-driven policies to be developed.
	In addition, application APIs will be re-designed and
	re-implemented so as to better support a fully dynamic
	policy framework.  We plan to make an initial prototype
	patchset available for review in June, with the intent of
	committing that patchset in mid-June.</p>
      <p>Updated prototype code may be retrieved from the TrustedBSD
	CVS trees on cvsup10.FreeBSD.org.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PAM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>
          <common>Murray</common>
        </name>
	<email>markm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dag-Erling</given>
	  <common>Sm&#370;rgrav</common>
        </name>
	<email>des@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~des/pam/pam-2002-03.html">March 2002 PAM activity report.</url>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~des/pam/pam-2002-04.html">April 2002 PAM activity report.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The painful parts are now completed, with all authentication-
	related utilities converted to PAM (except for those cases where
	it doesn't make sense, like Kerberos- or OPIE-specific
	commands).  OpenPAM is complete (except for a few missing man
	pages) and seems to work well.</p>

      <p>For more details, see the activity reports linked to above.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>OpenSSH</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dag-Erling</given>
	  <common>Sm&#370;rgrav</common>
        </name>
        <email>des@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>OpenSSH has been upgraded to 3.1, and the kinks seem to have
        been worked out by now.  OpenSSH will now use PAM for both ssh1
        and ssh2 authentication.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>KSE</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Julian</given>

          <common>Elischer</common>
        </name>

        <email>julian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jonthan</given>
	  <common>Mini</common>
	</name>
	<email>mini@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~julian/" />
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~jasone/kse/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KSE project had floundered due to lack of development
        time for awhile, but has been picked up recently by
        Jonathan Mini. Currently, the main focus is to prepare
        the "milestone 3" code for inclusion into -CURRENT.</p>

      <p>The project is still working towards "milestone 4"
	(allowing threads from the same process to run on
	multiple CPUs), which should be significantly easier
	now due to work done by the SMPng project over the past
	several months.</p>

      <p>Help could be used in several areas of the project,
	especially with porting the libc_r (pthreads) library
	to KSE's threading model.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>NEWCARD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>NEWCARD support tried to merge CardBus functions with PCI
	functions, but that failed to properly route interrupts.  A
	branch for the merge was created and will be merged into the
	main line at a later date.  Too many other things going on in my
	life to make much progress.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Wi Hostap</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>

          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>

	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work on the host access point support for the Prism2 and
        Prism2.5 based wireless cards has been integrated into the
        kernel.  This work is largely based on Thomas Skibo's initial
        implementation.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Fibre Channel</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Matthew</given>
          <common>Jacob</common>
          </name>
        <email>mjacob@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~mjacob/fibre_channel.html">Project Status Page.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Continued bug fixing and hardening for this last few months.</p>
        <p>Future work will include making target mode work correctly and fast.</p>
        <p>The LSI-Logic chipset's MPT Fusion driver is also being evaluated.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Athlon MTRR Problems</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>David</given>

          <common>Malone</common>
        </name>

        <email>dwmalone@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD MTRR code has been made more robust against
	unexpected values sometimes found in the Athlon's Memory
	Type Range Registers. Problems with these values had prevented
	XFree 4.2 running on some motherboards. Experimentation indicates
	that these undocumented values may control the mapping of
	BIOS/ROMs or have something to do with SMM. If anyone can provide
	details of what these values mean, can they
	please let me know, so the MTRR code can be completed. </p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>IPMI Tools for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Doug</given>

          <common>White</common>
        </name>

	<email>dwhite@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~dwhite/ipmi/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>IPMI Tools for FreeBSD is a collection of C and Python
	applications and modules for exploring the information available
	via the Intelligent Platform Management Interface (IPMI), as
	implemented on server motherboards by Intel and HP. IPMI is an
	open standard with patent protection for adopters which defines
	standard interfaces to on-board management hardware. The
	management hardware consists of a CPU, sensors such as temperature
	probes and fan speeds, and repositories such as the System Event
	Log and Field-Replaceable Unit (FRU) inventory, and other system
	information. </p>

      <p>A basic set of tools was recently made available which uses the
	KCS and SMIC system interfaces to retrieve the System Event Log,
	FRU repository, and system sensors. Additional features are
	currently under research. Suggestions for additional features and
	programs are greatly appreciated. </p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PowerPC Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Benno</given>

          <common>Rice</common>
        </name>

	<email>benno@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://jeamland.net/~benno/powerpc-boot.txt">Current boot
messages.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The PowerPC port is moving ahead.  It can now mount a root file system
	and exec init, but fails when trying to map init's text segment in.  I'm
	hoping to have it starting my fake "Hello, world!" init soon, after which
	I plan to try and get some libc bits in place so that I can build /bin
	and /sbin and try to get to actual single-user.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>jpman project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kazuo</given>
          <common>Horikawa</common>
        </name>

	<email>horikawa@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/man-jp/">
	jpman project page both for users and developers (in Japanese)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>4.5-RELEASE Japanese manpage package, ja-man-doc-4.5.tgz, once
	published with OpenSSH 2.3 (as reported by previous status
	report) on January 31, is replaced with new package with OpenSSH
	2.9 based manpages on March 3.  Since then, we have been
	updating Japanese manpages for 4.6-RELEASE.  For new translation
	and massive update, we have been making a lot of effort.</p>
      <p>Continuing section 3 updating has 73% finished.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>"GEOM" - generalized block storage manipulation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

	<email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~phk/Geom/">Old concept paper here.</url>

    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The GEOM code has gotten so far that it beats our current code
	in some areas while still lacking in others.  Work continues on
	a generalized interface for "magic data" (boot blocks, disklabels
	MBR's etc) manipulation from userland.</p>
      <p>With GEOM enabled in the kernel any FreeBSD platform will now
	recognize PC style MBR's, i386 disklabels, alpha disklabels,
	PC98 extended MBRs and SUN/Solaris style disklabels.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD ARM Port</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stephane E.</given>
          <common>Potvin</common>
        </name>
	<email>sepotvin@videotron.ca</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://pages.infinit.net/sepotvin" />
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>Since the last progress report, the initialization code was much
	cleaned (thanks to NetBSD's acort32 port) and partial DDB support as
	been added.  I'm now struggling to put the pmap module into a
	working state.  The latest patch set only includes the
	initialization changes.  I did some tries to get what I had so far
	working on my iPAQ without much successes (downloading a kernel
	over a serial link is way too painful). If anyone has had success in
	getting any iPAQ to work as a USB storage device under *BSD please
	contact me.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>locking up pcb's in the networking stack</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jeffrey</given>

          <common>Hsu</common>
        </name>

	<email>hsu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>I've been mentoring someone on locking up the protocol control
	blocks in the networking stack.  She has already finished TCP and
	UDP and I'm currently reviewing the patch with her and going over
	some networking lock order issues.  Locking up raw protocol
	interface control blocks follows next.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Network interface cloning and modularity</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for stf(4), faith(4), and loopback interfaces has been
	committed to current.  The stf and faith support has been MFC'd.
	In current the API has changed to move unit allocation into the
	generic cloning code reducing the amount of support code required
	in each driver.  Code improvements to increase our API
	compatibility with NetBSD will be committed soon along with cloning
	support for discard interfaces and ppp(4) interfaces.</p>
      <p>Thanks to <email>mux@FreeBSD.org</email> for the loopback support
	and unit allocation cleanups.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>IA64 Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Peter</given>
          <common>Wemm</common>
        </name>
	<email>peter@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>

      <p>IA64 has had a busy few months.  Aside from gcc, we are now fully
	self hosting on IA64.  Doug Rabson has performed his magic and
	implemented the execution of 32 bit i386 application binaries
	although more work remains to be done to make ld-elf.so.1 happy
	with the different underlying page size.  We have been using the
	i386 perforce binary to do actual development work and submit from
	the ia64 systems themselves.  Marcel Moolenaar has been working on
	SMP and machine-check support.  We have been running SMP kernels
	amazingly reliably on our development boxes for quite some time now.
	syscons is now functional.  We have produced a self-booting
	run-root-on-cdrom ISO image (idea taken from the sparc64 folks) that
	has been used to manually self install an IA64 system from a blank
	disk.  Aside from a few minor loose ends we now have complete 'make
	world' functionality.  sysinstall works on ia64.  We plan on
	producing a semi-respectable boot/install cdrom image shortly.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>GCC 3.1</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>David</given>
          <common>O'Brien</common>
        </name>
	<email>obrien@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>As of Thur May 9th, 2002 FreeBSD 5-CURRENT is now using a GCC 3.1
	prerelease snapshot as the system C compiler.  At this time of
	cutting over, the compiler is working well on i386, Alpha, Sparc64,
	and IA-64 for building world.  There is a known problem with our
	atomic ops on Alpha that prevents a GCC 3.1 built kernel from
	booting.</p>

      <p>Currently the C++ support libraries (libstdc++, et.al.) does not
	build and thus prevents the system C++ compiler from being used.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Release Engineering</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <common>Release Engineering</common>
        </name>

	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The release engineering team released FreeBSD <a
        href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/5.0R/DP1/announce.html">5.0-DP1</a>
	on 8 April 2002.  This Developer Preview gives developers and
	other interested parties a chance to help test some of the new
	features to appear in 5.0-RELEASE.  This distribution has known
	bugs and areas of instability, and should only be used for
	(non-production) testing and development.</p>

      <p>The next releases of FreeBSD will be 4.6-RELEASE (scheduled for
	1 June 2002) and 5.0-DP2 (scheduled for 25 June 2002).
	Information on the release schedules and more can be found on
	the team's new area on the FreeBSD Web site (see the URL
	above).</p>

      <p>Finally, the team has gained two new members: Brian Somers and
	Bruce A. Mah.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>ppp RADIUS/MS-CHAP support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brian</given>

          <common>Somers</common>
        </name>

	<email>brian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>libradius now supports RADIUS vendor attribute extensions and
	user-ppp is now capable of doing MS-CHAP authentication via a RADIUS
	server.  A new net/freeradius port has been created for support of
	MS-CHAP in a RADIUS server.</p>

      <p>MS-CHAPv2 support will be added soon.</p>

      <p>The work is sponsored by Monzoon.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Improving FreeBSD Startup Scripts</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Doug</given>
          <common>Barton</common>
        </name>
	<email>dougb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mike</given>
          <common>Makonnen</common>
        </name>
	<email>makonnen@pacbell.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gordon</given>
          <common>Tetlow</common>
        </name>
	<email>gordont@gnf.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://home.pacbell.net/makonnen/rcng.html" />
      <url href="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/FreeBSD-rc/" />
      <url href="http://www.mewburn.net/luke/bibliography.html" />
      <url href="http://www.netbsd.org/Documentation/rc/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Mike Makonnen has done quite a bit of excellent work on porting the
        scripts from FreeBSD into the NetBSD framework. The next step seems
        to be to try to reduce the amount of diffs between our implementation
        and the original set from NetBSD.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>

          <common>Baldwin</common>
        </name>

	<email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<email>smp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>The SMPng project has been picking up steam in the last few
        months thankfully.  In February, Seigo Tanimura-san committed
        the first round of process group and session locking.  Alfred
        Perlstein also added locking to most of the pipe
        implementation.  In March, Alfred fixed several problems with
        the locking for select() and pushed down Giant some in several
        system calls.  Andrew Reiter added locking for kernel module
        metadata, and Jeff Roberson wrote a new SMP-friendly slab
        allocator to replace both the zone allocator and the in-kernel
        malloc().  The use of the critical section API was cleaned up
        to not be abused as replacements for disabling and enabling
        interrupts.  Also, Matt Dillon optimized the MD portion of the
        critical section code on the i386 architecture.  Several other
        subsystems were also locked in April as well.  See the SMPng
        website and todo list for more details.</p>

      <p>Some of the current works in progress include locking for the
        kernel linker by Andrew Reiter and light-weight interrupt
        threads for the i386 by Bosko Milekic.  Seigo Tanimura-san,
        Alfred Perlstein, and Jeffrey Hsu are also working on locking
        down various pieces of the networking stack.  Alan Cox has
        started working on fixing the existing locking in the VM
        subsystem and moving bits of it out from under Giant.  John
        Baldwin has written an implementation of turnstiles as well as
        adaptive mutexes in the jhb_lock Perforce branch.  The
        adaptive mutexes appear to be stable on i386, alpha, and
        sparc64, but the turnstile code still contains several tricky
        lock order reversals.  John also plans to commit the
        p_canfoo() API change to use td_ucred in the very near future
        and then finish the task of making ktrace(4) use a worker
        thread.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>New mount(2) API</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

	<email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Maxime</given>

          <common>Henrion</common>
        </name>

	<email>mux@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The patch for the new mount API has now been committed to the
        tree.  Several filesystems also have been converted to this
        new mount API, namely procfs, linprocfs, fdescfs and devfs.
        I'm working on converting more filesystems to nmount, and
        actually already have UFS done.  It has not been committed yet
        to avoid conflicting with the UFS2 work, but it should hit the
        tree soon.  Manpages are still missing at the moment because
        I had to modify the API slightly.  I hope to have them done
        soon now.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD Developer Summit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/events/2002/bsdcon-devsummit.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The second FreeBSD Developer Summit, held following the BSD
	Conference in San Francisco in February, was a great success.  Around
	40 developers attended in person, another five by phone, and many
	others by webcast.  During a marathon-esque eight hour session, a
	variety of development topics were discussed, including adding
	inheritance to the KOBJ system, ports to new architectures,
	adaptations of the toolchain for new architectures, the GEOM
	extensible storage device framework, upcoming changes to the network
	stack, TrustedBSD features, KSE, SMPng, and the release engineering
	schedule.  This event was sponsored by DARPA and NAI Labs, with
	webcasting provided by Joe Karthauser, bandwidth provided by Yahoo!.
	Planning for future such events is now underway; a summary/transcript
	of discussion may be found at the URL above.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
