<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2013</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between October and
      December 2013.  This is the last of four reports planned for
      2013.</p>

    <p>The last quarter of 2013 was very active for the &os;
      community, much like the preceding quarters.  Many advances were
      made in getting &os; to run on ARM-based System-on-Chip boards
      like Cubieboard, Rockchip, Snapdragon, S4, Freescale i.MX6, and
      Vybrid VF6xx.  &os; is also becoming a better platform for Xen
      and the Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud.  There are plans for &os;
      to become a fully supported compute host for OpenStack.  The I/O
      stack has again received some performance boosts on
      multi-processor systems through work touching the CAM and GEOM
      subsystems, and through better adaptation of UMA caches to
      system memory constraints for ZFS.  The &os; Foundation did an
      excellent job in this quarter, and many of their sponsored
      projects like VT-d and UEFI support, iSCSI stack, Capsicum, and
      auditdistd are about to complete. At the same time, new projects
      like Automounter and Intel GPU updates have just been launched.
      The Newcons project has been merged into -CURRENT, which will
      make it possible to finally move to the latest version of X.Org
      in the Ports Collection. Efforts are also under way to improve
      testing with Jenkins and Kyua.  It is an exciting time for users
      and developers of &os;!</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 37 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering between January and
      March 2014 is April 7th, 2014.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>CBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Oleg</given>
	  <common>Ginzburg</common>
	</name>
	<email>olevole@olevole.ru</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdstore.ru"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/olevole/cbsd"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>CBSD is another &os; jail management solution, aimed at
	combining various features, such as <tt>racct(8)</tt>,
	<tt>vnet</tt>, <tt>zfs(8)</tt>, <tt>carp(4)</tt>, and
	<tt>hastd(8)</tt>, into a single tool.  This provides a more
	comprehensive way to build application servers using
	pre-installed jails with a typical set of software, and requires
	minimal effort to configure.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Proper English translation of the website and the
	documentation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>&os; Test Suite</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Julio</given>
	  <common>Merino</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmmv@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/TestSuite">Project page</url>
      <url href="http://kyua1.nyi.FreeBSD.org/">Continuous testing infrastructure</url>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-testing/2013-December/000109.html">Mailing list announcement</url>
      <url href="http://julipedia.meroh.net/2013/12/introducing-freebsd-test-suite.html">Blog post</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Test Suite project aims to equip &os; with a
	comprehensive test suite that is easy to run out of the box and
	during the development of the system.  The test suite is
	installed into <tt>/usr/tests/</tt> and the <tt>kyua(1)</tt>
	command-line tool (<tt>devel/kyua</tt> in the Ports Collection)
	is used to run them.</p>

      <p>The benefits of having a test suite that is easy to use and
	continuously run are obvious: regressions can be caught sooner
	rather than later and the Release Engineering Team can better
	assess the quality of the tree before deciding to cut a release.
	Additionally, because we choose to install the tests, we allow
	any end user to perform sanity checks on new installations of
	the system on their particular hardware configuration &mdash; a
	very attractive thing to do when deploying production
	servers.</p>

      <p>During the last few months, we have added the necessary pieces to
	the build system to support building and installing test programs of
	various kinds. To demonstrate the functionality of these, some test
	programs were added and others were migrated from the old testing tree
	in <tt>tools/regression/</tt> to the new layout for tests.</p>

      <p>The current test suite should be seen as a proof of concept at this
	point: it is only composed of a small set of test programs and the goal
	is to get the infrastructure in place before mass-migrating existing
	test code and/or importing external tests.</p>

      <p>As part of this work, two new releases of Kyua were published.
	Of special interest is the addition of a TAP-compliant backend so
	that existing tests from <tt>tools/regression/</tt> can be
	plugged into the test suite with minimum effort.</p>

      <p>As of December 31st, the basic continuous testing
	infrastructure is up and running, see the links section for the
	home page.  For further information, please see the related
	announcement and blog post on the subject (also in the links
	section).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We have three machines for the test cluster.  At the
	moment, only one of them is in use to continuously test amd64 on
	both <tt>head</tt> and <tt>stable/10</tt>.  We need to figure
	out the right level of parallelization to put other machines to
	use &mdash; but a first easy cut may be to just test different
	architectures (with the help of QEMU).</task>

      <task>Related to the above, the Kyua reporting engine needs
	significant tuning to make the reports nice and clean.  Ideally,
	Kyua should be able to coalesce results from different runs into
	a single location and generate cohesive reports out of them.
	Fixing this is a high priority.</task>

      <task>A tutorial on writing tests for &os; has been proposed for
	AsiaBSDCon&nbsp;2014.  The outcome of the proposal is still
	unknown, but stay tuned!</task>

      <task>Port, port, and port more tests to the new test suite.  A
	test suite is worthless if it does not validate stuff.  Stay tuned
	for a request for help once we have put all basic pieces in
	place and have streamlined the migration process.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Cubieboard{1,2}</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ganbold</given>
	  <common>Tsagaankhuu</common>
	</name>
	<email>ganbold@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://github.com/tsgan/allwinner_a10/blob/master/if_emac.c">EMAC driver code</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Cubieboard is a single-board computer based on the AllWinner
	A10 SoC, popular on cheap tablets, phones and media PCs.  The
	second version enhances the board mainly by replacing the
	AllWinner A10 SoC with an AllWinner A20 which contains 2 ARM
	Cortex-A7 MPCore CPUs and 2 Mali-400 GPUs (Mali-400MP2).  In the
	last few months, work has continued on their &os; port, and
	some work was done on the EMAC 10/100 Ethernet driver (see
	link).  The driver is now in a good shape, however the RX side
	is very slow and there is need to have an external DMA driver that
	can be used in this case.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Newer ARM Boards</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ganbold</given>
	  <common>Tsagaankhuu</common>
	</name>
	<email>ganbold@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/FreeBSD/arm/Radxa%20Rock">&os; on Radxa Rock</url>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/256949"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/tsgan/qualcomm">Some preliminary sources for Snapdragon board IFC6410</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Rockchip is a series of SoC (System on Chip) integrated
	circuits that are mainly for embedded systems applications in
	mobile entertainment devices such as smartphones, tablets, e-books,
	set-top boxes, media players, personal video, and MP3 players.
	Due to their evolution from the MP3/MP4 player market, most
	Rockchip ICs feature advanced media decoding logic but lack
	integrated cellular radio basebands.  Initial support for the
	Rockchip RK3188 (Quad core Cortex A9) SoC is committed to
	<tt>head</tt>.  Now &os; runs on Radxa Rock and it supports
	the following peripherals:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Existing DWC OTG driver in host mode</li>
	<li>GPIO</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Some work was also done on initial support for the Qualcomm
	Snapdragon S4 SoC, featuring the Krait CPU, which is considered
	a "platform" for use in smartphones, tablets, and smartbook
	devices.  Krait has many similarities with the ARM Cortex-A15
	CPU and is also based on the ARMv7 instruction set.  A minimal
	console driver was written, and &os;'s early boot messages can
	be now seen on the serial console.  The timer driver works too,
	and the boot now stops at the mountroot prompt.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Postmaster Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Postmaster Team</name>
	<email>postmaster@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/svn-src-stable-10"/>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/ctm-src-10"/>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/ctm-src-10-fast"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en/articles/committers-guide/pgpkeys.html">OpenPGP Keys section in the Committer's Guide</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the fourth quarter of 2013, the &os; Postmaster Team has
	implemented the following items that may be interest of the
	general public:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Retired the <tt>freebsd-aic7xxx</tt> mailing list.</li>

	<li>Created a <tt>graphics-team</tt> alias, requested by Niclas
	  Zeising.</li>

	<li>Worked with the &os; Port Management Team to set up
	  <tt>portmgr-lurkers</tt> so port managers can move addresses
	  between those two aliases at their discretion.</li>

	<li>Created the lists associated with the new <tt>stable/10</tt>
	  branch: <tt>svn-src-stable-10</tt>, <tt>ctm-src-10</tt>, and
	  <tt>ctm-src-10-fast</tt>.</li>

	<li>Redirected the <tt>vbox</tt> alias to the <tt>emulation</tt>
	  list, requested by Bernhard Fröhlich.</li>

	<li>Continued a discussion on current and possible future mail
	  and spam filtering.</li>

	<li>Disbanded <tt>lua</tt> and transferred it to Baptiste
	  Daroussin, requested by Matthias Andree and Baptiste
	  Daroussin.</li>

	<li>Modified the list moderators/administrators for
	  <tt>ports-secteam</tt>, requested by Dag-Erling Smørgrav.</li>

	<li>Assisted Warren Block with an update to the "OpenPGP Keys
	  for &os;" section of the Committer's Guide.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Xfce/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>&os; Xfce Team</name>
        <email>xfce@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Xfce">The &os; Xfce Team's wiki page</url>
      <url href="https://people.freebsd.org/~olivierd/xfce-core-unstable.html">Core</url>
      <url href="https://people.freebsd.org/~olivierd/parole-unstable.html">Parole</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xfce is a free software desktop environment for Unix and
	Unix-like platforms, such as &os;.  It aims to be fast and
	lightweight, while still being visually appealing and easy to
	use.  The &os; Xfce Team has kept most of the Xfce ports
	up-to-date, while fixing many issues along the way in this
	quarter.</p>

      <p>Currently, the following components with the following versions
	are available:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Applications:</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Orage (4.10.0)</li>
	  <li>Midori (0.5.6)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-terminal (0.6.3)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-parole (0.5.3, 0.5.4)</li>
	</ul>

	<li>Panel plugins:</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>xfce4-whiskermenu-plugin (1.2.0, 1.2.1, 1.2.2, 1.3.0)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-mailwatch-plugin (1.2.0)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-wmdock-plugin (0.6.0)</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>

      <p>We helped Midori's upstream switch from Waf (Python script)
	to CMake.  Xfce now also supports Gtk2, Gtk3, and the new
	WebKitGtk API, available from the 2.x branch, not present in our
	ports tree at the moment, though.  Most of the ports now use
	stage directories, with only some plugins left to convert.</p>

      <p>We also removed obsolete ports:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><tt>x11-themes/lila-xfwm4</tt> (Xfwm4 theme)</li>
	<li><tt>multimedia/xfce4-media</tt> (multimedia player)</li>
	<li><tt>net-im/xfce4-messenger-plugin</tt></li>
      </ul>

      <p>Besides, we followed the development of the Xfce core
	components and Parole closely.  See the links for documentation
	on how to upgrade those libraries.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix Midori's build on DragonFly, through DPorts.</task>

      <task>Fix build of the Granite framework (it is an extension to
	Gtk and Midori uses it) on &os;&nbsp;10 and <tt>head</tt>.
	Those are mostly LLVM failures.</task>

      <task>Add support for Berkeley DB 5 and higher to Orage.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Freescale i.MX6 processors</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ian</given>
	  <common>Lepore</common>
	</name>
	<email>ian@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-arm/2013-November/006877.html">Announcement of Wanboard support</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The i.MX range is a family of Freescale Semiconductor
	proprietary microprocessors for multimedia applications based on
	the ARM architecture and focused on low power consumption.  The
	i.MX6x series is based on the ARM Cortex A9 solo, dual, or quad
	cores.  Initial support for them has been committed to
	<tt>head</tt>, and merged to <tt>stable/10</tt>.  All members of
	the i.MX6 family (Solo, Dual, and Quad core) are supported, but
	SMP support on the multi-core SoCs has not yet been enabled.</p>

      <p>Initial driver support includes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>USB (EHCI)</li>
	<li>Ethernet (Gigabit)</li>
	<li>SD Card</li>
	<li>UART</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The initial hardware bringup was done on Wandboard hardware,
	see the announcement on <tt>freebsd-arm</tt> in the links section
	for more information.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Write drivers for additional on-chip hardware, including
	I2C, SPI, AHCI, audio, and video.</task>

      <task>Add support to &os;-crochet script to generate Wandboard
	images</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/10.0R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;10.0-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/VM-IMAGES/">&os;&nbsp;Virtual Machine Images</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os;&nbsp;Development Snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Release Engineering Team is finishing the
	10.0-RELEASE cycle.  The release cycle changed with two
	last-minute release candidate builds, each addressing
	fixes critical to include in the final release.</p>

      <p>The &os; 10.0-RELEASE cycle is expected to be completed by
	mid-January, approximately eight weeks behind the original
	schedule.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Centralized Panic Reporting</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Colin</given>
	  <common>Percival</common>
	</name>
	<email>cperciva@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/blog/2013-11-06-automated-freebsd-panic-reporting.html">Usage instructions</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>With the <tt>sysutils/panicmail</tt> port, a mechanism is now
	in place for automated submission of
	kernel panic reports to a central location.  It is hoped that
	this will prove useful, as similar systems have for other
	operating systems, in identifying common panics so that
	developers can be alerted and they can be fixed faster.</p>

      <p>In the first two months that this mechanism has been in place,
	28 kernel panics have been reported.  This is nowhere near enough
	to be useful, so readers are strongly encouraged to install the
	<tt>sysutils/panicmail</tt> port and follow the instructions to
	enable it.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Get more systems set up to automatically submit panic
	reports!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>UMA/ZFS and RPC/NFS Performance Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://docs.freebsd.org/cgi/mid.cgi?52894C92.60905">Discussion of the ZFS/UMA changes</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The performance of ZFS and NFS was suboptimal in &os;, so we
	have recently investigated some possible improvement paths.  The
	<tt>uma(9)</tt> memory allocator caching code was improved to
	adapt better to system memory constraints.  Combined with other
	virtual memory subsystem improvements done in the previous
	years, it should be safe to actively use <tt>uma(9)</tt> caches
	now.  Their use in ZFS for ZIO/ARC may be enabled via the
	<tt>vfs.zfs.zio.use_uma</tt> <tt>loader(8)</tt> tunable, which
	is now the default for amd64, where it is recommended.  Use of
	<tt>uma(9)</tt> caches for LZ4 compression buffers is
	unconditionally enabled on all architectures as it is has no
	serious drawbacks.  On systems with many CPUs, these changes
	doubled the performance in the benchmarks.</p>

      <p>Several areas of the NFS server stack (RPC, FHA, DRC) got a
	number of fixes and performance optimizations that significantly
	improve performance and reduce the CPU usage in a number of
	tests.  Together with the ZFS memory allocator changes mentioned
	above, it was possible to reach 200K NFS block read IOPS and 55K
	SPEC NFS IOPS.</p>

      <p>The code was committed to <tt>head</tt>.  The <tt>uma(9)</tt>
	ZFS commits have been already merged to <tt>stable/10</tt>, and
	the remainder will be done soon as well.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>iXsystems, Inc</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>The SPEC NFS test hits lock congestion on several global
	locks in the file system layer when a quite intensive
	<tt>READDIRPLUS</tt> NFS request is received.  Fixing this
	problem could improve performance on large systems even
	further.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>GEOM Direct Dispatch and Fine-Grained CAM Locking</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~mav/disk.pdf">Slides from EuroBSDCon 2013, also describing this project</url>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/260387">CAM improvements in the stable/10 branch</url>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/260385">GEOM improvements in the stable/10 branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The CAM and GEOM multi-processor scalability improvement
	project has completed.  The corresponding code has been committed
	to &os; <tt>head</tt> and recently merged to the
	<tt>stable/10</tt> branch; it shall appear in
	<tt>10.1-RELEASE</tt>.</p>

      <p>As part of this project, <tt>cam(4)</tt> (the ATA/SCSI subsystem)
	has received more fine-grained locking for better utilization of
	multi-core systems.  In addition, the locking in <tt>geom(4)</tt>
	(the block storage subsystem) has also been polished, and a new
	direct dispatch functionality was implemented to spread the load
	between multiple threads and processors, and reduce the number
	of context switches.</p>

      <p>Thanks to these <tt>cam(4)</tt> and <tt>geom(4)</tt> changes,
	the peak I/O rate has doubled on contemporary hardware, reaching
	up to 1,000,000&nbsp;IOPS!</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>iXsystems, Inc</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Some CAM controller drivers (SIMs) could also be optimized
	to get more benefits from this project, utilizing the new locking
	models and direct command completions from multiple interrupt
	threads.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/EC2</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Colin</given>
	  <common>Percival</common>
	</name>
	<email>cperciva@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/freebsd-on-ec2/">&os;/EC2 status page</url>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/blog/2013-12-09-FreeBSD-EC2-configinit.html">Configinit</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An Amazon Machine Image (AMI) is a special type of virtual
	appliance that is used to create a virtual machine within the
	Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud ("EC2").  It serves as the basic
	unit of deployment for services delivered using EC2.  Such AMIs
	are available for <tt>8.3-RELEASE</tt> and later &os; releases,
	and every ALPHA, BETA, and RC of &os;&nbsp;10.0.  Starting from
	&os;&nbsp;<tt>10.0-BETA1</tt>, &os;/EC2 images are running
	"fully supported" &os; binaries, and starting from
	&os;&nbsp;<tt>10.0-RC1</tt>, &os;/EC2 images include a
	<tt>"configinit"</tt> system for autoconfiguration using EC2
	user-data.</p>

      <p>Due to limitations of old (<tt>m1</tt>, <tt>m2</tt>,
	<tt>c1</tt>, <tt>t1</tt>) instance types,
	<tt>"Windows"</tt>-labelled images are required for those
	instance types; however all of the recent instances types
	&mdash; <tt>m3</tt> (general purpose), <tt>c3</tt> (high-CPU),
	and <tt>i2</tt> (high-I/O) &mdash; support &os; at the
	<tt>"unix"</tt> pricing rates.</p>

      <p>The maintainer of this platform considers it to be ready for
	production use.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Hand over the task of building &os; AMIs to the Release
	Engineering Team.</task>

      <task>Get Amazon to add <tt>"&os;"</tt> to the list of platforms
	supported by EC2, so that it can stop showing up as <tt>"Other
	Linux"</tt>.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Python Ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Python Team</name>
	<email>python@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Python">The &os; Python Team page</url>
      <url href="irc://freebsd-python@irc.freenode.net">IRC channel</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Python is a widely used general-purpose, high-level programming
	language.  For many operating systems, Python is a standard
	component; it ships with &os; as well.  A lot of progress has
	been made around the &os; Python ports in the last quarter.</p>

      <p>The <tt>devel/py-distribute</tt> port has been replaced by the
	refreshed <tt>devel/py-setuptools</tt> port, which comes with a
	lot of features that simplify the methods of installing Python
	packages.  The change also led us to install everything through
	Setuptools now, which resembles PyIP a bit and allows us to
	perform some major cleanup on the distutils installation
	behaviour.</p>

      <p>The implicit <tt>lang/python</tt> build and run-time dependency
	was removed from the ports infrastructure.  Every port now
	depends on a specific Python version or on the
	<tt>lang/python</tt> metaport.  This prevents compatibility
	issues for ports that depend on Python&nbsp;2.x OR
	Python&nbsp;3.x exclusively, but use the <tt>python</tt>
	command, which might point to a version of incompatible user
	choice.</p>

      <p>The <tt>lang/python27</tt> port was updated to version 2.7.6,
	and the <tt>lang/python33</tt> port was updated to version
	3.3.3, and the <tt>lang/pypy</tt> port was updated to version
	2.2.1.</p>

      <p>We are currently working on the necessary infrastructure quirks
	to support different Python versions for the same port.  Most of
	the work has been done and needs to be tested before it can be
	integrated.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Develop a high-level and lightweight Python Ports Policy.</task>

      <task>Add support for granular dependencies (for example
	<tt>&gt;=1.0</tt> or <tt>&lt;2.0</tt>).</task>

      <task>Look at what adding <tt>pip</tt> support looks like.</task>

      <task>Convert all <tt>USE_PYDISTUTILS=easy_install</tt> entries to
	<tt>yes</tt> and remove the use of <tt>easy_install</tt> from
	the ports infrastructure.</task>

      <task>More tasks can be found on the team's wiki page (see
	links).</task>
      </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; Host Support for OpenStack and OpenContrail</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grzegorz</given>
	  <common>Bernacki</common>
	</name>
	<email>gjb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michał</given>
	  <common>Dubiel</common>
	</name>
	<email>md@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafał</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.openstack.org"/>
      <url href="http://www.opencontrail.org"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/openstack-devstack"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/openstack-nova"/>
      <url href="https://github.com/Semihalf/contrail-vrouter"/>
      <url href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/nova/+spec/freebsd-compute-node"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenStack is a cloud operating system that controls large pools
	of compute, storage, and networking resources in a data center.
	OpenContrail is a network virtualization (SDN) solution
	comprising a network controller, a virtual router, and an
	analytics engine, which can be integrated with cloud
	orchestration systems like OpenStack or CloudStack.</p>

      <p>The goal of this work is to enable &os; as a fully supported
	compute host for OpenStack, using OpenContrail virtualized
	networking.  The main areas of development are the
	following:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>OpenStack compute driver (<tt>nova-compute</tt>) for the
	  &os; <tt>bhyve(4)</tt> hypervisor.</li>

	<li>OpenContrail vRouter (forwarding-plane kernel module) port
	  to &os;.</li>

	<li>Integration and performance optimizations.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The current state of development features a working demo of
	OpenStack with compute node components running on a &os; host:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The native <tt>bhyve(4)</tt> hypervisor is driven by a
	  <tt>nova-compute</tt> component for spawning guest instances
	  and a <tt>nova-network</tt> component for providing simple
	  networking between those guests.</li>

	<li>The <tt>nova-network</tt> approach (based on local host
	  bridging) is becoming an obsolete technology in OpenStack and
	  was used here only for demonstration and proof-of-concept
	  purposes, without exploring all the possible features.</li>

	<li>The main objective is to move to OpenContrail-based
	  networking, therefore becoming compliant with the modern
	  OpenStack networking API ("neutron").</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>Juniper Networks, Inc</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Decide how to integrate <tt>bhyve(4)</tt> with
	<tt>nova-compute</tt>, either natively or via the
	<tt>libvirt</tt> management layer.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>The LLDB Debugger</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/lldb"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>LLDB is the debugger in the LLVM family of projects.  It
	supports Mac OS X, Linux, and &os;, with ongoing work to support
	Windows.</p>

      <p>In the last quarter of 2013, LLDB gained support for live
	(<tt>ptrace(2)</tt>-based) debugging of multithreaded processes
	on &os;.  Initial &os; MIPS target support has also been
	committed, along with a number of endianness fixes in the
	general LLDB infrastructure.</p>

      <p>The LLDB snapshot in the &os; tree was updated to
	<tt>r196322</tt>.  Currently disabled by default, it will be
	enabled for <tt>amd64</tt> after the import of Clang&nbsp;3.4.
	In the interim, it may be enabled by adding <tt>WITH_LLDB=</tt>
	to <tt>src.conf(5)</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>DARPA/AFRL</sponsor>
    <sponsor>SRI International</sponsor>
    <sponsor>University of Cambridge</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Update the in-tree snapshot to build after the Clang 3.4
	import.</task>
      <task>Fix <tt>amd64</tt> watchpoints.</task>
      <task>Test and fix the <tt>i386</tt> port.</task>
      <task>Implement &os; ARM support.</task>
      <task>Add support for kernel debugging (live local and remote
	debugging, and core files).</task>
      <task>Fix the remaining test suite failures.</task>
      <task>Enable by default on the <tt>amd64</tt> architecture.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>UEFI Boot</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/UEFI">UEFI wiki page</url>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/base/projects/uefi/">UEFI project branch</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) provides boot-
	and run-time services for x86 computers, and is a replacement for
	the legacy BIOS.  This project will adapt the &os; loader and
	kernel boot process for compatibility with UEFI firmware, found
	on contemporary servers, desktops, and laptops.</p>

      <p>In 2013, The &os; Foundation sponsored Benno Rice for a short
	project to improve the UEFI bootloader.  This resulted in a
	working proof-of-concept in the UEFI project branch, but it was
	not ready to be merged to &os; <tt>head</tt>.</p>

      <p>Ed Maste has taken that original work and, with review feedback
	from Konstantin Belousov, been preparing it for integration into
	&os; <tt>head</tt>.  Some changes have been merged to
	<tt>head</tt> already.  The rest will be merged as they are
	refined.</p>

      <p>Intel provided a motherboard and CPU for the project, which
	proved invaluable for addressing bugs that did not appear while
	testing with the QEMU emulator.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Resolve a 32- versus 64-bit <tt>libstand(3)</tt> build issue.</task>
      <task>Merge kernel parsing of EFI memory map metadata.</task>
      <task>Integrate the EFI framebuffer with <tt>vt(9)</tt> (also
	known as Newcons).</task>
      <task>Connect <tt>efiloader</tt> to the build.</task>
      <task>Document manual installation for dual-boot configurations.</task>
      <task>Integrate UEFI configuration with the &os; installer.</task>
      <task>Support secure boot.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>GNOME/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; GNOME Team</name>
	<email>gnome@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/"/>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/ports/334661">Import of MATE</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>GNOME is a desktop environment and graphical user interface
	that runs on top of a computer operating system.  GNOME is part
	of the GNU Project and can be used with various Unix-like
	operating systems, including &os;.</p>

      <p>In this quarter, MATE&nbsp;1.6 was finally imported into the
	Ports Collection, thanks to the efforts of Jeremy Messenger.
	MATE is a desktop environment forked from the now-unmaintained
	code base of GNOME&nbsp;2, therefore it is basically a
	replacement for GNOME&nbsp;2.  Users wanting
	to keep GNOME&nbsp;2 as their desktop are advised to switch to MATE since
	GNOME&nbsp;2 will be replaced by GNOME&nbsp;3 in the near
	future.  This switch will be announced in advance, so people
	will have time to move to MATE if they have not already.  The
	complete MATE-based desktop environment can be installed via the
	<tt>x11/mate</tt> port, or, for a minimal install,
	<tt>x11/mate-base</tt>.</p>

      <p>Our home page is quite out of date.  An update for it for
	GNOME&nbsp;3.6 is underway.  Part of this update is rewriting
	and updating the old GNOME porting guide as a chapter of the
	Porter's Handbook.</p>

      <p>Another major task required for getting a bleeding-edge GNOME
	to build on &os; mostly out-of-the box is moving to JHbuild with
	some custom rules.  This is done to find and fix compile issues
	on other BSDs more quickly.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>GNOME&nbsp;2 ports still need to be sorted out to evaluate
	which GNOME&nbsp;2 components will be gone or be replaced with
	their newer GNOME&nbsp;3 versions.  This task is currently halted
	until we can get the documentation into a shape good enough to
	gather the issues and document the migration, including how
	to avoid the migration if the upgrade is not preferred.  (This
	does not mean we do not want to know about issues with
	upgrading, though).</task>

      <task>Help the X11 Team with Cairo&nbsp;1.12, since the next
	version of GNOME&nbsp;3 (3.12) will need an up-to-date version
	of Pango and GTK&nbsp;3.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Intel GPU Driver Update</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>This project will update the Intel graphics chipset driver,
	<tt>i915kms</tt>, to a recent snapshot of the Linux upstream
	code.  The update will provide at least 1.5 years of bugfixes
	from the Intel team, and introduce support for the newest
	hardware &mdash; in particular Haswell and ValleyView.  The
	IvyBridge code will also be updated.  The addition of several
	features which are required to update X.Org and Mesa
	is also planned.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Native iSCSI Stack</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierała</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Native%20iSCSI%20target"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>iSCSI is a popular block storage protocol.  Under this project,
	a new, fast, and reliable kernel-based iSCSI initiator (client)
	and target (server) have been implemented.</p>

      <p>During October to December, the work focused on performance and
	scalability.  The target and the initiator now spread the load
	over multiple kernel threads, and the locking is optimized to
	reduce contention.  This makes better use of multiple processor
	cores.</p>

      <p>Work to finish iSER support is ongoing.  All those
	optimizations will be gradually merged to <tt>head</tt> in
	February, and are expected to merged back to <tt>stable/10</tt>
	and finally arrive in <tt>10.1-RELEASE</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>BSDInstall ZFSBoot</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Allan</given>
	  <common>Jude</common>
	</name>
	<email>freebsd@allanjude.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Devin</given>
	  <common>Teske</common>
	</name>
	<email>dteske@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warren</given>
	  <common>Block</common>
	</name>
	<email>wblock@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-sysinstall" />
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/RootOnZFS/GPTZFSBoot/9.0-RELEASE">Original Root-on-ZFS instuctions on the &os; Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>BSDInstall has been the default installation program since
	&os;&nbsp;<tt>9.0-RELEASE</tt>.  However, it could not utilize
	one of the best features of &os;, ZFS.</p>

      <p>The ZFSBoot project started at EuroBSDCon&nbsp;2013 and reached
	stable status in December, just in time for
	&os;&nbsp;<tt>10.0-RELEASE</tt>.  Currently, ZFSBoot implements
	root-on-ZFS with 4k partition alignment, optional forced 4k
	sectors, optional <tt>geli(8)</tt> full disk encryption, and
	support for boot environments.</p>

      <p>As part of ZFSBoot, BSDInstall itself also received a number of
	updates, including enhanced debugging, more scriptability, a new
	keymap selection menu, and a number of other small changes to
	streamline the installation process.  The new keymap menu allows
	the user to test the selected keymap before continuing, to
	ensure it is the desired keymap.  Minor changes were made to the
	network configuration dialogues to make the identification of
	wireless interfaces easier.</p>

      <p>A number of additional features are also planned.  The
	user should be able to create additional datasets and adjust the properties on
	all datasets in an interactive menu.  There should also be integration with BSDConfig
	to allow users to install packages and the various other
	functionality that was previously provided by
	<tt>sysinstall</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Interactive dataset editor.</task>
      <task>Dataset property editor.</task>
      <task>Consider using shell <tt>geom(4)</tt> parser.</task>
      <task>BSDConfig integration.</task>
      <task>UFS as a file system option, to allow users to create
	encrypted UFS installs.</task>
      <task>Optionally make the boot pool UFS or reside on USB
	device(s).</task>
      <task>Further streamline the installation process.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Jenkins Continuous Integration for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Craig</given>
	  <common>Rodrigues</common>
	</name>
	<email>rodrigc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.ixsystems.com/whats-new/jenkins-bhyve-and-webdriver-continuous-integration-testing-on-freenas/">Vendor Summit presentation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>At the November 2013 &os; Vendor Summit, some work was
	presented that Craig Rodrigues has been doing with Continuous
	Integration and Testing at iXsystems.  Craig's presentation
	described how iXsystems is using modern best practices for
	building and testing the FreeNAS code.  Jenkins is a framework
	for doing continuous builds and integration that is used by
	hundreds of companies.  BHyve (BSD Hypvervisor) is the new
	virtual machine system which will be part of &os;&nbsp;10.
	Webdriver is a Python toolkit for testing web applications.  By
	combining these technologies, iXsystems is developing a modern
	and sophisticated workflow for testing and improving the quality
	of FreeNAS.</p>

      <p>Ed Maste from The &os; Foundation was interested in this work,
	and based on this interest, it is now being ported to &os;.
	Currently, a machine in the &os; cluster has been allocated for
	this purpose, where a <tt>bhyve(4)</tt>-based virtual machine
	was set up and Jenkins was installed.  The remainder is still in
	progress.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish setting up Jenkins.</task>
      <task>Add more builds to Jenkins.</task>
      <task>Integrate testing with Jenkins.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>X.Org on &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; X11 Team</name>
	<email>x11@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Graphics">X11 roadmap and supported hardware matrix</url>
      <url href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/ports/browser/trunk">Ports-related development repository</url>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-x11/2014-January/014003.html">CFT for Cairo 1.12 and 8.x survey</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The newer graphics stack (<tt>WITH_NEW_XORG</tt>) is now built
	by default on <tt>head</tt> and is provided as binary packages
	from the official &os; <tt>pkg(8)</tt> repository for
	<tt>11-CURRENT</tt>.  The major updates are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>X.Org server 1.12.</li>
	<li>Mesa 9.1.</li>
	<li>Recent Intel and Radeon X.Org drivers, using exclusively
	  the KMS kernel drivers available in &os;&nbsp;9.x (Intel) and &os;&nbsp;10.x
	  (Radeon).</li>
      </ul>

      <p>This change makes X.Org on &os; <tt>head</tt> work
	out-of-the-box on workstations and laptops based on recent Intel
	and Radeon GPUs.  &os;&nbsp;10.x will follow in a few weeks or
	months.</p>

      <p>Some software has started to require Cairo&nbsp;1.12, for
	example GTK+&nbsp;3.10 and Pango.  Unfortunately, this version
	of Cairo triggers a bug in the old Intel driver (2.7.1,
	installed when <tt>WITH_NEW_XORG</tt> is not set), which causes
	display artifacts.  A "Call For Testers" mail was posted on the
	<tt>freebsd-x11</tt> mailing-list (see the links above) to
	gather information about the behavior on other configurations
	(new Intel driver and non-Intel drivers).  As of this writing,
	the reports received talk about improvements or, at least, no
	change noticed.</p>

      <p>To better manage changes such as the <tt>WITH_NEW_XORG</tt> and
	the Cairo&nbsp;1.12 changes mentioned above, we asked on the
	<tt>freebsd-x11</tt> mailing-list if people are using
	&os;&nbsp;8.x on their desktop computers and why they do not
	upgrade to &os;&nbsp;9.x or 10.x.  So far, we received very few
	answers to this.</p>

      <p>The Radeon KMS driver in &os;&nbsp;10.x is now considered
	stable, especially now that integrated GPUs are properly
	initialized.  One of the next steps will be to merge this to
	<tt>stable/9</tt>.</p>

      <p>A "Graphics" wiki article (see links) was created to centralize
	and coordinate the work being done on both the ports and the
	kernel.  It contains the following important information:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>A roadmap of the team.</li>
	<li>A matrix of supported hardware.</li>
	<li>Instructions on upgrading to KMS.</li>
	<li>Project status and results.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>This starting page then points to project- and topic-specific
	articles where more detailed information is available.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Report why &os;&nbsp;8.x is still used on your desktop and
	why moving to &os;&nbsp;9.x or 10.x is not an option.</task>
      <task>Report about the Cairo&nbsp;1.12 update on your system.</task>
      <task>See the "Graphics" wiki page for up-to-date information.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>New Automounter</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierała</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Research and prototyping has begun on a new project to
	implement <tt>autofs(4)</tt> &mdash; an automounter filesystem
	&mdash; and its userland counterpart, <tt>automountd(8)</tt>.
	The idea is to provide a very similar user experience to the
	automounters available on Linux, MacOS X, and Solaris, including
	using the same map format.  The automounter will also integrate
	with directory services, such as LDAP.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Updated <tt>vt(9)</tt> System Console</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Aleksandr</given>
	  <common>Rybalko</common>
	</name>
	<email>ray@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Newcons">Project wiki page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Colloquially known as Newcons, <tt>vt(9)</tt> is a modern
	replacement for the existing, quite old, virtual terminal
	emulator called <tt>syscons(4)</tt>.  Initially motivated by the
	lack of Unicode support in <tt>syscons(4)</tt>, the project was
	later expanded to cover the new requirement of supporting Kernel
	Mode Switching (KMS).</p>

      <p>The project is now approaching completion and is ready for
	wider testing, as the related code was already merged to &os;
	<tt>head</tt>.  Hence, <tt>vt(9)</tt> can be tested easily by
	replacing the following two lines in the kernel config file:</p>

      <pre>device sc
device vga</pre>

      <p>with the following ones:</p>

      <pre>device vt
device vt_vga</pre>

      <p>Major highlights:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Unicode support.</li>
	<li>Double-width character support for CJK characters.</li>
	<li><tt>xterm(1)</tt>-like terminal emulation.</li>
	<li>Support for Kernel Mode Setting (KMS) drivers
	  (<tt>i915kms</tt>, <tt>radeonkms</tt>).</li>
	<li>Support for different fonts per terminal window.</li>
	<li>Simplified drivers.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Brief status of supported architectures and hardware:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>amd64 (VGA/<tt>i915kms</tt>/<tt>radeonkms</tt>) &mdash; works.</li>
	<li>ARM framebuffer &mdash; works.</li>
	<li>i386 (VGA/<tt>i915kms</tt>/<tt>radeonkms</tt>) &mdash; works.</li>
	<li>IA64 &mdash; untested.</li>
	<li>MIPS &mdash; untested.</li>
	<li>PPC and PPC64 &mdash; works, but without X.Org yet.</li>
	<li>SPARC &mdash; works on certain hardware (e.g., Ultra 5).</li>
	<li><tt>vesa(4)</tt> &mdash; in progress.</li>
	<li>i386/amd64 nVidia driver &mdash; need testing.</li>
	<li>Xbox framebuffer driver &mdash; need testing.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Known Issues:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Switching to <tt>vty0</tt> from X.Org on Fatal events will not work.</li>
	<li>Certain hardware (e.g., Lenovo X220) get a black screen when
	  i915kms is preloaded.</li>
	<li>Scrolling can be slow;</li>
	<li>Screen borders are not cleared when changing fonts.</li>
	<li><tt>vt(9)</tt> locks up with the <tt>gallant12x22</tt> font in VirtualBox.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>

    <help>
	<task>Create sub-directories for <tt>vt(9)</tt> under
	  <tt>/usr/share/</tt> to store key maps and fonts.</task>
	<task>Implement remaining features supported by
	  <tt>vidcontrol(1)</tt>.</task>
	<task>Write the <tt>vt(9)</tt> manual page.</task>
	<task>Support keyboard handled directly by device <tt>kbd</tt>
	  (without <tt>kbdmux(4)</tt>).</task>
	<task>CJK fonts (in progress).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Capsicum and Casper</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://freebsdfoundation.blogspot.com/2013/12/freebsd-foundation-announces-capsicum.html"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Capsicum is a lightweight OS capability and sandbox framework
	implementing a hybrid capability system model.  The Casper
	daemon enables sandboxed application to use functionality
	normally unavailable in capability-mode sandboxes.</p>

      <p>The Casper daemon, <tt>libcasper</tt>, <tt>libcapsicum(3)</tt>,
	<tt>libnv(3)</tt> and Casper services (<tt>system.dns</tt>,
	<tt>system.grp</tt>, <tt>system.pwd</tt>, <tt>system.random</tt>
	and <tt>system.sysctl</tt>) have been committed to &os;
	<tt>head</tt>.  The <tt>tcpdump(8)</tt> utility in <tt>head</tt>
	now uses the <tt>system.dns</tt> service to do DNS lookups.  The
	<tt>kdump(1)</tt> utility in <tt>head</tt> now uses the
	<tt>system.pwd</tt> and <tt>system.grp</tt> services to convert
	user and group identifiers to user and group names.</p>

      <p>There is ongoing work to sandbox more applications.  If you are
	interested in helping to make &os; more secure and would like to
	learn about Capsicum and Casper, do not hesitate to contact
	Pawel &mdash; he can provide candidate programs that could use
	sandboxing.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>auditdistd(8)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The <tt>auditdistd(8)</tt> daemon is responsible for
	distributing audit trail files over TCP/IP networks securely and
	reliably.  Currently, the daemon uses Transport Layer Security
	(TLS) for communication, but only server-side certificates are
	verified, based on the certificate's fingerprint.  The ongoing
	work will make it possible to use client-side certificates and
	will support more complete public-key infastructure, which
	includes validation of the entire certificate chain, including
	revocation checking against Certification Revocation Lists at
	every level.  From now on, <tt>auditdistd(8)</tt> will support
	TLSv1.2 and PFS modes only.  In addition, it will be possible to
	send audit trail files to multiple receivers.</p>

      <p>The work will be completed at the beginning of February
	2014.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Port Management Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Port Management Team</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en/articles/contributing-ports/" />
      <url href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/index.html" />
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html" />
      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/portmgr" />
      <url href="http://plus.google.com/communities/108335846196454338383" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Ports collection is a package management system for
	the &os; operating system, providing an easy and consistent way of
	installing software packages.  The &os; Ports Collection now
	contains approximately 24,500 ports, while the PR count exceeds
	1,900.</p>

      <p>The &os; Port Management Team ensures that the &os; ports
	developer community provides a Ports Collection that is
	functional, stable, up-to-date, and full-featured.  Its secondary
	responsibility is to coordinate among the committers and
	developers who work on it.  As part of these efforts, we added three
	new committers, took in three commit bits for safe keeping, and
	reinstated one commit bit in the fourth quarter of 2013.</p>

      <p>Ongoing effort went into testing larger changes, as many as eight a
	week, including sweeping changes to the tree, moderization of
	the infrastructure, and basic quality assurance (QA) runs.  Many
	iterations of tests against <tt>10.0-RELEASE</tt> were run to
	ensure that the maximum number of packages would be available
	for the release.</p>

      <p>We now have <tt>pkg(8)</tt> packages for the releases 8.3, 8.4,
	9.1, 9.2, 10.0 and -CURRENT on <tt>pkg.FreeBSD.org</tt>.  During
	this same time, further enhancements were put into
	<tt>pkg(8)</tt>, including secure package signing.</p>

      <p>Commencing November 1, the Port Management Team undertook a
	<q>portmgr-lurkers</q> pilot project in which ports committers
	could volunteer to assist the Port Management Team for a
	four-month duration.  The first two candiates are Mathieu Arnold
	(<tt>mat</tt>) and Antoine Brodin (<tt>antoine</tt>).</p>

      <p>Ongoing maintenance goes into <tt>redports.org</tt>, including
	QAT runs, ports and security updates.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>As previously noted, many PRs continue to languish; we would
	like to see some committers dedicate themselves to closing as many
	as possible!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Cluster Administration Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Cluster Administration Team</name>
	<!-- email intentionally left incomplete -->
	<email>admins@</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Cluster Administration Team consists of the people
	responsible for administering the machines that the project
	relies on for its distributed work and communications to be
	synchronised.  In the last quarter of 2013, they continued
	general maintenance of the &os; cluster across all sites.</p>

      <p>In addition to general upkeep tasks, additional
	cluster-related items were addressed.  Some of these
	items include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Added several machines for the Kyua testing framework.</li>
	<li>Replaced failed hardware hosting various web services.</li>
	<li>Coordinated with the &os; Security Officer and Ports
	  Management Teams to implement signed binary packages.</li>
	<li>Added the <tt>redports.org</tt> machines to the list of
	  machines managed by the Cluster Administration Team.</li>
	<li>Began discussion with contacts at Yandex regarding the
	  addition of a mirror site for binary packages and Subversion
	  repositories.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on Freescale Vybrid VF6xx</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ruslan</given>
	  <common>Bukin</common>
	</name>
	<email>br@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/258057"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Basic support for the Freescale Vybrid Family VF6xx
	heterogeneous ARM Cortex-A5/M4 System-on-Chip (SoC) was added to
	&os; <tt>head</tt>.  The Vybrid VF6xx family is an
	implementation of the new modern Cortex-A5-based low-power ARM
	SoC boards.  Vybrid devices are ideal for applications including
	simple HMI in appliances and industrial machines, secure control
	of infrastructure and manufacturing equipment, energy conversion
	applications such as motor drives and power inverters,
	ruggedized wired and wireless connectivity, and control of
	mobile battery-operated systems such as robots and industrial
	vehicles.</p>

      <p>Supported device drivers:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>NAND Flash Controller (NFC)</li>
	<li>USB Enhanced Host Controller Interface (EHCI)</li>
	<li>General-Purpose Input/Output (GPIO)</li>
	<li>Universal Asynchronous Receiver/Transmitter (UART)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Also supported:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Generic Interrupt Controller (GIC)</li>
	<li>MPCore timer</li>
	<li><tt>ffec</tt> Ethernet driver</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Add support for a number of different VF5xx- and VF6xx-based
	development boards.</task>
      <task>Expand device driver support, including framebuffer and
	other devices.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Intel 802.11n NIC (<tt>iwn(4)</tt>) Work</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Adrian</given>
	  <common>Chadd</common>
	</name>
	<email>adrian@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>There has been a large amount of work on <tt>iwn(4)</tt> over
	the last six months:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>New hardware support: 2xxx, 6xxx, 1xx series hardware.</li>

	<li>Many bugs were fixed, including scanning, association, EAPOL
	  related fixes.</li>

	<li><tt>iwn(4)</tt> now natively works with 802.11n rates from the
	  net80211 rate control code, rather than mapping non-11n rates to 11n
	  rates.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>There are still some scan hangs, due to how net80211 scans a
	single channel at a time.  This needs to be resolved.</task>

      <task>The transmit, receive, scan and calibration code needs to be
	refactored out of <tt>if_iwn.c</tt> and into separate source
	files.</task>

      <task>There still seem to be some issues surrounding 2&nbsp;GHz
	versus 5&nbsp;GHz association attempts leading to firmware
	assertions, especially on the Intel 4965 NIC.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Wine/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gerald</given>
	  <common>Pfeiffer</common>
	</name>
	<email>gerald@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Naylor</common>
	</name>
	<email>dbn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Wine">Wine wiki page</url>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/i386-Wine">Wine on amd64 wiki page</url>
      <url href="http://www.winehq.org/">Wine homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Wine is a free and open source software application that aims
	to allow applications designed for Microsoft Windows to run on
	Unix-like operating systems, such as &os;.  The Wine/&os; Team
	have continued to improve the experience of Wine under &os;.</p>

      <p>During the fourth quarter of 2013, the team has kept Wine
	updated by porting:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Stable releases: 1.6 and 1.6.1</li>
	<li>Development releases: 1.7.4 through 1.7.8</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The ports have included packages built for <tt>amd64</tt>
	(available through the Ports Collection).</p>

      <p>The Wine ports have been kept up-to-date with the changes in
	the Ports Collection, including some improvements:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Building with Clang by default (via <tt>USES=compiler:c11</tt>).</li>
	<li>Conditional X11 support (on by default; allowing for
	  headless instances of Wine).</li>
	<li>Staging support and other ports best practices.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Support in improving the experience of Wine on &os; is needed.
	Key areas including fixing regressions, adding copy protection
	scheme support, and fixing regressions when using Wine under
	&os;/<tt>amd64</tt>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Open Tasks and Known Problems (see links for the wiki
	page).</task>
      <task>&os;/<tt>amd64</tt> integration (see links for the i386-Wine
	wiki page).</task>
      <task>Porting WoW64 and Wine64.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>KDE &os; Team</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">KDE/FreeBSD home page</url>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org/area51.php">area51</url>
      <url href="http://portscout.freebsd.org/kde@freebsd.org.html">Out-of-date ports</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>KDE is an international free software community producing an
	integrated set of cross-platform applications designed to run on
	Linux, &os;, Solaris, Microsoft Windows, and OS X systems.  The
	KDE/&os; Team have continued to improve the experience of KDE
	software and Qt under &os;.</p>

      <p>During the last quarter, the team has kept most of the KDE and Qt
	ports up-to-date, working on the following releases:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>KDE SC (area51): 4.11.2, 4.11.3, 4.11.4</li>
	<li>Qt: 4.8.5 and 5.2 (area51)</li>
	<li>PyQt: 4.10.3; SIP: 4.15.2; QScintilla2: 2.8</li>
	<li>Qt Creator 2.8.0</li>
	<li>KDevelop: 4.5.2</li>
	<li>Calligra: 2.7.5</li>
	<li>CMake: 2.8.12, 2.8.12.1</li>
      </ul>

      <p>As a result, according to PortScout, our team has 464 ports
	(down from 473), of which 88.15% are up-to-date (down from
	98.73%).  iXsystems Inc. continues to provide a machine for
	the team to build packages and to test updates.  iXsystems Inc.
	has been providing the KDE/&os; Team with support for quite a
	long time and we are very grateful for that.</p>

      <p>As usual, the team is always looking for more testers and
	porters, so please contact us or visit our home page (see links).
	It would be especially useful to have more helping hands on
	tasks such as getting rid of the dependency on the defunct HAL
	project and providing integration with KDE's Bluedevil Bluetooth
	interface.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update out-of-date ports, see links for a list.</task>
      <task>Worke on KDE&nbsp;4.12 and Qt&nbsp;5.</task>
      <task>Make sure the whole KDE stack (including Qt) builds and
	works correctly with Clang and <tt>libc++</tt>.</task>
      <task>Remove the dependency on HAL.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Core Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Core Team</name>
	<email>core@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Core Team constitutes the project's <q>Board of
	Directors</q>, responsible for deciding the project's overall
	goals and direction as well as managing specific areas of the
	&os; project landscape.</p>

      <p>In the fourth quarter of 2013, the Core Team finally reached
	its previous goal of launching the official repositories for
	<tt>pkg(8)</tt>-based binary packages.  The Core Team also
	unified the commit bit expiration policies for all Project
	repositories, allowing committers to idle for 18 months before
	their commit bits are automatically taken into safekeeping.
	This was then followed by an extension to suspension of cluster
	accounts for the committers who lost all of their commit bits.
	This helps to improve the security of the Project server cluster
	by temporarily disabling inactive accounts.  In addition to the
	above efforts, Thomas Abthorpe resurrected the <q>Grim
	Reaper</q> service which helps to enforce the aforementioned
	policy.</p>

      <p>With the work of John Baldwin, Hiroki Sato, and others, many
	licenses in the base system source code have been revisited and
	cleaned up.  Furthermore, the Core Team is hoping that the
	situation can be improved by introducing periodic automated
	checks of the license agreements, and by providing developers
	guidelines on questions of licensing.  John Baldwin and David
	Chisnall have been guiding the work of the &os; Graphics Team on
	moving to the newer version of X.Org and related software in the
	Ports Collection, in coordination with the switch to Newcons on
	&os; 10.x.</p>

      <p>It was a busy quarter for the src repository as well.  The Core
	Team was happy to welcome Jordan K. Hubbard (<tt>jkh</tt>) back,
	who has recently returned to the &os; business, and joined
	iXsystems as project manager and release engineer of FreeNAS.
	In addition to this, there were three commit bits offered for new
	developers, two committers were upgraded, one commit bit was taken
	for safekeeping, and one src bit was reactivated.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Base GCC Updates</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pedro</given>
	  <common>Giffuni</common>
	</name>
	<email>pfg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The GCC compiler in the &os; base system is on its way to
	deprecation and is only used by some Tier-2 platforms at this
	time.  While Clang is much better in many aspects, we still
	cannot use all the new features that it
	brings in the base system until we can drop GCC completely.  As a stop-gap
	solution, several bug fixes and features from Apple GCC and
	other sources have been ported to our version of GCC&nbsp;4.2.1
	to make it more compatible with Clang.  &os;'s GCC has added
	more warnings and some enhancements like <tt>-Wmost</tt> and
	<tt>-Wnewline-eof</tt>.  An implementation for Apple's blocks
	extension is now available, too, and it will be very useful to
	enhance &os;'s support for Apple's Grand Central Dispatch
	(GCD).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>A merge from <tt>head</tt> to <tt>stable/9</tt> is being
	considered but it disables nested functions by default, so the
	impact on the Ports Collection needs to be evaluated.</task>

      <task>No further development of GCC&nbsp;4.2 in the base system is
	planned.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>The &os; Foundation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/press/2013Dec-newsletter">Semi-annual newsletter</url>
      <url href="http://freebsdjournal.com/">&os; Journal</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Foundation is a 501(c)(3) non-profit organization
	dedicated to supporting and promoting the &os; Project and
	community worldwide.  Most of the funding is used to support
	&os; development projects, conferences and developer summits,
	purchase equipment to grow and improve the &os; infrastructure,
	and provide legal support for the Project.</p>

      <p>We held our year-end fundraising campaign.  We are still
	processing donations and will post the final numbers by
	mid-January.  We are extremely grateful to all the individuals
	and organizations that supported us and the Project by making a
	donation in 2013.  We have already started our fundraising
	efforts for 2014.</p>

      <p>Some of the highlights from this past quarter include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>We sponsored or are sponsoring the following projects:

	  <ul>
	    <li>Projects completed last quarter: Capsicum, Casper daemon, and
	      Intel I/O Memory Management Unit driver.</li>
	    <li>Projects in progress: Native in-kernel iSCSI stack,
	      network stack layer 2 modernization, UEFI boot, updated
	      <tt>vt(9)</tt> system console.</li>
	    <li>Projects started last quarter: Automounter, Intel
	      graphics driver update.</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li>Continued work on the &os; Journal, our new online &os; magazine,
	  which debuts on January 27th (see links).</li>

	<li>Sponsored, organized, and ran the Bay Area Developer Summit.</li>

	<li>Sponsored and attended the first ever vBSDCon, which had an
	  impressive attendance.</li>

	<li>Sponsored and attended the OpenZFS developer summit.</li>

	<li>Represented the foundation at the following conferences: All
	  Things Open in Raleigh, NC and LISA in Washington, DC.</li>

	<li>Sponsored the &os; 20th Birthday Party, held in San
	  Francisco.</li>

	<li>Attended the ICANN meeting in Buenos Aires in November and
	  gave a short presentation on the change from BIND to unbound in
	  &os;&nbsp;10.0 during the ccNSO Tech Day.</li>

	<li>Met with a few companies to discuss their &os; use, what
	  they would like to see supported in &os;, and assist with
	  collaboration between them and the Project.</li>

	<li>Purchased an 80-core server to reside at Sentex for the
	  Project to use for stability, scalability, and performance
	  improvements.  It is a big step forwards for the Foundation in
	  providing this kind of hardware to the Project's developers.
	  It will let us test our scaling to 80 simultaneous cores and
	  1&nbsp;TB of RAM.  It will also be used to do performance
	  analysis on large workloads, such as large databases etc.</li>

	<li>Acquired a second rack to use at Sentex.</li>

	<li>We received a commitment from VMware, Inc. for BSD-licensed
	  drivers.  They also committed to a yearly silver level
	  donation.</li>

	<li>Signed up as a Google Compute trusted tester for the
	  Project.</li>

	<li>Funded a project to produce a white paper titled <q>Managed
	  Services Using &os; at NYI</q>.</li>

	<li>Finally, we published our semi-annual newsletter (see links)
	  highlighting what we did to support the &os; Project and
	  Community in 2013.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Intel IOMMU (VT-d, DMAR) Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/257251"/>
      <url href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/changeset/base/259512"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>An Input/Output Memory Management Unit (IOMMU) is a Memory
	Management Unit (MMU) that connects a Direct Memory
	Access-capable (DMA-capable) I/O bus to main memory; therefore,
	I/O virtualization is performed by the chipset.  An example
	IOMMU is the graphics address remapping table (GART) used by AGP
	and PCI Express graphics cards.  Intel has published a
	specification for IOMMU technology as Virtualization Technology
	for Directed I/O, abbreviated VT-d.</p>

      <p>A VT-d driver was committed to <tt>head</tt> and
	<tt>stable/10</tt>, so <tt>busdma(9)</tt> is now able to utilize
	VT-d.  The feature is disabled by default, but it may be enabled
	via the <tt>hw.dmar.enable</tt> <tt>loader(8)</tt> tunable
	&mdash; see the links for more information.  The immediate plans
	include increasing the support for this kind of hardware by
	testing and providing workarounds for specific issues, and
	by adding features of the next generation of Intel IOMMU.
	Hopefully, the existing and new consumers of VT-d will start to
	use the driver soon.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/Xen</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Roger</given>
	  <common>Pau Monné</common>
	</name>

	<email>royger@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Justin T.</given>
	  <common>Gibbs</common>
	</name>

	<email>gibbs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/FreeBSD_PVH">&os; PVH wiki page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xen is a native (bare-metal) hypervisor providing services that
	allow multiple computer operating systems to execute on the same
	computer hardware concurrently.  Xen&nbsp;4.4 will bring a
	virtualization mode called PVH &mdash; PV (paravirtualization)
	in an HVM (fully-virtual) container.  This is essentially a
	paravirtualized guest using paravirtualized drivers for boot and
	I/O.  Otherwise it uses hardware virtualization extensions,
	without the need for emulation.</p>

      <p>After merging the changes to improve Xen PVHVM
	support, work has shifted on getting PVH DomU support on &os;.
	Patches have been posted, and after a couple of rounds of review,
	the series looks almost ready for merging into <tt>head</tt>.
	Also, very initial patches for &os; PVH Dom0 support has been
	posted.  So far the posted series only focuses on getting &os;
	booting as a Dom0 and being able to interact with the
	hardware.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>Citrix Systems R&amp;D</sponsor>
    <sponsor>Spectra Logic Corporation</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Finish reviewing and commit the PVH DomU support.</task>
      <task>Work on PVH Dom0 support.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
