<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd" >
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>January-March</month>

    <year>2014</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between January and
      March 2014.  This is the first of four reports planned for 2014.</p>

    <!-- XXX: Add introduction -->

    <!-- XXX: Keep the number of entries updated -->
    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 6 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>The deadline for submissions covering between April and
      June 2014 is July 7th, 2014.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Chromium</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>Chromium on &os; Team</name>
	<email>freebsd-chromium@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.chromium.org/Home">Chromium website</url>
      <url href="https://github.com/gliaskos/freebsd-chromium">Development repository on GitHub</url>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Chromium">Chromium on &os; wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Chromium is the open source web browser project from which
	Google Chrome draws its source code.  The browsers share the
	majority of code and features, though there are some minor
	differences in features and they have different licensing.  Over
	the last four years, the Chromium team has been busy with
	porting Chromium to &os;.  This involves patching the browser so
	that it runs on &os;, tracking and documenting security updates,
	and merging patches back upstream.</p>

      <p>While there are already several browsers available for &os;,
	advantages of Chromium are:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Quick response from upstream to security issues, resulting
	  in approximately bi-weekly updates.</li>

	<li>A testbed for security features of &os;, like Capsicum.
	  While support for this capability and sandbox framework is
	  currently not included in the browser, a proof-of-concept
	  implementation for an early version of Chromium was realized
	  within a single weekend.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>George Liaskos and &a.rene; are currently busy with submitting
	the remaining patches specific to &os; back upstream.  Apart from
	making future updates easier, it sometimes also improves the
	overall code quality.</p>

      <p>&a.jonathan; recently updated the Capsicum patches for Chromium
	and is talking to upstream about them.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Advocate &os;.  While patches are getting accepted by both
	humans and bots, it is not an official platform so attitude varies
	from developer to developer.  While &a.rene; thinks it is a bit
	early, it might be fruitful to investigate what is required to
	make &os; (and possibly OpenBSD) an official platform in terms
	of both hardware and procedures.</task>

      <task>If you feel comfortable with large source trees, you can try
	to build the Git version of Chromium on &os;.  If you are also
	comfortable with signing Googles Contributor License Agreement,
	you can join testing and submitting patches upstream.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>ZFS Chapter of the Handbook</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Allan</given>
	  <common>Jude</common>
	</name>
	<email>freebsd@allanjude.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benedict</given>
	  <common>Reuschling</common>
	</name>
	<email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warren</given>
	  <common>Block</common>
	</name>
	<email>wblock@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.allanjude.com/zfs_handbook/zfs.html">Preview ZFS Handbook</url>
      <url href="http://www.allanjude.com/talks/AsiaBSDCon_2014_-_WIP_-_ZFS_Handbook.pdf">Slides from AsiaBSDCon 2014</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ZFS is one of the premier features of &os;.  The current
	documentation in the Handbook and elsewhere online is severely
	lacking.  Much of the original documentation from Sun and Oracle
	has disappeared, moved, or is about the proprietary version of
	ZFS.</p>

      <p>New users have many questions about ZFS and yet there exists a
	great deal more bad advice about ZFS than proper documentation.
	The current ZFS chapter of the &os; Handbook starts off with the
	required steps to configure an i386 machine to run ZFS.  This is
	more likely to scare off a new user than to educate them about
	how to properly use ZFS.</p>

      <p>At BSDCan&nbsp;2013, the process of writing an entirely new
	chapter of the Handbook on ZFS was started.  Currently this
	chapter consists of approximately 16,000 words covering all
	subcommands of the <tt>zpool(8)</tt> and <tt>zfs(8)</tt>
	utilities, delegation, tuning and a section devoted to
	defintions and explainations of the terms and features of
	ZFS.</p>

      <p>The remaining section is the FAQ.  To help users address the
	most common problems they might run into with ZFS.  It would be
	useful to hear experiences, questions, misconceptions, gotchas,
	stumbling blocks and suggestions for the FAQ section from other
	users.  Also, a use cases section that highlights some of the
	cases where ZFS provides advantages over traditional file
	systems.</p>

      <p>Please send suggestions to the <tt>freebsd-doc</tt> mailing
	list.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>ScaleEngine, Inc</sponsor>

    <help>
      <task>Technical review by Matt Ahrens (co-creator of ZFS).</task>
      <task>Improve delegation section.</task>
      <task>Improve tuning section, add new sysctls added in
	<tt>head</tt>.</task>
      <task>Add section on jails and the jailed property.</task>
      <task>Add FAQ section.</task>
      <task>Add <q>Use Cases</q> section.</task>
      <task>General editing and review.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Release Engineering Team</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/9.3R/schedule.html">&os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE schedule</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/9.3R/todo.html">&os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE todo list</url>
      <url href="http://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/snapshots/ISO-IMAGES/">&os;&nbsp;development snapshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In early January, the &os; Release Engineering Team became
	aware of several last-minute showstopper issues in
	&os;&nbsp;10.0, which lead to an extension in the final release
	builds.  &os;&nbsp;10.0-RELEASE was announced on January 20, two
	months behind the original schedule.</p>

      <p>The schedule for the &os;&nbsp;9.3-RELEASE cycle has been
	written and posted to the website, and the release cycle will
	begin early May.</p>

      <p>There is ongoing work to integrate support for embedded
	architectures as part of the release build process.  At this
	time, support exists for a number of ARM kernels, in particular
	the Raspberry Pi, BeagleBone, and WandBoard.</p>
    </body>

    <sponsor>The &os; Foundation</sponsor>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Documentation Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>&os; Documentation Engineering Team</name>
	<email>doceng@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-doc/2014-February/023265.html">Announcement of Warren Block's addition</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; Documentation Engineering Team is responsible for
	defining and following up documentation goals for the committers
	in the Documentation project.  The team is pleased to announce a
	new member &mdash; &a.wblock;.  In early March, the &os;
	Documentation Engineering Team members assumed responsibility
	for the &os; Webmaster Team.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Ada Ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Marino</common>
	</name>
	<email>marino@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.dragonlace.net"/>
      <url href="http://www.spark-2014.org/about/">SPARK 2014</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Ada is a structured, statically typed, imperative,
	wide-spectrum, and object-oriented high-level computer
	programming language, extended from Pascal and other languages,
	originally targeted at embedded and real-time systems.  The
	number of Ada ports in the collection has grown significantly
	since the last report six months ago.  There are almost 50
	Ada-related ports now, with new ones getting added the time.</p>

      <p>The previous plan was to move from the GCC 4.7-based GNAT
	compiler to a GCC 4.8-based one, but finally GCC 4.8 was skipped
	and now a GCC 4.9-based GNAT is the standard Ada compiler, which
	fully supports the new ISO standard, Ada 2012.  Moving to a
	newer compiler allowed several important ports like PolyOrb and
	GPRBuild to be upgraded to the latest available versions.  In
	fact, almost every Ada port is currrently at its most recent
	upstream version.</p>

      <p>For non-Windows-based Ada development, &os; and DragonFly are
	now undisputed as the go-to platforms.  The other candidates are
	Debian and Fedora, but there are few Ada software on those
	platforms that are not also in &os; ports tree, but the versions are
	much older.  The Ports Collection also features software not found
	anywhere else such as the USAFA's Ironsides DNS server,
	libsparkcrypto, matreshka, GNATDroid (Android cross-compiler) and
	several developer libraries.</p>

      <p>A desired addition to the Ada ports will be SPARK 2014 (see
	links), which should cement &os; as an option for professional,
	safety-critical application development.  This package should
	have its first release by early summer.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Xfce/&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os; Xfce Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>xfce@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/Xfce"/>
      <url href="https://svn.redports.org/olivierd/xfce4/">Development repository</url>
      <url href="https://people.freebsd.org/~olivierd/xfce-core-unstable.html"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=183690">ports/183690</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Xfce is a free software desktop environment for Unix and
	Unix-like platforms, such as &os;.  It aims to be fast and
	lightweight, while still being visually appealing and easy to
	use.  The Xfce team continues to keep up-to-date each piece of
	the Xfce Desktop.</p>

      <p>The latest commits concerned:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Applications:</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>Midori (0.5.7)</li>
	  <li>xfburn (0.5.0)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-parole (0.5.4)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-taskmanager (1.0.1)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-tumbler (0.1.30)</li>
	</ul>

	<li>Panel plugins:</li>

	<ul>
	  <li>xfce4-clipman-plugin (1.2.5)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-equake-plugin (1.3.4)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-wavelan-plugin (0.5.11)</li>
	  <li>xfce4-whiskermenu-plugin (1.3.2)</li>
	</ul>
      </ul>

      <p>We also follow development of core components (available in
	your repository).  See link for documentation on how to upgrade
	those libraries.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>garcon (0.3.0)</li>
	<li>libxfce4menu (4.11.1)</li>
	<li>libxfce4util (4.11.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-appfinder (4.11.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-desktop (4.11.4)</li>
	<li>xfce4-dev-tools (4.11.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-panel (4.11.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-parole (0.6.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-settings (4.11.2)</li>
	<li>xfce4-session (4.11.0)</li>
	<li>xfce4-wm (4.11.1)</li>
	<li>xfce4-xkb-plugin (0.7.0)</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Add support of DragonFly for xfce4-taskmanger.</task>

      <task>Finish to replace Tango icons theme by GNOME, in order to
	close <tt>ports/183690</tt> (see links, it remains
	Midori).</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
