<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/statusreport.dtd">

<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>March-April</month>
    <year>2004</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>2004 continues on with wonderful progress.  Work continues on locking
      down the network stack, ACPI made more great strides, an ARM port
      appeared in the tree, and the FreeBSD 4.10 release cycle wrapped up.
      Once 4.10 is released, the next big focus will be FreeBSD 5.3.  We
      expect this is be the start of the 5-STABLE branch, meaning that not
      only will it be stable for production use, it will also be largely
      feature complete and stable from an internal API standpoint.  We expect
      to release 5.3 in mid-summer, and we encourage everyone to download the
      latest snapshots from <url href="ftp://snapshots.jp.FreeBSD.org"/>
      for a preview.</p>
    <p>Thanks,</p>
    <p>Scott Long</p>
  </section>

  <project>
    <title>OpenOffice.org porting status</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>NAKATA</given>
          <common>Maho</common>
        </name>
        <email>maho@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>After almost three years efforts for porting OpenOffice.org 1.0.x and
        1.1.0 for FreeBSD by Martin Blapp (mbr@FreeBSD.org) and other
        contributors, There are four version of OpenOffice.org (OOo) in ports
        tree.  1.1.1: stable version, 1.1.2: next stable, 2.0: developer and
        1.0.3: legacy.
      </p>

      <p>Stable version 1.1.1 in /usr/ports/editors/openoffice-1.1/
        builds/installs/works fine for 5.2.1-RELEASE.  Packages for
        5.2.1-RELEASE, 26 localized versions and 4.10-PRELEASE only English
        version, are available at
        http://oootranslation.services.openoffice.org/pub/OpenOffice.org/ooomisc/
        (note: source of OOo 1.1.1.RC3 is identical OOo 1.1.1)</p>

      <p>Patches needed to build are currently 18 for 1.1.1, and 161 for 1.0.3
        the number of patches are greatly reduced.</p>

      <p>OOo 1.1.2, the next stable version in
        /usr/ports/editors/openoffice-1.1-devel is also builds/installs/works
        fine for 5.2.1-RELEASE. We are planning to upgrade this port as soon
        as 1.1.2 will be released.</p>

      <p>Next major release, 2.0 (planned to be released at January 2005
        according to
        http://development.openoffice.org/releases/OpenOffice_org_trunk.html),
        /usr/ports/editors/openoffice-2.0-devel, now compiles for
        5.2.1-RELEASE but have big problem that prohibits to remove BROKEN.</p>

      <p>Legacy version, OOo 1.0.3: /usr/ports/editors/openoffice-1.0/ I'm not
        interested in this port. We hope someone else will maintain this.</p>

      <p>For builds, my main environment is 5.2.1-RELEASE, and I have no access
        to 4-series, so several build problems had been reported for 5-current
        and 4-stable, however, they now seems to be fixed. Please make sure
        your Java and/or kernel are up-to-date.</p>

      <p>For version 1.1.1, yet we have serious reproducible core dumps, this
        means OOo cannot pass the Quality Assurance protocol of OpenOffice.org
        (http://qa.openoffice.org), so we cannot release OOo as quality
        assured package.  It seems to be FreeBSD's userland bug, since some
        reports show that there are no problem for 4-stable but we still
        searchingthe reason.</p>

      <p>Note that developers should sign JCA (Joint Copyright Assignment)
        before submitting patches via PR or e-mail, otherwise patches won't be
        integrated to OOo's source tree.  We seriously need more developers,
        testers and builders.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Network interface naming changes</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>An enhanced network interface cloning API has been created.  It
        allows interfaces to support more complex names than the current
        name# style.  This functionality has been used to enable
        interesting cloners like auto-configuring vlan interfaces.  Other
        features include locking of cloner structures and the ability of
        drivers to reject destroy requests.  A patch has been posted to
        the freebsd-net mailing list for review and will be committed in
        early May.  This work is taking place in the perforce repository
        under: //depot/user/brooks/xname/...</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD Dutch Documentation Project</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Remko</given>
          <common>Lodder</common>
        </name>
        <email>remko@elvandar.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.evilcoder.org/index.cgi?i=nav&amp;t=freebsd">Status and download of the documentation (not yet complete)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Dutch Documentation Project is a ongoing project in
        translating the handbook and other documentation to the Dutch
        language. Currently we have a small team of individuals who
        translate, check other's work, and publish them on the internet.
        You can view the current status on the webpage (listed above).
        Still we can use more people helping out, since we have a long
        way to go. Every hand that wants to help, contact me, and i will
        provide you details on how we work etc. Currently the project has
        translated the handbook pages of: The X Windows System, and
        Configuration and Tuning, they only need to be checked before
        publishing.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>ACPI</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Nate</given>
          <common>Lawson</common>
        </name>
        <email>njl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.root.org/~nate/freebsd/">ACPI TODO</url>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-acpi">
        ACPI Mailing List</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Much of the ACPI project is waiting for architectural changes to be
        completed.  For instance, the cpufreq driver requires newbus
        attachments for CPUs.  Support code for this should be committed
        at the time of publication.  Other architectural changes needed
        include rman support for memory/port resources and a generic hotkey
        and extras driver.  Important work in other areas of the kernel
        including PCI powerstate support and APIC support have been
        invaluable in improving ACPI on modern platforms.  Thanks go to
        Warner Losh and John Baldwin for this work.</p>

      <p>Code which is mostly completed and will go in once the groundwork
        is finished includes the cpufreq framework, an ACPI floppy controller
        driver, and full support for dynamic Cx states.</p>

      <p>ACPI-CA was updated to 20040402 in early April.  This has some GPE
        issues that persist in 20040427 that will hopefully be resolved by
        the date of publication.</p>

      <p>I'd like to welcome Mark Santcroos (marks@) to the FreeBSD team.
        He has helped in the past with debugging ACPI issues.
        If any developers are interested in assisting with ACPI, please
        see the ACPI TODO and send us an email.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Verify source reachability option for ipfw2</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>
          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>
        <email>andre@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/news/status/report-jan-2004-feb-2004.html#Verify-source-reachability-option-for-ipfw2"/>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=ipfw&amp;apropos=0&amp;sektion=0&amp;manpath=FreeBSD+5.2-current&amp;format=html"/>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>The verify source reachability option for ipfw2 has been committed
        on 23. April 2004 to FreeBSD-CURRENT.  For more information see the
        links above.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Convert ipfw2 to use PFIL_HOOKS mechanism</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>
          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>
        <email>andre@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://www.nrg4u.com/freebsd/ipfw-pfilhooks-and-more-20040510.diff"/>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>ipfw2 is built directly into ip_input() and ip_output() and it makes
        these functions more complicated.  For some time now we have the
        generic packet filter mechanism PFIL_HOOKS which are used by IPFILTER
        and the new OpenBSD PF firewall packages to hook themselves into the
        IP input and output path.</p>
      <p>This patch makes ipfw2 fully self contained and callable through the
        PFIL_HOOKS.  This is still work in progress and DUMMYNET and IPDIVERT
        plus Layer2 firewall are not yet fully functional again but normal
        firewalling with it works just fine.</p>
      <p>The patch contains some more cleanups of ip_input() and ip_output()
        that is work in progress too.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Move ARP out of routing table</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Luigi</given>
          <common>Rizzo</common>
        </name>
        <email>luigi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>
          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>
        <email>andre@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2004-April/026380.html"/>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>The ARP IP address to MAC address mapping does not belong into
        the routing table (FIB) as it is currently done.  This will move
        it to its own hash based structure which will be instantiated per
        each 802.1 broadcast domain.  With this change it is possible to
        have more than one interface in the same IP subnet and layer 2
        broadcast domain.  The ARP handling and the routing table will be
        quite a bit simplified afterwards.  As an additional benefit full
        MAC address based accounting will be provided.</p>
      <p>Luigi has become the driver of this project and posted a first
        implementation for comments on 25. April 2004 (see link).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Automatic sizing of TCP send buffers</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andre</given>
          <common>Oppermann</common>
        </name>
        <email>andre@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/news/status/report-jan-2004-feb-2004.html#Automatic-sizing-of-TCP-send-buffers"/>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>The current TCP send and receive buffers are static and set to a
        conservative value to preserve kernel memory.  This is sub-optimal
        for connections with a high bandwidth*delay product because the
        size of the TCP send buffer determines how big the send window can
        get.  For high bandwidth trans-continental links this seriously
        limits the maximum transfer speed per TCP connection.  A moredetailed
        description from the last status report can be found with the link
        above.</p>
      <p>Work on this project has been stalled due to some other network stack
        projects with higher precedence (ipfw2 to pfil_hooks and
        ip_input/ip_output cleanups).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>libarchive/bsdtar</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Tim</given>
          <common>Kientzle</common>
        </name>
        <email>kientzle@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~kientzle/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Both bsdtar and libarchive are now part of -CURRENT.
        A few minor problems have been reported and addressed,
        including performance issues with many hard-links, and
        options required by certain packages.
        For now, the "tar" command is still an alias for "gtar."
        Those who would like to use bsdtar as the default system tar
        can define WITH_BSDTAR to make "tar" be an alias for
        "bsdtar."</p>

      <p>My current plan is to make bsdtar be the default in -CURRENT in
        about another month, probably after the 5-STABLE split, and remove
        gtar from -CURRENT sometime later.  It's still open if and when
        this switch will occur in 5-STABLE.  On the one hand, I see
        potential problems if 5-STABLE and 6-CURRENT have different tar
        commands; on the other hand, switching could be disruptive for
        some users.</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>GEOM Gate</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Pawel Jakub</given>

          <common>Dawidek</common>
        </name>

        <email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>GEOM Gate class is now committed as well as ggatec(8), ggated(8)
        and ggatel(8) utilities. It makes distribution of disk devices
        through the network possible, but on the disk level (don't confuse
        it with NFS, which provides exporting data on the file system
        level).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Improved Multibyte/Wide Character Support</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Tim</given>
          <common>Robbins</common>
        </name>
        <email>tjr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <body>
      <p>New locales: Unicode UTF-8 locales have been added to the base system.
        All of the locales previously supported by FreeBSD now have a
        corresponding UTF-8 version, along with one or two new ones --
        53 in all.</p>
      <p>Library changes: The restartable conversion functions (mbrtowc(),
        wcrtomb(), etc.) in the C library have been updated to handle partial
        characters in the way prescribed by the C99 standard.
        The &lt;wctype.h&gt; functions have been optimized for handling
        large, fragmented character sets like Unicode and GB18030.
        Documentation has been improved.</p>
      <p>Utilities: The ls utility has been modified to work with wide
        characters internally when determining whether a character in a
        filename is printable, and how many column positions it takes on
        the screen. Character handling in the wc utility has been made
        more robust. Other text-processing utilities (expand, fold, unexpand,
        uniq) have been modified, but these changes have not been committed
        until the performance impact can be evaluated. Work on a POSIX-style
        localedef utility has started, with the aim to have it replace
        the current mklocale and colldef utilities in FreeBSD 6.
        (It is currently on the back-burner awaiting a response to a POSIX
        defect report.)</p>
      <p>Future directions: wide character handling functions need to be
        optimized so that they are more competitive with the single-byte
        functions when dealing with 8-bit character sets. Utilities need to
        be modified to handle multibyte characters, but with a careful eye
        on performance. Localedef needs to be finished.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>ATA project Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>S&#xF8;ren</given>
          <common>Schmidt</common>
        </name>
        <email>sos@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      There is finally support (except for RAID5) for the Promise SX4/SX4000
      line of controllers. The support is rudimentary still, and doesn't
      really make any good use of the cache/sequencer HW yet. The Silicon
      Image 3114 support has been completed. Lots of bug fixes and cleanups.
      Future work now concentrates on new controller chips (Marvell SATA
      chips probably the most prominent) and getting the SATA support
      finished so that hotswap etc works with SATA HW as well. Also ATA RAID
      is about to get rewritten to take advantage of the features that the
      ATA subsystem now offers, including support for the HW on
      Promise/Marvell and the like controllers. A number of new RAID metadata
      <p>formats (Intel, AMI) is also in the works.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Porting OpenBSD's packet filter</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>
          <common>Laier</common>
        </name>
        <email>mlaier@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Daniel</given>
          <common>Hartmeier</common>
        </name>
        <email>dhartmei@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Pyun</given>
          <common>YongHyeon</common>
        </name>
        <email>yongari@kt-is.co.kr</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://pf4freebsd.love2party.net/"/>
      <url href="http://www.benzedrine.cx/pf.html"/>
      <url href="http://openbsd.org/faq/pf/index.html"/>
      <url href="http://www.rofug.ro/projects/freebsd-altq/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The two months after the import was done were actually rather quiet.
        We imported a couple of minor fixes from the OpenBSD stable branch.
        The import of tcpdump 3.8.3 and libpcap 0.8.3 done by Bruce M.Simpson
        in late March finally put us into the position to build a working
        pflogd(8) and provide rc.d linkage for it. Tcpdump now understandsthe
        pflog(4) pseudo-NIC packet format and can be used to read the
        log-files.</p>

      <p>There has also been work behind the scenes to prepare an import of
        the OpenBSD 3.5 sources. The patches are quite stable already andwill
        be posted shortly. Altq is in the making as well and going alongquite
        well based on the great work from rofug.ro, but as it needs
        modifications to every network driver which have to be tested
        thoroughly it needs more time.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>The FreeBSD Simplified Chinese Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Xin</given>
          <common>LI</common>
        </name>

        <email>delphij@frontfree.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org.cn">The FreeBSD Simplified
        Chinese Project (In Simplified Chinese)</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org.cn/snap/doc/zh_CN.GB2312/books/handbook/">
        Translated Handbook Snapshot</url>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org.cn/cndocs/translations.html">
        Translation status</url>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org.cn/snap/zh_CN/">Translated
        Website Snapshot</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We have finished about 75% of the Handbook translation work.
        In the last two months we primarily worked on bringing the
        handbook chapters more up to date. To make the translation
        more high quality we are also doing some revision on it.</p>
      <p>We are still looking for manpower on SGML'ifying the FAQ
        translation which has been done last year by several volunteers.</p>
    </body>
  </project>


  <project>
    <title>Cronyx Tau-ISA driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Roman</given>
          <common>Kurakin</common>
        </name>
        <email>rik@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.cronyx.ru/hardware/wan.html">Cronyx WAN Adapters.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ctau(4) driver for Cronyx Tau-ISA was added. Cronyx Tau-ISA is family
        of synchronous WAN adapters with various set of interfaces such as
        V.35, RS-232, RS-530(449), E1 (both framed and unframed). This is a
        second family of Cronyx adapters that is supported by FreeBSD now. The
        first one was Cronyx Sigma-ISA, cx(4).</p>

      <p>Cronyx Tau-PCI family will become a third one. The peculiarity of this
        driver that it contains private code. This code is distributed as
        obfuscated source code with usual open source license agreement.Since
        code is protected by obfuscation it is satisfy needs of commerce. On
        the other hand it still stays a source code and thus it becomes closer
        to open source projects. I hope this form of private code distribution
        will become a real alternative to object form.</p>
    </body>
  </project>


  <project>
    <title>Sync protocols (Netgraph and SPPP)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Roman</given>
          <common>Kurakin</common>
        </name>
        <email>rik@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>As part of my work on synchronous protocol stack a ng_sppp driver was
        added to the system. This driver allows to use sppp as a Netgraph
        node.  Now I plan to update sppp driver as much as possible to make it
        in sync with Cronyxs one (PPP part). Also I work on FRF.12 support in
        FreeBSD (now I have FRF.12 support for Netgraph and SPPP (and for
        Cronyx linux fr driver) but only End-to-End). I plan to test it by my
        self within a week and after that I plan to make full support of
        FRF.12.</p>
      <p>If you want to get current version and test it, please feel free to
        contact me.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD threading support</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>David</given>
          <common>Xu</common>
        </name>
        <email>davidxu@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Doug</given>
          <common>Rabson</common>
        </name>
        <email>dfr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Julian</given>
          <common>Elischer</common>
        </name>
        <email>julian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Marcel</given>
          <common>Moolinar</common>
        </name>
        <email>marcel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>
          <common>Eischen</common>
        </name>
        <email>deischen@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~marcel/tls.html">basic data on
        TLS</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
        Threading developers have been active behind the scenes
        though not much has been visible. Real Life(TM) has been
        hard on us as a group however.</p>
      <p> Marcel and Davidxu have both (individually)
        been looking at the support
        for debugging threaded programs. David has a set of
        patches that allow gdb to correctly handle KSE programs and
        patches are being considered for libthr based processes.
        Marcel added a Thread ID to allow debugging code to unambiguously
        specify a thread to debug. He has also been looking at corefile
        support.  Both sets of patches are preliminary.</p>
      <p>Dan Eischen continues to support people migrating to
        libpthreads and it seems to be going well.</p>
      <p>Doug Rabson has done his usual miracle work and produced
        a set of preliminary patches to implement TLS (Thread
        Local Storage) for the i386 platform.</p>
      <p>Julian Elischer is investigating some refactoring of the kernel
        support code.</p>
      <p>Platforms:</p>
      <p>i386, amd64, ia64  libpthread works.</p>
      <p>alpha, sparc64   not implemented.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Binary security updates for FreeBSD</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Colin</given>
          <common>Percival</common>
        </name>
        <email>cperciva@daemonology.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/freebsd-update/"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Having recently passed its first birthday, FreeBSD Update is
        now being used on about 170 machines every day; on a typical
        day, around 60 machines will download updates (the others being
        already up to date).  To date, over 157000 files have been
        updated on over 4200 machines.</p>
    </body>
  </project>


  <project>
    <title>PCI Powerstates and Resource</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Warner</given>
          <common>Losh</common>
        </name>
        <email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Lazy allocation of pci resources has been merged into the main
        tree.  These changes allow FreeBSD to run on computers where PnP
        OS is set to true.  In addition, the saving and restoring of the
        resources across suspend/resume has helped some devices come
        back from suspend.</p>

      <p>Future work will focus on bus numbering.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Book: The Design and Implementation of the FreeBSD Operating System</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kirk</given>
          <common>McKusick</common>
        </name>
        <email>mckusick@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>
          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>
        <email>gnn@neville-neil.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
    <links>
      <url href="http://www.mckusick.com/FreeBSDbook.html"/>
    </links>
    <body>
      <p>The new Book "The Design and Implementation of the FreeBSD Operating
        System" is the successor of the legendary "The Design and
        Implementation of 4.4BSD" book which has become the de-facto standard
        for teaching of Operating System internals in universities
        world-wide.</p>
      <p>This new and completely reworked edition is based on FreeBSD 5.2 and
        the upcoming FreeBSD 5.3 releases and contains in-details looks into
        all areas (from virtual memory management to interprocess
        communication and network stack) of the operating system on 700
        pages.</p>
      <p>It is now in final production by Addison-Wesley and will be available
        in early August 2004.  The ISBN is 0-201-70245-2.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Status Report </title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Roland</given>
          <common>van Laar</common>
        </name>
        <email>the_mip_rvl@myrealbox.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wleiden.webweaving.org:8080/svn/node-config/other/enh-sec-patch/README"/>
      <url href="http://bsd.slashdot.org/article.pl?amp;sid=03/12/27/2035245&amp;mode=thread&amp;tid=122&amp;tid=126&amp;tid=137&amp;tid=172&amp;tid=185&amp;tid=190&amp;tid=193"/>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This patch if for if_wi current. It enables you to disable the ssid
        broadcasting and it also allows you to disable clients connecting
        with a blank ssid.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>
          <common>Baldwin</common>
        </name>
        <email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <email>smp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links/>

    <body>
      <p>Several folks continue to work on the locking the network stack
        as noted elsewhere in this report.  Outside of the network stack,
        the following items were worked on during the March and April time
        frame.  Giant was pushed down in the fork, exit, and wait system
        calls as far as possible.  Alan Cox (alc@) continues to lock the
        VM subsystem and push down Giant where appropriate.  A few system
        calls and callouts were marked MP safe as well.</p>

      <p>A few changes were made to the interrupt thread infrastructure.
        Interrupt thread preemption was finally enabled on the Alpha
        architecture with the help of the recently added support to the
        scheduler for pinning threads to a specific CPU.  An optimization
        to reduce context switches during heavy interrupt load was added
        as well as rudimentary interrupt storm protection.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD/arm</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Olivier</given>
          <common>Houchard</common>
        </name>
        <email>cognet@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>FreeBSD/arm is now in the FreeBSD CVS tree. Dynamic libraries now work,
        and NO_CXX=true NO_RESCUE=true buildworld works too (with patches for
        toolchain that will live outside the tree for now). Now the focus
        should be on xscale support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>CAM lockdown and threading</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>
          <common>Long</common>
        </name>
        <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work has begun on locking down the CAM subsystem.  The project is
        divided into several steps:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Separation of the SCSI probe peripheral from cam_xpt.c to
          scsi_probe.c</li>
        <li>Threading of the device probe sequence.</li>
        <li>Locking and reference counting the peripheral drivers.</li>
        <li>Locking the XPT and device queues.</li>
        <li>Locking one or more SIMs and devising a way for non-locked drivers
          to function.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>While the immediate goal of this work is to lock CAM, it also points
        us in the direction of separating out the SCSI-specific knowledgefrom
        the core.  This will allow other transports to be written, such as
        SAS, iSCSI, and ATA.</p>

      <p>Progress is being tracked in the FreeBSD Perforce server in the
        camlock branch.  I will make public patches available once it has
        progressed far enough for reasonable testing.  So far, the first two
        items are being worked on.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Network Stack Locking</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>
          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>
        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.watson.org/~robert/freebsd/netperf/">Robert's
        Network Stack Locking Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project is aimed at converting the FreeBSD network stack from
        running under the single Giant kernel lock to permitting it to run
        in a fully parallel manner on multiple CPUs (i.e., a fully threaded
        network stack). This will improve performance/latency through
        reentrancy and preemption on single-processor machines, and also on
        multi-processor machines by permitting real parallelism in the
        processing of network traffic. As of FreeBSD 5.2, it was possible to
        run low level network functions, as well as the IP filtering and
        forwarding plane, without the Giant lock, as well as "process to
        completion" in the interrupt handler.</p>

      <p>Work continues to improve the maturity and completeness of the
        locking (and performance) of the network stack for 5.3.  The network
        stack development branch has been updated to the latest CVS HEAD,
        as well as the following and more:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Review of socket flag and socket buffer flag locking;
          so_state broken out into multiple fields covered by different
          locks to avoid lock orders in frobbing the so_state field.
          Work in progress.</li>
        <li>WITNESS now includes hard ordering for many network locks to
          improve lock order debugging process.</li>
        <li>MAC Framework modified to use pcbs instead of sockets in a
          great many situations to avoid socket locking in network layer,
          especially when generating new mbufs.</li>
        <li>New annotations relating to socket and interface locking.</li>
        <li>Began NetGraph review and corrected NetGraph socket locking
          problems.</li>
        <li>sendfile() locking appears now to be fixed, albeit holding
          Giant more than strictly necessary.</li>
        <li>if_ppp global variable locking performed and merged.</li>
        <li>A variety of race conditions and bugs in soreceive() locking
          fixed, including existing race conditions triggered only rarely
          in -HEAD and -STABLE that triggered easily with SMP and Giant-free
          operation.</li>
        <li>Locking of socket buffer and socket fields from fifofs.
          Proposed patch to correct lock order problem between vnode
          interlock and socket buffer lock order problems.  fifofs
          interactions with UNIX domain sockets cleaned up.</li>
        <li>Research into KQueue issues.  Feedback to KQueue locking
          patch authors.</li>
        <li>netatalk AARP locked down, MPSAFE, and merged to CVS.</li>
        <li>Lock order issues between socket, socket buffer, and UNIX domain
          socket locks corrected.  Race conditions and potential deadlocks
          removed.</li>
        <li>if_gif recursion cleanups, if_gif is much more MPSAFE.</li>
        <li>First pass MPSAFE locking of NFS server uses an NFS server
          subsystem lock to allow so_upcall() from socket layer without
          Giant.  This closes race conditions in the NFS server when
          operating Giant free.  Second pass for data based locking is
          also in testing.</li>
        <li>if_sl.c (SLIP) fine-grained locking completed and merged to
          CVS.</li>
        <li>if_tun.c (tunnel) fine-grained locking completed and merged to
          CVS.</li>
        <li>Merge of conditional Giant locking on debug.mpsafenet to CVS;
          semantics now changed so that Giant isn't just twiddled over
          the forwarding path, but the entire stack.  Must be used with
          caution unless running with our patches.  Callouts also
          convered to conditional safety.</li>
        <li>if_gif, if_gre global variables locked and merged to CVS.</li>
        <li>netatalk DDP cleanup (break out PCB from protocol code),
          largely locked down at the PCB level.  Some work remains to
          be done before patches can be distributed for testing, but close
          to MPSAFE.</li>
        <li>Began review of netipx, netinet6 code for locking requirements,
          some bugs corrected.</li>
        <li>Race conditions in handling of socket so_comp, so_incomp
          debugged and hopefully closed through new locking of these
          fields.</li>
        <li>Many new locking annotations, field documentation, lock order
          documentation.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Netperf patches are proving to be quite stable in a broad variety
        of environment, as long as non-MPSAFE chunks are avoided.  Kqueue,
        IPv6, and ifnet locking remain the most critical areas where
        additional functionality is required.  Focus is shifting from new
        development to in depth testing, performance measurement, and
        interactions with other subsystems.</p>
      <p>This work would not be possible without contributions from the
        following people (and no doubt many others):
        John Baldwin, Bob Bishop, Brooks Davis, Pawel Jakub Dawidek, Matthew
        Dodd, Julian Elischer, Ruslan Ermilov, John-Mark Gurney, Jeffrey Hsu,
        Kris Kennaway, Roman Kurakin, Max Laier, Sam Leffler, Scott Long, Rick
        Maklem, Bosko Milekic, George Neville-Neil, Andre Oppermann, Luigi
        Rizzo, Jeff Roberson, Tim Robbins, Mike Silberback, Bruce Simpson,
        Seigo Tanimura, Hajimu UMEMOTO, Jennifer Yang, Peter Wemm.  We hope to
        present these patches on arch@ within a few days, although some
        elements required continued refinement (especially socket locking).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Mandatory Access Control (MAC)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>
          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>
        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <common>TrustedBSD Discussion List</common>
        </name>
        <email>trustedbsd-discuss@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The TrustedBSD Mandatory Access Control (MAC) Framework
        permits the FreeBSD kernel and userspace access control
        policies to be adapted at compile-time, boot-time, or
        run-time.  The MAC Framework provides common infrastructure
        components, such as policy-agnostic labeling, making it
        possible to easily development and distribute new access
        control policy modules.  Sample modules include Biba, MLS,
        and Type Enforcement, as well as a variety of system
        hardening policies.</p>

      <p>The TrustedBSD MAC development branch in Perforce was
        integrated to the most recent 5-CURRENT.</p>

      <p>mdmfs(8) -l to create multi-label mdmfs file systems (merged).</p>

      <p>Diskless boot updated to support MAC.</p>

      <p>Re-arrangement of MAC Framework code to break out mac_net.c
        into mac_net.c, mac_inet.c, mac_socket.c (merged).</p>

      <p>libugidfw(3) grows bsde_add_rule(3) to automatically allocate
        rule numbers (merged).  ugidfw(8) grows 'add' to use this
        (merged).</p>

      <p>pseudofs(4) no longer requires MAC localizations.</p>

      <p>BPF fine-grained locking now used to protect BPD descriptor
        labels instead of Giant (merged).</p>

      <p>Prefer inpcb's as the source of labels over sockets when
        creating new mbufs throughout the network stack, reducing
        socket locking issues for labels.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Security-Enhanced BSD (SEBSD) port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>
          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>
        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <common>TrustedBSD Discussion List</common>
        </name>
        <email>trustedbsd-discuss@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>

      <p>TrustedBSD "Security-Enhanced BSD" (SEBSD) is a port of NSA's
        SELinux FLASK security architecture, Type Enforcement (TE)
        policy engine and language, and sample policy to FreeBSD using
        the TrustedBSD MAC Framework.  SEBSD is available as a loadable
        policy module for the MAC Framework, along with a set of
        userspace extensions support security-extended labeling calls.
        In most cases, existing MAC Framework functions provide the
        necessary abstractions for SEBSD to plug in without SEBSD-specific
        changes, but some extensions to the MAC Framework have been
        required; these changes are developed in the SEBSD development
        branch, then merged to the MAC branch as they mature, and then
        to the FreeBSD development tree.</p>

      <p>Unlike other MAC Framework policy modules, the SEBSD module
        falls under the GPL, as it is derived from NSA's
        implementation.  However, the eventual goal is to support
        plugging SEBSD into a base FreeBSD install without any
        modifications to FreeBSD itself.</p>

      <p>Integrated to latest FreeBSD CVS and MAC branch.</p>

      <p>New FreeBSD code drop updated for capabilities in preference
        to superuser checks.</p>

      <p>Installation instructions now available!</p>

    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Audit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>
          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>
        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <common>TrustedBSD Discussion List</common>
        </name>
        <email>trustedbsd-discuss@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The TrustedBSD Project is producing an implementation of CAPP
        compliant Audit support for use with FreeBSD based on the Apple
        Darwin implementation.</p>

      <p>Experimentally integrated the XNU audit implementation from Apple's
        Darwin 7.2 into Perforce.</p>

      <p>Adapted audit framework to compile into FreeBSD -- required
        modifying memory allocation and synchronization to use FreeBSD
        SMPng primitives instead of Mach primitives.
        Pushed down the Giant lock out of most of the audit code, various
        other FreeBSD adaptations such as suser() API changes, using BSD
        threads, td-&gt;td_ucred, etc.</p>

      <p>Adapted per-thread audit data to map to FreeBSD threads</p>

      <p>Cleaned up userspace/kernel API interactions, including udev_t/
        dev_t inconsistencies between Darwin and FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>Use vn_fullpath() instead of vn_getpath(), which is a less
        complete solution we'll need to address in the future.</p>

      <p>Basic kernel framework now operates on FreeBSD; praudit
        tool written that can parse FreeBSD BSM and Solaris BSM.</p>

    </body>
  </project>
</report>
