<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD DocBook XML V5.0-Based Extension//EN"
	"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/freebsd50.dtd">
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  
  <info><title>Argentina.com : A Case Study</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author><personname><firstname>Carlos</firstname><surname>Horowicz</surname></personname><affiliation>
          <address><email>ch@argentina.com</email>
          </address>
        </affiliation></author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice xml:id="trademarks" role="trademarks">
      &tm-attrib.freebsd;
      &tm-attrib.intel;
      &tm-attrib.xfree86;
      &tm-attrib.general;
    </legalnotice>

    <pubdate>$FreeBSD$</pubdate>

    <releaseinfo>$FreeBSD$</releaseinfo>
  </info>

<sect1 xml:id="overview">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>Argentina.Com is an Argentine ISP with a small infrastructure
    of fewer than 15 employees and whose primary source of income
    originates in the free dialup business. It began operation in the
    year 2000 with barely one server for mail and chat.</para>

  <para>It has since grown to a market presence in the Argentine free
    dialup market of 4.5 billion minutes annually. Its most popular
    product provides nearly half a million users with free e-mail with
    webmail, POP3 and SMTP access, and 300M disk space. Towards the
    end of 2002 there were around 50,000 mail users. After two and a
    half years of re-engineering and consistent technical improvements
    this ISP has grown by a factor of 3 in terms of billing, and by a
    factor of 10 with regard to the mail user base.</para>

  <para>Our competitors in the Argentine market of free dialup include
    Fullzero which is owned by the Clarin Media Group, Alternativa
    Gratis, and Tutopia which is funded by IFX and promoted by
    Hotmail. Some of these large corporate competitors started their
    free dialup business with multi-million dollar investments and
    aggressive television and Internet ad campaigns. Argentina.Com
    does not rely on advertising like these other larger corporations.
    It has climbed to the fourth position and to an 8% market share
    during the last two years thanks to superior quality of service.</para>

  <para>In Argentina and Latin America in general people who do not
    have computers at home go to so called <quote>Locutorios</quote>
    (Internet Centers), where for a few pesos they can use a computer
    connected to the Internet and usually read and write emails
    through popular webmails like Hotmail, Yahoo or
    Argentina.Com.</para>

  <para>Due to limited financial resources, Argentina.Com made the
    decision to invest in a new email system instead of publicity in
    the media. This strategic decision opens the door to a future
    business in the corporate and paid email arena.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="challenge">
  <title>The Challenge</title>

  <para>The main challenge for Argentina.Com is to achieve a dialup
    uptime of at least 99.95%, or less than 5 hours yearly
    downtime. Due to the high rotation and volatility in this
    business, things have to work correctly so the user does not switch
    -voluntarily or not- the dialup provider or the number he calls to
    connect. The dialup business involves a support structure to deal
    with the Telcos about telephony problems and quality of service,
    plus a technical structure where latency and packet-loss should be
    minimized due to the UDP nature of Radius and DNS, and where
    recursive DNS should always be available.</para>

  <para>This also implies having a high uptime in the POP3 and SMTP
    services, and in the webmail. For POP3 and SMTP we estimated the
    need for an uptime equal to the one for dialup, whereas for the
    webmail we could live with 99.5% which means around two days of
    yearly downtime.</para>

  <para>We decided to migrate the email to a proprietary, opensource
    architecture which should be horizontally scalable, and whose
    antivirus and antispam infrastructure should support more than
    just one type of mailstore or back-end.</para>

  <para>The rough competition in the free email market, mostly due to
    the recent improvements introduced by Hotmail, Yahoo and Gmail,
    made it necessary to design the new system with at least 300M user
    disk space, but at a cost lower than 3 US dollars per GB with some
    degree of redundancy. Bear in mind that rackmountable hardware is
    hard to find in Argentina, and is between 30 and 40% more
    expensive than in the US. Our total budget for equipment
    acquisition in two years was 75,000 USD, which is only a fraction
    of our direct competitors' investments.</para>

  <para>With regard to the antispam service, it became necessary to
    develop a product that could compete with the systems offered by
    the big ones. Given the hostile conditions imposed by the
    existence of spam (dictionary attacks, spams with high degree of
    obfuscation and refinement, phishing, trojans, mail-bombs, etc.)
    it becomes very difficult to achieve an excellent uptime while
    repelling attacks. One must also be careful that the user does not
    lose mails because of false positives in the classification
    strategy, that he does not become flooded with spam or spam
    notifications, and dangerous mails do not make it through to his
    mailbox. In addition, the technical infrastructure for spam
    classification should not introduce noticeable delays in the
    delivery of mails. Finally, the mail system has to be protected
    from spammers who might misuse it to send spam.</para>

  <para>The opensource paradigm tends to require hiring large teams of
    system administrators, operators and programmers who apply
    patches, correct bugs and integrate platforms. The opposed
    paradigm is also costly because of expensive software licences,
    the need for increasingly expensive hardware and a large support
    staff. So the challenge was to find the right mixture for scarce
    human and monetary resources, high stability and predictability,
    and quick and reliable deployment. In Buenos Aires, well-trained
    Computer Science professionals are hard to find, most of them live
    and work abroad, while the remaining have stable jobs either at
    the government or big companies.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="freebsd">
  <title>The FreeBSD solution</title>

  <sect2 xml:id="freebsd-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>At the beginning of 2003 we had a CriticalPath mail system
      running on Solaris x86 plus a Redhat box for SMTP, Radius and
      DNS. The DNS and Radius services were constantly down and we
      were struggling with huge mail queues.  There was an attempt to
      install CriticalPath for Linux into Redhat on an Intel box with
      a Megaraid card, but the disk latency was enormous and the mail
      application never really worked.</para>

    <para>The first step depicted towards the "FreeBSD solution"
      consisted in migrating this hardware and commercial software to
      FreeBSD 4.8 with Linux emulation.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="freebsd-choice">
    <title>The choice of FreeBSD</title>

    <para>The FreeBSD operating system is well-known for its great
      stability, plus its pragmatism and common sense to put
      applications on-line thanks to its excellent <link xlink:href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports">Ports System</link>.  We
      consider its <link xlink:href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng">release
      engineering process</link> to be easily understandable, while
      the users' community at the official mailing lists keeps a
      polite and civilized style when it comes to asking for support
      or reading other people's problems and solutions.</para>

    <para>Another important feature is quick deployment. Fortunately,
      we could state our OS install policy around FreeBSD's great
      out-of-the-box capability. In a small company you sometimes need
      to run to a Datacenter and quickly setup a server for some
      service. In the last two years, Argentina.Com acquired around
      forty servers, most of them Pentium IV but also several
      double-Xeons and a few double-Opterons to be co-located in the
      Datacenters where we have dialup and hosting operation
      contracts. All of them run FreeBSD, ranging from 4.8 (there are
      a couple with two years uptime and zero trouble) til currently
      6.0-BETA2.</para>

    <para>The general policy for the operating system is to try to
      bring all servers periodically to the stable code branch by
      using <literal>RELENG_4</literal>, <literal>RELENG_5</literal>
      and now <literal>RELENG_6</literal>. This regularity lets us be
      more prepared regarding possible exploits at the operating
      system or base software level, especially in web servers.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="freebsd-engineer">
    <title>Basic re-engineering</title>

    <para>The first re-engineering step was to put in place two
      FreeBSD 4.8 boxes whose unique task was to be authoritative DNS
      for all our domains. The chosen software was Bind9. Those boxes
      were co-located in different datacenters, taking care that there
      was good latency between them to avoid zone transfer problems,
      and making it possible to deal with TTLs between 60 and 600
      seconds to have quicker response in case of trouble.</para>

    <para>Second step was to deploy two more boxes of the same class,
      again in different Datacenters, to only deal with Radius and
      recursive DNS. The Network Access Servers at the Telcos were
      configured to send Radius Authorization and Accounting to those
      servers, and to assign these recursive DNSs to dialup users.</para>

    <para>The third <quote>golden rule</quote> never to put SMTP
      incoming and outgoing in the same servers. We deployed separate
      FreeBSD boxes with postfix for incoming and outgoing mail.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="freebsd-email">
    <title>Email migration</title>

    <para>The email migration required careful planning due to the
      fact that we were going to migrate both mail front and
      back-ends. We first built a perimetral antispam and antivirus
      system in FreeBSD 4.x and 5.x based on postfix, amavisd-new,
      clamav and SpamAssassin. These systems were to deliver mails to
      both the old and the new system until the new back-end was in
      place. In the meantime, we added small FreeBSD NFS boxes to
      increase CriticalPath's mailspool, without any problem.</para>

    <para>At the frontline of incoming mail, we put in place several
      MXs of the Argentina.com domain to filter dictionary attacks
      (attempts to forward mail to nonexistent users) as well as a
      black-list derived from SURBL that resulted in almost no false
      positives. The mails are then multiplexed to a cluster of
      double-Xeons and double-Opterons where we run amavisd-new with
      MySQL based white and black-listing. We discarded the use of
      Bayes and Autowhitelisting at the global level because of great
      quantities of false positives and false negatives. We instead
      defined a few spam levels going from the least to the most
      tolerant, each one with cutoff or discard levels.  Every email
      with a score below the one associated with the selected spam
      tolerance goes to the user's Inbox. Emails between this level
      and the cutoff level go to a user's folder named Spam, and those
      above the cutoff level get discarded because it is a very obvious
      spam. For the sake of simplicity, we transparently associated
      the use of the Address Book with the antispam system, so that
      every personal contact gets automatically whitelisted.</para>

    <para>With the introduction of Spamassassin 3.x, the DNS traffic
      to query global blacklists grew considerably, so we signed
      agreements with SpamCop, Spamhaus and SURBL to install public
      mirrors of their databases in our FreeBSD equipment. Thanks to
      these mirrors that cost us between 1 and 2Mbps in traffic, we
      were able to dramatically cut down Spamassassin latency.</para>

    <para>At the 3rd level there is the delivery to the maildrops. As
      soon as we started building a new Cyrus-Imap back-end with MySQL
      authentication, we needed to multiplex incoming mail to users in
      both old and new maildrop formats. Finally, we managed to
      migrate hundreds of thousands of mailspools to the new Cyrus
      architecture using a great tool named imapsync, which is
      directly installable from ports. We also put perdition, a POP3
      and IMAP proxy, in the middle to assure a transparent migration
      and distribution of mailboxes across several servers. Briefly,
      all information of where a user's maildrop is located resides in
      MySQL, and is being used by all software pieces in the
      chain.</para>

    <para>With regard to the hardware for disk space, we currently use
      seven Cyrus-Imap loaded FreeBSD boxes with diverse hardware. The
      biggest are Pentium IV with 4G of RAM and 3ware cards in chassis
      with 12 hotswappable bays, organized in 3 RAID-5 units of 1
      Terabyte each. The 3ware software sends you en email whenever
      the RAID is degraded -mostly because of a failing disk- and lets
      you rebuild the RAID with everything up and running. We use
      smartmontools in the cases where we have less redundancy, to
      have immediate alerts of disks with temperature problems or
      failing selftests.</para>

    <para>As webmail software, we chose a commercial product named
      Atmail, which is available with perl sources and utilizes
      mod_perl. Under FreeBSD it is extremely easy to deal with perl
      modules, you do not even need to use the CPAN shell, you just
      have to choose the right port and run "make install". After
      several months of integration work, we integrated the
      Client-only version of Atmail that talks IMAP with our
      back-ends. We had to modify some parts of the code to adapt the
      product to our massive free environment, and to our antispam and
      antivirus perimeter, in addition to our specific customizations
      and translations.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="freebsd-web">
    <title>Web migration</title>

    <para>With the adoption of FreeBSD, there was almost no additional
      effort necessary to setup a working Apache, PHP and MySQL
      environment in minutes. Even the upgrades from PHP4 to PHP5 were
      painless. The ports system was again extremely useful in these
      cases, and permitted us to do things like compress text and html
      contents in Apache with just a few lines of documentation. In
      addition, we have experienced excellent performance and
      rock-solid stability and uptime.</para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="results">
  <title>Results</title>

  <para>We managed to deploy a FreeBSD based email architecture that
    is horizontally scalable, using 3 Terabyte Intel based storage
    servers at a current cost of 3 dollars per Gigabyte with
    redundancy.</para>

  <para>The great stability achieved enabled Argentina.Com to explore
    other fields like hosting for resellers and housing with presence
    in three Argentine Datacenters.</para>

  <para>We offer now also corporate dialup for roaming users in
    Argentina and Peru thanks to our presence and contracts with most
    Telcos. Among our indirect customers, there are major American
    companies like Ford, Exxon and Reuters. We now run the free dialup
    business in Brazil, Chile, Colombia and Panama as well.</para>
</sect1>

</article>
