<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Charter for the Ports Management Team">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<p>The FreeBSD Ports Collection is a product intended first and
  foremost for the end-users of FreeBSD.  The Ports Management Team
  (portmgr) is the group charged with overseeing its development.
  Its members are appointed by the FreeBSD Core Team (core).</p>

<p>The primary responsibility of the portmgr team is to ensure
  that the FreeBSD Ports Developer community provides a ports
  collection that is functional, stable, up-to-date and
  full-featured.  Its secondary responsibility is to coordinate
  among the committers and developers who work on it.</p>

<p>The Ports Management Team has the following specific
  responsibilities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Assure the integrity of the Ports Collection by managing
      commits to the <tt>ports</tt> portion of the FreeBSD repository.
      This includes maintaining certain key files directly;
      running test builds of proposed large changes; and acting as
      arbiter over other commits.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Maintain the automated <a href="http://pkg.FreeBSD.org">
      package building cluster</a>, and make the resulting packages
      available for download by FreeBSD users.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Work with the FreeBSD Security team to ensure that security
      problems are indentified and handled in a timely fashion.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Work with FreeBSD Ports and Documentation Committers to
      keep the relevant documentation up to date.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>To the extent possible with a volunteer project, ensure
      that the legal rights of authors whose works are installed in
      the Ports Collection are respected.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Act as arbiter of first resort for disputes between
      FreeBSD community members such as maintainers and
      committers.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Manage commit access to the ports tree.  All new
      committer approvals must be sent to admins@, and CC'd to
      core@; they must be PGP-signed.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Establish guidelines and policies governing the rights and
      responsibilities of Ports Committers and maintainers.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Help prioritize future directions for the overall Ports
      Collection.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In addition to its specific responsibilities, The Ports Management
  Team may take whatever actions it believes prudent to manage the ports
  collection responsibly.</p>

<p>Please see <a href="policies.html">Ports Team Policies</a> for
  a complete list of the current policies which have been adopted to
  help implement these goals.</p>

<p>This charter is under the control of the FreeBSD Core Team.  It
  is valid until such time as it is modified or revoked by the Core
  Team; any changes to this charter must be approved by the Core Team.</p>

</body>
</html>
