<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY email 'portmgr'>
<!ENTITY title "Ports Management Team">
<!ENTITY contact.re '<a href="mailto:re@FreeBSD.org">re@FreeBSD.org</a>'>
<!ENTITY contact.so '<a href="mailto:security-officer@FreeBSD.org">security-officer@FreeBSD.org</a>'>
<!ENTITY contact.portmgr '<a href="mailto:portmgr@FreeBSD.org">portmgr@FreeBSD.org</a>'>
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<p>The FreeBSD Ports Management Team (also known as <tt>portmgr</tt>
  due to its email alias) is responsible for issues relating to the
  <a href="&base;/ports">FreeBSD Ports Collection</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="charter.html">Charter</a></h3>

<p>Discusses the goals, rights, and responsibilities of the team.
The contents of this document are approved by the FreeBSD
Core Team.</p>

<h3><a href="policies.html">Policies</a></h3>

<p>Discusses current policies that the team has adopted to meet
its goals, such as
<a href="policies_contributors.html">timeouts for inactivity</a> and
<a href="policies_committing.html">when commits are allowed</a>.
Also contains <a href="policies_eol.html">the policy for supported
releases and branches</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="implementation.html">Implementation Issues</a></h3>

<p>Discusses how that the way that the Ports Collection is implemented
affects the above policies, and, in particular, such concepts as
<a href="implementation.html#requires_regression_test">
changes that require regression tests</a>
and
<a href="implementation.html#sweeping_changes">sweeping changes</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="qa.html">Quality Assurance Activities</a></h3>

<p>A behind-the-scenes look at the efforts that are made to ensure that
  the Ports Collection works as well as it possibly can.</p>

<h3>Team Members</h3>

<p><a href="mailto:portmgr@FreeBSD.org">portmgr@FreeBSD.org</a>:
  &a.portmgr.members;</p>

<p>Secretary: &a.rene; (<a href="mailto:portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org"
  >portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</a>)</p>

<h3>Resources Of Interest To FreeBSD Contributors and Developers</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a
      href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/ports-contributing.html">
      Contributing to the FreeBSD Ports Collection</a><br/>

      <small>An introduction to how you can help contribute to the Ports
	Collection, by either contributing new ports or helping to fix
	problems in existing ports.  Included is detailed information on
	what the community will expect from you if you volunteer to maintain
	one or more ports.  Also includes a list of <a
	href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/resources.html">
	further resources</a>.</small>
    </p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p><a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook/index.html">
      FreeBSD Porter's Handbook</a><br/>

      <small>The central reference book for FreeBSD ports submitters,
	maintainers, and committers, mostly technically oriented.  It
	includes both mandatory requirements and recommendations of
	what portmgr believes are the best approaches to common problems.
	one or more ports.  Also includes information about <a
	href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/porters-handbook/keeping-up.html">
	keeping with changes</a> as well.</small></p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p><a href="https://pkg-status.freebsd.org/">FreeBSD Ports Build
      Cluster</a><br/>

      <small>These machines continually build packages on all possible
	combinations of OS release and CPU architecture (in our terminology,
	<tt>build environments</tt>), and produce error logs of problems
	that are encountered along the way.</small></p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p><a
      href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/releng/article.html#release-build">
      FreeBSD Release Engineering for Third Party Packages</a><br/>

      <small>Describes the approach used by the FreeBSD release
	engineering team to produce a high quality package set
	suitable for official FreeBSD release media, with specific
	emphasis on how to split up the packages for the release
	media, and how to verify that a package set is
	consistent.</small></p>
  </li>

  <!-- arguably the following should be added here:
    portsmon; fenner's list; PR statistics; Problem Report -->

  <li>
    <p><a
      href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/committers-guide/index.html">
	FreeBSD Committer's Guide</a><br/>

      <small>Includes a discussion of policies and issues that are of <a
	href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/committers-guide/ports.html">
	particular interest to committers to the ports tree</a>.</small></p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p><a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/pr-guidelines/index.html">
      Problem Report Handling Guidelines</a><br/>

      <small>While primarily aimed at FreeBSD committers, this should
	also be read by users interested in how best to attract attention
	to their PRs.</small></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>Resources Of General Interest</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.FreshPorts.org">FreshPorts</a><br/>

      <small>A site maintained by Dan Langille that lets you browse
	the state of the entire Ports Collection or any individual port
	within it.  Includes cross-references, links, charts and graphs,
	and many other things.  Of interest to users and developers
	alike.</small></p>
  </li>
</ul>


</body>
</html>
