<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Quality Assurance Tasks for the Ports Management Team">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<p>There are a number of tasks that the Ports Management Team undertakes
to try to improve the quality of the Ports Collection.  These fall into
two main categories:
<a href="#qa-before-release">activities during a release cycle</a> and
<a href="#qa-between-releases">activities between release cycles</a>.
</p>

<h3><a name="qa-before-release">Activities During a Release Cycle</a></h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Work with the
      <a href="../releng/index.html">Release Engineering Team</a>
      to coordinate the release schedule.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Work with the RE team to determine which pre-built packages
      can be included on the default install ISOs.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Cut over to the new quarterly branch.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3><a name="qa-between-releases">Activities Between Release Cycles</a></h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Manage the <a href="https://pkg-status.freebsd.org/">Ports Build
      Cluster</a> machines.  These machines continually build packages
      on all possible combinations of OS release and CPU architecture
      (in our terminology, <tt>build environments</tt>.)</p>

    <p>These builds also produce error logs for packages that do not
      build correctly (see the above URL).  Periodically, the team
      marks these ports as BROKEN so that maintainers may be notified.
      (See below.)</p>

    <p>Successfully built packages (at least, the ones that are freely
      redistributable) are also copied to the master FTP server and thus
      become the default &quot;latest package&quot; for installations
      that use packages rather than ports.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Notify the FreeBSD community of problems within the Ports
      Collection so that problems do not get overlooked.  To do this,
      there are a number of emailed reports.  Ones marked
      <tt>public</tt> are posted to freebsd-ports.</p>

    <ul>

      <li><p>a public list of all ports to be removed due to security
	problems, build failures, or general obsolescence, unless they
	are fixed first.</p></li>

      <li><p>private email to all maintainers of the affected ports
	(including ports dependent on the above).</p></li>

      <li><p>private email to all maintainers of ports that are already
	marked BROKEN and/or FORBIDDEN.</p></li>

      <li><p>private email to maintainers who are not committers, who have
	PRs filed against their ports (to flag PRs that might never have
	been Cc:ed to them).</p></li>

      <li><p>public email about port commits that break building of
	INDEX.</p></li>

      <li><p>public email about port commits that send the revision
	metadata backwards (and thus confuse tools like portupgrade).</p></li>

      <li><p>a public list of all ports that have at least one file
	that fails to fetch from any non-FreeBSD mastersite.  For the
	complete list of results for all files versus all mastersites,
	see <a href="https://people.FreeBSD.org/~ehaupt/distilator/">
	Emanuel Haupt's port survey</a>.</p></li>

      <li><p>private email to an affected port maintainer when a port
	is about to be marked BROKEN, Cc:ed to the last committer to
	the port.  (This email is not automated but it should be sent
	as a courtesy.)</p></li>

    </ul>

  </li>

  <li>
    <p>Remove expired ports.  Ports that have been marked BROKEN for
      some time are marked DEPRECATED (with an EXPIRATION_DATE) and then
      are removed if no one has fixed them by that time.  The intent of
      this process is to try to ensure that if a user installs a port,
      there is the best possible chance that it can be made to work.</p>

    <p>In other cases, ports are marked DEPRECATED when they have been
      replaced by a newer version and the older version is no longer
      maintained by the authors.  The EXPIRATION_DATE should generally
      be set at least two months in the future to allow everyone sufficient
      time to upgrade.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</html>
