<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--
     The FreeBSD Documentation Project

     $FreeBSD$
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="porting-samplem">

  <title>A Sample <filename>Makefile</filename></title>

  <para>Here is a sample <filename>Makefile</filename> that can be
    used to create a new port.  Make sure to remove all the extra
    comments (ones between brackets).</para>

  <para>The format shown is the recommended one for ordering
    variables, empty lines between sections, and so on.  This format
    is designed so that the most important information is easy to
    locate.  We recommend using
    <link linkend="porting-portlint">portlint</link> to check the
    <filename>Makefile</filename>.</para>

  <programlisting>[the header...just to make it easier for us to identify the ports.]
# &dollar;FreeBSD&dollar;
[ ^^^^^^^^^ This will be automatically replaced with RCS ID string by SVN
when it is committed to our repository.  If upgrading a port, do not alter
this line back to "&dollar;FreeBSD&dollar;".  SVN deals with it automatically.]

[section to describe the port itself and the master site - PORTNAME
 and PORTVERSION or the DISTVERSION* variables are always first,
 followed by CATEGORIES, and then MASTER_SITES, which can be followed
 by MASTER_SITE_SUBDIR.  PKGNAMEPREFIX and PKGNAMESUFFIX, if needed,
 will be after that.  Then comes DISTNAME, EXTRACT_SUFX and/or
 DISTFILES, and then EXTRACT_ONLY, as necessary.]
PORTNAME=	xdvi
DISTVERSION=	18.2
CATEGORIES=	print
[do not forget the trailing slash ("/")!
 if not using MASTER_SITE_* macros]
MASTER_SITES=	${MASTER_SITE_XCONTRIB}
MASTER_SITE_SUBDIR=	applications
PKGNAMEPREFIX=	ja-
DISTNAME=	xdvi-pl18
[set this if the source is not in the standard ".tar.gz" form]
EXTRACT_SUFX=	.tar.Z

[section for distributed patches -- can be empty]
PATCH_SITES=	ftp://ftp.sra.co.jp/pub/X11/japanese/
PATCHFILES=	xdvi-18.patch1.gz xdvi-18.patch2.gz
[If the distributed patches were not made relative to ${WRKSRC},
 this may need to be tweaked]
PATCH_DIST_STRIP=	-p1

[maintainer; *mandatory*!  This is the person who is volunteering to
 handle port updates, build breakages, and to whom a users can direct
 questions and bug reports.  To keep the quality of the Ports Collection
 as high as possible, we do not accept new ports that are assigned to
 "ports@FreeBSD.org".]
MAINTAINER=	asami@FreeBSD.org
COMMENT=	DVI Previewer for the X Window System

[license -- should not be empty]
LICENSE=	BSD2CLAUSE
LICENSE_FILE=	${WRKSRC}/LICENSE

[dependencies -- can be empty]
RUN_DEPENDS=	gs:print/ghostscript

[If it requires GNU make, not /usr/bin/make, to build...]
USES= gmake
[If it is an X application and requires "xmkmf -a" to be run...]
USES= imake

[this section is for other standard bsd.port.mk variables that do not]
 belong to any of the above]
[If it asks questions during configure, build, install...]
IS_INTERACTIVE=	yes
[If it extracts to a directory other than ${DISTNAME}...]
WRKSRC=		${WRKDIR}/xdvi-new
[If it requires a "configure" script generated by GNU autoconf to be run]
GNU_CONFIGURE=	yes
[et cetera.]

[If it requires options, this section is for options]
OPTIONS_DEFINE=	DOCS EXAMPLES FOO
OPTIONS_DEFAULT=	FOO
[If options will change the files in plist]
OPTIONS_SUB=yes

FOO_DESC=		Enable foo support

FOO_CONFIGURE_ENABLE=	foo

[non-standard variables to be used in the rules below]
MY_FAVORITE_RESPONSE=	"yeah, right"

[then the special rules, in the order they are called]
pre-fetch:
	i go fetch something, yeah

post-patch:
	i need to do something after patch, great

pre-install:
	and then some more stuff before installing, wow

[and then the epilogue]

.include &lt;bsd.port.mk&gt;</programlisting>
</chapter>
