<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD &java; Project: How To Help">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">
<p><b>I want to</b>:</p>
<br/>...<a href="#testing">help testing</a>
<br/>...<a href="#bug">report a bug</a>
<br/>...<a href="#documentation">write documentation</a>

<a name="testing"></a>
<p><b><font color="#660000">You want to help, but do not know C or FreeBSD <i>that</i> well?</font></b></p>
<p>The absolute best thing you can do is download the <a href="dists/">latest release</a>, install it, and try all your favorite Java applications.  If they don't work, see below.</p>

<a name="BUG"></a>
<p><b><font color="#660000">I have a bug!</font></b></p>
<p>If you find an application that does not work, or crashes, here are the steps you should follow before reporting it:</p>
<ol>
<li>Try it again.</li>
<li>Check your settings for this application.  Check to see if you made a mistake in starting it up.</li>
<li>Try it on a different platform.  If you have access to a reference platform, try it there.  (We need to determine if it is an application error, a Java bug, or a FreeBSD specific bug.)</li>
<li>Narrow down the problem.  If it is your own code, narrow down the bug to the offending code.  Otherwise, determine the steps required to reproduce the problem.</li>
<li>Notify the JDK porting team.  Send email to <a href="mailto:freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org">freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org</a>.  Be sure to include the steps you have followed.</li>
<li>Finally, and most importantly, be willing to work with the team to fix the problem.</li>
</ol>

<a name="documentation"></a>
<p><b><font color="#660000">I can help with the web site or documentation!</font></b></p>
<p>Everyone can help here.  If you have a suggestion to add to the documentation, write it up and send it to <a href="mailto:freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org">freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org</a></p>

</body>
</html>
