<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD &java; Project">
<!ENTITY url.books "../../doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

  <a href="http://java.sun.com/"><img src="j2j.gif" hspace="10"
    border="0" alt="Jump to &java;" align="right"/></a>

  <h2>Getting Java</h2>

  <p>There are two choices of Java Development Kits on FreeBSD:</p>

  <ul>

  <li>
    <h3>OpenJDK</h3>

    <p>The &openjdk; project provides a native open-source
      implementation of the &java; SE Platform and is available in
      versions 6, 7 and 8 for all supported FreeBSD releases on the i386
      and amd64 platforms.</p>

    <p>&openjdk; 7 is frequently updated, and it is suggested to refer to a
    <a href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/ports/head/java/openjdk7/Makefile?view=log">revision log</a> for
    detailed release history. Additionally, one may choose to review more information at
    <a href="http://www.freshports.org/java/openjdk7">FreshPorts</a>.</p>

    <p>To install &openjdk; 7 package use the pkg(8) utility:</p>

    <p>
      <code>pkg install openjdk</code>
      <br/>
      or
      <br/>
      <code>cd /usr/ports/java/openjdk7
      <br/>make install clean
      </code>
    </p>

    <p>&openjdk; 8 is frequently updated, and it is suggested to refer to a
    <a href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/ports/head/java/openjdk8/Makefile?view=log">revision log</a> for
    detailed release history. Additionally, one may choose to review more information at
    <a href="http://www.freshports.org/java/openjdk8">FreshPorts</a>.</p>

    <p>To install &openjdk; 8 package use the pkg(8) utility:</p>

    <p>
      <code>pkg install openjdk8</code>
      <br/>
      or
      <br/>
      <code>cd /usr/ports/java/openjdk8
      <br/>make install clean
      </code>
    </p>

    <p>&openjdk; 6 is frequently updated, and it is suggested to refer to a
    <a href="http://svnweb.freebsd.org/ports/head/java/openjdk6/Makefile?view=log">revision log</a> for
    detailed release history. Additionally, one may choose to review more information at
    <a href="http://www.freshports.org/java/openjdk6">FreshPorts</a>.</p>

    <p>To install &openjdk; 6 package use the pkg(8) utility:</p>

    <p>
      <code>pkg install openjdk6</code>
      <br/>
      or
      <br/>
      <code>cd /usr/ports/java/openjdk6
      <br/>make install clean
      </code>
    </p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <h3>Oracle JDK for Linux</h3>

    <p>This port installs the Java Development Kit from Oracle which was built for Linux. It will run under FreeBSD using the Linux compatibility.</p>

    <p><code>cd /usr/ports/java/linux-sun-jdk17
    <br/>make install clean
    </code></p>

    <p><b>Note:</b> Please note that due to the current licensing policy the
    Oracle JDK on FreeBSD binaries can not be distributed and you are only
    permitted to use them personally.  For the same reason, the sources
    must be fetched manually.</p>
  </li>

  <li>
    <h3>Legacy Native JDK</h3>
    <p>The FreeBSD Foundation is no longer providing supported &java; &jdk; and
      &jre; packages based on Sun's partner sources.  Older packages for &java;
      &jdk; and &jre; 5.0 and 6.0 are still available below for reference and
      legacy use only, but are no longer supported.</p>

    <p>Further information about downloading the unsupported binaries is
      available from the
      <a href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/java">FreeBSD
      Foundation &java; Downloads</a> page.</p>
  </li>
  </ul>

  <h2>Documentation</h2>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="&url.books;/porters-handbook/using-java.html">Creating Ports</a></li>
  </ul>

  <h2>I want to help by...</h2>

  <h3>... testing</h3>

  <p>The best thing you can do is download the latest release, install it, and try all your favorite Java applications.  If they don't work, see below.</p>

  <h3>... reporting a bug</h3>
  <p>If you find an application that does not work, or crashes, here are the steps you should follow before reporting it:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Try it again.</li>
    <li>Check your settings for this application.  Check to see if you made a mistake in starting it up.</li>
    <li>Try it on a different platform.  If you have access to a reference platform, try it there.  (We need to determine if it is an application error, a Java bug, or a FreeBSD specific bug.)</li>
    <li>Narrow down the problem.  If it is your own code, narrow down the bug to the offending code.  Otherwise, determine the steps required to reproduce the problem.</li>
    <li>Notify the JDK porting team.  Send email to <a href="mailto:freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org">freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org</a>.  Be sure to include the steps you have followed.</li>
    <li>Finally, and most importantly, be willing to work with the team to fix the problem.</li>
  </ol>

  <h3>...writing documentation</h3>
  <p>Everyone can help here.  If you have a suggestion to add to the documentation, write it up and send it to <a href="mailto:freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org">freebsd-java@FreeBSD.org</a></p>

  </body>
</html>
