<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Bug Reports">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.support">

	<h2>Problem Report Database</h2>

	    <p>Current FreeBSD problem reports are tracked using the <a
	      href="http://www.gnu.org/software/gnats/">GNATS</a>
	      database.</p>

	    <p>A FreeBSD problem report (PR) is not necessarily a bug with FreeBSD
	      itself.  In some cases it may be reporting a mistake in the
	      documentation (which could be a simple typo).  In other cases it may
	      be a 'wishlist' item that the submitter would like to see incorporated
	      in to FreeBSD.  In many cases a PR contains a port which has been
	      prepared for inclusion in the FreeBSD
	      <a href="&base;/ports/index.html">Ports and Packages</a> collection.</p>

	    <p>Problem reports start 'open', and are closed as the issue they report
	      is resolved.  In addition, each PR is assigned a unique tracking ID
	      to ensure that it is not lost.  Many FreeBSD changes include the
	      tracking ID of the PR that prompted the change.</p>

	    <ul>
	      <li><a href="&cgibase;/query-pr-summary.cgi">View or
		  search problem reports</a></li>

	      <li><a href="&base;/send-pr.html">Submit a Problem Report</a></li>

	    </ul>

	<h2>How to Submit A Problem Report</h2>

	    <p>Problem reports may be submitted to the development team using the
	      <a href="&cgibase;/man.cgi?query=send-pr&amp;sektion=1">send-pr(1)</a>
	      command on a &os; system or by
	      using the web based <a href="&base;/send-pr.html">form</a>.
	      Please note that
	      messages sent to a mailing list are <em>not</em> tracked as
	      official problem reports, and may get lost in the noise!</p>

	    <p>Before submitting a problem report, you might find it useful to
	      read the <a
	      href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/problem-reports/">Writing
	      FreeBSD Problem Reports</a> article.  This article describes
	      when you should submit a problem report, what you are expected
	      to include in one, and what the best way to submit your problem
	      report is.  Some useful background information is also contained
	      in the <a href="&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/pr-guidelines/">Problem
      Report Handling Guidelines</a> article.</p>


</body>
</html>
