<?Xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Project Associates">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h1>FreeBSD Project Associate</h1>

    <p>An Associate is an individual who has made a notable contribution
      to the FreeBSD project. That may be in the form of new code,
      documentation, or patches to existing code and documentation
      committed through a currently valid Committer, or in other ways
      that the Core Team designates, including community management and
      advocacy. Associates do not have any voting rights or
      responsibilities to the project other than to ensure their
      contributed material adheres to the project's standards and
      practices, that the work is original to the author and is made
      available under the standard, FreeBSD license.</p>

    <h2>Associates receive:<h2>

    <ul>
      <li>an @freebsd.org email address which also gives them regular
        Bugzilla and Phabricator logins</li>
      <li>permission to assign bugs to themselves in bugzilla</li>
      <li>access to freefall and the universe build machines</li>
      <li>access to the test clusters</li>
      <li>the right to attend developer summits</li>
      <li>access to the developers@ mailing list</li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>Associates MUST create SSH and PGP keys in exactly the same way
      that a committer would to gain access to project resources.</p>

    <p>Associates are bound by the Code of Conduct of the FreeBSD Project.</p>

    <p>Associate status is conferred by a ballot of Core members, or
      by other groups that Core may designate such as Portmgr or Doceng.
      Any FreeBSD committer or associate may propose candidates for
      associate status.</p>

    <p>Core, or groups that core may designate, that award associate
      status, should review that status at least once annually and
      retire inactive accounts. There is no minimum level of
      contribution required, Core and the designated teams may use their
      own discretion.</p>

    <hr/>

    <h2>FAQ:</h2>

    <dl>
      <dt>Assigning a buddy (or group of buddies) to the
        associate.</dt>
      <dd>No. Associates will be assigned a mentor when they reach a
        level to upgrade from Associate to Committer. Until that time,
        they can use the mailing lists and the phabricator review
        groups.</dd>
      <dt>Do committers who have given up their commit bits
        effectively become associates?</dt>
      <dd>No, they become Alumni.</dd>
      <dt>How does this affect the existing 3rd Party Developer
        status?</dt>
      <dd>Existing 3rd party developers will be promoted to
        Associates.</dd>
    </dl>
    
  </body>
</html>
