<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Charter for the Cluster Administrators">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.docs">


<p>Lead cluster administrator is a delegated officer role (aka.  "hat")
  that answers to the &os; Core Team and ultimately the &os; community
  at large.  This person shall have the operational authority over the
  &os; cluster infrastructure (to the extent that the Core Team can
  delegate this authority) and will be responsible for the following in
  general:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ensure the reliable operation of the Project's equipment and
    network resources.</li>

  <li>Ensure that the Project's resources are suitably and effectively
    used to serve the Project's interests.</li>

  <li>Ensure that reasonable security precautions and mitigations are
    implemented within the constraints of the nature of a highly
    distributed project.</li>

  <li>Delegate to and coordinating with both the site-specific admin
    teams and the admins at large.</li>

  <li>Ensure that standard operating procedures, rules, guidelines etc
    are documented and understandable.</li>

  <li>Take measures to ensure that a competent administrator would be
    expected to be able to adopt a predecessor's work in a reasonable
    amount of time.</li>

  <li>Contingency planning and implementation to ensure continuity
    across site specific problems (including donated site withdrawal or
    outages).</li>

  <li>Keep the interested parties (Core Team, Security Team, &os;
    Foundation, Port Management Team, etc), project members and community
    members appropriately informed.</li>

  <li>Give timely and authoritive answers to questions, or a direct
    referral to the appropriate party.</li>

  <li>Aid other hat wearers and cluster administrators to get their job
    done.</li>

  <li>Where practical and appropriate, use the Project's own product as
    a proving ground.</li>

  <li>Make sure that it is easy for developers to know what hardware
    resources they have access to for project purposes.</li>
</ul>

<p>The lead cluster administrator answers to the &os; Core Team.  If a
  party is unhappy with a position that the hat wearer takes and is
  unable to change their mind, they may take the issue to the Core Team.
  The Core Team has the final say in the matter.  If the lead cluster
  administrator is a member of the Core Team then a complaint may be
  made in confidence via the core secretary or another member if
  desired.</p>

<p>Any of the following still require a sign-off from the Core Team:</p>

<ul>
  <li>New public facing services.</li>

  <li>Planned withdrawal of public facing services.</li>

  <li>New team members.</li>
</ul>

<p>Notable interaction with other hats:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The lead cluster administrator will consult with the Security
    Officer and the Security Team where appropriate but will be
    responsible for making decisions.  However, the Security Officer may
    respond to security emergencies involving project infrastructure as
    necessary.</li>

  <li>The Port Management Team has a large resource footprint and
    arrangements will be made with them to effectively operate their
    resources within the constraints of the overall cluster
    operation.</li>
</ul>

<p>Earmarked resources:</p>

<p>Some site resources are provided for specific purposes.  Any such
  earmarking or use restrictions will be documented to make sure such
  resources are used as intended.</p>

  </body>
</html>
