<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Code of Conduct">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>Introduction</h2>

    <p>We expect everyone involved with the &os; project to follow
      this Code of Conduct.  This not only includes developers and
      contributors to &os; but also anyone posting to &os; mailing
      lists or using the &os; Forums or chatting on &os; specific IRC
      channels, or otherwise interacting with the &os; community.</p>

    <p>Each individual's behaviour is primarily a matter for their
      personal conscience.  Even so, there are limits whose breach
      will not be tolerated.  This page explains what is normally
      expected of &os; community members, and what is absolutely
      required.</p>

    <h2>Interpersonal Interaction</h2>

    <ul>
      <li>Keep it civil.</li>
      <li>Be tolerant.</li>
      <li>Remember that you are in public and that your actions
        determine the public perception of the project.</li>
      <li>Do not make it personal.  Do not take it personally.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Always strive to present a civil and courteous demeanour in
      your dealings with other project members; moreso when dealing
      with third parties from outside the project.  Avoid foul or
      abusive language: remember that cultural standards differ, and
      that what may seem to you to be a very mild statement can be
      deeply shocking to another.  Avoid contentious topics (unless
      directly technically relevant).  These things all have their
      places, but not here, where they are out of context.</p>

    <p>Try not to take offense where no offense was intended.  Not
      everyone speaks or writes English fluently.  Not everyone can
      express themselves clearly.  Give people the benefit of the
      doubt.  Even if the intent was to provoke, do not rise to
      it.</p>

    <p>Conflict is inevitable, but unseemly conduct is not.  If you
      must disagree forcefully, do so within the appropriate technical
      discussion group and in a manner that will be acceptable to your
      audience.  Stay focused on the topic at hand.  Heated
      arguments have a way of dragging in bystanders and mutating
      until the original point is lost.</p>

    <p>Stick to the facts.  Anyone may disagree with you: this does
      not give you a license to descend into personal insults.  If
      your arguments cannot stand up in their own right, then either
      admit defeat gracefully or formulate better arguments.</p>

    <h2>What Will Not Be Tolerated</h2>

    <p>The following will not be tolerated, and can result in
      expulsion from the community</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Discrimination based on gender, race, nationality,
	sexuality, religion, age or physical disability.</li>
      <li>Bullying or systematic harassment.</li>
      <li>Incitement to or condoning of any of these.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>There can be no place
      within the &os; Community for discriminatory speech or action.
      We do not believe anyone should be treated any differently based
      on who they are, where they are from, where their ancestors were
      from, what they look like, what gender they identify as, who
      they choose to sleep with, how old they are, their physical
      capabilities or what sort of religious beliefs they may hold.
      What matters is the contribution they are able to make to the
      project, and only that.</p>

    <p>There is no place within the &os; Community for
      behaviour intended to intimidate or persecute other members of
      the community.  No one should have any cause to fear involvement
      with the &os; project.</p>

    <p>We will not tolerate any member of the community, either
      publicly or privately, giving aid or encouragement to any
      third party to behave in such a way towards any members of
      the &os; community.</p>

    <p>Core will remove any and all access to &os; resources or
      privileges for whatever period it deems fit, up to and including
      a permanent ban where it rules that a transgression has
      happened.</p>

    <h2>In Case of Conflict</h2>

    <ul>
      <li>If contested, back out your changes first, then argue your
        case.</li>
      <li>Ask for review.</li>
      <li>Seek approval from maintainers.</li>
      <li>When no mutually satisfactory resolution can be achieved,
	defer to security-officer, doceng, portmgr, or core</li>
    </ul>

    <p>If there are a sustained set of objections to a change you
      have made, be graceful and revert what you have done.
      Objections are hardly likely to be raised for trivial reasons,
      and commits can always be re-applied.  The potential loss of
      reputation for the project from shipping bad code is
      permanent.</p>

    <p>Seeking review beforehand is the best way to avoid
      misunderstanding.  It is not just good practice for improving
      code quality: it facilitates putting opposing technical
      arguments clearly and reasonably.</p>

    <p>It is strongly encouraged that you consult maintainers before
      making changes in their particular areas, although in many areas
      some teams have given blanket approval for certain types of
      change.  For instance, various types of sweeping updates to the
      ports are permitted without reference to individual port
      maintainers.  It is the duty of committers and maintainers to
      keep up-to-date with such standards and practices, and abide by
      them.  Getting maintainer approval for any change, even if not
      strictly required, is never a bad thing, and certainly
      courteous.</p>

    <p>If you cannot agree, who should you turn to for arbitration?
      Core itself is directly responsible for the base system, but has
      delegated control over ports, documentation, release engineering
      and security related functions to sub-committees.  Operational
      control of &os; cluster servers, user accounts, e-mail, various
      web-based and other services have been similarly devolved to <a
      href="../administration.html">specific teams</a>.  These teams
      are the first line of resort when disputes cannot be resolved and
      require mediation.  Failing that, a decision by core will be
      final.</p>
  </body>
</html>
