<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Code of Conduct">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword
      xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>&os; Community Code of Conduct</h2>

    <p>The &os; community has always worked to be a welcoming and
      respectful community, and we want to ensure that doesn't change
      as we grow and evolve. To that end, we have a few ground rules
      that we ask people to adhere to:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>be friendly and patient,</li>

      <li>be welcoming,</li>

      <li>be considerate,</li>

      <li>be respectful,</li>

      <li>be careful in the words that you choose and be kind to
	others,</li>

      <li>when we disagree, try to understand why.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>This isn't an exhaustive list of things that you can't do.
      Rather, take it in the spirit in which it's intended - a guide
      to make it easier to communicate and participate in the
      community.</p>

    <p>This code of conduct applies to all spaces managed by the &os;
      project. This includes online chat, mailing lists, bug trackers,
      &os; events such as the developer meetings and socials, and any
      other forums created by the project that the community uses for
      communication. It applies to all of your communication and
      conduct in these spaces, including emails, chats, things you
      say, slides, videos, posters, signs, or even t-shirts you
      display in these spaces. In addition, violations of this code
      outside these spaces may, in rare cases, affect a person's
      ability to participate within them, when the conduct amounts to
      an egregious violation of this code.</p>

    <p>If you believe someone is violating the code of conduct, we ask
      that you report it by emailing <a
	href="mailto:conduct@freebsd.org">conduct@FreeBSD.org</a>. For
      more details please see our <a
	href="conduct-reporting.html">Reporting Guide</a>.</p>

    <ul>
      <li><b>Be friendly and patient.</b></li>

      <li><b>Be welcoming.</b> We strive to be a community that
	welcomes and supports people of all backgrounds and
	identities. This includes, but is not limited to members of
	any race, ethnicity, culture, national origin, color,
	immigration status, social and economic class, educational
	level, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity and
	expression, age, size, family status, political belief,
	religion or lack thereof, and mental and physical
	ability.</li>

      <li><b>Be considerate.</b> Your work will be used by other
	people, and you in turn will depend on the work of others. Any
	decision you take will affect users and colleagues, and you
	should take those consequences into account. Remember that
	we're a world-wide community, so you might not be
	communicating in someone else's primary language.</li>

      <li><b>Be respectful.</b> Not all of us will agree all the time,
	but disagreement is no excuse for poor behavior and poor
	manners. We might all experience some frustration now and
	then, but we cannot allow that frustration to turn into a
	personal attack. It's important to remember that a community
	where people feel uncomfortable or threatened is not a
	productive one. Members of the &os; community should be
	respectful when dealing with other members as well as with
	people outside the &os; community.</li>

      <li><b>Be careful in the words that you choose and be kind to
	others.</b> Do not insult or put down other participants.
	Harassment and other exclusionary behavior aren't acceptable.
	This includes, but is not limited to:

	<ul>
	  <li>Violent threats or language directed against another
	    person.</li>

	  <li>Discriminatory jokes and language.</li>

	  <li>Posting sexually explicit or violent material.</li>

	  <li>Posting (or threatening to post) other people's
	    personally identifying information ("doxing").</li>

	  <li>Personal insults, especially those using racist or
	    sexist terms.</li>

	  <li>Unwelcome sexual attention.</li>

	  <li>Advocating for, or encouraging, any of the above
	    behavior.</li></ul></li>

        <li><b>In general, if someone asks you to stop, then
	  stop.</b> Persisting in such behavior after being asked to
	  stop is considered harassment.</li>

	<li><b>When we disagree, try to understand why.</b>
	  Disagreements, both social and technical, happen all the
	  time and &os; is no exception. It is important that we
	  resolve disagreements and differing views constructively.
	  Remember that we're different. The strength of &os; comes
	  from its varied community, people from a wide range of
	  backgrounds. Different people have different perspectives on
	  issues. Being unable to understand why someone holds a
	  viewpoint doesn't mean that they're wrong. Don't forget that
	  it is human to err and blaming each other doesn't get us
	  anywhere. Instead, focus on helping to resolve issues and
	  learning from mistakes.</li></ul>

    <h2>Questions?</h2>

    <p>If you have questions, please feel free to contact the &os;
      Code of Conduct Committee by emailing <a
	href="mailto:conduct@freebsd.org">conduct@FreeBSD.org</a> or
      the &os; Core team <a
	href="mailto:core@freebsd.org">core@FreeBSD.org</a>.</p>

    <p>(This text is based on the LLVM Project's <a
	href="https://llvm.org/docs/CodeOfConduct.html">draft
      CoC</a>, which in turn is based on the <a
	href="https://www.djangoproject.com/conduct/">Django
	Project</a> Code of Conduct, which is in turn based on
      wording from the Speak Up! project.)</p>
  </body>
</html>
