<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Code of Conduct Reporting Instructions">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword
      xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>&os; Code of Conduct Reporting Instructions</h2>

    <p>If you believe someone is violating the
      <a href="code-of-conduct.html">code of conduct</a> we ask
      that you report it to the &os; Code of Conduct Committee by
      emailing <a
      href="mailto:conduct@freebsd.org">conduct@freebsd.org</a>.</p>

    <p>All reports will be kept confidential whenever possible.  We
      strive to protect the identity and safety of reporters.  In some
      cases we may need to make a public statement of some form, in
      which case we will use the minimum of details and identifying
      information necessary to protect our community.  In rare cases,
      we may need to identify some of the people involved to comply
      with the law or protect other potential victims.  In these
      cases, we will consult with the reporter to find out what their
      wishes are and take them into account in our final decision.  In
      all cases, we will not directly or indirectly identify reporters
      without their consent unless we see no other option.</p>

    <p>If you believe anyone is in physical danger, please notify
      appropriate law enforcement first.</p>

    <p>In your report please include:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Your name and contact info (so we can get in touch with you
	if we need to follow up)</li>

      <li>Names (real, nicknames, and/or pseudonyms) of any
	individuals involved.  If there were other witnesses besides
	you, please try to include them as well.</li>

      <li>When and where the incident occurred.  Please be as specific
	as possible.</li>

      <li>Your account of what occurred.  If there is a publicly
	available record (e.g. a mailing list archive, tweet, or a
	public IRC logger) please include a link and/or screen
	shots.</li>

      <li>Any extra context you believe relevant for the
	incident.</li>

      <li>If you believe this incident is ongoing.</li>

      <li>Any other information you believe we should have.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>What happens after you file a report?</h2>

    <p>You will receive an email from the &os; Code of Conduct
      Committee acknowledging receipt of your report within 48
      hours.</p>

    <p>The committee will meet as quickly as possible to review the
      incident and determine:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Whether an investigation is needed, including interviewing
	additional parties or witnesses;</li>

      <li>What appears to have happened and;</li>

      <li>Whether the behavior constitutes a Code of Conduct
	violation.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>If a member of the &os; Code of Conduct Committee is one of
      the individuals included in the report they will recuse
      themselves from handling the report.</p>

    <p>Once the working group has a complete account of the events
      they will make a decision as to how to respond.  Actions taken
      may include:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Nothing (for example, if we determine that no violation
	occurred).</li>

      <li>If determined to be solely technical in nature or if it
	falls outside the scope of the Code of Conduct, forwarding the
	incident to the &os; Core Team</li>

      <li>A private reprimand from the working group to the
	individual(s) involved.</li>

      <li>A public reprimand.</li>

      <li>An imposed vacation from &os; Project controlled spaces
	(e.g. asking someone to &quot;take a week off&quot; from a
	mailing list or IRC).</li>

      <li>A permanent or temporary ban from some or all &os;
	Project controlled spaces (events, meetings, mailing lists,
	IRC, etc.)</li>

      <li>A request for a public or private apology.</li>

      <li>A request to engage in mediation and/or an accountability
	plan.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>We will do our best to respond within one week to the person
      who filed the report with either a resolution or an explanation
      of why the situation is not yet resolved.</p>

    <p>Once we have determined our final action, we will contact the
      original reporter to let them know what action (if any) we will
      be taking.  We will take into account feedback from the reporter
      on the appropriateness of our response, but we do not guarantee
      we will act on it.</p>

    <p>Finally, the committee will make a report on the situation to
      the &os; Core Team.  The Core Team may choose to issue a
      public report of the incident.</p>

    <h2>Appeals</h2>

    <p>Only permanent resolutions (such as bans) may be appealed.  To
      appeal a decision of the CoC Committee, contact the &os; Core
      Team at <a href="mailto:core@freebsd.org">core@freebsd.org</a>
      with your appeal and the Core Team will review the case.</p>

  </body>
</html>
