<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Hats Term Limits Policy">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2>Rationale</h2>

    <p>The FreeBSD Core team appoints several individuals
      (&quot;hats&quot;) that perform critical roles within the
      project.  It is important to reduce single points of failure in
      these roles.  Additionally, turnover in hats can provide fresh
      insight and help avoid burnout.</p>

    <p>The current set of core-appointed hats is core secretary,
      head release engineer, the security officer, and postmaster.</p>

    <p>The FreeBSD Core team has approved the following hats term
      limits policy.  This was first posted to the Developers mailing
      list on June 22, 2012, and amended in June 2015.</p>

    <h2>Policy</h2>

    <p>An individual may serve as a core-appointed hat given that:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Core approves their appointment or re-appointment to the
	role.</li>
      <li>The individual is willing to continue.</li>
      <li>The individual is still able to perform the role
	effectively.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Hats are appointed at the pleasure of core.  Appointments may
      be rescinded by core at any time where this serves the needs of
      the project.</p>

    <p>Each hat's term begins three months after the start of a core
      team's two year term and ends three months after the end of the
      core team's term.  Hats are explicitly approved by the new core
      team at the start of the hat's term.</p>

    <p>If a hat becomes vacant during a term, core shall appoint a
      replacement for the remainder of the term.</p>

    <p>Core shall review all hats annually.</p>

    <p>In general it is expected that volunteers serving in hat
      positions will be limited to serving for four consecutive years,
      rounded up to the first natural review/appointment cycle.</p>

    <p>Non volunteers serving in hat positions are still expected to
      participate in annual reviews and provide for continuity to
      core's satisfaction.</p>

    <p>Each hat must appoint a deputy who can cover their role in
      the case of absence or illness, and be trained and ready to take
      over the role (subject to core approval) should the role holder
      resign before the end of their term.</p>

    <p>If a core team is dissolved prematurely, then the next term
      for each hat will begin three months after the new core team's
      term begins.</p>

    <p>These limits apply to individual hats and not to teams.  For
      teams with a single lead role, the limits shall apply to the
      lead role.  An individual that is not eligible to serve as the
      lead of a team may continue to serve as a member of the
      team.</p>

  </body>
</html>
