<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Project Members">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h1>FreeBSD Project Members</h1>

    <p>A FreeBSD Project Member is an individual who has made a
      notable contribution to the FreeBSD Project, and who is
      continuing to contribute to the Project.  That may be in the
      form of new code, documentation, or patches to existing code and
      documentation, or in other ways that the Core Team designates,
      including community management and advocacy.</p>

    <h3>Committers</h3>

    <p>Committers are those Project members who have been granted
      commit access (a "commit bit") to one or more of the Project's
      repositories.</p>

    <h2>Member Benefits:</h2>

    <ul>
      <li>an @freebsd.org email address which also gives them regular
	Bugzilla and Phabricator logins</li>
      <li>permission to assign bugs to themselves in bugzilla</li>
      <li>access to freefall and the universe build machines</li>
      <li>access to the test clusters</li>
      <li>the right to attend developer summits</li>
      <li>access to the developers@ mailing list</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Committer Benefits:</h2>

    <p>In addition to the Ordinary Member benefits, active
      Committers (those who have made a commit within the previous
      year) are able to vote in Core elections.</p>

    <h2>Member Responsibilities:</h2>

    <p>All Members should ensure that all contributed material:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>adheres to the Project's standards and practices.</li>
      <li>is correctly attributed to its authors.</li>
      <li>has appropriate licensing.  Where this is the original work
	of the Project Member, the standard FreeBSD license is
	preferred.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Members MUST create SSH and PGP keys in order to gain access to
      Project resources.</p>

    <p>Members are bound by the Project's Code of Conduct,
      particularly when representing the Project in external fora.</p>

    <p>Member status is conferred by a ballot of Core members, or by
      a ballot of other groups that Core may designate such as Portmgr
      or Doceng.  Any FreeBSD Committer or Member may propose
      candidates for member status.</p>

    <p>Core, or groups designated by Core that award Member status,
      should review that status at least once annually and retire
      inactive accounts.  There is no formal definition of inactive
      accounts.  Core and the designated teams may use their own
      discretion.</p>

    <hr/>

    <h2>FAQ:</h2>

    <dl>
      <dt>Is a mentor assigned to each newly created Project
	Member?</dt>
      <dd>Project Members are only assigned a mentor if they become
	a committer, or if they have a commit bit reactivated after
	a significant period of inactivity.  This only applies to
	Committers since the primary purpose of a mentor is to review
	what the mentee intends to commit.</dd>
      <dd>No such formal arrangement is required when someone is
	made into an ordinary Project Member, but it is expected that
	the people that sponsor a new Member will assist them with
	setting up their accounts and gaining access to Project
	resources and so forth.</dd>
      <dt>Do you have to become an Ordinary Member before you can be
	granted a commit bit?</dt>
      <dd>No.  There is no requirement for prospective Committers to
	have spent time as Ordinary Members.  However it is
	anticipated that this will become a common practice as part of
	the route towards committer-hood.</dd>
      <dt>Do Committers who have given up their commit bits
	effectively become just Ordinary Members?</dt>
      <dd>All Committers are Project members, but former Committers
	are considered Committer Alumni.  Alumni may revert back to
	active Committers simply by requesting reinstatement of their
	commit access.</dd>
      <dt>How does this affect the existing 3rd Party Developer
	status?</dt>
      <dd>Existing 3rd Party Developers will be promoted to Project
	Members.</dd>
    </dl>
  </body>
</html>
