<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Proposing Committers">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

<p>The following paragraphs contain an advice from &a.kib;, member of
  the Core Team, who summarizes what constitutes a good proposal, how
  you as potential mentor, could increase your chances to have your
  mentee granted a commit bit.</p>

<p>When proposing somebody, you should just forget for a moment that you
  know the candidate personally.  After that, look unprejudiced on the
  person's activity on the mailing lists, and evaluate the patches
  submitted.</p>

<p>Now, you can ask yourself, is it enough confidence in both technical
  abilities and the social behavior of the candidate, from what you see
  only on the media?  If you do, then write down the reasons why are
  you sure, using the said list of the contributions as the evidence,
  and do include the reasoning in the commit bit application.</p>

<p>Due to several failures of the premature granting of commit bits, the
  Core Team became quite sensitive to these criteria.  Most of the
  members only see the activity of applicants on the lists, and not
  seeing much there causes the cautious choice.</p>

<p>The Core Team wants to see a good list of the work already done for
  &os; (e.g., the long list of the commits, submitted by the applicant,
  the list of PRs opened etc.), which can make us confident that the
  person has an established interest in the project, backed by the
  technical ability and work done.</p>

<p>Also, the history of the good engagement with the community on the
  public media, such as mailing list, is a deciding factor too.  The
  Core Team wants to filter out the controversial personalities, since
  it is almost impossible and highly undesirable to revoke the commit
  bit, once granted.</p>

<p>Vendor-proposed maintainers for the hardware drivers usually approved
  without applying the listed criteria.  Still, the Core Team requires
  an experienced mentor for a vendor committer to avoid unwanted tension
  and to make sure that vendor commits follow the Project procedures and
  community expectations.</p>

  </body>
</html>
