<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Proposing Committers">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>&title;</title>

    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
  </head>

  <body class="navinclude.docs">

<p>The following advice is intended for potential mentors in deciding 
  whether a candidate might be suitable to propose for a commit bit, and 
  in preparing a commit-bit proposal for consideration by the Core Team or 
  its delegates. Note that in the case of delegated approval (e.g., to 
  Portmgr or Doceng), additional procedures or constraints may apply 
  (e.g., to the nature of the contribution).</p>

<p>Commit-bit proposal reviewers will look for several key attributes from 
  potential developers: strong technical abilities, a track record of 
  contributions to the &os; Project, evidence of their ability to work 
  independently within the community (i.e., that mentoring will not need 
  to continue indefinitely), evidence of the ability of a developer to 
  engage constructively with the &os; community (and in particular, 
  have the social skills to navigate occasionally heated online debate), 
  and a commitment to contribute to the project in the future. Typically, 
  supporting material for a commit-bit proposal will include a description 
  of the candidate's background and training/education, the context for 
  their contributions to the project (e.g., as a volunteer, employee, 
  etc), references to patches/PRs/commits justifying their contribution 
  track record, pointers at mailing-list or other community participation 
  (e.g., presentations at BSD conferences), a strong indication of 
  constructive engagement with their mentor to date, and a list of 
  interests and potential areas of continuing and future contribution.</p>

<p>Potential mentors are reminded that it is far easier to grant commit 
  access than revoke it, and hence significant weight is given to 
  constructive interaction with the community, rather than simply 
  technical contributions. If a mentor is uncertain as to whether a 
  candidate is suitable, it may be sensible to initially contact the Core 
  Team via an informal request for guidance rather than a formal proposal 
  -- this might lead to advice to continue, requests for further 
  supporting material, or the suggestion that a proposal should be 
  deferred while further track record is accrued. It is hoped that 
  requests to gain further experience or to generate additional evidence 
  of community participation and contribution will be taken in the spirit 
  that they are intended: granting of a commit bit is a significant action 
  and based in large part on work performed, rather than simply strong 
  technical abilities. The project would rather take a conservative 
  approach in granting commit rights than grant them prematurely.</p>

<p>In some cases, 'vendor commit bits' may be granted to allow direct 
  commits to device drivers (or potentially other components) maintained 
  by, for example, a device vendor. These may be held to a lower standard 
  of past community involvement based on a strong commitment by the vendor 
  and an experienced mentor, as well as limited charter to make changes in 
  the system independently. It is extremely important that such commit 
  bits be used with suitable discretion and awareness of community 
  concerns; it is the responsibility of the mentor to ensure that no 
  undesirable tension arises, and that changes are in keeping with project 
  procedures and community expectations. If a commit bit is granted in 
  this context, it may be revoked when the individual leaves their 
  employer; however, there is also a substantial history of individuals 
  with 'vendor commit bits' making more broad contributions and this is 
  the hoped for outcome! Mentors proposing vendor commit bits should take 
  all steps necessary to ensure that commit bits are granted only to 
  individuals who can take responsibility for the quality and testing of 
  contributions they make on behalf of the vendor, and have the necessary 
  technical and social skills to engage constructively with the community. 
  It is recommended that proposals for such bits contain to the greatest 
  extent the same content as expected of ordinary commit bits, with a 
  particular focus on quality of technical contribution.</p>

  </body>
</html>
