<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status
Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>April-September</month>

    <year>2009</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers FreeBSD related projects between April and
    September 2009.  During that time a lot of work has been done on
    wide variety of projects, including the Google Summer of Code
    projects. The BSDCan and EuroBSDCon conferences were held in Ottawa,
    CA, and Cambridge, UK which were both very successful.
    A new major version of FreeBSD, 8.0, is to be released soon.
    If you are wondering what's new in this long awaited release, read
    the Ivan Voras' excellent <a
    href="http://ivoras.sharanet.org/freebsd/freebsd8.html">summary</a>.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
    enjoy the reading.</p>

    <p>Please note that the next deadline for submissions covering
    reports between October and December 2009 is January 15th,
    2011.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>FreeBSD Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>pefs - stacked cryptographic filesystem</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Gleb</given>

          <common>Kurtsou</common>
        </name>

        <email>gk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stanislav</given>

          <common>Sedov</common>
        </name>

        <email>stas@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/gleb/">Blog</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/SOC2009GlebKurtsov">FreeBSD wiki
      page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pefs is a kernel level filesystem for transparently encrypting
      files on top of other filesystem (like zfs or ufs). pefs adds no
      extra information into files (unlike others), doesn't require
      cipher block sized io operations, supports per directory/file keys
      and key chaining, uses unique per file tweak for encryption.
      Supported algorithms: AES, Camellia, Salsa20 Code is ready for
      testing.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Implement encrypted name lookup/readir cache</task>

      <task>Optimize sparse files handling and file resizing</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BSD# Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Romain</given>

          <common>Tarti.re</common>
        </name>

        <email>romain@blogreen.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://code.google.com/p/bsd-sharp/">The BSD# project on
      Google-code</url>

      <url href="http://www.mono-project.org/">Mono (Open source .Net
      Development Framework)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The BSD# Project is devoted to porting the Mono .NET framework
      and applications to the FreeBSD operating system.</p>

      <p>During the past year, the BSD# Team continued to track the Mono
      development and the lang/mono port have almost always been
      up-to-date (we however had to skip mono-2.2 because of some
      regression issues in this release). Most of our patches have been
      merged in the mono trunk upstream, and should be included in the
      upcoming mono-2.6 release.</p>

      <p>In the meantime, a few more .NET related ports have been updated
      or added to the FreeBSD ports tree. These ports include:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>www/xsp and www/mod_mono that make it possible to use FreeBSD
        for hosting ASP.NET application;</li>

        <li>lang/boo, a CLI-targeted programming language similar to
        Python;</li>

        <li>lang/mono-basic, the Visual Basic.NET Framework for
        Mono;</li>

        <li>devel/monodevelop, an Integrated Development Environment for
        .NET;</li>

<!--li>deskuils/gnome-do, an all-in-one launch-box to perform actions quickly with your computer;</li-->
        <li>and much more...</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test mono ports and send feedback (a special attention to
      environments where NO_PORTSDOC / WITH_DEBUG is set has to be
      taken).</task>

      <task>Port the mono-debugger to FreeBSD.</task>

      <task>Build a debug live-image of FreeBSD so that Mono hackers
      without a FreeBSD box can help us fixing bugs more
      efficiency.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Dutch Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>René</given>

          <common>Ladan</common>
        </name>

        <email>rene@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Remko</given>

          <common>Lodder</common>
        </name>

        <email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/docproj/translations.html#dutch">
      Current status of the Dutch translation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The current translations (Handbook and some articles) are kept
      up to date with the English versions. Some parts of the website
      have been 
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/nl">translated</url>, more work
      is in progress.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Find more volunteers for translating the remaining parts of
      the website and the FAQ.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The FreeBSD German Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Johann</given>

          <common>Kois</common>
        </name>

        <email>jkois@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Benedict</given>

          <common>Reuschling</common>
        </name>

        <email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Martin</given>

          <common>Wilke</common>
        </name>

        <email>miwi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="https://doc.bsdgroup.de" />

      <url
      href="http://code.google.com/p/bsdcg-trans/wiki/BSDPJTAdede" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In May 2009, Benedict Reuschling received its commit bit to the
      www/de and doc/de_DE.ISO8859-1 trees under the mentorship of Johann
      Kois. Since then, he has worked primarily on the handbook, updating
      existing chapters and translating new ones. Most notably, the
      filesystems and DTrace chapters were newly translated. Bugs found
      in the original documents along the way were reported back so that
      the other translation teams could incorporate them as well.</p>

      <p>Christoph Sold has put his time in translating the wiki pages of
      the BSD Certification Group into the german language. This is a
      great help for germans who want to take the exam and like to read
      the information about it in their native language. Daniel Seuffert
      has sent valuable corrections and bugfixes. Thanks to both for
      their time and efforts!</p>

      <p>The website is translated and updated constantly. Missing parts
      will be translated as time permits.</p>

      <p>We appreciate any help from volunteers in proofreading
      documents, translating new ones and keeping them up to date. Even
      small small error reports are of great help to us. You can find
      contact information at the above URL.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update the existing documentation set (especially the
      handbook).</task>

      <task>Translate more articles into german.</task>

      <task>Read the translations. Check for problems/mistakes. Send
      feedback.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>FreeBSD KDE Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Thomas</given>

          <common>Abthorpe</common>
        </name>

        <email>tabthorpe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>

          <common>Brazhnikov</common>
        </name>

        <email>makc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Martin</given>

          <common>Wilke</common>
        </name>

        <email>miwi@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://freebsd.kde.org" />

      <url href="http://miwi.bsdcrew.de/category/kde/" />

      <url href="http://blogs.freebsdish.org/tabthorpe/category/kde" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since the spring, the FreeBSD KDE team has been busy upgrading
      KDE from 4.2.0 up through to 4.3.1. As part of the ongoing
      maintenance of KDE, the team also updated Qt4 from 4.4.3 through to
      4.5.2</p>

      <p>We added two new committers/maintainers to the team, Kris Moore
      (kmoore@) and Dima Panov (fluffy@). We also granted enhanced area51
      access to contributors Alberto Villa and Raphael Kubo da Costa.
      Alberto has been our key contributor updating and testing Qt
      4.6.0-tp1. Raphael is a KDE developer that has become our Gitorious
      liaison, he has been responsible for getting FreeBSD Qt patches
      merged in upstream.</p>

      <p>Markus Brüffer (markus@) spent a lot of time patching widgets
      and system plugins so they would work under FreeBSD. We would like
      to thank him for all his effort!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update to Qt 4.6.0</task>

      <task>Update to KDE 4.4.0</task>

      <task>Work with our userbase on fixing an EOL for KDE3 in the ports
      tree</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>EuroBSDcon 2009</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Sam</given>

          <common>Smith</common>
        </name>

        <email>eurobsdcon@ukuug.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://2009.eurobsdcon.org/">2009</url>

      <url href="http://2010.eurobsdcon.org/">2010</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>EuroBSDcon 2009 happened in Cambridge, with over 160 users,
      developers, friends and others. Slides, papers and audio are now up
      on the website for those who couldn't make it to Cambridge. Next
      year's event in 2010 will take place in Karlsruhe from 8 10 October
      2010. If you're interested in what you missed in 2009, or to join
      the mailing list so you don't miss out next year, visit 
      <a href="http://2009.eurobsdcon.org/">
      http://2009.eurosbsdcon.org</a>

      .</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>The FreeBSD Forums</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeBSD Forums</given>

          <common>Admins</common>
        </name>

        <email>forum-admins@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeBSD Forums</given>

          <common>Moderators</common>
        </name>

        <email>forum-moderators@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://forums.freebsd.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since their public launch in November 2008, the FreeBSD Forums
      (the most recent addition to the user community and support
      channels for the FreeBSD Operating System), have witnessed a
      healthy and steady growth.</p>

      <p>The user population is now at over 8,000 registered users, who
      have participated in over 6,000 topics, containing over 40,000
      posts in total. The sign-up rate hovers between 50-100 each week.
      The total number of visitors (including 'guests') is hard to gauge,
      but is likely to be a substantial multiple of the registered
      userbase.</p>

      <p>New topics and posts are actively 'pushed out' to search
      engines. This in turn makes the Forums show up in search results
      more and more often, making it a valuable and very accessible
      source of information for the FreeBSD community.</p>

      <p>One of the contributing factors to the Forum's success is its
      'BSD-style' approach when it comes to administration and
      moderation. The Forums have a strong and unified identity, they are
      neatly divided into sub-forums (like 'Networking', 'Installing
      &amp; Upgrading', etc.), very actively moderated, spam-free, and
      with a core group of very active and helpful members, dispensing
      many combined decades' worth of knowledge to starting, intermediate
      and professional users of FreeBSD.</p>

      <p>We expect the Forums te be, and to remain, a central hub in
      FreeBSD's community and support efforts.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>New approach to the locale database</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Edwin</given>

          <common>Groothuis</common>
        </name>

        <email>edwin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>i18n</given>

          <common>mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>freebsd-i18n@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/LocaleNewApproach">
      Documentation</url>

      <url href="svn://svn.freebsd.org/base/user/edwin/locale">Code</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Problem: Over the years the FreeBSD locale database
      (share/colldef, share/monetdef, share/msgdef, share/numericdef,
      share/timedef) has accumulated a total of 165 definitions (language
      - country-code - character-set triplets). The contents of the files
      is for Western European languages often low-ASCII but for Eastern
      European and Asian languages partly or fully high-ASCII. Without
      knowing how to display or interpret the character-sets, it is
      difficult to make sure by the general audience that the local
      languages (language - country-code) definitions is displayed
      properly in various character-sets. Suggested approach: With the
      combination of the data in the Unicode project (which goal is to
      define all the possible written characters and symbols on this
      planet) and the Common Locale Data Repository (which goal is to
      document all the different data and definitions needed for the
      locale database), we can easily keep track of the data, without the
      need for being able to display the data in the required
      charactersets or understand them fully when updates are submitted
      by third parties. Current status: Conversion of share/monetdef,
      share/msgdef, share/numericdef, share/timedef to the newdesign is
      completed. The Makefile infrastructure is converted. Regression
      checks are done. Most of the tools are in place, waiting on the
      import of bsdiconv to the base system.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>At this moment the system isn't self-hosted yet, because of
      the lack of an iconv-kind of program in the base operating system.
      Gabor@ is working on bsdiconv as a GSoC and once that has been
      imported we will be able to clean install from the definitions in
      Unicode text format to the required formats and
      charactersets.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>

