<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-july-2002-aug-2002.xml,v 1.4 2003/04/13 16:31:52 hrs Exp $ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July - August</month>
    <year>2002</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>Throughout July and August, the FreeBSD Project has been working on
      pulling together the last few major pieces of new functionality for
      FreeBSD 5.0-RELEASE.  At this point, the release appears to be on track
      for late November or early December.  Work on fine-grained locking
      continues, especially in the VFS, as with improved support for threading
      through the KSE work;  features such as GEOM, UFS2, and TrustedBSD MAC are
      maturing, and the new ia64 and sparc64 hardware ports are approaching
      production quality.  In the next two months, we have a lot to look forward
      to: additional 5.0 developer preview snapshots, additional locking and
      threading improvements, and many cleanups on the new supported
      architectures. Firewire support has been imported into the main tree, and
      substantial cleanup of the ACPI/legacy PCI code is also in the works. 
      Also, expect the import of new IPsec hardware acceleration support in the
      near future.</p>
    <p>When new developer previews are posted, please give them a try!  While we
      know that 5.0-RELEASE will be for "early adopters", the more testing we
      get out of the way now, the less we have to tidy up later.  The new
      features are extremely exciting, and understanding when and how to deploy
      them properly will be important.  In the next two months, among other
      things, the release engineering team will post updated release schedules,
      as well as guidance for FreeBSD consumers as to how to decide what
      releases of FreeBSD will be right for them.  Keep an eye out for this, and
      provide us with feedback.</p>
    <p>Also, for those of you in Europe -- we look forward to seeing you at
      BSDCon Europe in a couple of months!</p>
    <p>Scott Long, Robert Watson</p>

  </section>

<project>
  <title>BSDCon 2003</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Gregory</given>
	<common>Shapiro</common>
      </name>
      <email>gshapiro@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.usenix.org/events/bsdcon03/cfp/">BSDCon 2003 Call For Papers</url>
  </links>

  <body>

    <p>The BSDCon 2003 Program Committee invites you to contribute
    original and innovative papers on topics related to BSD-derived
    systems and the Open Source world. Topics of interest include
    but are not limited to:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Embedded BSD application development and deployment</li>
      <li>Real world experiences using BSD systems</li>
      <li>Using BSD in a mixed OS environment</li>
      <li>Comparison with non-BSD operating systems; technical,
      practical, licensing (GPL vs. BSD)</li>
      <li>Tracking open source development on non-BSD systems</li>
      <li>BSD on the desktop</li>
      <li>I/O subsystem and device driver development</li>
      <li>SMP and kernel threads</li>
      <li>Kernel enhancements</li>
      <li>Internet and networking services</li>
      <li>Security</li>
      <li>Performance analysis and tuning</li>
      <li>System administration</li>
      <li>Future of BSD</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Submissions in the form of extended abstracts are due by
    April 1, 2003. Be sure to review the extended abstract
    expectations before submitting. Selection will be based on the
    quality of the written submission and whether the work is of
    interest to the community.</p>

    <p>We look forward to receiving your submissions!</p>

  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>Network interface cloning and modularity</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Brooks</given>

	<common>Davis</common>
      </name>

      <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <body>
    <p>Cloning support for ppp(4) and disc(4) interfaces has been
      committed.  A man page for disc has been created and the disc
      devices now appear as disc# instead of ds#.  Some work is still
      needed on pppd to make it understand cloning though it should work
      as long as the devices are created beforehand.</p>
    <p>On the API front, management of mandatory interfaces (i.e. lo0) 
      is handled by the generic cloning code so if_clone_destroy has the
      same API as NetBSD again and &lt;if&gt;_modevent doesn't need to create
      the necessary devices manually.</p>
    <p>At this point, all pseudo interfaces have been converted to the
      cloning API or already did their own cloning (sl(4) for example
      uses it's own mechanism).  Some devices such as tun(4) and
      tap/vmware should probably be converted to use the cloning API
      instead of their current ad-hoc, devfs based cloning system.  This
      would be a good junior kernel hacker task.  Also, the handbook and
      FAQ could use some general cloning documentation prior to 5.0
      release.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>jpman project</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Kazuo</given>
	<common>Horikawa</common>
      </name>

      <email>horikawa@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/man-jp/">jpman project</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>We have been updating RELENG_4 targeting for 4.7-RELEASE.
      When port ja-man-1.1j_5 was broken around the end of July,
      Kumano-san and Mori-san tried to update the port to be based
      on a newer FreeBSD base system's man commands.
      But, we decided only to fix the port ja-man-1.1j_5 to be buildable,
      as the new one was not complete at that time.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>GEOM - generalized block storage manipulation</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Poul-Henning</given>

	<common>Kamp</common>
      </name>

      <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~phk/Geom/">Old concept paper here.</url>

  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The GEOM code has gotten so far that it beats our current code
      in some areas while still lacking in others.  The goal is for
      GEOM to be the default in 5.0-RELEASE.</p>
    <p>Currently work on a cryptographic module which should be able
      to protect a diskpartition from practically any sort of attack
      is progressing.</p>

  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>UFS2 - 64bit UFS with native extended attributes</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Poul-Henning</given>

	<common>Kamp</common>
      </name>

      <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Kirk</given>

	<common>McKusick</common>
      </name>

      <email>mckusick@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <body>
    <p>The UFS2 filesystem approaches feature completion:  Extended
      attribute functionality have been added, including a new
      compound modification API and basic testing has been passed.</p>

  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>French FreeBSD Documentation Project</title>
  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Sebastien </given>
	<common>Gioria</common>
      </name>

      <email>gioria@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Marc </given>
	<common>Fonvieille</common>
      </name>
      <email>blackend@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Stephane</given>
	<common>Legrand</common>
      </name>
      <email>stephane@FreeBSD-fr.ORG</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.freebsd-fr.org">The French FreeBSD Documentation Project.</url>
    <url href="http://www.freebsd-fr.org/index-trad.html">The FreeBSD Web Server translate in French.</url>
    <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~blackend/doc/fr_FR.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/"> Translation of the Hanbook.</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>We've got currently almost 50% of the new handbook translated (all the
      installation part is translated). Most of the articles are translated
      too.</p>
    <p>The web site in on the way, see the Web Server. We need now to
      integrate it on the US CVS tree.</p>
    <p>One of the big job now, is to translate the latest FAQ and the very
      big project will be the manual pages</p>
  </body>
</project>
<project>
  <title> Bluetooth stack for FreeBSD (Netgraph implementation)</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
        <given>
          Maksim
        </given>

        <common>
          Yevmenkin
        </common>
      </name>

      <email>
        m_evmenkin@yahoo.com
      </email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.geocities.com/m_evmenkin/ngbt-fbsd-20020909.tar.gz">Latest snapshot</url>

    <url href="http://bluez.sf.net">Linux BlueZ stack</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>I'm very pleased to announce that another engineering
      release is available for download at
      http://www.geocities.com/m_evmenkin/ngbt-fbsd-20020909.tar.gz</p>
    <p>This release features several major changes and includes
      support for H4 UART and H2 USB transport layers, Host
      Controller Interface (HCI), Link Layer Control and
      Adaptation Protocol (L2CAP) and Bluetooth sockets layer.
      It also comes with several user space utilities that
      can be used to configure and test Bluetooth devices.
      Also there are several man pages.</p>
    <p>Service Discovery Protocol (SDP) is now supported. This
      release includes SDP daemon, configuration tool and user
      space library (ported from BlueZ-sdp-0.7).</p>
    <p>RFCOMM is now supported. This release includes rfcommd
      daemon that provides RFCOMM service via pseudo ttys.
      Not very useful for legacy application, but it is possible
      to run PPP over Bluetooth now. This was ported from old
      BlueZ-rfcommd-1.1 (no longer supported by BlueZ) and
      still has some bugs in it.</p>
    <p>Next step is to fix current RFCOMM support and work on
      new in-kernel RFCOMM and BNEP (Bluetooth Network
      Encapsulation Protocol) implementation. Also user space
      need more work (better tools, libraries, documentation
      etc.).</p>
  </body>
</project>
<project>
  <title>Netgraph ATM</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Harti</given>

	<common>Brandt</common>
      </name>

      <email>brandt@fokus.fhg.de</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.fokus.fhg.de/research/cc/cats/employees/hartmut.brandt/ngatm/index.html">Introduction to NgAtm</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>Version 1.2 has been released recently. It should compile and work
      an any recent FreeBSD-current. Support to manipulate SUNI registers
      has been added to the ATM drivers (to switch between SONET and SDH
      modes, for example). The ngatmsig package now includes a small and
      simple call control module that may be used to build a simple ATM
      switch. The netgraph stuff has been patched to use the official
      netgraph locking.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>FreeBSD C99 &amp; POSIX Conformance Project</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Mike</given>

	<common>Barcroft</common>
      </name>

      <email>mike@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
        <common>FreeBSD-Standards Mailing List</common>
      </name>

      <email>standards@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/c99/" />
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>On the API front, fmtmsg(3) was implemented, glob(3) was given support
      for new flags, ulimit(3) was implemented, and wide character/string
      support was significantly improved with the addition of 30 new functions
      (see the project status board for details).  Work is progressing on
      adding the C99 restrict type-qualifier to functions throughout the
      system.  This allows the compiler to make additional optimizations based
      on the knowledge that a restrict-qualified argument is the only reference
      to a given object (ie. it doesn't overlap with another argument).</p>
    <p>Several headers have been brought up to conformance with POSIX.1-2001,
      they include: &lt;fmtmsg.h&gt;, &lt;poll.h&gt;, &lt;sys/mman.h&gt;, and
      &lt;ulimit.h&gt;.  The header &lt;cpio.h&gt; was implemented.  The
      headers &lt;machine/ansi.h&gt; and &lt;machine/types.h&gt; were merged
      into a single header to help simplify the way variable types are
      created.</p>
    <p>The sh(1) built-in, command(1), was reimplemented to conform with
      POSIX.  Additionally, several utilities which were previously brought
      up to conformance were merged into the 4-STABLE branch.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>FreeBSD GNOME Project</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Joe</given>

	<common>Marcus</common>
      </name>

      <email>marcus@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Maxim</given>

	<common>Sobolev</common>
      </name>

      <email>sobomax@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>

  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/gnome/">FreeBSD GNOME Project
      Homepage.</url>

  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The GNOME 2 desktop port has reach version 2.0.2rc1 with an expected
      2.0.2 release before 4.7-RELEASE.  Mozilla 1.1 has been ported,
      and is resident in the tree with Mozilla 1.0.1.  The GNOMENG porting
      effort is going well.  A good deal of ports have been moved to the
      new infrastructure with the help of
      Edwin Groothuis.  We are now working on
      smoothing out some of the rough edges, then, once all the work is done,
      make GNOMENG the default.</p>
    <p>A long-standing annoyance in Nautilus has also been recently
      corrected.  The desktop is no longer cluttered with volume icons, and
      removable media (such as CDs) should now be handled correctly.</p>

  </body>
</project>
<project>
  <title>ATAPI/CAM Status Report</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Thomas</given>

	<common>Quinot</common>
      </name>

      <email>thomas@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.cuivre.fr.eu.org/~thomas/atapicam/"/>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The ATAPI/CAM module allows ATAPI devices (CD-ROM, CD-RW, DVD
    drives, floppy drives such as Iomega Zip, tape drives) to
    be accessed through the SCSI subsystem (CAM). ATAPI/CAM has been
    integrated in -CURRENT. The code should be fairly functional (it
    has been used by many testers as patches against -STABLE and
    -CURRENT over the past eight months), but there are pending issues
    on SMP machines. Testers most welcome.</p>
    <p>A MFC of this feature will probably happen after the end
    of the 4.7 code freeze.</p>
  </body>
</project>
<project>
  <title>Hardware Crypto Support Status</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Sam</given>
          <common>Leffler</common>
        </name>
      <email>sam@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>
  <body>
    <p>The goal of this project is to import the OpenBSD kernel-level crypto
      subsystem. This facility provides kernel- and user-level access to
      hardware crypto devices for the calculation of cryptographic hashes,
      ciphers, and public key operations. The main clients of this facility
      are the kernel RNG (/dev/random), network protocols (e.g. IPSEC), and
      OpenSSL (through the /dev/crypto device).</p>
    <p>OpenSSL 0.9.7 beta 3 was imported and patched with fixes from OpenBSD's
      source tree.  This permits any user-level application that use -lcrypto to
      automatically get hardware crypto acceleration.  Otherwise the core crypto
      support is stable and has been in production use on -stable machines for
      several months.</p>
    <p>Import of this work into the -current tree has started.  A publicly
      available patch against 4.7 will be released once 4.7 ships. Integration
      of this work into the -stable source tree is planned for 4.8.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>Fast IPsec Status</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Sam</given>
          <common>Leffler</common>
        </name>
        <email>sam@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
  <body>
    <p>The main goal of this project is to modify the IPsec protocols to use
      the kernel-level crypto subsystem imported from OpenBSD (see elsewhere). A
      secondary goal is to do general performance tuning of the IPsec
      protocols.</p>
    <p>Recent work focused on increasing performance. Support is still limited
      to IPv4 protocols, with IPv6 support coded but not yet tested. </p>
    <p>Import of this work into the -current tree has started.  A publicly
      available patch against 4.7 will be released once 4.7 ships.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>VM issues in -stable</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Matthew</given>

	<common>Dillon</common>
      </name>

      <email>dillon@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://apollo.backplane.com/FreeBSD/wiring_patch_03.diff">
      VM corruption patch for -stable.</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>Work is in progress to MFC a number of bug fixes related
    to vm_map corruption into -stable.  This work is probably
    too involved to make it into the 4.7 release but is expected to
    be committed just after the freeze is lifted.  The corruption 
    in question typically occurs in large-memory systems under heavy
    loads and typically panics or KPFs (kernel-page-fault's) the machine
    in a vm_map related function.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>New SCSI Target Emulator</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Nate</given>

	<common>Lawson</common>
      </name>

      <email>nate@root.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.root.org/~nate/freebsd/" />
  </links>

  <body>

    <p>The existing SCSI target code has been rewritten.  The kernel driver is
      much simpler, deferring all functionality to usermode and simply passing
      CCBs to and from the SIM.  The supplied usermode emulates a disk (RBC)
      with IO going to a backing file.  It replaces /sys/cam/scsi/scsi_target*
      and /usr/share/examples/scsi_target.</p>
    <p>The code is definitely alpha quality and has known problems on
      -current although it appears to work ok on -stable.  See the included
      README for how to install and test.  Feedback is welcome!</p>

  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>Lottery Scheduler for FreeBSD -STABLE</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>M&#225;rio S&#233;rgio Fujikawa</given>

	<common>Ferreira</common>
      </name>

      <email>lioux@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <body>
    <p>Yet another implementation of Lottery Scheduling devised by
      Carl Waldspurger et. al. is being developed against FreeBSD
      -STABLE branch.  It is being developed as part of a graduation
      project in Computer Science at Universidade de Bras&#237;lia
      in Brazil.  Therefore, other implementations have not yet
      been verified to avoid plagiarization but will be checked in
      a later stage of this project searching for better implementation
      ideas.  Currently, part of the necessary scheduling kernel
      structure has been mapped and work has progressed despite the
      general lack of kernel documentation.  Further outcomes of
      this project will be a simple documentation of the kernel
      scheduler structure of -STABLE branch, a port of the Lottery
      Scheduler to -CURRENT branch and additional implementations
      of other scheduling disciplines from Carl Waldspurger et. al.
      Members of the FreeBSD community have been and will continue
      to be instrumental in both testing and providing feedback for
      ideas implemented here.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>The FreeBSD Brazilian Portuguese Documentation Project</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Edson</given>

	<common>Brandi</common>
      </name>

      <email>ebrandi.home@uol.com.br</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>M&#225;rio S&#233;rgio Fujikawa</given>

	<common>Ferreira</common>
      </name>

      <email>lioux@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Ricardo Nascimento</given>

	<common>Ferreira</common>
      </name>

      <email>nightwish@techemail.com</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Diego</given>

	<common>Linke</common>
      </name>

      <email>gamk@gamk.com.br</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Jean Milanez</given>

	<common>Melo</common>
      </name>

      <email>jmelo@freebsdbrasil.com.br</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Patrick</given>

	<common>Tracanelli</common>
      </name>

      <email>eksffa@freebsdbrasil.com.br</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Alexandre</given>

	<common>Vasconcelos</common>
      </name>

      <email>alexandre@sspj.go.gov.br</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.fugspbr.org/">FUG-BR Grupo de Usu&#225;rios
      FreeBSD - Brasil</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The FreeBSD Brazilian Portuguese Documentation Project is
      merging with a translation group formed by members of the
      FUG-BR FreeBSD Brazilian user group.  The Brazilian Project
      decided to become an official group under FUG-BR after receiving
      continued excellent contributions from them.  They have managed
      to complete the translation of the FreeBSD FAQ which is
      currently undergoing both proofing and SGML"fication" stages.
      Work is progressing fast: the Handbook has been half translated
      and articles are under way.  The previous Brazilian Project
      is proud to become part of such a dedicate group.  The contacts
      above represent the current official contacts for the new
      translation group.  We hope to have at least part of this
      work ready for the FreeBSD 4.7 Release.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
    <title>KSE</title>
 
    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Julian</given>
          <common>Elischer</common>
        </name>
        <email>julian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jonathon</given>
          <common>Mini</common>
        </name>
        <email>mini@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>
          <common>Eischen</common>
        </name>
        <email>deischen@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>
 
    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~julian">poor description</url>
    </links>
 
    <body>
      <p> David Xu and I have been working on cleaning up some of the work done
        in KSE-III and Jonathon and Dan have been working on the userland
        interface.  The userland library will be committed soon in a
        prototypical state and a working test program using that interface will
        hopefully accompany it. I have just committed a rework of the run
        states for kernel threads that simplifies or solves some problems that
        were being seen recently.</p>
      <p>Hopefully in the next few weeks we will be able to run threads on
        separate processors. The basics of Signal support are presently
        evolving. Archie Cobbs will also be assisting with some of this work.
        I have a mail alias for all the developers at kse@elischer.org. It is
        managed by hand at the moment.</p>
    </body>
 </project>

<project>
  <title>Release Engineering</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The Release Engineering (RE) Team completed and released FreeBSD
      4.6.2.  This ``point release'' fixes several important bugs in
      the ATA subsystem, as well as addressing a number of security
      issues in the base system that surfaced shortly after FreeBSD
      4.6 was released.  The release documentation distributed with
      FreeBSD 4.6.2 contains more details.  (Note: Some earlier
      documents and reports referred to this release as version
      4.6.1.)  The next release in the 4.X series will be FreeBSD 4.7,
      which has a scheduled release date of 1 October 2002.</p>
    <p>Concurrently, work is continuing on the 5.0-DP2 developer
      preview snapshot, an important milestone along the release path
      of FreeBSD 5.0, which is scheduled for release on 20 November.
      As 5.0 draws closer, we are focusing more on getting the system
      stabilized, as opposed to adding new functionality.  To help us
      with this effort, developers should discuss with us any new
      features planned for -CURRENT, beginning 1 October.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
 <title>jp.FreeBSD.org daily SNAPSHOTs project</title>
 <contact>
  <person>
   <name>
    <given>Makoto</given>
    <common>Matsushita</common>
   </name>
   <email>matusita@jp.FreeBSD.org</email>
  </person>
 </contact>
 <links>
  <url href="http://snapshots.jp.FreeBSD.org/">Project Webpage</url>
  <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/snapshots/">Project Webpage (in Japanese
)</url>
 </links>
 <body>
  <p>The project runs as it should be.  New security-branch snapshots are
    available for both 4.5 and 4.6(.2).  I've update buildboxes OS to
    the latest 5-current/4-stable without any errors.  Also current
    problem, less CPU power for the future, is not solved yet -- but
    situation is not so bad, I hope I'll show a good news in the next
    report.</p>
 </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>FreeBSD Donations Team</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Michael</given>

	<common>Lucas</common>
      </name>

      <email>donations@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/donations/index.html" />
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The Donations team started rolling in the last couple of
      months.  Offers of equipment are coming in, and we are
      allocating them to FreeBSD committers as quickly as possible.
      We now have a "Committer Want List" available in our section of
      the Web site.  Several small items, such as network cards, have
      been routed to people who are willing to write the code to
      support them.  We have a few larger donations (i.e., actual
      servers) ready to go to developers, once shipping information is
      straightened out.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>RAIDFrame for FreeBSD</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Scott</given>

	<common>Long</common>
      </name>

      <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~scottl/rf">Project homepage</url>
  </links>

  <body>
    <p>Work on RAIDFrame stalled for quite a bit, then it picked up in
      early summer, then it stalled, and now it's going again.  A
      significant amount of work has been done to make the locking
      SMPng-friendly and to cut down on kernel stack abuse.  I'm happy
      to say that it's starting to work reliably when used with file-
      backed 'md' disks.  Even more exciting is that it's finally starting
      to work on real disks, too.  A lot of cleanup is still needed, and
      a few gross hacks still exist, but it might actually be ready for
      the FreeBSD 5.0 release.  Patches for FreeBSD 5-current and 4-stable
      are available from the website.  The 4-stable patches are a year old
      but still apply and perform well.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>Libh Status Report</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Antoine</given>

	<common>Beaupr&#233;</common>
      </name>

      <email>anarcat@anarcat.ath.cx</email>
    </person>

    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Alexander</given>

	<common>Langer</common>
      </name>

      <email>alex@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
    <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/libh.html">Project's home
    page</url>

  </links>

  <body>
    <p>The primary libh development box, where the CVS repo and
      development webpage was living, is dead. The server has crashed
      after a system upgrade and has never came back to life. We had
      to pull the drives out of it to make proper backups. We will
      setup another box in place of this one and hope for the best. So
      right now, the port is broken because the CVS is unaccessible,
      as the development web page. We're working on it, please bear
      with us.</p>
    <p>On a brighter note, Max started implementing the changes he
      proposed to the build system and the TCL API; LibH is switching
      to SWIG for its TCL bindings, which should simplify the system a
      lot, and shorten build times. The Hui subsystem is therefore
      being completely re-written. On my side, I made a few tests in
      building and running LibH under rhtvision, and it didn't fulfill
      the promises I thought it would, so I just put aside that
      idea. Work on libh stalled during July because I completely lost
      network access for the whole month. So right now, LibH is in a
      bit of a mess, but we have high hopes of settling everything
      down to a new release pretty soon, which will make full use of
      the new SWIG bindings.</p>
  </body>
</project>


<project>
  <title>FreeBSD Security Officer Team</title>

  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Jacques</given>

	<common>Vidrine</common>
      </name>

      <email>nectar@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>

  <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/security/"/>
  </links>

  <body>

  <p>The Security Team continues to be very busy.  The
    security-officer mailing list traffic for the months of June, July,
    and August consisted of 1,230 messages (over 13 messages a day).
    This is well over 50% of the freebsd-hackers traffic volume in the
    same period!</p>
  <p>Since June (the time of our last report), 9 new Security
    Advisories were published, and one Security Notice was published
    covering 25 Ports Collection issues.</p>
  <p>FreeBSD 4.6.2-RELEASE was released on August 15th.  This marked
    the first time a point release was created from the security branch.
    The process went smoothly from the Security Team perspective, despite
    a schedule slippage due to newly discovered bugs, and a snafu which
    resulted in 4.6.1-RELEASE being skipped.</p>
  <p>In September, the FreeBSD Security Officer published a new PGP
    key (ID 0xCA6CDFB2, found on the FTP site and in the Handbook).
    This aligned the set of those who possess the corresponding private
    key with the membership of the security-officer alias published on
    the FreeBSD Security web site.  It also worked around an issue with
    the deprecated PGP key being found corrupted on some public key
    servers.</p>
  </body>
</project>

<project>
  <title>TrustedBSD Mandatory Access Control (MAC)</title>
  <contact>
    <person>
      <name>
	<given>Robert</given>
	<common>Watson</common>
      </name>
      <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>
	<common>TrustedBSD Discussion Mailing List</common>
      </name>
      <email>trustedbsd-discuss@TrustedBSD.org</email>
    </person>
  </contact>
  <body>
    <p>It's been a busy few months, with a variety of development,
      documentation, and public relations activities.  The MAC Framework,
      our pluggable kernel access control mechanism for FreeBSD, has
      matured substantially, and large parts of it were merged to the
      main FreeBSD tree over July and August.</p>
    <p>A variety of entry point changes were made, including: component
      names are now passed to VFS namespace VOPs; aggressive caching
      of MAC labels in vnodes; mmap memory access downgrades on subject
      relabel; check for access()/eaccess(); checks for vnode read,
      write, ioctl, pool, permitting revocation post-open() by aware
      policies; labeling and access control checks for pipe IPC objects,
      clean up of socket/visibility checks; checks for socket bind,
      connect, listen, ....; many locking improvements and assertions,
      especially for vnodes, processes; framework now supports partial
      label updates on subjects and objects; credential management in
      'struct file' improved so that active_cred and file_cred are
      more carefully distinguished and passed to MAC framework
      explicitly; accounting system uses cached credentials for
      write operations now; socreate() can use cached credential to
      label sockets fixing deferred nfs socket connections and
      reconnections with TCP; kse interactions with proc1 fixed;
      IO_NOMACCHECK flag to vn_rdwr() for internal use to avoid
      redundant or incorrect MAC checks on aio vnode operations;
      mac_syscall() policy function demux; su no longer changes MAC
      labels by default; mac_get_pid() to support ps and getpmac -p pid;
      mmap revocation defaults to "fail stop"; MAC_DEBUG wraps atomic
      label counters; UFS2 extended attributes supported; initial
      port of LOMAC to the MAC framework; update all policies for all
      these changes; merge of KSE III; merge of nmount(); upgrade of
      ugidfw to speak user and group names; libugidfw; many namespace
      and naming consistency improvements; module dependencies on
      MAC framework; large scale merging of MAC functionality to the
      main FreeBSD tree.  KDE interfaces to common management
      activities.</p>
    <p>Wrote and taught full-day MAC framework tutorial at STOS
      BSD and Darwin Security Symposium; first draft of MAC framework
      architecture and API guide.  This is now in the Developer's
      Handbook.</p>
    <p>Next couple of months will bring continued maturity improvements,
      labeling and protection of more objects; VFS performance
      improvements; better support for UFS2 EAs and separate EA
      entries for each policy; improved support for LOMAC; MLS
      compartments; IPsec security association labeling; improved
      SEBSD FLASK/TE port; and much more.</p>
  </body>
</project>
</report>
