<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
Status Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>October-December</month>

    <year>2010</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between October and
      December 2010.  It is the last of the four reports planned for 2010.
      The work on the new minor versions of &os;, 7.4 and 8.2, has been
      progressing well and they should be released around the end of this
      month.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work!  This report
      contains 34 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>Please note that the deadline for submissions covering the period
      between January and March 2011 is April 15th, 2011.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Ethernet Switch Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Luiz</given>
	  <common>Otavio O. Souza</common>
	</name>
	<email>loos.br@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://loos.no-ip.org/rspro/switch-1.diff" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Implementation of a framework for ethernet switch control
	(directly connected to the ethernet MAC controller) usually found
	on embedded systems.  Currently based on ifconfig keywords, adds the
	vlan control (filter/pass) on each switch port and adds the
	possibility for the management of media state on interfaces with
	multiple PHYs.</p>

      <p>Currently, the code supports the IP175D (from some mikrotik
      routerboards) and AR8316 (from Ubiquiti RSPRO) switches.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish the IP175C driver (and maybe IP178x).</task>

      <task>Better integration with miibus (rewrite of switchbus).</task>

      <task>Fix (some) ifconfig keywords (better keywords, better usage
	compatibility).</task>

      <task>Export the ports statistics through SNMP (if available on
	switch chip).</task>

      <task>Add a swctl tool (?) for global settings management.</task>

      <task>Write usage examples and the man page information about the
	new ifconfig(8) keywords.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Robot Operating System</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ren&eacute;</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>rene@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.ros.org/wiki/">ROS website</url>

      <url href="ftp://rene-ladan.nl/pub/ros-freebsd.pdf">
	Presentation</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Porting ROS to &os; started in March 2010.  In May 2010, it
	was possible to build  <filename
	  role="package">devel/ros</filename>
	without needing to apply patches, but some more changes were
	necessary to be able to write a port for it.  Currently this and
	several other ports related to ROS are available, most notably
	<filename role="package">devel/ros-tutorials</filename>
	to get up and running with ROS and
	<filename role="package">devel/ros-nxt</filename>
	to use LEGO Mindstorms NXT robots with ROS and &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Port the software required for nxt-rviz-plugin, which is part
	of devel/ros-nxt but currently excluded from the build.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>&os; 802.11n</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Adrian</given>
	  <common>Chadd</common>
	</name>
	<email>adrian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/AdrianChadd/AtherosStuff" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <ul>
	<li>Net80211 station mode works in 2.4ghz HT/20 mode.  HT/40 and
	  5ghz do not currently work.</li>

	<li>Basic 802.11 TX and RX on the AR9160 works, from MCS0 to
	  MCS15</li>

	<li>TX A-MPDU and A-MSDU do not currently implemented - so no
	  aggregate TX will happen</li>

	<li>RX A-MPDU and A-MSDU is implemented and is supposed to work
	  but does not &mdash; this needs to be debugged</li>

	<li>802.11n RTS/CTS protection for legacy packets does not
	  currently work.  There is some magic required to fix the TX packet
	  length.  This is in progress.</li>

	<li>WPA2 now works - a commit which enabled the hardware
	  multicast broke AES-CCMP encryption on at least the AR9160.
	  Further investigation is needed to fix this (and any other
	  hardware encryption bugs that are lurking.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>mdocml Replacing groff For manpage Rendering</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ulrich</given>
	  <common>Spörlein</common>
	</name>
	<email>uqs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://mdocml.bsd.lv/" />

      <url href="https://www.spoerlein.net/cgit/cgit.cgi/freebsd.work/log/?h=mdocml" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Kristaps' groff-replacement (only for rendering manual pages) is
	already available in NetBSD and OpenBSD, and used to render the
	base system manpages for the latter.  This project aims to do
	similar things for &os;.  Since the last status report, mdocml
	has grown rudimentary tbl(1) support and a whole lot of bugfixes
	have gone in.  A groff port has been created and needs some more
	testing before it can be committed to the tree.  Also the
	WITHOUT_GROFF support in base has been fleshed out and is awaiting
	review before commit.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Get ru@ to review WITHOUT_GROFF changes.</task>

      <task>Get textproc/groff tested and committed.</task>

      <task>Push more mdoc fixes into the tree.</task>

      <task>Import mandoc(1), switch to catpages for base.  Discuss future
	of groff in base wrt. share/doc.</task>

      <task>Supply necessary ports infrastructure to opt-in to
	mandoc(1).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Port-Sandbox</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marcelo</given>
	  <common>Araujo</common>
	</name>
	<email>araujo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.arjmobile.com/Marcelo_Araujo/Blog/Entries/2010/11/22_Port-sandbox.html">
	  A little bit about</url>

      <url href="http://gitorious.org/port-sandbox/port-sandbox/trees/master">
	  Source</url>

      <url href="http://www.arjmobile.com/Marcelo_Araujo/My_Albums/Pages/Port-Sandbox.html">
	 Screenshots</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Port-Sandbox now works properly and it is able to run by itself
	through an embedded web server and bring a lot of information about
	the port build process and all dependencies related.  Currently
	Port-Sandbox is in the final stage and needs only only a few code
	changes, more tests and should also be included in the ports
	tree.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Change the way how it connects to database, fix it to maintain
	a persistent connection.</task>

      <task>Remove any kind of internal configuration from source code to
	an external file configuration.</task>

      <task>Create a Port-Sandbox port with all dependencies related to
	it and test it in a clean system.</task>

      <task>Create some documentation to let other people to keep
	helping Port-Sandbox to grow up.</task>

      <task>Finally, release it.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Chromium</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ren&eacute;</given>
	  <common>Ladan</common>
	</name>
	<email>freebsd-chromium@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.chromium.org/Home">Chromium homepage</url>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bapt/chrome9-fbsd.png">
	  Screenshot</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are working on updating the Chromium web browser in our ports
	to stay up to date with the latest supported release.  We currently
	have the Chromium 9 beta running, but not all features are fully
	implemented and the port still needs some polish before it can be
	committed to the Ports Collection.  We have also been making
	arrangements with Google to merge our work with their upstream,
	which should ease the number of features and fixes we have to
	maintain for ourselves in the future.  Our first release should be
	in a few weeks and coincide with the official release of Chromium
	9.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="docs">
    <title>The &os; Japanese Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hiroki</given>
	  <common>Sato</common>
	</name>
	<email>hrs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ryusuke</given>
	  <common>Suzuki</common>
	</name>
	<email>ryusuke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ja/">Japanese &os; Web
	  Pages</url>

      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/doc-jp/">The &os; Japanese
	  Documentation Project Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Although there is no radical change in this effort since the
	last report, the www/ja and doc/ja_JP.eucJP/books/handbook have
	constantly been updated.  During this period, generating translated
	RSS feed for newsflash was started and links to the manual pages
	were fixed in the Books and Articles documentation.  Some more
	progress has been made in the Porter's Handbook and Contributing to
	&os; as well.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Further translation of the &os; <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/ja_JP.eucJP/books/handbook/">
	  Handbook</a> and contents of the
	<a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">www.FreeBSD.org</a>
	website to the Japanese language.</task>

      <task>Pre-/post-commit review of the translation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; German Documentation Project Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Johann</given>
	  <common>Kois</common>
	</name>
	<email>jkois@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benedict</given>
	  <common>Reuschling</common>
	</name>
	<email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://doc.bsdgroup.de">Website of the &os; German
	  Documentation Project.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The committers to the German Documentation Project managed to
	update the German documentation just in time to get the changes
	included into the next &os; releases.  The website translations
	were also kept in sync with the ones on FreeBSD.org.</p>

      <p>We tried to re-activate committers who did not contribute for
	some time but most of them are currently unable to free up enough
	time.  We hope to gain fresh contributor blood as we are getting
	occasional reports about bugs and grammar in the german
	translation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Submit grammar, spelling or other errors you find in the
	german documents and the website.</task>

      <task>Translate more articles and other open handbook
	sections.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Generic IEEE 802.3 annex 31B full duplex flow control support
      for Ethernet in mii(4)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marius</given>
	  <common>Strobl</common>
	</name>
	<email>marius@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethernet_flow_control" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In r213878 a NetBSD-compatible mii_attach() was added to mii(4)
	as an replacement for mii_phy_probe() and subsequently all Ethernet
	device drivers in the tree which use this framework were converted
	to take advantage of the former.  This allowed to considerably clean
	up mii(4) as well as the converted MAC and PHY drivers and get rid
	of quite a few hacks, amongst others the infamous "EVIL HACK".
	However, the main motivation of this change was to allow the
	addition of generic IEEE 802.3 annex 31B full duplex flow control
	support to mii(4), which was ported from NetBSD but also enhanced
	and fixed quite a bit and committed in r215297.  Along with this
	bge(4), bce(4), msk(4), nfe(4) and stge(4) as well as brgphy(4),
	e1000phy(4) and ip1000phy(4), which previously all implemented
	their own flow control support based on mostly undocumented special
	media flags separately, were converted to take advantage of the
	generic support.  At least for CURRENT this means that these drivers
	now no longer unconditionally advertise support for flow control
	but only do so if flow control was selected as media option.  The
	reason for implementing the generic flow control support that way
	was to allow it to be switched on and off via ifconfig(8) with the
	PHY specific default to typically being off in order to protect
	from unwanted effects.  Subsequently support for flow control based
	on the generic support was added to alc(4), fxp(4), cas(4), gem(4),
	jme(4), re(4) and xl(4) as well as atphy(4), bmtphy(4), gentbi(4),
	inphy(4), jmphy(4), nsgphy(4), nsphyter(4) and rgephy(4).  For
	several of the remaining Ethernet drivers it also would only
	require minor changes to enable flow control support if supported
	by the respective MAC.  Due to the fact that each implementation
	should be thoroughly tested and tuned this was only done for
	drivers were hardware was available though.</p>

      <p>An example for identifying support for flow control based on the
	generic implementation in the dmesg-output for a certain
	MAC-PHY-combination would be:</p>

      <blockquote>bge0: &lt;Broadcom NetXtreme Gigabit Ethernet
	Controller, ASIC rev. 0x002003&gt; mem 0
	xfe010000-0xfe01ffff,0xfe000000-0xfe00ffff irq 25 at device 2.0 on
	pci2
	<br />

	bge0: CHIP ID 0x00002003; ASIC REV 0x02; CHIP REV 0x20; PCI-X
	<br />

	miibus0: &lt;MII bus&gt; on bge0
	<br />

	brgphy0: &lt;BCM5704 10/100/1000baseTX PHY&gt; PHY 1 on miibus0
	<br />

	brgphy0: 10baseT, 10baseT-FDX, 100baseTX, 100baseTX-FDX, 1000baseT,
	1000baseT-master, 1000baseT-FDX, 1000baseT-FDX-master, auto,
	<strong>auto-flow</strong>
      </blockquote>

      <p>or in the output of <kbd>ifconfig -m</kbd> for a given device:</p>

      <blockquote>supported media:
	<blockquote>media autoselect
	  <em>mediaopt flowcontrol</em>
	</blockquote>
      </blockquote>

      <p>The latter also is what one would use to enable flow control for
	such a device, i.e.:</p>

      <blockquote>ifconfig bge0 media autoselect mediaopt
	flowcontrol</blockquote>

      <p>or in order to turn it off again:</p>

      <blockquote>ifconfig bge0 media autoselect -mediaopt
	flowcontrol</blockquote>

      <p>Note that some PHY drivers, currently only rgephy(4) though, also
	support enabling flow control support when using manual media
	configuration like in the following example:</p>

      <blockquote>ifconfig re0 media autoselect mediaopt
	full-fuplex,flowcontrol</blockquote>

      <p>In CURRENT this can also be further abbreviated (support for this
	will eventually be merged back into the supported stable branch(es)
	but not be present in 7.4-RELEASE or 8.2-RELEASE) as:</p>

      <blockquote>ifconfig re0 media auto mediaopt fdx,flow</blockquote>

      <p>For a device which has successfully negotiated flow control support
	with its link partner will report it in the output of
	<kbd>ifconfig</kbd> along with the available directions like in the
	following example:</p>

      <blockquote>media: Ethernet autoselect &lt;flowcontrol&gt;
	(100baseTX &lt;full-duplex,
	<em>flowcontrol,rxpause,txpause</em>&gt;)</blockquote>

      <p>Another thing that was introduced with r215297 was generic support
	for setting 1000baseT master mode via a media option when using
	manual media configuration.  Consequently, brgphy(4), ciphy(4),
	e1000phy(4) as well as ip1000phy(4) have been converted to take
	advantage of this generic support.  At least for CURRENT this means
	that these drivers now no longer take the link0 parameter for
	selecting master mode but the master media option has to be used
	instead like in the following example:</p>

      <blockquote>ifconfig bge0 media 1000baseT mediaopt
	full-duplex,master</blockquote>

      <p>Selection of master mode now is also available with all other PHY
	drivers supporting 1000baseT.</p>

      <p>With the exception of the media option abbreviations all of the
	above mentioned changes were merged into 7-STABLE in 215879 and
	into 8-STABLE in r215881 respectively.  This means that they will be
	part of 7.4-RELEASE and 8.2-RELEASE.  In order to no break POLA,
	unlike as in CURRENT bge(4), bce(4), msk(4), nfe(4) and stge(4)
	were changed to continue to always advertise support of flow
	control to their link partners in these stable branches with no way
	to turn that off as they also did before with their custom
	implementations.  Additionally, brgphy(4), ciphy(4), e1000phy(4) as
	well as ip1000phy(4) were changed to still also accept the link0
	parameter in addition to the master media option for setting master
	mode.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We actually miserably fail to properly document the available
	media types and options in manual pages.  For example several of the
	media lists in manual pages of MAC drivers like bge(4) already were
	outdated and with the addition of generic flow control and
	1000baseT master mode support these are now even more outdated.  Yet
	worse is the fact that for MAC drivers which use the mii(4)
	framework it is technically just plain wrong to include these lists
	in their manual page as the PHY drivers actually are responsible
	for handling the media types and options.  However, given that the
	PHY drivers determine the available media types and options mostly
	dynamically at run-time it generally makes no sense to have static
	documentation of these in their manual pages (apart from the fact
	that we currently have no manual pages for PHY drivers).  One good
	way out of this should be to replace the media lists in MAC drivers
	using mii(4) with just a note to check the output of
	<kbd>ifconfig -m</kbd>
	to get a list of the media types and options actually supported by
	a given device and to add a generic ifmedia(4) manual page which
	provides some general background information about media types and
	options similar to what NetBSD and OpenBSD also have.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/sparc64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marius</given>
	  <common>Strobl</common>
	</name>
	<email>marius@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>CPUTYPE support for sparc64 has been added to CURRENT in
	r216820.  The three flavors currently supported are
	"ultrasparc", "ultrasparc3" and "v9".  So it is now possible to
	let the compiler produce code optimize for the family of
	UltraSPARC-III CPUs by setting CPUTYPE to "ultrasparc3".
	Setting it to "ultrasparc" as well as omitting it completely
	optimizes for UltraSPARC-I/II family CPUs as before.  Support
	for generating generic 64-bit V9 code was mainly added for
	reference purposes.  As it turned out, at least for SPARC64-V
	CPUs running code optimized for UltraSPARC-III CPUs does not
	perform measurably better than UltraSPARC-I/II one though so
	the default is just fine for these.  This change was merged into
	7-STABLE in r217005 and into 8-STABLE in r217004 respectively,
	neither 7.4-RELEASE nor 8.2-RELEASE will include it
	though.</p>

      <p>Support for a certain feature available with
	UltraSPARC-III+ and greater, i.e. with all sun4u CPUs following
	the original UltraSPARC-III, has been added to CURRENT in
	r216803.  The net effect of this change is that we now can use a
	kernel TSB and thus a kernel address space of virtually any
	size up to the full 64-bit address space on machines equipped
	with these CPUs, apart from the fact that 1GB of address space
	still takes up 4MB worth of data structures.  Before, the
	theoretical limit was 16GB due to the fact that the MMUs of
	these UltraSPARC CPUs only have 16 lockable TLB slots
	(UltraSPARC-I/II have 64 and SPARC64 CPUs again have at least
	32), with the actual limit being several GB below that because
	we need some of these slots also for mapping the PROM, the
	kernel itself and in MP-systems the per-CPU page.  Currently,
	the kernel TSB and thus the kernel virtual address space is now
	always sized one time the physical memory present in these
	machines with the plan being to actually allow to it extend
	beyond the size of the RAM as this helps especially ZFS.  Most
	of this is implemented by patching the instructions used to
	access the kernel TSB based on the CPU present, so the run-time
	overhead of this change is rather low.  Once it is also enabled
	and successfully tested with SPARC64 CPUs this change will be
	merged back into the supported stable branch(es).</p>

      <p>Theoretically it should be also possible to use the same
	approach for the user TSB, which already is not locked into the
	TLB but can cause nested traps.  However, for reasons I do not
	understand yet, OpenSolaris only does this with SPARC64 CPUs.
	On the other hand I think that also using it for the user TSB
	and thus avoiding nested traps would get us closer to running
	the &os;/sparc64 code on machines equipped with sun4v CPUs,
	which only supports trap level 0 and 1, too, so eventually we
	could have a single kernel which runs on both sun4u and sun4v
	machines (as does Linux and OpenBSD).</p>

      <p>Work on adding support for Sun Fire 3800 and similar models
	has begun but still is in its early stages.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Webcamd</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.selasky.org/hans_petter/video4bsd" />

      <url href="http://www.freshports.org/multimedia/webcamd/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Webcamd is a small daemon that enables about 1500 different USB
	based webcam, DVB and remote control USB devices under the
	&os;-8.0 and later operating system.  The webcam daemon is
	basically an application which is a port of Video4Linux USB drivers
	into userspace on &os;.  The daemon currently depends on libc,
	pthreads, libusb and libcuse4bsd.</p>

      <p>During Q3 2010 webcamd got manpages thanks to Dru Lavigne.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>I hope to get a Google summer of code project this year
	building the default Linux Kernel 2.6.37+ and allowing use of
	relevant Linux USB device drivers under &os;.  Webcamd is not a
	replacement for native &os; kernel drivers and will only be used
	when no existing &os; drivers exist for a given device staying
	clear of any GPLv2 issues.  If you are a student and/or is
	interested in participating in such a project feel free to send an
	e-mail to hselasky@FreeBSD.org.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Additions</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Josh</given>
	  <common>Paetzel</common>
	</name>
	<email>jpaetzel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://bigbluebutton.org" />

      <url href="http://smb4k.berlios.de/" />

      <url href="http://www.freeswitch.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Bigbluebutton has joined the list of ready to run applications
	in the ports tree.  Dru Lavigne has been instrumental on getting it
	to run, as well as offering suggestions for improvements to the
	port.</p>

      <p>smb4k was updated to the latest release version, which requires
	kde4.  This was enough of a change that a new port was created,
	net/smb4k-kde4.  the initial port went through a number of quick
	changes, including a patch to the source code to fix a &os;
	source code submitted by PC-BSD's Kris Moore.  This application
	greatly eases the task of working with samba shares in a &os;
	environment.</p>

      <p>Freeswitch is the resullt of 3 Asterisk developers working on a
	VoIP package that fulfills their goals.  They have switched away from
	a release model to a "just run latest SVN checkout" model.  With
	the help of Richard Neese and Eric Crist, static snapshots of their
	SVN repo have been taken, the port has been modified to use the
	newer version, and extensive build and run testing has been
	done.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>TRIM support for UFS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kirk</given>
	  <common>McKusick</common>
	</name>
	<email>mckusick@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>TRIM support for UFS is implemented in HEAD.  Potentially, this
	may increase the steady speed and longevity of SSDs.</p>

      <p>Due to concerns with the speed of TRIM operations on many SSDs,
	and not a lot of experience with the real-world behaviour, the
	support is off by default, and should be enabled on the
	per-filesystem basis.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Non-executable Stacks</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Konstantin</given>
	  <common>Belousov</common>
	</name>
	<email>kib@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The support for non-executable stacks, using the approach
	identical to one used by GNU toolchain and Linux'es, is implemented
	for amd64 and PowerPC.  The support is already committed to HEAD.
	For now, non-executable stacks are turned off by default.</p>

      <p>I plan to provide a detailed information to ports@ and switch
	the knob after port tree is unfrozed for 7.4/8.2 releases.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>SYSCTL Type Safety</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Matthew</given>
	  <common>Fleming</common>
	</name>
	<email>mdf@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>I started upstreaming a patch from Isilon that adds
	type-checking to the various SYSCTL_FOO and SYSCTL_ADD_FOO macros
	for various scalar types, which has turned into quite the
	discussion on the src mailing list.  The type-checking macros are
	committed to sys/sysctl.h but under #if 0.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>As of right now, it looks like I will be rolling a new sysctl
	macro for the kernel that detects they type at compile time and
	does the Right Thing.  Existing uses of the legacy SYSCTL_FOO and
	SYSCTL_ADD_FOO for scalar types can be replaced, and will probably
	turn into invocations of the new interface via preprocessor
	macro.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BSDInstall</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BSDInstall">BSDInstall Wiki
	  Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>BSDInstall is a replacement for the venerable sysinstall
	installer.  It is designed to be modular and easily extensible,
	while being fully scriptable and streamlining the installation
	process.  It is mostly complete, and installs working systems on
	i386, amd64, sparc64, powerpc, and powerpc64, with untested PC98
	support.</p>

      <p>New Features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Allows installation onto GPT disks on x86 systems</li>

	<li>Can do installations spanning multiple disks</li>

	<li>Allows installation into jails</li>

	<li>Eases PXE installation</li>

	<li>Virtualization friendly: can install from a live system onto
	  disk images</li>

	<li>Works on PowerPC</li>

	<li>Streamlined system installation</li>

	<li>More flexible scripting</li>

	<li>Easily tweakable</li>

	<li>All install CDs are live CDs</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Wireless networking configuration wizard.</task>

      <task>ZFS installation support.</task>

      <task>Itanium disk setup.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on the Playstation 3</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>On January 5, support for the Playstation 3 was imported into
	&os; 9.0-CURRENT.  This port is still somewhat raw (only
	netbooting is supported, no access to the SPUs, etc.), but hardware
	support should be more fleshed out by the time &os; 9.0 is
	released.  The port uses the OtherOS mechanism, and so requires a
	"fat" console with firmware earlier than 3.21.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>SATA driver.</task>

      <task>Sound support.</task>

      <task>SPU driver.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>GEOM-based ataraid(4) Replacement &mdash; geom_raid</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>M. Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~mav/graid_design.h">General
	  design description.</url>

      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/viewvc/base/projects/graid/">
	  Project SVN branch.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>New project started to create GEOM-based replacement for
	ataraid(4) &mdash; software RAID, that will be obsoleted by
	migration to the new CAM-based ATA implementation.</p>

      <p>This implementation planned with accent to modular design,
	that includes common core and two sets of modules, handling data
	transformations (RAID levels) and on-disk metadata formats
	specifics.  Such design should make further extension easier.</p>

      <p>At this moment work focused around RAID0/RAID1 transformations
	and Intel metadata format.  Module is now able to read, write and
	create Intel volumes.  Error recovery and rebuild work is now in
	progress.  Support for other RAID levels and metadata formats,
	supported by ataraid(4), planned later.</p>

      <p>This project is sponsored by Cisco Systems, Inc.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete error recovery/rebuild work and stabilize modules
	API.</task>

      <task>Implement metadata modules for other formats.</task>

      <task>Implement transformation modules for other RAID
	levels.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/EC2</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Colin</given>
	  <common>Percival</common>
	</name>
	<email>cperciva@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/freebsd-on-ec2/">&os;/EC2
	  status page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; is now able to run on t1.micro instances in the Amazon
	EC2 cloud.  &os; 9.0 is not very stable, but it seems likely that
	&os; 8.2-RELEASE will approach the stability normally expected
	of &os;.</p>

      <p>A list of available &os; AMIs (EC2 machine images) appears on
	the &os;/EC2 status page.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Bring &os; to a wider range of EC2 instance types.</task>

      <task>Completely rework the locking in head/sys/i386/xen/pmap.c to
	eliminate races and make 9.0-CURRENT stable under
	paravirtualization.</task>

      <task>Track down several possibly-related problems with scheduling
	and timekeeping.</task>

      <task>Fix other issues shown on the &os;/EC2 status page.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Portmaster</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Doug</given>
	  <common>Barton</common>
	</name>
	<email>dougb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://dougbarton.us/portmaster-proposal.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Portmaster version 3.6.1 is now in the ports tree, and the
	emphasis in the last year has been on improving the stability and
	performance of existing features, with a few new features sprinkled
	in.  A lot of work has gone into error handling, both for unexpected
	states in the ports system and for user input.  For example, all
	prompts are now wrapped in code to verify that what was entered was
	one of the valid options.</p>

      <p>Perhaps the most interesting new element is that for the
	features -e, -s, --clean-distfiles, --clean-packages,
	--check-depends and --check-port-dbdir you can now specify either
	-y or -n to automatically provide the corresponding answer to the
	yes/no questions.  The -o, -r, and --index-only options have
	received major overhauls, and now either work better or at least as
	advertised.</p>

      <p>There has also been a lot of work put into reducing the memory
	footprint, especially in the environment variables that are shared
	between the parent and child processes.  And for those operating
	without a local ports tree (--index-only/--packages-only) all of
	the features that <em>can</em>
	work without the ports tree now do.</p>

      <p>Significant support for the upgrading of operating without a
	ports tree was provided by GridFury, LLC.  Their support, as well as
	the support received from other members of the community continues
	to be greatly appreciated.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>There are still interesting features that have been suggested
	by users listed on the page above that I have not been able to work
	on, but would like to be able to.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>IPv6 and VIMAGE</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern A.</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://ecdysis.viagenie.ca/">NAT64 patches for pf</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the last quarter a lot of work was spent on quality time
	hunting down and fixing open bugs and races in the network stack,
	mostly IPv6, as well as testing and getting virtualized network
	stack parts more stable.  Tests for the pf(4) firewall update were
	started with VIMAGE.  In addition Viagenie's NAT64 patch was ported
	over.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Port</given>
	  <common>Management Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/" />

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html" />

      <url href="http://blogs.FreeBSDish.org/portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=135441496471197" />

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree slowly moves up closer to 23,000.  The PR count
	still remains at about 1000.</p>

      <p>In Q4 we added 2 new committers, took in 2 commit bit for safe
	keeping, and welcomed back 4 returning committers.</p>

      <p>The Ports Management team bid farewell to Kris Kennaway in
	November 2010.  Kris was the root of krismail, the mail we all got
	from time to time when ports broke on pointyhat.  Kris did a lot
	of work benchmarking and testing &os; for stability, scalability
	and usability.</p>

      <p>Mark Linimon has put a lot of effort into refactoring and
	refining the code that runs the 'pointyhat' package build
	dispatch system.  In 2010, the &os; Foundation purchased for
	portmgr a pair of new machines, pointyhat-west and
	pointyhat-east, to take over from the existing machine.  (The
	new machines have much greater RAM, CPU, and disk capacity.)
	However, to properly utilize them, the existing code needed
	to be generalized.</p>

      <p>Persistent bugs, and some hardware troubles, have delayed the
	rollout far beyond what was originally planned, but there
	appears to be light at the end of the tunnel. (And, this time,
	it does not appear to be an oncoming train.)</p>

      <p>A document entitled "Mentoring Guidelines" as been circulated
	among ports developers, and has been greeted with a lot of positive
	feedback, and updates have been included.  In the short term,
	updated copies will be maintained at
	http://people.FreeBSD.org/~portmgr/mentor_guidelines.txt.asc.</p>

      <p>The Ports Management team have been running -exp runs on an
	ongoing basis, verifying how base system updates may affect the
	ports tree, as well as providing QA runs for major ports updates.
	Of note, -exp runs were done for:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>ade: multiple runs for autotools refactoring</li>

	<li>ed: test to replace libgcc.a with libcompiler_rt.a</li>

	<li>jiles: test sh(1) against r212508</li>

	<li>kde: Qt 4.7.0 update</li>

	<li>kde: KDE 4.5.4 updte</li>

	<li>kwm: Gnome 2.32 update</li>

	<li>ports/144164: ensure package-noinstall target include rc.d
	  scripts</li>

	<li>ports/145598: include etc/devd in mtree</li>

	<li>ports/145955: silence make fetch-required-list</li>

	<li>ports/147701: perform DESKTOP_ENTRIES sanity check</li>

	<li>ports/149657: removal of MD5 checksums</li>

	<li>ports/149670: remove checks in _OPTIONSFILE</li>

	<li>ports/150303: for INSTALL_LIBS</li>

	<li>ports/150337: for PLIST_DIRSTRY</li>

	<li>ports/151047: pass CPP to CONFIGURE/MAKE_ENV</li>

	<li>ports/151799: fix PLIST_DIRSTRY</li>

	<li>ports/151806: remove 2004 legacy hack</li>

	<li>ports/152055 and ports/152059: for pear infrastructure</li>

	<li>ports/152558: boost update</li>

	<li>ports/152626: fix pkg-message display if installed from
	  package</li>

	<li>ports/152964: embed LICENSE name for STDOUT</li>

	<li>ports/153018: implement variables in Mozilla
	  dependencies</li>

	<li>ports/153033: fix un-escaped shell metacharacters</li>

	<li>ports/153041: clean up ruby plists</li>

	<li>ports/153132: autotools cleanup</li>

	<li>ports/153318: set PGSQL default to 8.4</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Looking for help fixing <url
	 link="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnCurrent">ports
	broken on CURRENT</url>.</task>

      <task>Looking for help with <url
	  link="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnTier2Architectures">
	Tier-2 architectures</url>.</task>

      <task>Most ports PRs are assigned, we now need to focus on testing,
	committing and closing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Bringing up OMAP3</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@bsdimp.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mohammed</given>
	  <common>Farrag</common>
	</name>
	<email>mfarrag@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~raj/patches/arm/dove_v6.diff">an
	  old patch for arm</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The attached file is an old patch for ARM.  We are developing new
	patch and then we are going toward Porting OMAP3.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>Release Engineering Team Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Release Engineering Team</given>
	</name>

	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Release Engineering Team reports the joint release of
	&os; 7.4 and 8.2 has been delayed slightly but should be
	completed within a week or two of the original schedule:
	http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/7.4R/schedule.html
	http://www.FreeBSD.org/releases/8.2R/schedule.html</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Resource Containers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of this project is to implement resource containers and
	a per-jail resource limits mechanism, so that system administrators
	can partition resources like memory or CPU between jails and
	prevent users from DoS-ing the whole system.  Project is close to
	completion.  One big item that needs to be fixed before releasing a
	patch for people to test is %CPU accounting; initial idea of just
	using %CPU calculated by the scheduler turned out to be useless.
	Implementing it cleanly will also make it easier to support other
	similar resources (e.g. writes-per-second) in the future.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>&os; as Home Theater PC</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bernhard</given>
	  <common>Froehlich</common>
	</name>
	<email>decke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juergen</given>
	  <common>Lock</common>
	</name>
	<email>nox@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HTPC" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; could be a much better platform for a Home Theater PC
	than it currently is.  We are focusing on improving support for
	media center applications.  Extending the major ports (MythTV, VDR,
	XBMC) and create some documentation to guide interested people.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Improve remote control support in webcamd and with
	lirc.</task>

      <task>Port more Media Center applications (Enna, me-tv, ...).</task>

      <task>Create a small guide on how to build a great &os; Home
	Theater PC.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>The &os; Foundation Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We raised $325,000 towards our goal of $350,000 for 2010! This
	will allow us to increase our project development and equipment
	spending for 2011.</p>

      <p>We were proud to be a sponsor for EuroBSDCon 2010, BSDDay
	Argentina 2010, MeetBSD California 2010, and NYBSDCon 2010.</p>

      <p>Completed the Foundation funded projects: DAHDI Project by Max
	Khon and BSNMP Improvements by Shteryana Sotirova.</p>

      <p>We kicked off a new project by the University of Melbourne
	called Feed-Forward Clock Synchronization Algorithms Project.  The
	Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms for &os; Project by
	Swinburne University also officially started.</p>

      <p>We continued our work on infrastructure projects to beef up
	hardware for package-building, network-testing, etc.  This includes
	purchasing equipment as well as managing equipment donations.</p>

      <p>Stop by and visit with us at FOSDEM (Feb 5-6), SCALE (Feb 26),
	AsiaBSDCon (March 17-20), and Indiana Linuxfest (March 26).</p>

      <p>Read more about how we supported the project and community by
	reading our end-of-year newsletter at: <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/press/2010Dec-newsletter.shtml">
	  http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/press/2010Dec-newsletter.shtml</a>.</p>

      <p>We are fund-raising for 2011 now! Find out more at <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/">
	  http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/</a>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Hayes</common>
	</name>
	<email>dahayes@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Lawrence</given>
	  <common>Stewart</common>
	</name>
	<email>lastewart@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/freebsd/5cc/" />

      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/projects.shtml" />

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/5cc/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project is nearing completion, with the following code
	already available in the svn head branch:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Modular congestion control framework.</li>

	<li>Modularised implementations of NewReno, CUBIC and HTCP
	  congestion control algorithms.</li>

	<li>Khelp (Kernel Helper) and Hhook (Helper Hook)
	  frameworks.</li>

	<li>Basic Khelp/Hhook integration with the TCP stack.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The ERTT (Enhanced Round Trip Time) Khelp module is days away
	from being imported, which will then pave the way for the delay
	based congestion control algorithms to follow.  Finally, a large
	documentation dump will be committed in the form of new and
	updated man pages.</p>

      <p>We anticipate the project will conclude around the end of
	January 2011.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Import the ERTT Khelp module.</task>

      <task>Import the VEGAS, HD and CHD delay based congestion control
	algorithm modules.</task>

      <task>Import the documentation dump for all the code
	contributed/developed as part of the project.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>DIstributed Firewall and Flow-shaper Using Statistical
      Evidence (DIFFUSE)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sebastian</given>
	  <common>Zander</common>
	</name>
	<email>szander@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/diffuse/" />

      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/diffuse/downloads.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>
	<p>DIFFUSE is a system enabling &os;'s IPFW firewall subsystem
	  to classify IP traffic based on statistical traffic
	  properties.</p>

	<p>With DIFFUSE, IPFW computes statistics (such as packet lengths
	  or inter-packet time intervals) for observed flows, and uses ML
	  (machine learning) techniques to assign flows into classes.  In
	  addition to traditional packet inspection rules, IPFW rules may
	  now also be expressed in terms of traffic statistics or classes
	  identified by ML classification.  This can be helpful when direct
	  packet inspection is problematic (perhaps for administrative
	  reasons, or because port numbers do not reliably identify
	  applications).</p>

	<p>DIFFUSE also enables one instance of IPFW to send flow
	  information and classes to other IPFW instances, which then can
	  act on such traffic (e.g. prioritise, accept, deny, etc)
	  according to its class.  This allows for distributed
	  architectures, where classification at one location in your
	  network is used to control fire-walling or rate-shaping actions
	  at other locations.</p>

	<p>In December 2010 we released DIFFUSE v0.1, a set of patches
	  for &os;-CURRENT.  It can be downloaded from the project's web
	  site.  The web site also contains a more comprehensive
	  introduction, including application examples, links to related
	  work and documentation describing the software design.</p>

	<p>We hope to release DIFFUSE v0.2 soon.  Keep an eye on the
	  freebsd-ipfw and freebsd-net mailing lists for project-related
	  announcements.</p>
      </p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>gpart Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrey V.</given>
	  <common>Elsukov</common>
	</name>
	<email>ae@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>GEOM class PART is the default disk partitioning class since
	&os; 8.0.  Compared to 8.1 now it does have several new features:
	Partition resizing.  New "gpart resize" subcommand was implemented
	for all partitioning schemes but EBR. GPT recovering.  Guid
	Partition Table does have redundant metadata and it can be
	recovered when some of them is damaged.  New "gpart recover"
	subcommand was implemented for that purpose.  Ability to
	backup/restore of partition table.  New "gpart backup" and "gpart
	restore" subcommands were implemented.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>xz Compression for Packages and Log Files</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Martin</given>
	  <common>Matuska</common>
	</name>
	<email>mm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Creating and processing xz-compressed packages is now supported
	by pkg_create(1), pkg_add(1) and bsdtar(1) in both 9-CURRENT and
	8-STABLE.  Users can test working with .txz packages by adding
	"PKG_SUFX=.txz" into /etc/make.conf.</p>

      <p>The ports-mgmt/portupgrade utility supports .txz packages from
	version 2.4.8 and a patch for ports-mgmt/portmaster has been
	submitted but not yet accepted by the author.</p>

      <p>A patch for newsyslog(8) with a rewrite of the use of
	compression tools supporting xz compression is under maintainer
	review.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Import xz(1) compression support into newsyslog(8).</task>

      <task>Add .txz package support to ports-mgmt/portmaster.</task>

      <task>Add .txz package support to the &os; port building
	cluster (pointyhat).</task>

      <task>Test building all packages in .txz format and compare
	results with .tbz.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ZFS pool version 28</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Martin</given>
	  <common>Matuska</common>
	</name>
	<email>mm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-fs/2010-December/010292.html" />
      <url href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-fs/2010-December/010321.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A new version of the ZFS pool v28 patch was released for
	testing, this time for 9-CURRENT and 8-STABLE.  Compared to
	the previous patch it does include updated boot support,
	improved sendfile(2) handling, a compatibility layer with
	older ZFS and several other bugfixes.</p>

      <p>If there are no major issues we can expect ZFS v28 imported
	into the &os;-CURRENT after 8.2 is released.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Import of ZFS v28 into &os;-CURRENT.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>&os; VirtIO Network Driver</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bryan</given>
	  <common>V.</common>
	</name>
	<email>deboomerang@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.linux-kvm.org/page/Virtio" />
      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-current/2011-January/022036.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>VirtIO is a device framework offered by KVM/Qemu and Virtualbox
	to allow guests to achieve better I/O performance.  A beta
	network driver was made available earlier this month, and work
	continues on completing the block device and refinements the
	existing network driver.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>TCP SMP scalability project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A long-running TCP SMP scalability project is beginning to wrap
	up, with the goal of committing a large outstanding patch to the
	&os; 9.x tree in the next month.  This work implements a
	derivative of Willman, Rixner, and Cox's TCP connection group
	model, blended with support for hardware load distribution
	features in contemporary NICs (including RSS).  Additional
	software distribution support can do work redistribution based
	on new notions of CPU affinity for individual TCP
	connections.</p>
	
      <p>On-going work is refining performance on non-RSS supporting
	configurations, and adding APIs to allow socket affinity to be
	queried (and where supported) set by applications.  These
	changes significantly improve network scalability by reducing
	global lock contention, encouraging CPU affinity for
	connections, and avoiding cache line contention.  The goal is
	to allow steady-state TCP connections to use only CPU-local
	cache lines, with work distributed to all CPUs.  Current
	performance results are extremely promising.</p>
	
      <p>This project has been sponsored by Juniper Networks.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Allow the hash model to be selected at boot-time or run-time
	rather than compile-time; currently "options RSS" enables RSS
	support unconditionally &mdash; for systems without RSS NICs,
	this leads to a small one-time performance penalty at the
	creation of each call to bind() or connect().</task>
  
      <task>Add missing socket options to query (and override) default
	CPU affinity for connections, which is derived from the active
	software or hardware hash model.</task>
  
      <task>Teach the network stack and appropriate NIC drivers to
	propagate software-overriden connection affinity to hardware
	using new device driver ioctls for managing TCAMs and hardware
	hash tables.</task>
  
      <task>Refine software redistribution of work in the event that
	there are fewer hardware queues than available CPU threads in
	which to process packets; the current prototype is able to do
	this with significant performance benefits, but the model
	requires refining.</task>
  
      <task>Experiment with (and measure) software work redistribution
	at run-time based on RSS bucket rearrangement.  This will
	require a new event notification to device drivers so that
	they can update hardware caches of the network stack's
	authoritative table.</task>
  
      <task>Commit.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
