<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">

<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2001-07.xml,v 1.9 2007/04/11 04:11:09 brd Exp $ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July</month>

    <year>2001</year>
  </date>

  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2001-07.xml,v 1.9 2007/04/11 04:11:09 brd Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>Last month's status report was apparently a great success: I
    received countless e-mails with comments, questions, and
    suggestions. I've tried to incorporate any suggestions and address
    any problems from these e-mails in this month's report, which
    captures a far more extensive snapshot of FreeBSD activity in the
    last month. Unlike last month's report, it does a better job of
    reflecting non-development activity, such as on-going conference
    planning, documentation, and so on. This is a trend I hope to see
    improve in future months as well.</p>

    <p>On the topic of conferences, in the future I'd like to report
    more on publication activities relating to FreeBSD, including
    online journals with articles relating to FreeBSD, paper journals,
    conference papers, and so on. Likewise, I would be interested in
    including references to Call for Papers relating to FreeBSD. I'll
    take this opportunity to plug both registration and paper
    submission for BSDCon Europe in November, which has status included
    in this report, and for the general BSD Conference being hosted by
    USENIX in February. Your attendance and submissions make these
    conferences "happen", and promote FreeBSD as a platform for new
    research, feature development, and application products. Work of
    extremely high calibre is performed on FreeBSD, and we need to get
    the word out.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Submission for Future Editions</title>

    <p>Next month, we're maintaining much the same submission
    requirements: reports should be one or two paragraphs long, sent by
    e-mail, and approximate the layout of the entries this month
    (Project, Contact, URL, and text). I'll send out reminders again
    over the week before the deadline, with more specific instructions.
    An area where I'd like to explore improvement lies in the
    coordination of related status reports for larger projects, such as
    new architectural work or platform ports. This might even have the
    effect of encouraging communication within these projects :-). I'd
    like to continue to focus on pulling in a broader range of groups
    and their activities, including the Security Officer, Release
    Engineer, and Core Team.</p>

    <p>
      <i>-- Robert Watson &lt;
      <a href="mailto:rwatson@FreeBSD.org">rwatson@FreeBSD.org</a>

      &gt;</i>
    </p>
  </section>

  <project>
    <title>ACPI</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mike</given>

          <common>Smith</common>
        </name>

        <email>msmith@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>ACPI (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface) is an
      industry standard which obsoletes APM, Intel MPS, PnPBIOS, and
      other Intel PC firmware interface standards. It is also used on
      the IA64 platform. More information on ACPI is available at</p>

      <a href="http://developer.intel.com/technology/iapc/acpi">
      http://developer.intel.com/technology/iapc/acpi</a>

      <p>The FreeBSD ACPI subsystem project is based heavily on the
      Intel ACPI Component Architecture. This status report outlines
      the current state of the project; future updates will focus on
      changes as they occur.</p>

      <p>The Intel ACPI interpreter is fully integrated, although bugs
      are still coming out of the woodwork occasionally.</p>

      <ul>
        <li>PCI bus detection and interrupt routing are functional, but
        power management interaction will require work on the core PCI
        subsystem.</li>

        <li>Non-PCI motherboard peripheral probing is implemented, but
        believed to have problems on some systems.</li>

        <li>A power policy manager has been implemented. The initial
        policy manager has two modes, "performance" and "economy".</li>

        <li>CPU speed throttling is integrated with the platform power
        policy.</li>

        <li>System thermal monitoring is implemented, but fan control
        is believed to have problems.</li>

        <li>Pushbutton suspend and power-off is implemented.</li>

        <li>System timekeeping using the ACPI timer is supported.</li>

        <li>Battery status monitoring is implemented.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Work is ongoing in the following areas:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>System suspend and resume.</li>

        <li>Timekeeper accuracy/reliability.</li>

        <li>Power profiles.</li>

        <li>User-level management interfaces.</li>

        <li>PCI power management.</li>

        <li>Bug-hunting.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>ARM Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Stephane</given>

          <common>Potvin</common>
        </name>

        <email>septovin@videotron.ca</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The ARM port is currently going pretty well. The kernel is
      compiling and is able to boot to the point where it panics trying
      to initialize the network subsystem. The current reference
      platform is the Netwinder but this may change as many people
      expressed interest in a more broadly available platform. Things
      that need to be done before it can get further includes adding
      footbridge, timer and interrupt supports. The pmap module is not
      completed yet either.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>BIND 9</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Doug Barton</name>

        <email>dougb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>Jeroen Ruigrok</name>

        <email>asmodai@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Now that BIND 8.2.4 is finally imported the time has come to
      look at getting BIND 9 imported into CURRENT. The current idea is
      to have it imported alongside BIND 8 so that people can play with
      either one until all import problems have been taken care of and
      people have tested it a bit.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>binup</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Eric Melville</name>

        <email>eric@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Although gaining a new name, the project has been at a
      standstill due to both resource availability during the move
      between BSDi and Wind River, and other commitments of the
      developers. The project should obtain an official mailing list,
      as well as return to an active state after the dust settles.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>BSDCon Europe</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdconeurope.org" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Paul Richards</name>

        <email>paul@freebsd-services.co.uk</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>Josef Karthauser</name>

        <email>joe@tao.org.uk</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The conference will take place at the Thistle Hotel, Brighton,
      UK from 9-11 November 2001.</p>

      <p>The aim of the conference is to provide a focal point for
      European users and developers of all the BSD derived operating
      systems. The format will be similar to other conferences, with 2
      days of technical sessions over the Saturday and Sunday.</p>

      <p>We'll be finalizing the schedule towards the end of the month
      and anybody who is interested in doing a talk should contact us
      ASAP. There are no restrictions on the use of talks; if it's been
      done before we may still be interested in having it presented to
      an European audience, and we make no claims to the talks so
      speakers are free to present the talks again at other
      conferences.</p>

      <p>We're also still looking for sponsors.</p>

      <p>We had 80 pre-registrations in the first week so we're
      expecting a good turnout.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>CAM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Matthew Jacob</name>

        <email>mjacob@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>Justin Gibbs</name>

        <email>gibbs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The new CAM transport code is starting to get supported in
      more HBAs and to get refined so that it does the intended
      per-protocol support. No progress on doing any SMPng work for CAM
      has been made yet. This is a fairly high priority.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Problem Reports</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://phk.freebsd.dk/Gnats/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Poul-Henning</given>

          <common>Kamp</common>
        </name>

        <email>phk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Thanks to various outstanding individual efforts, we are now
      down to just below 2300 open bug-reports. This means that we have
      fought our way back to the level we had around march 2000.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Documentation Project</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/docs.html" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/docproj/index.html" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Documentation Project</name>

        <email>doc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work continues (in large part sponsored by WRS) on updating
      the Handbook ready for the second print edition. There has been a
      flurry of activity in this area recently, and the ToDo list can
      be seen at</p>

      <p>
        <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/docproj/handbook.html">
        http://www.FreeBSD.org/docproj/handbook.html</a>
      </p>

      <p>Dima and others are doing a stellar job of keeping up with the
      steady flow of incoming PRs relating to the documentation
      project.</p>

      <p>The Developers' Handbook,</p>

      <p>
        <a
        href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/developers-handbook/index.html">
        http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/developers-handbook/index.html</a>
      </p>

      <p>is a year old; it contains a wealth of useful content for
      developers developing on, or for, FreeBSD. As ever, more
      contributions are always required, not only for the developers'
      handbook, but for all of the FreeBSD documentation set.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Fibre Channel Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Matthew Jacob</name>

        <email>mjacob@feral.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The basic design hasn't changed and this project mainly is in
      the phase of continued hardening and test case development. The
      next major feature will be to fully integrate into the new CAM
      TRAN code and to fully support on the fly device addition and
      removal. The only HBA supported is QLogic at this time. Future
      support for the QLogic line is planned to have 2300 (2Gb) and IP
      support before October.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Hardware Watchpoints in the Kernel Debugger</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brian Dean</name>

        <email>bsd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Hardware watchpoints are now available for kernel debugging on
      the IA32 (i386) architecture. One can now set hardware
      watchpoints using the new ddb command 'hwatch', which is
      analogous to the existing 'watch' command. Alternatively, if
      greater flexibility is required, direct access to the debug
      registers is available using the ddb 'set' command which allows
      complete control over the processor hardware debug facilities.
      Hardware watchpoints are very useful in tracking down those
      elusive memory overwrite bugs in the kernel. Hardware watchpoints
      can even be used to set a code breakpoint in ROM, which is
      commonly found in embedded systems.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>ifconfig support for IEEE 802.11 wireless devices</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brooks Davis</name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for configuring IEEE 802.11 wireless devices via
      ifconfig has been committed to -current and -stable. It contains
      most of the functionality needed to configure an wireless device.
      Some missing features are being worked on including integrated
      support for DHCP so a single entry in /etc/rc.conf can be used to
      fully configure a wireless device on a DHCP lan and setting the
      CTS/RTS threshold. Currently the an(4) and wi(4) drivers are
      supported in -current and -stable with the awi(4) device
      supported in -current. Further work is needed to support
      Frequency Hopping devices such as ray(4).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>jailNG</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Robert Watson</name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>jailNG is a from-scratch rewrite of the popular jail(8)
      service, focusing on improved management functions, as well as
      more fine-grained configurability. An initial prototype has been
      written, based on explicitly named and configured jails, and work
      is proceeding on userland integration. Currently, it's not clear
      if the timeline for this will be 5.0-RELEASE, or 5.1-RELEASE.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD Java Project</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/java/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Greg Lewis</name>

        <email>glewis@eyesbeyond.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The main development in the FreeBSD Java Project over the last
      month was the release of an initial "Developers Only" patchset
      for the JDK 1.3.1. Since that release progress had been made
      towards a much more usable alpha quality patchset which is
      likely to be turned into a port, as per the current JDK 1.2.2
      patchset. This new patchset will feature a number of bugfixes,
      which essentially get the JDK to a working state for early
      adopters, and an initial implementation of "native threads" based
      on FreeBSD's userland pthreads. Unfortunately this implementation
      isn't fully functional, but is included in the hope of
      getting more eyeballs on the code (particularly experienced
      pthread programmers). We'd also like to welcome Fuyuhiko
      Maruyama-san as a new committer, the usual punishment for too
      many good patches.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>jpman project</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/man-jp/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Japanese Man Page Project</name>

        <email>man-jp@jp.FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>We have been working to provide Japanese version of FreeBSD
      online manuals, since 1996. Currently, RELENG_4 manuals are
      based. Translated versions are placed on doc/ja_JP.eucJP/man and
      provided to users using ports/japanese/man-doc. Also, we discuss
      about related commands (e.g. ports/japanese/man and
      ports/japanese/groff).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Kernel Summit - Usenix 2001</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/~jhb/summit/usenix01/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>John Baldwin</name>

        <email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The first FreeBSD kernel summit meeting was held June 29-30,
      2001 in Boston, MA at the Usenix 2001 Annual Technical
      Conference. Links to a variety of files are posted on the web
      site.</p>

      <p>Note: I (jhb) am still working on writing up a general summary
      of the meeting. When that is completed it will be posted here and
      mailed to the -hackers mailing list.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>KSE threading the kernel</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~jasone/kse/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Julian Elischer</name>

        <email>julian@elischer.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>I'm working on multithreading the kernel. So far I have over
      400KB of diffs relative to today's -current (I'm keeping my tree
      updated with changes as they occur rather than get hit with a big
      update at the end).</p>

      <p>I have split the proc structure and am changing most of the
      kernel to pass around a thread identifier instead of a proc
      structure.</p>

      <p>The following interfaces have been changed so far:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>device devsw entries</li>

        <li>vfs calls</li>

        <li>mutexes</li>

        <li>events</li>

        <li>system calls</li>

        <li>scheduler</li>

        <li>+ a lot of code in between.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>I have still a lot of work to go with a lot of "dumb editing"
      (s/struct proc \*p/struct thread \*td/) usually I change a few
      items and then fix everything that breaks when I try compile it.
      I'd like to check it in on a branch so others can help the
      editing but haven't worked out the best way to do it yet.</p>

      <p>I have implemented changes to the scheduler so that KSE's are
      scheduled instead of processes, and threads sleep, letting the
      KSE pick up a new thread. but it's not anywhere ready yet (heck
      it doesn't compile yet :-)</p>

      <p>Note that I have not yet updated the document listed above..
      everywhere it mentions "ksec" or "KSE-context", the code uses the
      word "thread". I will update it soon as Jason has sent me the
      source.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD Monthly Development Status Reports</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/news/status/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Robert Watson</name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org&gt;</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>Chris Costello</name>

        <email>chris@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Monthly Development Status Report aims to keep
      users and developers up-to-date on the latest goings-on in the
      FreeBSD project by providing summaries of each project and its
      status. At the time of this writing, the July 2001 status report
      is being prepared and is very near release. The FreeBSD Web site
      now has a Status Reports section, which, when the July 2001
      report is released, will be updated to include a link to an
      HTML-ified version.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>NetBSD rc.d port</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/FreeBSD-rc" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Doug Barton</name>

        <email>dougb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>Sheldon Hearn</name>

        <email>sheldonh@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The NetBSD rc.d port aims to improve the FreeBSD startup
      process by porting Luke Mewburn's rc.d work from NetBSD to
      FreeBSD. This will score FreeBSD startup and shutdown
      dependencies without losing the traditional and much loved
      monolithic configuration filesystem.</p>

      <p>Luke Mewburn's USENIX paper and slides on the system as
      implemented in NetBSD are available here:</p>

      <p>
        <a href="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/FreeBSD-rc/message/3">
        http://groups.yahoo.com/group/FreeBSD-rc/message/3</a>
      </p>

      <p>Interested parties are urged to study this material before
      joining the discussion list.</p>

      <p>The intention at this stage is to decide on an approach that
      will ensure that the differences between the NetBSD rc.d system
      and the system as ported to FreeBSD will be kept to a minimum.
      This will probably involve discussions with Luke around those
      areas of the system that are identified as areas for potential
      improvement.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Netgraph ATM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Hartmut Brandt</name>

        <email>brandt@fokus.gmd.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of this project is the implementation of ATM
      signalling and other ATM protocols by means of the netgraph(4)
      framework. This should provide an easily extensible architecture
      for using ATM on FreeBSD. Currently the full UNI4.0 stack (except
      for the LIJ capability) has been implemented, including ILMI and
      a first version of the ATM Forum API for UNI. An implementation
      of Classical IP over ATM is also available. Drivers have been
      implemented for the Fore PCA200E and Fore HE-155 cards.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>network device cloning</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brooks Davis</name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Network device cloning support has been imported from NetBSD.
      This allows virtual devices to be allocated on demand rather then
      being statically allocated at compile time. Our implementation
      differs slightly from that of NetBSD's in that we allow both the
      creation of specific devices (i.e. gif0) and arbitrary devices
      instead of just allowing specific devices. Currently, the only
      device in the tree which has been converted is the gif(4) device
      which has been converted in both -current and -stable. Work is
      ongoing to convert all other virtual network devices with work in
      progress on faith, stf, and vlan interfaces. In general this
      conversion is accompanied by appropriate modifications to make
      these devices fully modular.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Next Generation POSIX threads (NGPT)</title>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/pthreads/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Arun Sharma</name>

        <email>arun@sharma.dhs.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <h4>Porting NGPT (next generation pthreads) to FreeBSD</h4>

      <p>NGPT is an effort led by IBM engineers to implement MxN
      threads (also known as many user threads to one kernel thread
      mapping) on Linux. I have ported it to FreeBSD to use
      rfork(2).</p>

      <p>The port is right here:</p>

      <p>
        <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=29239">
        http://www.FreeBSD.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=29239</a>
      </p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>OLDCARD upgrade to support PCI cards</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~imp/oldcard-status.html" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Warner Losh</name>

        <email>imp@village.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>
        <i>Funded by: Monzoon Networking, LLC</i>
      </p>

      <p>This month has been a month of conventration and
      consolidation. Much of the changes from current have been
      migrating into stable. I've improved power support,
      suspend/resume interactions, interrupt handling, and ability to
      work after windows/NEWCARD has run. Interrupt routing continues
      to be a locking issue for a complete MFC. Current patches are
      available at the above website. I'm racing to get this done
      before 4.4 is released.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Open Runtime Platform (ORP)</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.intel.com/research/mrl/orp/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Arun Sharma</name>

        <email>arun@sharmas.dhs.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>eGroups: ORP</name>

        <email>orp@egroups.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Information on Intel ORP - a BSD licensed Java VM is right
      here:</p>

      <p>
        <a href="http://www.intel.com/research/mrl/orp/">
        http://www.intel.com/research/mrl/orp/</a>
      </p>

      <p>A FreeBSD patch has been tested to work with NGPT and
      submitted to the ORP project. The patch is available here:</p>

      <p>
        <a
        href="http://www.sharma-home.net/~adsharma/projects/orp/orp-freebsd-1.0.5.patch.txt.gz">
        http://www.sharma-home.net/~adsharma/projects/orp/orp-freebsd-1.0.5.patch.txt.gz</a>
      </p>

      <p>There are some issues to be ironed out to make it work with
      FreeBSD's default (user level) pthread implementation.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>OpenPackages</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://openpackages.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenPackages intends to create a software packaging system
      that will allow third-party programs to be installed, without
      operating system dependent changes, on as many platforms as are
      feasible. OpenPackages was originally based on code from the BSD
      ports systems, and has been improved and extended by developers
      of many heritages.</p>

      <p>The OpenPackages Project is pleased to release the Milestone 2
      codebase. This release contains a working package building system
      and a single test package. OP currently is known to build on
      certain instances of the following operating systems: FreeBSD,
      HP/UX, IRIX, Linux (Debian, Red Hat, Suse, Mandrake, TurboLinux,
      Caldera, etc.), NetBSD, OpenBSD, Solaris</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PAM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Mark R V Murray</name>

        <email>mark@grondar.za</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>(First report)</p>

      <p>Large cleanup and extension of FreeBSD PAM modules. All
      modules are to be documented, consistent in style (style(9) used)
      and as complete as possible WRT functionality. Mostly done.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PowerPC Port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Benno Rice</name>

        <email>benno@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>We now have the rudiments of device support. We have a nexus
      driver for OpenFirmware machines, along with support for the
      Apple UniNorth PCI/AGP host bridge. I'm currently trying to get
      the USB hardware working so that I can get closer to having a
      console driver independent of OpenFirmware, then I'll be trying
      to get the system to get to single-user mode using NFS.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PPP IPv6 Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brian Somers</name>

        <email>brian@freebsd-services.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work has begun, but nothing has yet been committed. The NCP
      addresses used by ppp have been abstracted and initial support
      has been added to the filter set for ipv6 addresses. NCP
      negotiation hasn't yet been started.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>Porting ppp to hurd &amp; linux</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brian Somers</name>

        <email>brian@Awfulhak.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Patches have been submitted to get ppp working under HURD, and
      mostly under Linux. There are GPL copyright problems that need to
      be addressed.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>pppoed</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Brian Somers</name>

        <email>brian@freebsd-services.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Making pppoed function in a production environment. Most of
      the work is complete and committed. Additional work includes
      adding a -l option where ``-l label'' is shorthand for ``-e exec
      ppp -direct label'' and discovering why rogue child processes are
      being left around.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>PRFW - Hooks within the FreeBSD kernel</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Evan Sarmiento</name>

        <email>ems@open-root.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>PRFW is a set of hooks which I have integrated into the
      FreeBSD kernel. This allows modules to easily intercept system
      calls with less overhead. It also supports per-pid restrictions,
      which means, one process may not be able to use X function in Y
      manner, but another process may.</p>

      <p>Progress: I was working on this in 4.3-RELEASE, but now I'm
      merging it into current. I will be submitting a patch to the
      mailing lists in about a week.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SCSI Tape Support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Matthew Jacob</name>

        <email>mjacob@feral.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>This driver is currently not working well under -current and
      is undergoing some work at this time. No major design or feature
      changes are planned. There was some notion of adding TapeAlert
      support, but HP supports that as a binary product via a user
      library and it was felt that it'd be more politically prudent to
      leave it alone.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Peter Wemm</name>

        <email>peter@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>John Baldwin</name>

        <email>jhb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <h4>Development</h4>

      <p>In the 'smpng' p4 branch there is code to make the ast()
      function loop to close the race when an AST is triggered while we
      are handling previously triggered AST's.</p>

      <p>In the 'jhb_preemption' p4 branch work is being done to make
      the kernel fully preemptive. It is reportedly stable on UP x86,
      but SMP x86 locks up, UP alpha has problems during shutdown and
      can recurse indefinitely until it exhausts its stack.</p>

      <h4>Management</h4>

      <p>We are using a perforce repository for live development work,
      which can track multiple separate long-lived works-in-progress
      and collaborate between multiple developers at the same time on
      the same change set.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD-current is being imported into p4 hourly, for easy
      tracking of the moving -current tree.</p>

      <p>I haven't written up a good primer yet, but we're able to open
      this up to the general developer community. NEWCARD work looks
      like it will be done here too. Perforce is ideal for tracking
      this sort of long-lived project without having to resort to
      passing patches around.</p>

      <p>KSE work is now being checked into a kse p4 branch - thanks
      Julian!</p>

      <p>KSE work is focusing on getting the main API changes into the
      base tree well before 5.0.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SMPng mbuf allocator</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bmilekic/code/mb_slab/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Bosko Milekic</name>

        <email>bmilekic@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>mb_alloc is a specialized allocator for mbufs and mbuf
      clusters. It offers various important advantages over the old
      mbuf allocator, particularly for MP machines. Additionally, it
      is designed with the possibility of important future
      enhancements in mind.</p>

      <p>The mb_alloc code has been committed to -CURRENT a month ago
      and appears to be holding up well. Prior to committing it,
      preliminary performance measurements were done merely to ensure
      that it is not significantly worse than the old allocator, even
      with Giant still in place. Results were promising 
      <a
      href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bmilekic/code/mb_alloc/results.html">
      [http://people.FreeBSD.org/~bmilekic/code/mb_alloc/results.html]</a>

      - also see jlemon's results (link at the bottom of accompanying
      text). Since the commit, Matt Jacob has provided useful feedback
      and bugfixes. Work is now being done to re-enable mbtypes
      statistics and make appropriate changes to netstat(1) and
      systat(1).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>sparc64 port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Jake Burkholder</name>

        <email>jake@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The sparc64 port has been committed to the FreeBSD repository.
      As such further development will occur in cvs, rather than as a
      separately maintained patch set. Significant progress has been
      made since the last status report, including; support for kernel
      debugging with ddb, much more complete pmap support, support for
      context switching and process creation, and filling out of
      important machine dependent data structures. Thomas Moestl has
      shown a strong interest in working on the port and is in the
      process of implementing support for saving and restoring a
      process's floating point context. I look forward to working with
      him and any other developers that happen to fall out of the wood
      works.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>FreeBSD/sparc64 kernel loader</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Robert Drehmel</name>

        <email>robert@ferrari.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The sparc64 loader is functional enough to boot an ELF binary
      from an UFS filesystem using the existent openfirmware library,
      which has been revised to work flawlessly on 32-bit and 64-bit
      architectures. Support for netbooting and modules will be
      implemented next, followed by a better openfirmware mapping
      strategy.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>SYN cache implementation for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Jonathan Lemon</name>

        <email>jlemon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>This project brings a SYN cache implementation to FreeBSD, in
      order to make it more robust to DoS attacks. A SYN cookie
      approach was considered, but ultimately rejected because it does
      not conform to the TCP protocol. The SYN cache will work with
      T/TCP, IPV6 and IPSEC, and the size of each cache element is
      currently is less than 1/5th the size of a normal TCP control
      block.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project>
    <title>TrustedBSD Project</title>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/" />
    </links>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>Robert Watson</name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>It's been a busy month, with a number of relevant news items.
      Not least important is that NAI Labs was awarded a $1.2M contract
      from the US Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) to
      work on a variety of components relevant to the TrustedBSD
      Project, including support for pluggable security models, and
      supporting features such as improving the extended attributes
      implementation, simple crypto support for swap and filesystems,
      documentation, and much more.</p>

      <p>On the features side, progress continues on Mandatory Access
      Control, object labeling, and improving the consistency of kernel
      access control mechanisms--in particular, with regard to
      inter-process authorization and credential management. Work has
      begun on porting LOMAC, NAI Labs' Low-Watermark Mandatory Access
      Control scheme, from Linux to FreeBSD, and it has been
      re-licensed under a BSD license. We hope to have an initial port
      complete in time for 5.0-RELEASE later this year.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>

