<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
Status Report//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2011-01-2011-03.xml,v 1.2 2011/04/24 22:49:11 bcr Exp $ -->
<report>
  <date>
    <month>January-March</month>
    <year>2011</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between January and March
      2011.  It is the first of the four reports planned for 2011.  During
      this quarter, the work was focused on releasing the new minor
      versions of &os;, 7.4 and 8.2, which were released in February 2011.
      Currently, the project is starting to work on the next major version,
      9.0.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! This report
      contains 31 entries and we hope you enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>Please note that the deadline for submissions covering the period
      between April and June 2011 is July 15th, 2011.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>
    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>
    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>
    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>
    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>
    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>
    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>
    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>
    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>gsoc</name>
    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='gsoc'>
    <title>Google Summer of Code 2011</title>
    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brooks</given>
	  <common>Davis</common>
	</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/org/google/gsoc2011/freebsd" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; is proud to be participating in our seventh year of Google
	Summer of Code.  We are currently ranking student proposals.
	Accepted proposals will be announced Monday April 25th.  We look
	forward to working with the accepted students over the summer.</p>

      <p>As we did last year we plan to ask students to submit weekly
	status reports to the 
	<a href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/soc-status">
	  soc-status</a> mailing list.  Those wishing to keep up with
	the work in progress and offer review may wish to
	subscribe.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Bugbusting Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Linimon</common>
	</name>
	<email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Remko</given>
	  <common>Lodder</common>
	</name>
	<email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Volker</given>
	  <common>Werth</common>
	</name>
	<email>vwe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/support.html#gnats">&os; Support
	  page</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BugBusting">Resources and
	  documentation available for Bugbusting</url>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~linimon/studies/prs/">Links
	  to all of the auto-generated PR reports</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The bugmeister team is happy to welcome Eitan Adler (eadler@) as
	the newest GNATS-only contributor.  Eitan has been helping triage
	new bugs as they come in, as well as making good progress on many
	of the older bugs, closing duplicates and obsolete bugs and
	contacting submitters for extra information where necessary.  For
	the first time in a long time we managed to get below 6000 open
	PRs, in no small part due to Eitan's efforts.  Welcome aboard!</p>

      <p>PRs continue to be classified as they arrive, by adding 'tags'
	to the subject lines corresponding to the kernel subsystem
	involved, or man page references for userland PRs.  Reports are
	generated from these nightly, grouping related PRs into one place,
	sorted by tag or man page.  This allows an interested party working
	in one area or on one subsystem to easily find related bugs and
	issues in the same area, which has proven quite effective in
	getting some of the older bug reports closed.  These reports can all
	be found by following the third link above.</p>

      <p>We continue to look for ideas for other reports that may help
	improve the PR closure rate.  If you have any suggestions for
	reports which would contribute positively to the way you work,
	please email bugmeister@ and we shall try to produce such a
	report.</p>

      <p>Our clearance rate of PRs, especially in kern and bin, seems to
	be improving.  The number of non-ports PRs has stayed almost
	constant since the last status report.</p>

      <p>As always, anybody interested in helping out with the PR queue
	is welcome to join us in #freebsd-bugbusters on EFnet.  We are
	always looking for additional help, whether your interests lie in
	triaging incoming PRs, generating patches to resolve existing
	problems, or simply helping with the database housekeeping
	(identifying duplicate PRs, ones that have already been resolved,
	etc).  This is a great way of getting more involved with &os;!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Try to find ways to get more committers helping us with
	closing PRs that the team has already analyzed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Hayes</common>
	</name>
	<email>dahayes@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Lawrence</given>
	  <common>Stewart</common>
	</name>
	<email>lastewart@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bjoern</given>
	  <common>Zeeb</common>
	</name>
	<email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/freebsd/5cc/" />
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/" />
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/projects.shtml" />
      <url href="http://FreeBSDfoundation.blogspot.com/2011/03/summary-of-five-new-tcp-congestion.html" />
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/5cc/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project is now complete, with the following code available
	in the svn head branch:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Modular congestion control framework.</li>
	<li>Khelp (Kernel Helper) and Hhook (Helper Hook)
	frameworks.</li>
	<li>Basic Khelp/Hhook integration with the TCP stack.</li>
	<li>Enhanced Round Trip Time (ERTT) Khelp module.</li>
	<li>Modularised implementations of NewReno, CUBIC, H-TCP, Vegas,
	  Hamilton-Delay and CAIA-Hamilton-Delay congestion control
	  algorithms.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>In addition to the code, a large set of documentation was
	committed (see the following man pages: cc(4), cc_newreno(4),
	cc_cubic(4), cc_htcp(4), cc_vegas(4), cc_hd(4), cc_chd(4),
	h_ertt(4), cc(9), khelp(9), hhook(9)) and a <a
	  href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/reports/110228A/CAIA-TR-110228A.pdf">
	technical report</a> was released which evaluates the
	computational overhead associated with TCP before and after
	the project's changes.</p>

      <p>A candidate patch to MFC the modular congestion control
	framework to the 8-STABLE branch is ready for testing  <a
	  href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/5cc/modularcc_mfc_8.x.r219091.patch">
	here</a>.  If you try the patch, please send a note detailing
	your experience (positive or negative) to Lawrence
	Stewart.</p>

      <p>Thanks go to the &os; Foundation for funding this work, to the
	project's technical reviewers for providing detailed feedback, and
	to all &os; users who have provided testing feedback thus far.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test <a
	  href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/5cc/modularcc_mfc_8.x.r219091.patch">
	  8-STABLE MFC candidate patch</a> and do the merge in time
	  for 8.3-RELEASE.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="team">
    <title>The &os; Foundation Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We created our <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/documents/Budget2011.pdf">
	2011 budget</a>.  Some of our plans for 2011 include spending
	$125,000 on project development and $75,000 on equipment to
	build up &os; facilities in three locations.</p>

      <p>We were proud to be a sponsor for AsiaBSDCon 2011 in Tokyo.  We
	also committed to sponsoring BSDCan 2011 in May, and EuroBSDCon
	2011 in October.  The Foundation was also represented at SCALE in
	Los Angeles, Indiana LinuxFest in Indianapolis, and Flourish in
	Chicago.</p>

      <p>Completed Foundation-funded projects: <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/announcements.shtml#Swinburne">
	  Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms project</a> by
	Swinburne University and Resource Containers project by
	Edward Napierala.</p>

      <p>In February we visited companies in the Bay Area that use &os;.
	Our goal was to promote &os;, better understand their interests and
	needs, and help facilitate stronger relationships between these
	companies and the Project.  The presentations we gave included the
	benefits of &os;, Project road-map, potential areas of
	collaboration, case studies, and how the Foundation supports the
	project.  By visiting in person we were able to show our commitment
	to the Project and respond directly to questions and concerns they
	may have had.  We were pleased with the positive responses we
	received and plan on visiting more companies in the future.</p>

      <p>We are funding two new projects.  The first project is
	Implementing Support of GEM, KMS, and DRI for Intel Drivers by
	Konstantin Belousov.  The second is Improving the Maturity of IPv6
	Support of &os; and PC-BSD by Bjoern Zeeb.</p>

      <p>We continued our work on infrastructure projects to beef up
	hardware for package-building, network-testing, etc.  This includes
	purchasing equipment as well as managing equipment donations.</p>

      <p>Stop by and visit with us at BSDCan (May 13-14) and SouthEast
	LinuxFest (June 10-12).</p>

      <p>The work above as well as many other tasks we do for the
	project, couldn't be done without donations.  Please help us by
	making a donation or asking your company to make a donation.  We
	would be happy to send marketing literature to you or your company.
	Find out how to make a donation at <a
	  href="http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/donate/">
	  http://www.FreeBSDfoundation.org/donate/</a>.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>KDE-&os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>KDE</given>
	  <common>&os;</common>
	</name>
	<email>kde-freebsd@kde.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org">KDE-&os;</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The KDE on &os; team have continued to improve the experience of
	KDE and Qt under &os;.  The latest round of improvements
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Improved shared resources (i.e. pixmaps for KDE)</li>
	<li>Improved file monitoring (using kevent)</li>
	<li>Improved KSysGuard support (new and refined sensors)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The team have also made many releases and upstreamed many fixes
	and patches.  The latest round of releases include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Qt: 4.7.2</li>
	<li>KDE: 4.5.5; 4.6.1; 4.6.2</li>
	<li>KOffice: 2.3.3</li>
	<li>KDevelop: 4.2.0; 4.2.2 (KDevPlatform: 1.2.0; 1.2.2)</li>
	<li>many smaller ports</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The team needs more testers and porters so please visit us at
	kde-freebsd@kde.org</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Continue improvements of KSysGuard.</task>
      <task>General maintenance.</task>
      <task>General testing.</task>
      <task><b>Porting</b>.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Chromium</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os;</given>
	  <common>Chromium Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>chromium@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/chromium" />
      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-chromium" />
      <url href="http://www.chromium.org/Home" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Thanks to a great collaborative effort from the &os; community, the
	OpenBSD community, and the Chromium developers, Chromium has been
	updated in the Ports tree.</p>

      <p>In the spirit of release early and release often, updates to
	Chromium happen frequently.  The contributors of the &os; Chromium
	team have demonstrated great agility in keeping pace with updates
	in the development repository hosted at <a
	  href="http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/chromium">
	  http://trillian.chruetertee.ch/chromium</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>A task that lies ahead is working with the Chromium
	developers at integrating the &os; patches into the codebase.
	Volunteers are welcome.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>DIstributed Firewall and Flow-shaper Using Statistical
      Evidence (DIFFUSE)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Sebastian</given>
	  <common>Zander</common>
	</name>
	<email>szander@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/diffuse/" />
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/diffuse/downloads.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>DIFFUSE is a system enabling &os;'s IPFW firewall subsystem to
	classify IP traffic based on statistical traffic properties.</p>

      <p>With DIFFUSE, IPFW computes statistics (such as packet lengths
	or inter-packet time intervals) for observed flows, and uses ML
	(machine learning) to classify flows into classes.  In addition to
	traditional packet inspection rules, IPFW rules may now also be
	expressed in terms of traffic statistics or classes identified by
	ML classification.  This can be helpful when direct packet
	inspection is problematic (perhaps for administrative reasons, or
	because port numbers do not reliably identify applications).</p>

      <p>DIFFUSE also enables one instance of IPFW to send flow
	information and classes to other IPFW instances, which then can act
	on such traffic (e.g. prioritise, accept, deny, etc.) according to
	its class.  This allows for distributed architectures, where
	classification at one location in your network is used to control
	fire-walling or rate-shaping actions at other locations.</p>

      <p>DIFFUSE is a set of patches for &os;-CURRENT.  It can be
	downloaded from the project's web site.  The web site also contains
	a more comprehensive introduction, including application examples,
	links to related work and documentation.</p>

      <p>In February 2011 we released DIFFUSE v0.2.2.  This release
	contains a number of bug fixes and new features.  Most notably since
	version 0.2 there is a tool to build classifier models, and there
	is a feature module and classifier model to classify Skype
	traffic.</p>

      <p>We hope to release DIFFUSE v0.3 soon.  Keep an eye on the
	freebsd-ipfw and freebsd-net mailing lists for project-related
	announcements.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="ports">
    <title>&os; as Home Theater PC</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Bernhard</given>
	  <common>Froehlich</common>
	</name>
	<email>decke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juergen</given>
	  <common>Lock</common>
	</name>
	<email>nox@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/HTPC" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; could be a much better platform for a Home Theater PC than
	it currently is.  We are focusing on improving support for media
	center applications by extending the major ports (MythTV, VDR, XBMC)
	and creating some documentation to guide interested people.</p>

      <p>In the last months we continued to work on HTPC relevant ports,
	improved lirc and multimedia/webcamd remote control support.  The
	last missing major HTPC application VDR (Video Disk Recorder) has
	finally been committed to the portstree as multimedia/vdr including
	17 vdr plugin ports.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Improve remote control support in webcamd and with
	lirc.</task>

      <task>Port more Media Center applications (Enna, me-tv, ...)</task>

      <task>Create a small guide on how to build a great &os; Home
	Theater PC.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Bringing up OMAP3</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@bsdimp.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mohammed</given>
	  <common>Farrag</common>
	</name>
	<email>mfarrag@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>OMAP3 Emulation:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Step #1: qemu-omap3 isn't ported to &os; yet.  So,</li>
	<li>Step #2: Use qemu-omap3 on Gentoo Host ..</li>
	<li>Step #3: Is the end reached ?! No, bcz qemu-omap3 is not
	  full.  So, go to step #4.</li>
	<li>Step #4: Use Meego &gt;&gt; Download Ubuntu 10.10 &gt;&gt;
	  Install it, and</li>
	<li>Step #5: Compile &os; kernel, Create root file system,
	  mkimage, Emulate using Meego.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Device Drivers for OMAP3 Processors.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>New &os; Installer</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BSDInstall">BSDInstall Wiki Page
	(with test images)</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PCBSDInstallMerge">Wiki for
	Integration Plan with PC-BSD installer</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>On March 14th, sysinstall was replaced on the 9.0 snapshot media
	by a new, modular installer called BSDInstall.  This adds support
	for a wide variety of new features while simplifying the
	installation process.  Testing before the 9.0 release will be very
	much appreciated -- CD and memory stick images for a variety of
	platforms are linked from the BSDInstall wiki page.</p>

      <p>Interesting features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Install CD media are always live CDs</li>
	<li>Installations spanning multiple disks</li>
	<li>Wireless setup</li>
	<li>GPT disk formatting</li>
	<li>Virtualization friendly: can install from a live system onto
	  disk images</li>
	<li>Easily hackable and more modular than sysinstall</li>
	<li>Greater flexibility: shells available throughout the
	  installation</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Work is presently ongoing to integrate this installer with the
	backend provided by pc-sysinstall (second wiki link).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>ZFS installation support.</task>
      <task>IA64 disk setup.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>Webcam and DVB Compatibility List</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Matthias</given>
	  <common>Apitz</common>
	</name>
	<email>guru@unixarea.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/WebcamCompat" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><strong>Webcam and DVB Compatibility List</strong></p>

      <p>This is the &os; Webcam, DVB, and Remote Control Compatibility
	List.  The main goal of this page is to give an exact answer about
	which application works with a given cam or DVB.  Combinations of
	the hardware and software mentioned in this table are known to
	work.</p>

      <p>Please add more lines to the table or ask me to do so by just
	sending a mail with your Cam/DVB information.  Please note: you
	should only add information you have seen working and not you may
	think of or imagine that they could work.  The contact information
	(name and/or email addr) is optional.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Move this to a real database in where &os; enduser could self
	insert their gadgets, like the &os; Laptop Compat List.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>OpenAFS port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benjamin</given>
	  <common>Kaduk</common>
	</name>
	<email>kaduk@mit.edu</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Derrick</given>
	  <common>Brashear</common>
	</name>
	<email>shadow@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://openafs.org">OpenAFS home page</url>

      <url href="http://web.mit.edu/freebsd/openafs/openafs.shar">&os;
	port for OpenAFS 1.6.0 prerelease 4</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>AFS is a distributed network filesystem that originated from the
	Andrew Project at Carnegie-Mellon University.  The OpenAFS client
	implementation has not been particularly useful on &os; since the
	&os; 4.X releases.  Work covered in previous reports brought the
	OpenAFS client to a useful form on 9.0-CURRENT, though with some
	rough edges.  Since our last report, we have fixed several bugs that
	were impacting usability, and we expect the upcoming 1.6.0 release
	to be usable for regular client workloads (though not heavy load).
	Accordingly, we have submitted packaging for inclusion in the Ports
	Collection (PR ports/152467).</p>

      <p>There are several known outstanding issues that are being worked
	on, but detailed bug reports are welcome at
	port-freebsd@openafs.org.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update VFS locking to allow the use of disk-based client
	caches as well as memory-based caches.</task>

      <task>Track down races and deadlocks that may appear under
	load.</task>

      <task>Integrate with the bsd.kmod.mk kernel-module build
	infrastructure.</task>

      <task>Eliminate a moderate memory leak from the kernel
	module.</task>

      <task>PAG (Process Authentication Group) support is not
	functional.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; NYI Admins Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>NYI Admins Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>nyi-admin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD.org site at New York Internet is progressing, though
	more slowly than we had hoped.  Due to problems with the old power
	controllers and serial console servers, new equipment has been
	bought by the &os; Foundation.  Installing the new equipment
	required re-racking all the existing servers which was done by the
	local &os; team (Steven Kreuzer and John Baldwin).</p>

      <p>For basic infrastructure at the site (such as DHCP, DNS, console
	etc.) the &os; Foundation bought some new servers which are in the
	process of being configured.</p>

      <p>The &os; Ports team are currently using 9 of the NYI servers for
	package building.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We are looking for a storage system (15TB+) for keeping
	replicas of all the main FreeBSD.org systems, a full ftp-archive
	mirror, site local files etc.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>RCTL, aka Resource Containers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Most of the code has already been merged into CURRENT.  There are
	two remaining problems I would like to solve before 9.0-RELEASE - see
	below - but otherwise, the code is stable; please test and report
	any problems.  You will need to rebuild the kernel with "options
	RACCT" and "options RCTL".  The rctl(8) manual page should be a good
	introduction on how to use it.</p>

      <p>This project was sponsored by The &os; Foundation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Reimplementing %CPU accounting and CPU throttling.</task>

      <task>Making jail rules persistent - right now, one cannot add jail
	rule before that jail is created, which makes it impossible to put
	them into /etc/rctl.conf; also, rules disappear when jail gets
	destroyed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>portmaster</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Doug</given>
	  <common>Barton</common>
	</name>
	<email>dougb@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://dougbarton.us/portmaster-proposal.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The latest version of portmaster contains numerous improvements
	aimed at large-scale enterprise users.  Particularly, support for
	the --index-only/--packages-only code has been significantly
	improved.  Some of the highlights include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>New --update-if-newer option which takes a list of ports
	  and/or a glob pattern on the command line and only updates those
	  that are out of date.  This feature is very useful for ensuring
	  that the packages needed for updating a system are all available
	  and up to date on the package building system.</li>

	<li>The portmaster.rc file can now be stored in the same
	  directory as the script itself, which aids in shared access to
	  the script (for example over an NFS mount)</li>

	<li>More features now work (or work better) with --index-only,
	  including --check-depends</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>I have received some support for items E.2 and E.3 on the web
	page listed above so I will be putting some effort into those areas
	in the coming months.  I also have in mind to split out the "fetch"
	code to be its own script, in part to support goal E.2, and to
	allow for more efficient parallelization when downloading multiple
	distfiles (especially for multiple ports that download the same
	distfile).  This will also allow me to set a global limit for the
	number of parallel fetches which should aid users on slow
	links.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>pfSense</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Scott</given>
	  <common>Ullrich</common>
	</name>
	<email>sullrich@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Chris</given>
	  <common>Buechler</common>
	</name>
	<email>cmb@pfsense.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ermal</given>
	  <common>Luci</common>
	</name>
	<email>eri@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="www.pfsense.org">pfSense home page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work on 2.0 is rapidly coming to an end.  We released RC1 around
	Feb 25 2011 and so far it seems to be rather stable.  2.0 is our first
	major release in 2 years and almost all limitations of the previous
	version has been overcome.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish testing RC1 and certify for release.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Linux compatibility layer - DVB and V4L2 support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juergen</given>
	  <common>Lock</common>
	</name>
	<email>nox@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~nox/dvb/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Following (separate) discussions on the mailing lists I have
	made patches to add DVB and V4L2 ioctl translation support to the
	Linux compatibility layer, allowing Linux apps like SageTV, Skype,
	and Flash to use DVB/ATSC tuners and webcams that previously only
	worked for native &os; apps. (Most of this hardware uses Linux
	drivers via the <a
	  href="http://www.freshports.org/multimedia/webcamd">
	  multimedia/webcamd</a> port.)</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Handle the remaining ioctls that (I think) are not used by
	DVB tuners/cameras supported by webcamd (it only supports USB
	devices, the unhandled ioctls mostly have to do with video overlays
	and hardware MPEG2 decoding on analog or DVB tuners, features that
	AFAIK don't exist on USB hardware.)</task>

      <task>Make the DVB support a port because there were concerns
	putting it in base due to the LGPL in one of the header files even
	though I already separated out the code into an extra kld.
	(linux_dvbwrapper.ko)</task>

      <task>Get the patches polished and committed. :) (Until they are
	you can check my <a
	  href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~nox/dvb/">DVB page</a>
	and the freebsd-emulation@ mailing list for updates.)</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/powerpc on Freescale QorIQ</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Michal</given>
	  <common>Dubiel</common>
	</name>
	<email>md@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafal</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>QorIQ is a brand of Power Architecture-based communications
	microprocessors from Freescale.  It is an evolutionary step from the
	PowerQUICC platform (MPC85xx) and is built around one or more Power
	Architecture e500/e500mc cores.  This work is bringing up &os; on
	these system-on-chip devices along with device drivers for
	integrated peripherials.</p>

      <p>Current &os; QorIQ support includes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>QorIQ P2020 support</li>
	<li>Booting via U-Boot bootloader</li>
	<li>L1, L2 cache</li>
	<li>Serial console (UART)</li>
	<li>Interrupt controller</li>
	<li>Ethernet (TSEC, SGMII mode)</li>
	<li>I2C</li>
	<li>EHCI controller (no Transaction Translation Unit)</li>
	<li>Security Engine (SEC) 3.1</li>
	<li>PCI Express controller (host mode)</li>
	<li>Enhanced SDHC (no MMC support)</li>
	<li>Dual-core (SMP) support</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/arm on Marvell Raid-on-Chip</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grzegorz</given>
	  <common>Bernacki</common>
	</name>
	<email>gjb@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rafal</given>
	  <common>Jaworowski</common>
	</name>
	<email>raj@semihalf.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Marvell 88RC8180 is an integrated RAID-on-Chip controller, based
	on the Feroceon 88FR331 CPU core (ARMv5TE).  The 88RC9580 is a next
	generation version, based on the Sheeva 88SV581 CPU core (ARMv6) of
	this system-on-chip devices family.</p>

      <p>Current &os; suppport for 88RC8180 and 88RC9580 includes:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Booting via U-Boot bootloader</li>
	<li>L1, L2 cache</li>
	<li>Serial console support (UART)</li>
	<li>Interrupt controller</li>
	<li>Integrated timers</li>
	<li>PCI Express (root complex and endpoint modes)</li>
	<li>Doorbells and messages</li>
	<li>Ethernet controller</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete, clean up, merge with HEAD.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSDCan</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dan</given>
	  <common>Langille</common>
	</name>
	<email>dvl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/">BSDCan 2011</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Our <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/schedule/events.en.html">list
	  of talks</a> has been settled, and the <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/schedule/index.en.html">
	  schedule</a> is pretty much finalized.  There is still time
	  to get into the <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/schedule/events/259.en.html">
	  Works In Progress</a> session.</p>

      <p>Best to book your <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/campus.php">on-campus
	  accommodation</a>  now.  Or stay at one of the <a
	  href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2011/travel.php">nearby
	  hotels</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Show up.  Enjoy.  Profit.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Port</given>
	  <common>Management Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/" />
      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html" />
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html" />
      <url href="http://blogs.FreeBSDish.org/portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />
      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=135441496471197" />
      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree slowly moves up closer to 23,000.  The PR count
	still remains at about 1000.</p>

      <p>In Q1 we added 2 new committers, and took in 4 commit bits for
	safe keeping.</p>

      <p>After a year of serving as the team secretary, Thomas Abthorpe's
	membership was upgraded to full voting status.</p>

      <p>The Ports Management team have been running -exp runs on an
	ongoing basis, verifying how base system updates may affect the
	ports tree, as well as providing QA runs for major ports updates.
	Of note, -exp runs were done for:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>erwin did a clang -exp run, and sent results to interested
	  parties</li>

	<li>kde@ requested an -exp run for KDE 4.6.1 and Qt 4.7.2</li>

	<li>linimon -exp for update of default zope version to 3.2</li>

	<li>miwi performed the following -exp runs, make fetch-original,
	  xorg, cmake, pear, kde4 / py-qt / sip, and python2.7</li>

	<li>mm requested an -exp run to test the last GPLv2 version of
	  gcc 4.2.2</li>

	<li>pav completed open-motif and mono -exp runs for respective
	  submitters</li>

	<li>ports/127214, -exp run to make copy/paste of portaudit user
	  friendly</li>

	<li>ports/144482, -exp run to fix package depends</li>

	<li>ports/152102, -exp run to make dirrmtry more friendly</li>

	<li>ports/152268, -exp run to update binutils</li>

	<li>ports/153539, -exp run to allow checking STRIP when
	  WITH_DEBUG is defined</li>

	<li>ports/153547, -exp run to remove NO_SIZE</li>

	<li>ports/153625, -exp run to pass CPPFLAGS to
	  MAKE/CONFIGURE_ENV</li>

	<li>ports/153634, -exp run to remove redundant PKGNAMEPREFIX for
	  localised ports</li>

	<li>ports/154121, -exp run to use --title for new libdialog</li>

	<li>ports/154122, -exp run to update libtool to 2.4</li>

	<li>ports/154186, -exp to allow using linux 2.4 emulation on &os;
	  8+</li>

	<li>ports/154390, -exp run to make fetching output copy/paste
	  friendly</li>

	<li>ports/154653, -exp run to remove superfluous slash</li>

	<li>ports/154799, -exp run to update glib + gtk</li>

	<li>ports/154994, -exp run for MASTER_SITE_PERL_CPAN
	  enhancements</li>

	<li>ports/155502, -exp run to remove sanity check for
	  X_WINDOW_SYSTEM</li>

	<li>ports/155504, -exp run to remove USE_XPM from b.p.m.</li>

	<li>ports/155505, -exp run to update GNU m4</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Looking for help fixing <a
	  href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnCurrent">ports
	  broken on CURRENT</a>.</task>

      <task>Looking for help with  <a
	  href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnTier2Architectures">
	  Tier-2 architectures</a>.</task>

      <task>Most ports PRs are assigned, we now need to focus on testing,
	committing and closing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>GEOM-based ataraid(4) replacement &mdash; geom_raid.</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>M. Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>A new RAID GEOM class (geom_raid) was added to &os; 9-CURRENT, to
	replace ataraid(4) in supporting various BIOS-based software RAIDs.
	Unlike ataraid(4) this implementation does not depend on legacy
	ata(4) subsystem and can be used with any disk drivers, including
	new CAM-based ones (ahci(4), siis(4), mvs(4) and ata(4) with
	`options ATA_CAM`).  To make code more readable and extensible, this
	implementation follows modular design, including a core part and two
	sets of modules, implementing support for different metadata
	formats and RAID levels.</p>

      <p>Support for such popular metadata formats is now implemented:
	Intel, JMicron, NVIDIA, Promise (also used by AMD/ATI) and
	SiliconImage.</p>

      <p>Such RAID levels are now supported: RAID0, RAID1, RAID1E,
	RAID10, SINGLE, CONCAT.</p>

      <p>For any all of these RAID levels and metadata formats this class
	supports full cycle of volume operations: reading, writing,
	creation, deletion, disk removal and insertion, rebuilding, dirty
	shutdown detection and resynchronization, bad sector recovery,
	faulty disks tracking, hot-spare disks.  For Intel and Promise
	formats there is support for multiple volumes per disk set.</p>

      <p>See the graid(8) manual page for additional details.</p>

      <p>Sponsored by: Cisco Systems, Inc. and iXsystems, Inc.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Implement metadata modules for other formats (DDF, Highpoint,
	VIA, ...).</task>

      <task>Implement transformation modules for other RAID levels
	(RAID5, ...).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>www/apache22 default</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Philip</given>
	  <common>Gollucci</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgollucci@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Olli</given>
	  <common>Hauer</common>
	</name>
	<email>ohauer@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Apache</given>
	  <common>Apache</common>
	</name>
	<email>apache@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~pgollucci/FreeBSD/prs/maintainers.html#apache">
      prs</url>

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/cgi/query-pr.cgi?pr=ports/147009">-exp
      request</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Apache" />

      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-apache/2011-March/002174.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>95% done, pending final -exp run, and pulling the switch.  HEADS-UP
	announcement already sent to relevant lists.  This will be for
	8.3/9.0.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/EC2</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Colin</given>
	  <common>Percival</common>
	</name>
	<email>cperciva@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.daemonology.net/freebsd-on-ec2/">&os;/EC2
	status page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; is now able to run on t1.micro and cc1.4xlarge instances in
	the Amazon EC2 cloud. &os; 8.2-RELEASE is stable subject to the
	limitations of the instance type (e.g., running ZFS on a micro
	instance with only 600 MB of RAM doesn't work very well), but &os;
	9.0 has significant stability issues.</p>

      <p>A list of available &os; AMIs (EC2 machine images) appears on
	the &os;/EC2 status page.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Bring &os; to a wider range of EC2 instance types.</task>

      <task>Completely rework the locking in head/sys/i386/xen/pmap.c to
	eliminate races and make 9.0-CURRENT stable under
	paravirtualization.</task>

      <task>Track down several possibly-related problems with scheduling
	and timekeeping.</task>

      <task>Fix other issues shown on the &os;/EC2 status page.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>&os; Haskell Ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor J&aacute;nos</given>
	  <common>P&Aacute;LI</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ashish</given>
	  <common>SHUKLA</common>
	</name>
	<email>ashish@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Giuseppe</given>
	  <common>Pilichi</common>
	</name>
	<email>jacula@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Haskell">&os; Haskell Wiki
	Page</url>

      <url href="https://github.com/freebsd-haskell/freebsd-haskell">&os;
	Haskell ports repository</url>

      <url href="http://haskell.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-haskell/">
	&os; Haskell mailing list</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We are proud to announce that the &os; Haskell team has updated
	GHC to 7.0.3, and all other existing Haskell ports to the latest
	stable versions, as well as added new ports.  The total number of
	Haskell ports in the &os; repository is now more than 200.  These
	ports are still waiting to be committed.  At the moment, they are
	available from <a
	  href="https://github.com/freebsd-haskell/freebsd-haskell">&os;
	  Haskell ports repository</a>.  Any users who would like to get
	early access to them, please refer to the <a
	  href="http://www.haskell.org/pipermail/freebsd-haskell/2011-April/000278.html">
	  &os; Haskell ports Call For Testing</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Create a metaport for Haskell Platform.</task>
      <task>Create a port for Happstack.</task>
      <task>Create a port for gitit.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Journaled Soft Updates</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jeff</given>
	  <common>Roberson</common>
	</name>
	<email>jeff@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kirk</given>
	  <common>McKusick</common>
	</name>
	<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>All known problems with journaled soft updates have been fixed
	in head.  If you have any problems while running with journaled soft
	updates, please report them to us.</p>

      <p>We have addressed several performance issues that have been
	brought to our attention.  If you have any performance problems
	while running with journaled soft updates, please report them to
	us.</p>

      <p>We have improved the recovery of resources when running with
	soft updates on small (root) filesystems.  We anticipate being able
	to use soft updates for root filesystems in the 9.0 system.</p>

      <p>We expect to have journaled soft updates default to enabled in
	the 9.0 system.  We encourage users of -CURRENT to enable journaled
	soft updates to help shake out any remaining performance problems
	and bugs.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>MIPS/Octeon support and bootinfo</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Andrew</given>
	  <common>Duane</common>
	</name>
	<email>aduane@juniper.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Working on improving support for Octeon processors and
	integrating with other MIPS processor families.  Currently working
	on support for the standard MIPS bootinfo structure as a boot API
	(to supplement/replace the Caviums-specific structure).  Other
	Octeon improvements including cleanups to CF and USB drivers to
	come.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; German Documentation Project Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Johann</given>
	  <common>Kois</common>
	</name>
	<email>jkois@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benedict</given>
	  <common>Reuschling</common>
	</name>
	<email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://doc.bsdgroup.de">Website of the &os; German
	Documentation Project.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Benedict Reuschling contributed the translation of the new
	handbook section about HAST, while Benjamin Lukas was working on
	the first translation of the firewall chapter of the handbook.  The
	committers to the German Documentation Project were busy with
	keeping the existing German documentation up-to-date.  The website
	translations were also kept in sync with the ones on &os;.org.</p>

      <p>We tried to re-activate committers who did not contribute for
	some time but most of them are currently unable to free up enough
	time.  We hope to gain fresh contributor blood as we are getting
	occasional reports about bugs and grammar in the german
	translation.</p>
     </body>

    <help>
      <task>Submit grammar, spelling or other errors you find in the
	german documents and the website.</task>

      <task>Translate more articles and other open handbook
	sections.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="docs">
    <title>The &os; Japanese Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hiroki</given>
	  <common>Sato</common>
	</name>
	<email>hrs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ryusuke</given>
	  <common>Suzuki</common>
	</name>
	<email>ryusuke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ja/">Japanese &os; Web
	Pages</url>

      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/doc-jp/">The &os; Japanese
	Documentation Project Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The www/ja and doc/ja_JP.eucJP/books/handbook have constantly
	been updated.  During this period, translation of the handbook
	installation page was finished.  The following chapters are now
	synchronized with the English version:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>introduction</li>
	<li>install</li>
	<li>ports</li>
	<li>x11</li>
	<li>desktop</li>
	<li>multimedia</li>
	<li>mirrors</li>
	<li>pgpkeys</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Merging translation results from the www tree on a separate
	repository for the translation work into the main tree was also
	finished.  Since outdated and/or non-translated documents also
	remain in both doc/ja_JP.eucJP and www, further translation work is
	still needed.  Some progress has been made in the Porter's Handbook
	as well in this period.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='gsoc'>
    <title>Extfs Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zheng</given>
	  <common>Liu</common>
	</name>
	<email>lz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://p4web.FreeBSD.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/soc2010/extfs/src/sys/fs/&amp;c=rFV@//depot/projects/soc2010/extfs/src/sys/fs/ext2fs/?ac=83">
	ext2fs</url>

      <url href="http://p4web.FreeBSD.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/soc2010/ext4fs/src/sys/fs/&amp;c=cc4@//depot/projects/soc2010/ext4fs/src/sys/fs/ext4fs/?ac=83">
	ext4fs</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>I have implemented a reallocblks in ext2fs, like in ffs,
	and submitted a patch file to mailing list.  Next I will try to
	implement htree directory index in ext2fs.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Linux emulation ports</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Leidinger</common>
	</name>
	<email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Emulation</given>
	  <common>Mailinglist</common>
	</name>
	<email>freebsd-emulation@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.leidinger.net/blog/2011/02/25/howto-creating-your-own-updated-linux-rpm-for-the-freebsd-linuxulator/">
	HOWTO: cre­at­ing your own updated linux RPM for the &os;
	linuxulator</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Old linux_base ports (all which are not used by default in some
	release) where marked as deprecated with a short expiration
	period.  The reason is that all those ports are long past their end
	of life and do not receive security updates anymore.  Unfortunately
	this is also true for the linux_base ports which are still used by
	default in the releases, but no replacement is available ATM (see
	open tasks).</p>

      <p>The linux-f10-pango port was updated to a more recent version
	whoch does not have a security problem by generating a linux-RPM in
	a VM with "&os;" as the vendor (see the links section for a
	HOWTO).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Decide which RPM based linux distribution+version to track
	next for the linux_base ports, create ports for it and test for
	compatibility with our kernel code.</task>
    </help>
  </project>
</report>
