<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for
Status Report//EN" "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD: www/en/news/status/report-2010-07-2010-09.xml,v 1.4 2010/10/24 22:03:09 danger Exp $ -->

<report>
  <date>
    <month>July-September</month>

    <year>2010</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>This report covers &os;-related projects between July and
      September 2010.  It is the third of the four reports planned for
      2010. During this period, we were victims of one
      of the biggest BSD events of the year &mdash; EuroBSDCon.
      We hope that the ones of you who have been able to attend it
      have enjoyed your stay.  Another good news is that work on the
      new minor versions of &os;, 7.4 and 8.2, is progressing well.</p>

    <p>This report, with 54 entries, is the longest report in
      the whole history and shows a good condition of the &os;
      community.</p>

    <p>Thanks to all the reporters for the excellent work! We hope you
      enjoy reading it.</p>

    <p>Please note that the deadline for submissions covering the period
      between October and December 2010 is January 15th, 2011.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>soc</name>

    <description>Google Summer of Code</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>team</name>

    <description>&os; Team Reports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network Infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>docs</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland Programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Atheros AR913x SoC support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Adrian</given>
	  <common>Chadd</common>
	</name>
	<email>adrian@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/AdrianChadd/AtherosStuff">(The
	Atheros hackery will eventually live here)</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/AdrianChadd/AtherosHalStuff">
	Atheros wireless device work</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os;-CURRENT runs on the AR9132 SoC.  Minor platform-specific
	tweaks are needed to use it on a given piece of hardware (eg.,
	where in flash the Ethernet MAC address is stored.) The AR910x
	wireless MAC/PHY is supported.  The only available test platform
	uses a 2.4GHz radio; 5GHz 11a mode has not been tested.  As with
	other atheros chipset support in &os;, 11n support is not yet
	finished.  The current development platform is the TP-Link
	TP-WN1043ND 802.11n wireless bridge/router.  It is currently being
	successfully used as a 11bg access point.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>USB support is currently not functional.</task>

      <task>There is currently no support for the realtek gigabit
	switch/PHY chip.  This is being worked on.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Binary Package Patch Infrastructure &mdash; pkg_patch</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ivan</given>
	  <common>Voras</common>
	</name>
	<email>ivoras@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/IvanVoras/pkg_patch" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pkg_patch is a tool meant to be used with the rest of the
	pkg_* utilities whose job is to create and apply binary patches
	to &os; package archives.  The SoC project was successfully
	completed but there are some open issues about the integration of
	the tool in the &os; system.  Some changes are necessary to the
	port/patch infrastructure to support the "update" mode instead of
	"remove+add".</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Solve pending issues about the ports install/upgrade
	workflow, probably within the <a
	   href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Pkg_install2_specs">pkg_install2</a>
	effort.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>ExtFS Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Zheng</given>
	  <common>Liu</common>
	</name>
	<email>gnehzuil@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/SOC2010ZhengLiu">project
	wiki</url>

      <url href="http://p4web.FreeBSD.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/soc2010/extfs/src/sys/fs/&amp;c=rFV@//depot/projects/soc2010/extfs/src/sys/fs/ext2fs/?ac=83">
	pre-allocation</url>

      <url href="http://p4web.FreeBSD.org/@md=d&amp;cd=//depot/projects/soc2010/ext4fs/src/sys/fs/&amp;c=cc4@//depot/projects/soc2010/ext4fs/src/sys/fs/ext4fs/?ac=83">
	ext4 read-only mode</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This project has two goals: pre-allocation algorithm for
	ext2fs and ext4 read-only mode.  The aim of pre-allocation
	algorithm is to implement a reservation window mechanism.
	This mechanism has been implemented and I have submitted a patch
	file to mailing list (fs@FreeBSD.org).  The aim of ext4 read-only
	mode is to make it possible to read ext4 file systems in read-only
	mode when the disk is formatted with default features.  Until now it
	can read data from ext4 file systems with default features in
	read-only mode.  I have submitted a patch to mailing list
	(fs@FreeBSD.org) and am building a new kernel module for it, which
	is called ext4fs.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More testing of pre-allocation algorithm.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BSD# Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Romain</given>
	  <common>Tarti&egrave;re</common>
	</name>
	<email>romain@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://code.google.com/p/bsd-sharp/">The BSD# project
	on Google-code</url>

      <url href="http://www.mono-project.org/">Mono (Open source .Net
	Development Framework)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The BSD# Project is devoted to porting the Mono .NET framework
	and applications to the &os; operating system.</p>

      <p>Mono 2.8 has been released a few days ago and is already
	available in the BSD# repository.  The update breaks a few ports
	so the lang/mono update in the &os; ports tree will be delayed
	until those programs are fixed for a smoother update
	experience.</p>

      <p>Work is in progress to include some long-awaited ports such as
	deskutils/gnome-do but they require a lot of testing and hacking
	because they have clearly been designed to run on GNU/Linux and
	portability has never been a priority (which is quite amusing if
	you consider portability is the main reason to be for mono).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>If you have some time, test mono ports and send
	feedback.</task>

      <task>If you have more time, join the BSD# Team! There are many
	ways to help out!</task>

      <task>Currently low priority, some mono hackers who do not use
	&os; would be interested in a debug live-image of &os; to help us
	diagnose and fix bugs more effectively.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Clang Replacing GCC in the Base System</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Schouten</common>
	</name>
	<email>ed@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Roman</given>
	  <common>Divacky</common>
	</name>
	<email>rdivacky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Brooks</given>
	  <common>Davis</common>
	</name>
	<email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel</given>
	  <common>Worach</common>
	</name>
	<email>pawel.worach@gmail.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dimitry</given>
	  <common>Andric</common>
	</name>
	<email>dim@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BuildingFreeBSDWithClang" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We recently imported the 2.8 release of Clang into CURRENT.  This
	release contains many new features and improvements.  The
	integrated assembler ships with this version, but it is not ready
	for general use yet.</p>

      <p>Since r212979, all necessary changes have been committed to be
	able to build world with Clang, at least on amd64 and i386.  It
	can also be installed and run, and we are now starting the
	process of shaking out the inevitable bugs.</p>

      <p>Because LLVM and Clang are still being improved continuously,
	we want to import new versions regularly, approximately every two
	months, to gain access to new features, bug fixes and performance
	improvements.</p>

      <p>There is also an effort on behalf of the ports people, to make
	as many ports as possible compile and run properly with Clang.
	Most of the time, this means fixing the incorrect assumption that
	gcc is the only existing compiler, but sometimes more complicated
	issues pop up.  Help in this area is greatly appreciated.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Importing new Clang snapshots fairly regularly
	(approximately bi-monthly).</task>

      <task>Seeing if Clang can be used to build world for ARM
	(volunteers and ARM experts wanted).</task>

      <task>Fixing as many ports as possible to build with Clang.</task>

      <task>Running periodical ports exp builds with Clang (on amd64
	and i386), for example once a month.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Updating base tools to accommodate ports
      requirements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gordon</given>
	  <common>Tetlow</common>
	</name>
	<email>gordon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of the project is to allow easier extension of base
	system tools by the ports system.  Ideally, no files in /etc
	should need to be modified by a port installation.</p>

      <p>The man toolset was recently reimplemented as a BSDL version
	instead of the old GPL version.  It is also a single shell script
	instead of multiple C programs.  Ports can extend the man
	functionality by dropping files into
	/usr/local/etc/man.d/portname.conf.</p>

      <p>Next up on the list is to finish the implementation for
	newsyslog thereby allowing ports that need logs rotated to take
	advantage of that tool.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/mips on Octeon</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Juli</given>
	  <common>Mallett</common>
	</name>
	<email>jmallett@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/FreeBSD/mips/Octeon" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>All Octeon development is now ongoing in 9.0-CURRENT and most
	Octeon-specific and general MIPS changes from the old Octeon
	branch have been checked in.  The Simple Executive from the Cavium
	Octeon SDK has been checked into Subversion and most of the
	Octeon port has been updated to use it where appropriate,
	including moving to a port of the Linux Ethernet driver, octe.
	SMP support is stable on 2-core systems and has seen some testing
	on systems with up to 16 cores.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Some PCI devices still do not seem to work
	completely.</task>

      <task>Host-mode USB support is incomplete and needs further
	testing and debugging.</task>

      <task>Work on an ATA-based Compact Flash driver for boards that
	support DMA has begun.</task>

      <task>A GPIO driver should be trivial using the Simple
	Executive.</task>

      <task>Performance in the Linux-derived octe Ethernet driver could
	be improved.  Support for some switch chipsets that are commonly
	present in Octeon-based equipment is in progress.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Kernel event timers infrastructure</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Motin</common>
	</name>
	<email>mav@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201010DevSummit?action=AttachFile&amp;do=get&amp;target=timers.pdf">
	Slides from DevSummit in Karlsruhe.</url>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~mav/tm6292_idle.patch">
	Proof of concept (dirty) patch, removing some timer events.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work on new event timers infrastructure continues.  In CURRENT
	amd64, arm (Marvell), i386, mips, pc98, powerpc, sparc64, sun4v
	architectures were refactored to use new timers API.</p>

      <p>New machine-independent timers management code was written.  It
	can utilize both legacy periodic and new one-shot timer
	operation modes.</p>

      <p>Using one-shot mode allows to significantly reduce the number of
	timer interrupts and respectively increase CPU sleep time
	during idle periods.  Timer interrupts on idle CPUs are now
	generated only when they are needed to handle registered
	time-based events.  Busy CPUs unluckily still receive the full
	interrupt rate for purposes of resource accounting, scheduling
	and timekeeping.</p>

      <p>With some additional tuning it is now possible to have an
	8-core system, receiving only about 100 interrupts per second
	and respectively have CPU idle periods up to 100ms.  This
	allows to effectively use any supported CPU idle states
	(C-states), that reduces power consumption and increases effect
	of the Intel TurboBoost technology.</p>

      <p>New manual pages were written to document this functionality:
	eventtimers(7), attimer(4), atrtc(4), hpet(4).</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Troubleshoot possible hardware issues.</task>

      <task>Refactor remaining architectures (arm, ia64, XEN
	PV).</task>

      <task>Do some optimizations in different subsystems to reduce
	number of time-based events.  Extend callout API with terms of
	precision, allowing to group close events.</task>

      <task>Make schedulers tickless, or at least less depending on
	time events to make skipping timer interrupts possible when CPUs
	are busy.</task>

      <task>Merge code into 8-STABLE when it is considered ready.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports distfile and WWW checker</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Emanuel</given>
	  <common>Haupt</common>
	</name>
	<email>ehaupt@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~ehaupt/distilator/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Given the current status of fenner's Distfiles Survey, a new
	distfile checker was written in order to have an overview for the
	state of each distfile in the ports tree.  The distfile checker is
	also able to verify WWW entries in pkg-descr files.  This is an
	attempt to weed out broken MASTER_SITES and outdated WWW
	entries.</p>

      <p>The current version uses a MySQL database backend and is able
	to verify 432512 distfiles (30 concurrent threads) within 24
	hours.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
   <task>provide JavaScript to sort/filter/search tables.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Userland DTrace</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/DTrace/userland" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Userland DTrace support was a &os; Foundation sponsored
	project that was developed during this summer.  The project aimed
	to bring the userland DTracing functionality to &os; as it is
	available on OpenSolaris.  &os; now supports the pid provider and
	the usdt probes.  plockstat is available with a separate patch.
	Dtruss, a DTrace script that works similarly to ktrace, but with
	other advantages was imported into &os;.  The mysql-server and
	postgresql-server ports also have DTrace support.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os; on the Playstation 3</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Nathan</given>
	  <common>Whitehorn</common>
	</name>
	<email>nwhitehorn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Peter</given>
	  <common>Grehan</common>
	</name>
	<email>grehan@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="svn://svn.FreeBSD.org/base/user/nwhitehorn/ps3">PS3
	SVN Repository</url>

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~nwhitehorn/ps3">Pre-built
	PS3 kernel</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os;/powerpc64 now boots multi-user SMP and is self-hosting on
	the Playstation 3.  Booting requires a PS3 console with the
	OtherOS capability (fat model console with firmware &lt; 3.21).
	The only supported hardware at present is the Ethernet
	controller.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>USB and SATA support.</task>

      <task>Boot loader enhancements to allow user input at the loader
	prompt.</task>

      <task>Support for the Cell SPU units.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Bringing up ARM to &os; Tree</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@bsdimp.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mohammed</given>
	  <common>Farrag</common>
	</name>
	<email>mfarrag@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>We are still in the beginning of the project since we started
	it after the summer of code.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Reading ARM structure.</task>
      <task>Reading MicroC OS.</task>
      <task>Using Qemu to emulate the work.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr-secretary@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Port</given>
	  <common>Management Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>portmgr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ports/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/" />

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/portmgr/index.html" />

      <url href="http://blogs.FreeBSDish.org/portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.twitter.com/freebsd_portmgr/" />

      <url href="http://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=135441496471197" />

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The ports tree count now exceeds 22,000.  With the assistance
	of many people, especially Philip Gollucci, the open PR count is
	below 1000 for the first time in quite a while.  This is very
	encouraging progress.</p>

      <p>Since the last report, we added five new committers, and took
	in two commit bits for safe keeping.</p>

      <p>With onsite assistance from jhb@, gnn@, skreuzer@, and
	pgollucci@, we now have 11 new servers at NYI.  The machines still
	need testing for stability and will soon be assigned for package
	building.</p>

      <p>The Ports Management team have been running -exp runs on an
	ongoing basis, verifying how base system updates may affect the
	ports tree, as well as providing QA runs for major ports updates.
	Of note, -exp runs were done for:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>des: test libfetch</li>
	<li>gabor: tests for BSD iconv and grep</li>
	<li>mezz: switch www/neon28 to www/neon29</li>
	<li>beat: update www/libxul</li>
	<li>johans: update devel/bison and devel/m4</li>
	<li>dinoex: update graphics/tiff</li>
	<li>jpaetzel: update devel/popt</li>
	<li>ade: multiple runs autotools upgrade</li>
	<li>gerald: setting USE_GCC=4.5 as default</li>
	<li>ashish: changes to Mk/bsd.license.mk</li>
	<li>kwm: test of clang in CURRENT</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Looking for help fixing <a
	  href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnCurrent">ports
	  broken on CURRENT</a>.</task>

      <task>Looking for help with  <a
	  href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PortsBrokenOnTier2Architectures">
	  Tier-2 architectures</a>.</task>

      <task>Most ports PRs are assigned, we now need to focus on
	testing, committing and closing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>&os; Developer Summit, Karlsruhe</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>P&aacute;li</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201010DevSummit" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We were happy to have more than 40 &os; developers and guests
	attending the &os; Developer Summit prior to EuroBSDCon&nbsp;2010
	in Karlsruhe, Germany.  This workshop-style event was hosted at
	Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, and included prepared
	presentations in the morning, as well as group hacking and
	discussion sections in the afternoon.  We had various talks on
	several topics, covering the USB subsystem, state of the
	toolchain, the &os; documentation, NanoBSD improvements, &os;
	port of PF, jails, Virtual Private Systems, cooperation with the
	PC-BSD Project, FreeNAS, the new event timers subsystems,
	bugbusting discussions and Ports Tinderbox presentations, and
	many of this year's and last year's Google Summer of Code
	projects.  Photos, videos, and slides for most of the talks are
	available on the wiki page.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>USB stack</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hans Petter</given>
	  <common>Selasky</common>
	</name>
	<email>hselasky@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/viewvc/base/head/sys/dev/usb/controller/xhci.c?view=log">
	XHCI driver</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the last two months the USB stack in &os;-CURRENT has
	been enhanced to support USB 3.0 and the XHCI USB 3.0 chipset
	from Intel.  The XHCI chip will eventually replace the EHCI, OHCI
	and UHCI chips.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>&os; testers which have access to USB 3.0 hardware are
	wanted.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/mips Ralink RT3052F/Broadcom BCM5354</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Aleksandr</given>
	  <common>Rybalko</common>
	</name>
	<email>ray@dlink.ua</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.ddteam.net/wiki.cgi?page=DIR-320+FreeBSD">
	Description</url>

      <url href="http://my.ddteam.net/hg/BASE/">Mercurial
	repository</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os;/mips has been ported to D-Link DAP-1350, wireless
	AP/router based on Ralink RT3052F SoC.</p>

      <p>Drivers status:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>rt2860: Ralink RT2860 802.11n - Worked, but RT3022 2.4G
	2T2R radio tuning required.</li>

	<li>rt: Ralink RT3052F onChip Ethernet MAC - DONE</li>

	<li>rtsw: OnChip Ethernet switch - not done (initialized by
	UBoot)</li>

	<li>usb-otg: DWC like USB OTG controller - Worked</li>

	<li>gpio: RT3052F onChip GPIO - Worked (LEDs, Buttons)</li>

	<li>cfi: CFI NOR Flash - Worked</li>
      </ul>

      <p>&os;/mips D-Link DIR-320 project(BCM5354 SoC).</p>

      <p>New profile openvpn-router available for testing.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Debug/Fix USB OTG driver (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>Debug/Fix 802.11n driver (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>Write rtswitch driver (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>Implement Timer unit driver (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>Implement Hardware NAT/PPPoE/VLAN offload (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>Implement I2C/I2S/PCM/SPI drivers (RT3052F).</task>

      <task>switch configuration utility (BCM5354).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>Web feeds for UPDATING files</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Kojevnikov</common>
	</name>
	<email>alexander@kojevnikov.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://updating.versia.com/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p><a href="http://updating.versia.com/">updating.versia.com</a>
      features web feeds for UPDATING files from ports, head, stable/7
      and stable/8.  These feeds provide an easy way to track important
      changes in the ports tree and the base system.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>&os;/sparc64</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Marius</given>
	  <common>Strobl</common>
	</name>
	<email>marius@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Apart from the constant bug fixing and adaptions to
	machine-independent changes that pretty much always take place,
	not much has happened in the area of sparc64 since the last
	status report.  The only noteworthy exception are some performance
	optimizations which take advantage of features of Fujitsu SPARC64
	CPUs.  These were a bit too risky for putting them in shortly
	before &os; 8.1-RELEASE but will be part of 7.4-RELEASE and
	8.2-RELEASE now that they have received the necessary testing.</p>

      <p>Part of reasons why not much has happened in this spot was some
	lack of time on my side but also due to nobody showing up with a
	not yet supported sun4u machine lately and me delving in the
	network land instead, which yielded some things to report about
	in the next status report.  On the other hand I recently got a
	hold of a Sun Fire 3800, so these and other models from the same
	family likely will be supported by &os; at some point in the
	future.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>The &os; German Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Johann</given>
	  <common>Kois</common>
	</name>
	<email>jkois@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benedict</given>
	  <common>Reuschling</common>
	</name>
	<email>bcr@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://doc.bsdgroup.de">Website of the &os; German
	Documentation Project.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The committers to the German Documentation Project were mostly
	trying to keep the documents and the website translations in sync
	with the ones on &os;.org.  Fabian Ruch was helpful in catching up
	with the changes to the Porters Handbook.  Benedict translated the
	Solid State article into German because this is becoming a good
	addition to traditional hard drive storage.</p>

      <p>We tried to re-activate committers who did not contribute for
	some time but most of them are currently unable to free up enough
	time.  We hope to gain fresh contributor blood as we are getting
	occasional reports about bugs and grammar in the German
	translation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Submit grammar, spelling or other errors you find in the
	German documents and the website.</task>

      <task>Translate more articles and other open handbook
	sections.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='docs'>
    <title>mandoc/mdocml &mdash; groff replacement for rendering manpages
      in &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ulrich</given>
	  <common>Sp&ouml;rlein</common>
	</name>
	<email>uqs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://mdocml.bsd.lv/">Kristaps' mdocml project page.</url>
      <url href="https://www.spoerlein.net/cgit/cgit.cgi/freebsd.work/log/?h=mdocml">
	Git branch for &os; mdocml related work.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Kristaps' groff-replacement (for rendering manpages, only) is
	already available in NetBSD and OpenBSD, and used to render the base
	system manpages for the latter. This project aims to do similar
	things for &os;.</p>

      <p>mandoc(1) is more strict in what it accepts as input and is still
	lacking some features that are used by some selected few manpages.</p>

      <p>Getting manpage fixes accepted by upstream vendors has been
	challenging. Waiting for them to round-trip back into &os; will take
	even longer. Future work will therefore result in direct commits to
	our contrib/ and gnu/ repository areas, in the hope this will not
	impact future vendor imports too much.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Finish the Big Manpage Cleanup of 2010.</task>

      <task>Write a textproc/groff port for the latest groff version.</task>

      <task>Import mandoc(1), switch to catpages for base.</task>

      <task>Supply necessary ports infrastructure to opt-in to mandoc(1).
      </task>

      <task>Discuss future of groff(1) in base wrt. share/doc.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>pkg_upgrade (sysutils/bsdadminscripts)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dominic</given>
	  <common>Fandrey</common>
	</name>
	<email>kamikaze@bsdforen.de</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://sf.net/projects/bsdadminscripts">
	bsdadminscripts SF project</url>

      <url href="http://sf.net/projects/bsdadminscripts/files/publications/2010-10-eurobsdcon/">
	  EuroBSDCon2010 slides and paper</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pkg_upgrade was (to my knowledge) the first binary packages
	only update tool for the &os; ports.  Using it does not require a
	copy of the ports tree.</p>

      <p>Currently the tool is in the final stages of a recode, that
	will greatly improve support for sharing packages over NFS or
	nullfs mounts (e.g.  for distributing packages into jails) and
	also offers improved dependency tracking and performance, more in
	line with how pointyhat and Tinderbox build packages.</p>

      <p>I recently had the opportunity to present my work at the
	EuroBSDCon2010.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete session code.</task>

      <task>Add INDEX generator script that harvests information
	directly from packages and hence is always accurate.</task>

      <task>Testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Registration of optional kernel subsystems via
      sysctl</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ilya</given>
	  <common>Bakulin</common>
	</name>
	<email>kibab@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://socghop.appspot.com/gsoc/student_project/show/google/gsoc2010/freebsd/t127230759508">
	Project description on GSoC website</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201010DevSummit?action=AttachFile&amp;do=view&amp;target=kibab_sysctlreg.pdf">
	Slides (from &os; DevSummit in Karlsruhe)</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>All work is now in Perforce.  Rich set of features is added to
	the kernel, userland tools and libc modifications are ready,
	documentation is ready.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Documentation review.</task>

      <task>Presentation of feature set on the various mailing
	lists.</task>

      <task>Committing to CURRENT, possibly merging to stable branches
	(changes do not break ABI/KBI).</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Kernel-level stacked cryptographic filesystem &mdash;
      PEFS</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gleb</given>
	  <common>Kurtsou</common>
	</name>
	<email>gk@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/PEFS" />

      <url href="http://github.com/glk/pefs" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>PEFS is a kernel level stacked cryptographic filesystem, i.e.
	it stacks on top of existing mounted filesystems.  AES and
	Camellia algorithms in XTS mode are supported.  The project has
	matured since Summer of Code 2009, most important improvements
	for last few months include: switch to use XTS encryption mode,
	implementation of sparse file support, fixing rename bugs
	including race and livelock conditions, addition of ext2 support.
	PEFS suite contains pam module facilitating user authentication
	with filesystem key and adding keys to mounted filesystem on
	login.  PEFS passes fsx, pjdfstest, blogbench and dbench tests
	running on top of UFS and ZFS.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='soc'>
    <title>Packet Capturing Stack &mdash; ringmap</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alexander</given>
	  <common>Fiveg</common>
	</name>
	<email>afiveg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://code.google.com/p/ringmap/">Project-Page on
	Google Code</url>

      <url href="http://ringmap.googlecode.com/files/ringmap_slides.pdf">
	Slides</url>

      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/AlexandreFiveg">Wiki</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Ringmap is a complete &os; packet capturing stack specialized for
	very high-speed networks.  The goal of this project is to develop the
	software for efficient packet capturing and integrate it with the
	generic network drivers and libpcap.</p>

      <p>Current Status:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>integrated with <b>lem</b> driver.  Intel network controllers:
	  8254X are supported.</li>

	<li>packet filtering using BPF in both kernel and user-space</li>

	<li>partly integrated with <b>ixgbe</b> driver for 10Gb capturing</li>
      </ul>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Support for hardware timestamping.</task>

      <task>Writing packets to the disc from within the kernel.</task>

      <task>Multiqueue support.</task>

      <task>Extending the "ringmap" for packet transmission.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat="team">
    <title>The &os; Foundation Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Deb</given>
	  <common>Goodkin</common>
	</name>
	<email>deb@FreeBSDFoundation.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We were proud to be a sponsor for MeetBSD 2010 Poland and
	KyivBSD 2010 in Kiev, Ukraine.  We also committed to sponsoring
	BSDDay Argentina 2010, MeetBSD California 2010, and NYBSDCon 2010
	all in November.  The Foundation was also represented at MeetBSD
	Poland and Ohio LinuxFest.</p>

      <p>Completed the Foundation funded projects: &os; Jail Based
	Virtualization by Bjoern Zeeb and DTrace Userland by Rui
	Paulo.</p>

      <p>We kicked off a new project by Swinburne University called
	Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms for &os;.</p>

      <p>We continued our work on infrastructure projects to beef up
	hardware for package-building, network-testing, etc.  This
	includes purchasing equipment as well as managing equipment
	donations.</p>

      <p>We are three quarters of the way through the year and we have
	raised around $160,000 towards our goal of $350,000.  Find out how
	to make a donation at
	<a href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/">
	  http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/donate/</a>
      </p>

      <p>Stop by and visit with us at MeetBSD California (Nov 5-6),
	LISA (Nov 10-11), and NYCBSDCon (Nov 12-14).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Chromium web browser</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ruben</given>
	</name>
	<email>chromium@hybridsource.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://chromium.hybridsource.org">Main chromium
	site</url>

      <url href="http://chromium.hybridsource.org/issues">Porting
	summary</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Chromium is a Webkit-based web browser that is largely BSD
	licensed and was recently committed to ports.  It has been working
	well on &os; and supports new features like HTML 5 video.  Newer
	builds use the Clang compiler, Clang first compiled a non-debug
	build of Chromium, a very large C++ project, on &os;.  This
	porting effort employs a new hybrid-source model: portions of the
	latest &os; patches are kept closed for a limited time and new
	builds are made available only to paying subscribers, while older
	builds are eventually spun off to ports.  Further work remains to
	port all of Chromium to &os;, I am now porting the task manager
	to use &os;'s libkvm and the ALSA audio backend needs to be
	ported to OSS.  There are other issues listed at the porting
	summary, contact me if you would like to pitch in.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSD-Day@2010</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>P&aacute;li</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BSDDay_2010" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The purpose of this one-day event is to gather Central
	European developers of today's open-source BSD systems to
	popularize their work and their organizations, and to meet each
	other in the real life.  We would also like to motivate potential
	future developers and users, especially undergraduate university
	students to work with BSD systems.  This year's BSD-Day will be
	held in Budapest, Hungary at E&ouml;tv&ouml;s Lor&aacute;nd
	University, Faculty of Informatics on November 20, 2010.
	Everybody is welcome!</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Five New TCP Congestion Control Algorithms for &os;</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>David</given>
	  <common>Hayes</common>
	</name>
	<email>dahayes@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Lawrence</given>
	  <common>Stewart</common>
	</name>
	<email>lstewart@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Grenville</given>
	  <common>Armitage</common>
	</name>
	<email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Rui</given>
	  <common>Paulo</common>
	</name>
	<email>rpaulo@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/freebsd/5cc/" />

      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/projects.shtml" />

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/5cc/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work has commenced on a newly funded &os; Foundation project
	to bring six modular TCP congestion control (CC) algorithm
	implementations (the existing NewReno and five new algorithms:
	HTCP, CUBIC, Vegas, HD and CHD) to the &os; kernel.  See the
	CAIA 5cc and NewTCP websites for more details on the
	algorithms.</p>

      <p>To support the project's primary deliverable, we will also
	be incorporating the CAIA modular CC and Khelp frameworks into
	the &os; kernel, along with the Enhanced Round Trip Time Khelp
	module.</p>

      <p>The project will make a sizable, state-of-the-art
	contribution to &os; and in certain areas, add completely novel
	work unavailable in any other operating system known to us.</p>

      <p>We anticipate a number of benefits, including vastly
	improved researcher friendliness, reduced work for TCP oriented
	vendors of &os;-based appliances, and greater choice for system
	administrators who operate &os; systems in atypical network
	scenarios.</p>

      <p>Keep an eye on the freebsd-net@FreeBSD.org mailing list for
	project related announcements.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Enhancing the &os; TCP Implementation</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Lawrence</given>
	  <common>Stewart</common>
	</name>
	<email>lstewart@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/freebsd/etcp09/" />

      <url href="http://caia.swin.edu.au/urp/newtcp/" />

      <url href="http://www.FreeBSDFoundation.org/projects.shtml" />

      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~lstewart/patches/tcp_ffcaia2008/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>All outstanding patches have been committed to the svn "head"
	branch after a lengthy review process.  I anticipate merging all
	of the project's SIFTR and reassembly queue related patches from
	head to the stable branches in time for the upcoming 7.4 and 8.2
	releases.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Resource Containers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Edward Tomasz</given>
	  <common>Napierala</common>
	</name>
	<email>trasz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The goal of this project is to implement resource containers
	and a simple per-jail resource limits mechanism.  Resource
	containers are also a prerequisite for other resource management
	mechanisms, such as Hierarchical Resource Limits, for "Collective
	Limits on Set of Processes (aka.  Jobs)" Google Summer of Code
	2010 project, for implementing mechanism similar to Linux
	cgroups, and might be also used to e.g.  provide precise resource
	usage accounting for administrative or billing purposes.  So far,
	a generic resource usage framework has been developed, along with
	limit enforcement for most resources.  Work is ongoing on adding
	limits for remaining resources, debugging and generally improving
	the implementation.  This project is being sponsored by The &os;
	Foundation.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BSNMP enhancements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Shteryana</given>
	  <common>Shopova</common>
	</name>
	<email>syrinx@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Philip</given>
	  <common>Paeps</common>
	</name>
	<email>philip@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/CategorySNMP">bsnmpd(1)
	related pages on &os; wiki</url>

      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/syrinx/snmp_ieee80211&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
	snmp_wlan(3) P4 code tree</url>

      <url href="http://p4db.FreeBSD.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/syrinx/syrinx_bsnmpv3&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
	SNMPv3 for bnmspd(1) P4 code tree</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During the previous few months several additions were
	developed to &os;'s built-in SNMP daemon - bsnmpd(1).  First a
	snmp_wlan(3) module was developed that allows monitoring and
	configuration of wlan(4) interfaces operating in various modes,
	including statistics, attached/neighboring station information,
	MAC access control entries and mesh routing information.  The
	module's code was submitted in SVN and is now a part of the &os;
	base system.  Next, SNMPv3 authentication and encryption support
	were added to bsnmplib(3), bsnmpd(1) and bsnmptools (which are
	available via the ports system currently).  The message digest and
	cipher calculation calls use the implementation of the relevant
	cryptographic algorithm implementation in OpenSSL's crypto(3)
	library.  bsnmpd(1) may still optionally be compiled without the
	crypto(3) library, in which case only unauthenticated plain-text
	SNMPv3 PDUs may be processed.  In addition, a snmp_usm(3) module
	was developed that is used to configure SNMPv3 users parameters
	(name, authentication &amp; encryption algorithms used and relevant
	keys, etc.) into bsnmpd(1) as per RFC 3414.  Finally, a
	snmp_vacm(3) module was developed that allows configuration of
	view-based access control as per RFC 3415, and relevant checks
	are made by bsnmpd(1) that allow or restrict access to specific
	SNMPv1/SNMPv2 communities or SNMPv3 users to certain MIB subtrees
	as per the configuration in the snmp_vacm(3) module.  If none of
	the SNMPv3-related modules is loaded, bsnmpd(1) preserves its
	current behavior with SNMPv1/SNMPv2c PDUs.  This work is being
	funded by the &os; Foundation.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update Wiki Page to reflect latest work and document proper
	use.</task>

      <task>Finish cleanup and have it reviewed.</task>

      <task>More extensive user testing.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>&os; Services Control (fsc)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Tom</given>
	  <common>Rhodes</common>
	</name>
	<email>trhodes@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~trhodes/fsc/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>&os; Services Control is a mix of binaries which integrate
	into the rc.d system and provide for service (daemon)
	monitoring.  It knows about signals, pidfiles, and uses very
	little resources.</p>

      <p>The fsc daemon (fscd) runs in the background once the system
	has started.  Services are then added to this daemon via the
	fscadm control utility and from there they will be monitored.
	When they die, depending on the reason, they will be restarted.
	Certain signals may be ignored (list not decided), and fscd
	will remove that service from monitoring.  Every action is
	logged to the system logging daemon.  Additionally, the fscadm
	utility may be used to inquire about what services are
	monitored, their pidfile location, and current process id.</p>

      <p>FSC provides several advantages over the third party
	daemontools package.  For example, fscd uses push notifications
	instead of polling; fscd is an internal, &os; maintained
	software package accessible to all developers where daemontools
	would have to be a port and require us to maintain patches;
	fscd could be easily integrated with the current rc.d
	infrastructure.</p>

      <p>Partially based on the ideas of daemontools and Solaris
	Service Management Facility (SMF), this could be an extremely
	useful tool for &os; systems.</p>

      <p>Since the last status report, two bugs have been fixed and
	the documentation has been updated.  In the coming weeks we hope
	to get more developer attention and review, perhaps even push
	to commit the code into &os;.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Testing and feedback would be really helpful.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Netdump support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Attilio</given>
	  <common>Rao</common>
	</name>
	<email>attilio@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/Netdump" />

      <url href="svn://svn.FreeBSD.org/base/project/sv/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Netdump provides kernel core dumping over the network, instead
	of to a local disk.  It implements a very minimal TCP/IPv4 stack
	and uses a custom UDP protocol to transmit the dump to the
	netdump server running on another host.  Network interfaces
	selected for dumping perform I/O in polling mode.</p>

      <p>Netdump should find its use in diskless workstation clusters,
	PXE-booted test machines, and perhaps when doing disk driver
	development.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>General &os; dumping mechanism refinements.</task>

      <task>Implement checksum on UDP packets.</task>

      <task>Investigate the possibility to replace the custom protocol
	with tftp.</task>

      <task>Investigate the possibility to replace the custom TCP/IPv4
	stack with Contiki.</task>

      <task>Implement network console and gdb backend using a shared
	debug context stack.</task>

      <task>Add IPv6 support.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>PC-BSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kris</given>
	  <common>Moore</common>
	</name>
	<email>kmoore@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.pcbsd.org">PC-BSD Website</url>

      <url href="http://trac.pcbsd.org/browser/pcbsd/current/">PC-BSD
	Current Repo</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work is progressing quickly on a major re-factoring of PC-BSD
	tools and the PBI format for 9.0.  Our GUI tools have been
	converted to compile / run within native QT without KDE now,
	allowing us to begin offering support for other desktop
	environments for 9.0, such as Gnome, XFCE, LXDE, KDE, etc.  The
	PBI format has undergone a complete evolution, and is now
	entirely command-line based for all aspects of it, with only a
	few dependencies upon curl &amp; xdg-utils.  This will allow us to
	begin offering PBIs for traditional &os; users starting with 9.0,
	who will be able to install the pbi-manager from ports in the
	near future.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We are still busy converting / fixing all our tools to play
	nicely with various DE's, but making quick progress.</task>

      <task>The new PBI format is still undergoing extensive testing,
	and bugs are being isolated and fixed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>xz compression for packages and logfiles</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Martin</given>
	  <common>Matuska</common>
	</name>
	<email>mm@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for xz compression has been enabled in bsdtar (CURRENT
	8-STABLE) and added to pkg_create(1) and pkg_add(1) (CURRRENT).
	Packages with the .txz suffix can be created and installed.
	Logfile compression using xz in newsyslog(8) will be integrated
	soon.  Benchmarks show 15-30% better compression ratios and up to
	halved decompression times when compared to bzip2.  A switch from
	the default package format from .tbz to .txz is to be
	considered.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test building all &os; packages with xz compression.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>meetBSD California 2010 DevSummit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@ixsystems.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/201011DevSummit">Information
	page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We will be having a developers summit meeting at meetBSD
	California 2010 on November 4th, the day before the conference.
	Based on who is in attendance, we will be talking about the status
	of pressing issues; working on pressing problems and using the
	opportunity for face to face meetings to work out issues that are
	difficult in email.  This is an invitation only event, but any
	developer can invite people they think would help drive this
	meeting forward.  An agenda will be published closer to the date.
	For more information, please contact Warner Losh.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>External toolchain support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>One problem that the project has with its push towards
	embedded platforms is with the toolchain.  The compilers and
	linkers and such in the current &os; support the architectures
	generically, but often times silicon vendors produce specialized
	toolchains to wring the most performance out of their silicon.
	Right now, it is difficult to compile &os; with these tools, as
	many manual steps are required to make things 'just so'.  The
	external toolchain project will leverage some of the work done by
	the clang team to support clang in the base system (breaking the
	strict dependency on CC=cc (except for the broken intel CC
	support)).  In addition, the orchestration of the build (make
	buildworld) will change to avoid bootstrapping certain tools, or
	compiling the compilers at all.  In addition, support for using
	alternate assemblers, linkers, etc., will be added.  The work will
	be done in subversion in projects/xtc (for eXternal Tool
	Chain).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Target Big Endian Must Die</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Warner</given>
	  <common>Losh</common>
	</name>
	<email>imp@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The "tbemd" or Target Big Endian Must Die effort is nearing
	completion.  Most of the big sweeping changes to the tree have
	been committed.  The last change, actually pulling the switch, is
	stalled waiting for make universe improvements.  This work will
	change the TARGET_ARCH from a plain 'mips' to 'mipsel' or
	'mipseb' based on which endian the platform has.  It introduces
	the concept of multiple architectures being implemented with one
	set of files, and regularizes that design pattern into the &os;
	build process.  In the past, you had to set TARGET_BIG_ENDIAN=t to
	compile for big endian, but that had a number of problems: can not
	share /usr/obj between little and big endian targets, sometimes
	the produced compilers will not work right unless TARGET_BIG_ENDIAN
	is defined in the environment, etc.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Update make universe to cope with the new architectures
	when building kernels.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; KDE Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>&os; KDE</given>
	  <common>Team</common>
	</name>
	<email>kde@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Thomas</given>
	  <common>Abthorpe</common>
	</name>
	<email>tabthorpe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Max</given>
	  <common>Brazhnikov</common>
	</name>
	<email>makc@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kris</given>
	  <common>Moore</common>
	</name>
	<email>kmoore@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Dima</given>
	  <common>Panov</common>
	</name>
	<email>fluffy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Alberto</given>
	  <common>Villa</common>
	</name>
	<email>avilla@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://FreeBSD.kde.org" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The &os; KDE team has been actively keeping pace with <a
	  href="http://techbase.kde.org/Schedules">development cycle</a>
	as it is released by the KDE developers.  Often having KDE in the
	ports tree within the same week it has been released.</p>

      <p>An integral part of maintaining KDE exists in supporting the
	Qt toolchain.  As Nokia releases <a
	  href="http://qt.nokia.com/">Qt</a>,
	our team is keeping pace making it available in our <a
	  href="http://area51.pcbsd.org/">development repository</a>.</p>

      <p>We are fortunate to have a strong contributor base that helps to
	keep the process moving along.  Our heartfelt thanks go out to all
	that have helped with patches, maintaining ports, and responding
	with help on the mailing lists.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>KDE 4.5.4 is due out at the end of November, with 4.6.0 to
	be released early in 2011.</task>

      <task>The &os; KDE team is always looking for helpers, if you are
	interested in assisting, please feel free to contact any of our
	team members.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>pc-sysinstall</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kris</given>
	  <common>Moore</common>
	</name>
	<email>kmoore@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>John</given>
	  <common>Hixson</common>
	</name>
	<email>john@ixsystems.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Josh</given>
	  <common>Paetzel</common>
	</name>
	<email>jpaetzel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://it.toolbox.com/blogs/bsd-guru/eurobsdcon-presentation-on-pcsysinstall-41831" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pc-sysinstall was imported into CURRENT recently.  For the moment
	it is feature complete, although progress on the text front end
	for it may expose additional functionality it needs.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The automated/scripted install features of pc-sysinstall
	need wider testing and use to expose potential weaknesses, bugs,
	and additional features it may require.</task>

      <task>Related tasks include getting a text front end to
	pc-sysinstall working and hooking up pc-sysinstall to the build
	so install media is generated that runs pc-sysinstall.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>DAHDI/&os; Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Max</given>
	  <common>Khon</common>
	</name>
	<email>fjoe@samodelkin.net</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.asterisk.org/dahdi/" />

      <url href="http://svn.digium.com/svn/dahdi/freebsd/" />

      <url href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=0Arw6eRL10yIwdGhLdGJWUHF4b3ExQzBsd3BGd2tublE&amp;hl=en&amp;single=true&amp;gid=0&amp;output=html">
	Project Status</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The purpose of DAHDI/&os; project is to make it possible to
	use &os; as a base system for software PBX solutions.</p>

      <p>DAHDI (Digium/Asterisk Hardware Device Interface) is an
	open-source device driver framework and a set of hardware drivers
	for E1/T1, ISDN digital, and FXO/FXS analog cards [<a
	  ref="http://www.asterisk.org/dahdi/">1</a>].
	Asterisk is one of the most popular open-source software PBX
	solutions [<a href="http://www.asterisk.org/">2</a>].</p>

      <p>The project includes porting DAHDI framework and hardware
	drivers for E1/T1, FXO/FXS analog, and ISDN digital cards to
	&os;.  This also includes TDMoE support, software and hardware
	echo cancellation (Octasic, VPMADT032), and hardware transcoding
	support (TC400B).  The work is ongoing in the official DAHDI SVN
	repository with the close collaboration with DAHDI folks at
	Digium.</p>

      <p>DAHDI/&os; project is completed.  ports/misc/dahdi now contains
	the most recent DAHDI/&os; version and additional stuff that is
	not available in DAHDI/&os; SVN repository due to licensing and
	copyright restrictions (OSLEC echo canceler, experimental zaphfc
	driver).  Experimental sparc64 support is also implemented and is
	currently being tested.</p>

      <p>There is a pile of minor changes in queue that will be handled
	soon:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>add ability to run asterisk+dahdi under non-root user
	  account</li>

	<li>add support for bri_net_ptmp ISDN signalling to asterisk
	  port and drop old and outdated zaptel+asterisk-bristuff
	  ports</li>
      </ul>

      <p>I will continue periodic merges from DAHDI/Linux SVN on a
	regular basis and roll out new DAHDI/&os; releases (most likely
	synchronized with DAHDI/Linux releases).</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>V4L Support in Linux Emulator</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>J.R.</given>
	  <common>Oldroyd</common>
	</name>
	<email>fbsd@opal.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://opal.com/freebsd/sys/compat/linux/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The V4L support in the Linux emulator has been MFC'd to
	8-STABLE allowing use of video in skype calls using a camera
	supported by the pwcbsd or video4bsd drivers.  A known issue for
	skype is that your camera must support YUV420 mode which is what
	skype uses.  Note that V4L2 support is not included in the current
	work, and remains as a project for anyone interested.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Syncing pf(4) with OpenBSD 4.5</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ermal</given>
	  <common>Lu&ccedil;i</common>
	</name>
	<email>eri@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/viewvc/base/user/eri/pf45/">
	Viewing the changes.</url>

      <url href="http://svn.FreeBSD.org/base/user/eri/pf45/head/">The
	actual repo to build from.</url>

      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-pf/2010-October/005842.html">
	Public announcement.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This work is based on OpenBSD 4.5 state of pf(4).  It includes
	many improvements over the code currently present in &os;.  The
	actual new feature present in pf45 repository is support for
	divert(4), which should allow tools like snort_inline to work
	with pf(4) too.  This work also enables pfsync(4) to be loaded as
	a module as well.</p>

      <p>Currently, this work is considered stable and a patch against
	CURRENT has been released on freebsd-pf@ mailing list.</p>

      <p>The reason why this work is based off of OpenBSD 4.5 is that
	after this release they have changed the syntax which is not
	backwards compatible.</p>

      <p>After importing this one the work will go on the newest
	version and decisions on it will then be done.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Make a decision whether we need pflow(4) in base.</task>

      <task>More regression testing is needed.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>OpenAFS port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Benjamin</given>
	  <common>Kaduk</common>
	</name>
	<email>kaduk@mit.edu</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Derrick</given>
	  <common>Brashear</common>
	</name>
	<email>shadow@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://openafs.org">OpenAFS home page</url>

      <url href="http://web.mit.edu/freebsd/openafs/openafs.shar">
	&os; port for the OpenAFS 1.5.77 release</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>AFS is a distributed network filesystem that originated from
	the Andrew Project at Carnegie-Mellon University; the OpenAFS
	client implementation has not been particularly useful on &os;
	since the &os; 4.X releases.  The previous status report
	brought the OpenAFS client to a useful form on 9.0-CURRENT,
	though with many rough edges.  Only a couple of those edges have
	been smoothed out during the past few months, as developer time
	was scarce.  A mismatch between file size and vmobject size
	tracking was resolved (allowing executables to be run from AFS),
	and our system call entry has been updated on CURRENT and 8-STABLE
	to match reality.  Thanks to kib@ for both of those! The code is
	useful enough that we plan to submit an openafs-devel port to the
	Ports Collection in the coming cycle.</p>

      <p>There are several known outstanding issues that are being
	worked on, but detailed bug reports are welcome at
	port-freebsd@openafs.org.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Rework vnode locking for lookup operations to avoid an
	easily-triggered deadlock between two threads when one is looking
	up the parent directory.</task>

      <task>Update VFS locking to allow the use of disk-based client
	caches as well as memory-based caches.</task>

      <task>Track down races and deadlocks that appear under
	load.</task>

      <task>Integrate with the bsd.kmod.mk kernel-module build
	infrastructure.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>gptboot improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/svn-src-head/2010-September/020957.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The gptboot now fully follows GPT specification (verifies
	checksums and falls back to backup header and table if primary is
	corrupted).</p>

      <p>One can now use new attributes to configure partition that
	gptboot will try to boot only once from and in case of a failure
	it will fall back to the previous one.</p>

      <p>For more information check out the commit message.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>HAST (Highly Available Storage) improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>HAST is now better than ever!:) Some recent improvements
	include:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Hooks supports - HAST will execute the given command on
	  various events (connect, disconnect, synchronization start,
	  synchronization completed, synchronization interrupted,
	  split-brain condition, role change).</li>

	<li>Configuration reload on SIGHUP, a very missing
	  functionality.</li>

	<li>Internal keepalive mechanism.</li>

	<li>Many bug fixes, majority of them reported by Mikolaj
	  Golub.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>ZFSv28 is ready for wider testing</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/pipermail/freebsd-fs/2010-August/009197.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>ZFS v28 which includes data deduplication and plenty of other
	shiny new features is ready for testing.  For more information
	check out the announcement.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>GELI additions</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Pawel Jakub</given>
	  <common>Dawidek</common>
	</name>
	<email>pjd@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>There are three new GELI (a disk encryption GEOM class)
	features available in &os;-CURRENT:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>AES-XTS encryption.  XTS mode is a standard that is
	  recommended these days for storage encryption.  This is the
	  default now.  AES-XTS support was also added to opencrypto
	  framework and aesni(4) driver.</li>

	<li>Multiple encryption keys.  GELI will use one encryption key
	  for at most 2^20 blocks (sectors), as it is not recommended to
	  use the same encryption key for too much data.  It generates a key
	  array from the master key on attach and uses it accordingly.  This
	  is the default now.</li>

	<li>Passphrase can now also be loaded from a file (-J and -j
	  options).</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Valgrind port</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Stanislav</given>
	  <common>Sedov</common>
	</name>
	<email>stas@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ed</given>
	  <common>Maste</common>
	</name>
	<email>emaste@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/Valgrind">Wiki page</url>

      <url href="http://bitbucket.org/stass/valgrind-freebsd/overview">
	bibtbucket repository</url>

      <url href="https://bugs.kde.org/show_bug.cgi?id=208531">Bug
	tracker</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Valgrind is a tool for detecting memory management and
	threading bugs, and profiling.  Version 3.6.0 has recently been
	released and the &os; port has now been updated.</p>

      <p>Development of the Valgrind port has moved from perforce to
	bitbucket.org, in order to make it easier for others to track
	changes as we progress towards getting the port into shape to
	commit upstream.  You can access the repository at the bitbucket
	URL at the beginning of this report.</p>

      <p>A bugzilla entry has been submitted to track the &os; Valgrind
	port.  You can see the status and vote for the bug to express your
	interest at <a
	  href="https://bugs.kde.org/show_bug.cgi?id=208531">
	  https://bugs.kde.org/show_bug.cgi?id=208531</a>.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Port exp-ptrcheck valgrind tool and fix outstanding issues
	that show up in memcheck/helgrind/DRD in the Valgrind regression
	tests suite.</task>

      <task>More testing (please, help).</task>

      <task>Integrate our patches upstream.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Capsicum: practical capabilities for UNIX</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Robert</given>
	  <common>Watson</common>
	</name>
	<email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Jonathan</given>
	  <common>Anderson</common>
	</name>
	<email>anderson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ben</given>
	  <common>Laurie</common>
	</name>
	<email>benl@google.com</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Kris</given>
	  <common> Kennaway </common>
	</name>
	<email>kennaway@google.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/capsicum/">
	Capsicum: practical capabilities for UNIX</url>

      <url href="https://lists.cam.ac.uk/mailman/listinfo/cl-capsicum-discuss">
	Capsicum project mailing list</url>

      <url href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/capsicum/papers/2010usenix-security-capsicum-website.pdf">
	USENIX Security 2010 paper on Capsicum</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Capsicum is a lightweight OS capability and sandbox framework
	developed at the University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory,
	supported by a grant from Google.  Capsicum extends the POSIX API,
	providing several new OS primitives to support object-capability
	security on UNIX-like operating systems: capabilities, a new
	sandboxed capability mode for processes, anonymous shared memory
	objects, process descriptors, and a modified C runtime able to
	support distributed applications within sandboxes.  Capsicum
	has been prototyped on &os; 9-CURRENT, with a 8-STABLE
	backport.</p>

      <p>Capsicum is intended to supplement existing system-centric
	mandatory access control protections by providing an
	application-centric protection model, which better supports
	compartmentalised user programs that set up one (or many)
	sandboxes to process untrustworthy data in.  A number of
	applications, from tcpdump to the Chromium web browser, have been
	modified to use sandboxing to confine risky activities such as
	the parsing of untrusted packets and HTML/JavaScript
	rendering.</p>

      <p>We plan to begin merging the core Capsicum kernel features
	to &os; 9-CURRENT in November/December 2010 once a number of
	known problems have been resolved.  Following a KBI analysis, we
	will consider merging our 8-STABLE backport to Subversion.  For
	the time being, and while APIs stabilise, we plan to distribute
	the Capsicum libraries via ports. However, simply having the
	kernel features in place is sufficient to support sandboxing in
	tcpdump and Chromium.</p>

      <p>The Capsicum paper by Robert Watson / Jonathan Anderson
	(Cambridge) and Ben Laurie/ Kris Kennaway (Google) won a best
	paper award at the 2010 USENIX Security Symposium!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>More aggressively test (and as needed, fix) possible UNIX
	domain socket garbage collector interactions with Capsicum.</task>

      <task>Using results of our recent model checking analysis of the
	namei() sandboxing approach, make robustness improvements.</task>

      <task>Merge to &os; 9-CURRENT in November/December.</task>

      <task>KBI analysis for possible 8-STABLE merge.</task>

      <task>Convert more applications to use Capsicum sandboxing!</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Bugbusting Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Gavin</given>
	  <common>Atkinson</common>
	</name>
	<email>gavin@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Mark</given>
	  <common>Linimon</common>
	</name>
	<email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Remko</given>
	  <common>Lodder</common>
	</name>
	<email>remko@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Volker</given>
	  <common>Werth</common>
	</name>
	<email>vwe@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/support.html#gnats" />
      <url href="http://wiki.FreeBSD.org/BugBusting" />
      <url href="http://people.FreeBSD.org/~linimon/studies/prs/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The bugbusting team continue work on trying to make the contents
	of the GNATS PR database cleaner, more accessible and easier for
	committers to find and resolve PRs, by tagging PRs to indicate the
	areas involved, and by ensuring that there is sufficient info
	within each PR to resolve each issue.</p>

      <p>July saw the addition of Alexander Best (arundel@) to this
	bugbusting team, he is helping with the triaging PRs as they come
	in, creating patches for problems and working with submitters to
	get the solutions tested, and working through the PR backlog.</p>

      <p>Also in July, Gavin Atkinson worked with Hans Petter Selasky on
	the USB PRs, attempting to go through many of them and determine
	the status of each of them.  As a result, nearly 10% of the USB
	PRs were determined to be closeable, with many more either being
	marked as patched already or able to be committed quickly.
	Several PRs that only affect the old (pre-8.0) USB stack were
	also identified and marked as such.  More work will take place
	in this area in the future.</p>

      <p>August saw us host another bugathon, with an aim of
	investigating and getting into a committable state several of the
	PRs with patches.  Turnout was not as great as in the past -
	mainly believed to be die to the short notice, but still several
	PRs were progressed, with several commits made and several PRs
	closed.</p>

      <p>The number of PRs has held steady over the last three months,
	with improvements in numbers in some categories (especially usb
	and bin) being offset by slight increases in others.</p>

      <p>Reports continue to be produced from the PR database, all of
	which can be found from the links above.  Committers interested
	in custom reports are encouraged to discuss requirements with
	bugmeister@ - we are happy to create new reports where needs are
	identified.</p>

      <p>As always, anybody interested in helping out with the PR queue is
	welcome to join us in #freebsd-bugbusters on EFnet.  We are
	always looking for additional help, whether your interests lie in
	triaging incoming PRs, generating patches to resolve existing
	problems, or simply helping with the database housekeeping
	(identifying duplicate PRs, ones that have already been resolved,
	etc).  This is a great way of getting more involved with
	&os;!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Try to find ways to get more committers helping us with
	closing PRs that the team has already analyzed.</task>

      <task>Try to get more non-committers involved with the triaging
	of PRs as they come in, and generating patches to fix reported
	problems.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='team'>
    <title>&os; Release Engineering Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Release Engineering Team</given>
	</name>
	<email>re@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/releng/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The Release Engineering Team has announced the schedule for the
	upcoming joint release of &os; 7.4 and 8.2.  The schedules
	are available on the Web site:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><a href="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/7.4R/schedule.html">
	    7.4-RELEASE schedule</a></li>
	<li><a href="http://www.freebsd.org/releases/8.2R/schedule.html">
	    8.2-RELEASE schedule</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>It is expected that 7.4 will be the last of the 7.X releases.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat="docs">
    <title>The &os; Japanese Documentation Project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Hiroki</given>
	  <common>Sato</common>
	</name>
	<email>hrs@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Ryusuke</given>
	  <common>Suzuki</common>
	</name>
	<email>ryusuke@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/ja/">Japanese &os; Web Pages</url>

      <url href="http://www.jp.FreeBSD.org/doc-jp/">The
	&os; Japanese Documentation Project Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The www/ja and doc/ja_JP.eucJP/ have been updated constantly
	since the last status report.  We committed a big patch for
	the "Installing &os;" chapter of the &os; Handbook which was
	contributed by many people since a long time.  This chapter is
	still outdated and needs more work.  Some progress was made in
	the Porter's Handbook as well.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Further translation of the &os; Handbook and contents of
	the <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">www.FreeBSD.org</a> site to
	the Japanese language.</task>

      <task>Pre-/post-commit review of the translation.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>EuroBSDCon 2010</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>Wolfgang</given>
	  <common>Zenker</common>
	</name>
	<email>eurobsdcon2010@egeling.de</email>
      </person>

      <person>
	<name>
	  <given>G&aacute;bor</given>
	  <common>P&aacute;li</common>
	</name>
	<email>pgj@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://2010.EuroBSDCon.org/" />
      <url href="http://2011.EuroBSDCon.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>EuroBSDCon&nbsp;2010 happened in Karlsruhe, Germany, with many
	users, developers, friends, and others.  We had many tutorials,
	and 22 interesting presentations on various topics connected to
	&os;, OpenBSD, NetBSD, like the new USB stack, jail
	improvements, Virtual Private Systems, SSH and PGP convergence,
	ZFS, journaled Soft-Updates, BSD certification, porting to the
	latest ARM processors, and pc-sysinstall.  The event was opened by
	a keynote speech from Poul-Henning Kamp on software tools and
	their future, and it was closed by short status reports on
	different BSD flavors.  Next year's event in 2011 will take place
	in the Netherlands from 6th to 9th October 2011.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>
