<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE report PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Status Report//EN"
                        "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/www/share/sgml/statusreport.dtd">

<report>
  <date>
    <month>January-March</month>

    <year>2006</year>
  </date>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>The highlights of this quarters report certainly include the
    availability of native Java binaries thanks to the 
    <a href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/">FreeBSD Foundation</a>

    , as well as progress has been made with Xen support and Sun's
    Ultrasparc T1. Furthermore we are looking forward to FreeBSD 6.1 and
    TrustedBSD audit support has been imported into FreeBSD 7-CURRENT.
    All in all, a very exiting start to 2006.</p>

    <p>In just under a month the developers will be gathering at 
    <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/">BSDCan 2006</a>

    for, FreeBSD Dev Summit, a two day meeting of FreeBSD developers.
    Once again the 
    <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/schedule.php">BSDCan schedule</a>

    is filled with many interesting talks.</p>

    <p>We hope you enjoy reading and look forward to hear from you for
    the next round. Consult the list of 
    <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/ideas/">projects and
    ideas</a>

    for ways to get involved. The submission date for the second quarter
    reports will be July, 7th 2006.</p>

    <p>Thanks to everybody who submitted a report and to Brad Davis, who
    joined the Status Report team, for proof reading.</p>
  </section>

  <category>
    <name>proj</name>

    <description>Projects</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>net</name>

    <description>Network infrastructure</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>kern</name>

    <description>Kernel</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>doc</name>

    <description>Documentation</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>bin</name>

    <description>Userland programs</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>arch</name>

    <description>Architectures</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>ports</name>

    <description>Ports</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>vendor</name>

    <description>Vendor / 3rd Party Software</description>
  </category>

  <category>
    <name>misc</name>

    <description>Miscellaneous</description>
  </category>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>FreeBSD Security Officer and Security Team</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Security</given>

          <common>Officer</common>
        </name>

        <email>security-officer@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Security</given>

          <common>Team</common>
        </name>

        <email>security-team@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/security/" />

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/administration.html#t-secteam" />

      <url href="http://vuxml.freebsd.org/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In March 2006, Marcus Alves Grando, George Neville-Neil, and
      Philip Paeps joined the FreeBSD Security Team. The current Security
      Team membership is published on the web site.</p>

      <p>In the time since the last status report, eight security
      advisories have been issued concerning problems in the base system
      of FreeBSD; of these, three problems were in "contributed" code,
      while five were in code maintained within FreeBSD. The
      Vulnerabilities and Exposures Markup Language (VuXML) document has
      continued to be updated by the Security Team and the Ports
      Committers documenting new vulnerabilities in the FreeBSD Ports
      Collection; since the last status report, 50 new entries have been
      added, bringing the total up to 686.</p>

      <p>The following FreeBSD releases are supported by the FreeBSD
      Security Team: FreeBSD 4.10, FreeBSD 4.11, FreeBSD 5.3, FreeBSD
      5.4, and FreeBSD 6.0. Upon their release, FreeBSD 5.5 and FreeBSD
      6.1 will also be supported. The respective End of Life dates of
      supported releases are listed on the web site; of particular note,
      FreeBSD 4.10 and FreeBSD 5.4 will cease to be supported at the end
      of May 2006.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>FreeBSD NFS Status Report</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Chuck</given>

          <common>Lever</common>
        </name>

        <email>cel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Support for NFS in FreeBSD received a boost this quarter as a
      kernel developer from Network Appliance has volunteered to help
      with the clients. Chuck Lever is now a src committer, mentored by
      Mike Silbersack. Mohan Srinivasan and Jim Rees have ended their
      apprenticeships and are now full committers. Mohan continues his
      effort to make the NFSv2/3 client SMP safe. He expects to make the
      changes available for review soon.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD gained presence at the annual NFS interoperability event
      known as Connectathon. Rick Macklem's FreeBSD NFSv4 server is
      pretty stable now and available via anonymous ftp. NFSv4.1 features
      are not a part of it yet and are not likely to happen until at
      least the end of 2006. Contact rick@snowhite.cis.uoguelph.ca for
      details.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>BSDCan</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Dan</given>

          <common>Langille</common>
        </name>

        <email>dan@langille.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The 
      <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/schedule.php">schedule</a>

      for BSDCan 2006 demonstrates just how strong and popular BSDCan has
      become in a very short time. Three concurrent streams of talks make
      sure that there is something for everyone. We provide high quality
      talks at very affordable 
      <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/registration.php">prices</a>

      .</p>

      <p>BSDCan is the biggest BSD event of 2006. Ask others who attended
      in past years how much they enjoyed their time in Ottawa. Ask them
      who they met, who they talked to, the contacts they made, the
      information they learned.</p>

      <p>Remember to bring your wife/husband/spouse/etc because we will
      have things for them to do while you are attending the conference.
      Ottawa is a fantastic tourist destination.</p>

      <p>See you at BSDCan 2006!</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>
      <a href="http://www.bsdcan.org/2006/activity.php?id=110">Works in
      Progress</a>

      - if you want to talk about your project for 5 minutes, this is
      your chance. Get in touch with us ASAP to reserve your spot.</task>

      <task>We're looking for volunteers to help out just before and
      during the conference. Contact Dan at the above address.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Ports Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Mark</given>

          <common>Linimon</common>
        </name>

        <email>linimon@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/ports/">The FreeBSD Ports
      Collection</url>

      <url
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing-ports/">
      Contributing to the FreeBSD Ports Collection</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~fenner/portsurvey/">FreeBSD
      ports unfetchable distfile survey (Bill Fenner's report)</url>

      <url href="http://edwin.adsl.barnet.com.au/~edwin/ports/">FreeBSD
      ports updated distfile survey (Edwin Groothius' report)</url>

      <url href="http://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/index.html">FreeBSD ports
      monitoring system</url>

      <url href="http://www.freebsd.org/portmgr/index.html">The FreeBSD
      Ports Management Team</url>

      <url href="http://tinderbox.marcuscom.com">marcuscom
      tinderbox</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>During this time, the number of ports PRs rose dramatically from
      its impressive low number seen late last quarter. This was due to
      the holidays, the freeze for the 5.5/6.1 release cycle, and the
      aggressive work several submitters have been doing to correct
      long-standing problems with stale distfiles, stale WWW sites, port
      that only work on i386, and so forth. Over 200 new ports have also
      been added. The statistics do not truly reflect the state of the
      Ports Collection, which continues to improve despite the increased
      number of ports.</p>

      <p>We now have 3 people who are qualified to run the 5-exp
      regression tests. Due to this, we were able to run several cycles,
      resulting in a series of commits that retired more than 3 dozen
      portmgr PRs. There were a few snags during one commit due to some
      unintended consequences, but the breakage was fixed in less than
      one day. Notable changes include the addition of physical category
      net-p2p and virtual categories hamradio and rubygems. Once 5.5 and
      6.1 are released, portmgr hopes to be able to run regression tests
      more often.</p>

      <p>We have added 5 new committers since the last report.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>We need help getting back to our modern low of 500
      PRs.</task>

      <task>We have over 4,000 unmaintained ports (see, for instance, 
      <url
      href="http://portsmon.freebsd.org/portsconcordanceformaintainer.py?maintainer=ports@FreeBSD.org">
      the list on portsmon</url>

      ). We are always looking for dedicated volunteers to adopt at least
      a few ports.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>OpenBSD dhclient</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Brooks</given>

          <common>Davis</common>
        </name>

        <email>brooks@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Sam</given>

          <common>Leffler</common>
        </name>

        <email>sam@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>All dhclient changes in HEAD have been merged to 6-STABLE for
      6.1-RELEASE. New patches currently in testing include startup
      script support for fully asynchronous starting of dhclient which
      eliminates the wait for link during startup and support for sending
      the system hostname to the server when non is specified.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>FAST_IPSEC Upgrade</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>George</given>

          <common>Neville-Neil</common>
        </name>

        <email>gnn@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Bjoern A.</given>

          <common>Zeeb</common>
        </name>

        <email>bz@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://sources.zabbadoz.net/freebsd/ipv6/fast-ipsec.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Split out of PF_KEY code between the kernel and user space has
      been completed and committed to CVS.</p>

      <p>The diff between Kame IPv4 based IPSec and FAST_IPSEC IPv4 did
      not show any glaring issues.</p>

      <p>Moving on to making IPv6 work in FAST_IPSEC including being able
      to run the kernel with the following variations: 
      <ul>
        <li>FAST_IPSEC in v4 only</li>

        <li>KAME IPv6 and IPSec</li>

        <li>KAME IPv6 and FAST_IPSEC</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Any patches for FAST_IPSEC, KAME IPsec of either variant (v4
      or v6) should be forwarded to bz@ and gnn@.</task>

      <task>Build a better TAHI. TAHI, the test framework, will not be
      maintained and is not the easiest system to use and understand. A
      better test harness is possible and is necessary for other
      networking projects as well. Contact gnn@ if you have time to work
      on this as he has some code and ideas to start from.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>FreeSBIE</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeSBIE</given>

          <common>Staff</common>
        </name>

        <email>staff@FreeSBIE.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>FreeSBIE</given>

          <common>Mailing List</common>
        </name>

        <email>freesbie@gufi.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freesbie.org">Website</url>

      <url href="http://liste.gufi.org/mailman/listinfo/freesbie">ML
      Subscribe Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The project is alive and plans to release an ISO image of
      FreeSBIE 2.0 based on FreeBSD 6.1-RELEASE few day after the same
      has been release. FreeSBIE 2.0 will be available for i386 and amd64
      archs. Tests images can be download via BitTorrent from 
      <a href="http://torrent.freesbie.org">torrent.freesbie.org</a>

      .</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Test "test ISO images" for both amd64 and i386</task>

      <task>Suggest packages to be added to the ISO image.</task>

      <task>Suggestions needed for Xfce and fluxbox look.</task>

      <task>Suggestions needed for applications' configuration
      files.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>HPLIP (Full HP Printer and MFD support)</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Anish</given>

          <common>Mistry</common>
        </name>

        <email>amistry@am-productions.biz</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://am-productions.biz/docs/hplip.php">HPLIP FreeBSD
      Information</url>

      <url href="http://hplip.sourceforge.net/">Official Site</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A preliminary version of HP's hplip software for their printers
      and multi-function devices has been ported. This allows viewing of
      the status informantion from the printer. Such as ink levels, error
      messages, and queue information. If you have an Officejet you can
      also fax and scan. Photocard and Copies functionality is
      untested.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>General Testing</task>

      <task>Photocard Testing</task>

      <task>Various ugen fixes</task>

      <task>Fix Officejet Panel Display</task>

      <task>Run hpiod and hpssd as unprivileged users</task>

      <task>Banish the Linuxisms in the Makefile</task>

      <task>Fix "Make Copies"</task>

      <task>Automatically Setup Scanner</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Low-overhead performance monitoring for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joseph</given>

          <common>Koshy</common>
        </name>

        <email>jkoshy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~jkoshy/projects/perf-measurement">
      Project home page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This projects implements a kernel module (hwpmc(4)), an
      application programming interface (pmc(3)) and a few simple
      applications (pmcstat(8) and pmccontrol(8)) for measuring system
      performance using event monitoring hardware in modern CPUs.</p>

      <p>New features since the last status report:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Support for profiling dynamically loaded kernel and user
        objects has been added.</li>

        <li>pmcstat(8) now supports command-line syntax for logging to a
        network socket.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='doc'>
    <title>FreeBSD list of projects and ideas for volunteers</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Joel</given>

          <common>Dahl</common>
        </name>

        <email>joel@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/ideas/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD list of projects and ideas for volunteers is doing
      well. Several items were picked up by volunteers and have found
      their way into the tree. Others are under review or in
      progress.</p>

      <p>We are looking forward to hear about new ideas, people willing
      to be technical contacts for generic topics (e.g. USB) or specific
      entries (already existing or newly created), suggestions for
      existing entries or completion reports for (parts of) an entry.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Add more ideas.</task>

      <task>Find more technical contacts.</task>

      <task>Find people willing to review/test implementations of
      (somewhat) finished items.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>Java Binaries</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Deb</given>

          <common>Goodkin</common>
        </name>

        <email>deb@freebsd.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/downloads/java.shtml">
      FreeBSD Foundation Java Homepage</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD Foundation released official certified JDK and JRE
      1.5 binaries for the official FreeBSD 5.4 and FreeBSD 6.0 releases
      on the i386 platform. 
      <br />

      We were able to accomplish this by hiring a contractor to run the
      Sun certification tests and fixing the problems found. This could
      not have been completed without the support from the BSD Java
      Team.</p>

      <p>We provided financial support for Java development and funded
      the certification process. We spent a significant amount of time
      and money on legal issues from contract and NDA creation for our
      contractor to license agreements from Sun and creating our own for
      the binaries. We worked with OEMs who would like to use the
      binaries, but needed to understand what they need to do legally to
      be able to redistribute the binaries. This is an area we are still
      working on at our end. We are waiting for a letter from Sun to put
      on our website to OEMs. We are also in the process of updating our
      OEM license agreement. This should be available by mid-April.</p>

      <p>We have received a positive response from the FreeBSD community
      regarding the release of the binaries. We received a few requests
      to support the FreeBSD 6.1/amd64 platform. We have decided to move
      forward and support this too. We currently are working with a
      contractor to provide Java support on 5.5/i386, 6.1/i386, and
      6.1/amd64. Once 5.5 and 6.1 are released, we'll update the FreeBSD
      Foundation website with the Java status. Regular updates to the
      website will continue.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>Update of the linux infrastructure in the Ports
    Collection</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Emulation</given>

          <common>Mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>freebsd-emulation@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Boris</given>

          <common>Samorodov</common>
        </name>

        <email>bsam@ipt.ru</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work is underway to use the new linux_base-fc3 as the new
      default linux base. Since there's some infrastructure work to do
      before it can be made the new default, this will not happen before
      the release of FreeBSD 5.5 and 6.1. At the same time a new X.org
      based linux port will replace the outdated XFree86 based linux X11
      port.</p>

      <p>The use of fc3 instead of fc4 or fc5 is to make sure we have a
      smooth transition with as less as possible breakage. We already use
      several fc3 RPM's with the current default of linux_base-8, so
      there should be not much problems to solve.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Mark all old linux_base ports as DEPRECATED (after making fc3
      the default linux_base port).</task>

      <task>Have a look at a linux-dri version which works with the
      update to X.org.</task>

      <task>When everything is switched to fc3 and everything works at
      least as good as before, have a look at porting fc4 or fc5.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='bin'>
    <title>Mouse Driver Framework</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Jordan</given>

          <common>Sissel</common>
        </name>

        <email>jls@csh.rit.edu</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.semicomplete.com/projects/newpsm">mouse
      framework project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The current mouse system is a mess with moused, psm, ums, and
      mse supporting, individually, multiple kinds of mice. This project
      aims to move all driver support into moused modules in userland. In
      addition, many features lacking in the existing mouse
      infrastructure are being added. It is my hope that this new system
      will make both using mice and writing drivers easier down the
      road.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Testing. Contact if interested.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>SMPng Network Stack</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/projects/netperf/">FreeBSD
      Netperf Project</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The FreeBSD netperf project has recently focused on revising the
      socket and protocol control block reference counts to define and
      enforce reference and memory management invariants, allowing the
      removal of unnecessary checks, error handling, and locking. Use of
      global pcbinfo locks has now been eliminated from the socket send
      and receive paths into all network protocols, including netipx,
      netnatm, netatalk, netinet, netinet6, netgraph, and others. Checks
      have generally been replaced with assertions; so_pcb is now
      guaranteed to be non-NULL. This should improve performance by
      reducing lock contention and unnecessary checks, as well as
      facilitate future work to eliminate long holding of pcbinfo locks
      in the TCP input path through proper reference counting for pcbs.
      These changes have been committed to FreeBSD 7-CURRENT, and will be
      merged in a few months once they have stabilized.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>pfSense</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>

          <common>Ullrich</common>
        </name>

        <email>sullrich@gmail.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.pfsense.com">pfSense website</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>pfSense continues to grow and fix bugs. Since the last report we
      have grown to 14 developers working part and full time on bringing
      pfSense to 1.0. Beta 3 is scheduled for release on 4/15/2006.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Fix remaining bugs listed in CVSTrac</task>

      <task>Fine tune existing code</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>Symbol Versioning</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Daniel</given>

          <common>Eischen</common>
        </name>

        <email>deischen@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url
      href="http://people.freebsd.org/~deischen/symver/library_versioning.html">
      Symbol Versioning in FreeBSD.</url>

      <url href="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/doc/817-1984">Symbol
      Versioning in Solaris.</url>

      <url href="http://people.redhat.com/~drepper/symbol-versioning">
      Symbol Versioning in Linux</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Symbol versioning libraries allows us to maintain binary
      compatibility without bumping library version numbers. Recently,
      symbol versioning for libc, libpthread, libthread_db, and libm was
      committed to -current. It is disabled by default, and can be
      enabled by adding "SYMVER_ENABLED=true" to/etc/make.conf. A final
      version bump for libc and other affected libraries (perhaps all)
      should be done before enabling this by default.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Determining the impact on ports - portmgr (Kris) is running a
      portbuild to identify any problems. I am working to resolve the few
      problems that were found.</task>

      <task>Making our linker link to libc and libpthread (when using
      (-pthread)) when building shared libraries. This is needed so that
      symbol version dependencies are recorded in the shared library. I
      think kan@ is working on this.???</task>

      <task>Identify and symbol version any other libraries that should
      be symbol versioned. If anyone has any suggestions, I'm all
      ears.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Status Report ATA project</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>S&#248;ren</given>

          <common>Schmidt</common>
        </name>

        <email>sos@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>The last months has mostly been about stabilizing ATA for
      6.1-RELEASE, and adding support for new chipsets. On that front
      JMicron has raised the bar for vendors as they have provided not
      only hardware but documentation on both their hardware and their
      software RAID implementation, making it a breeze to add support for
      their, by the way excellent, products. Other vendors can join in
      here. :) Otherwise I'm always in the need for any amount of time or
      means to get it if nothing else.</p>

      <p>ATA has grown a USB backend so that fx. flash keys and external
      HD/CD/DVD drives can be used directly without atapicam/CAM etc.
      This is very handy on small (embedded) systems where resources are
      limited and kernel space at a premium. burncd(8) is in the process
      of being updated so it will support this along with SATA ATAPI
      devices, and if time permits adding DVD support.</p>

      <p>The next months will be used to (hopefully) work on getting ATA
      to work properly on systems with &gt; 4G of memory and utilize the
      64bit addressing of controllers that support it. RAID5 support for
      ataraid is on the list together with hardening of the RAID
      subsystem to help keep data alive and well.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>BSDInstaller</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Turner</common>
        </name>

        <email>soc-andrew@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/BSDInstaller" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>The BSDInstaller integration work has progressed since the
      previous report. The backend has been changed to the new Lua
      version. This is to ensure the version we use will be maintained.
      The release Makefile now uses the Lua package rather the local copy
      in Perforce. Ports are also being created for the required modules
      to remove the need to bring Lua into the base.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Create a port for all the Lua modules required</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='ports'>
    <title>libpkg - Package management library</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Turner</common>
        </name>

        <email>andrew@fubar.geek.nz</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://libpkg.berlios.de/" />

      <url href="http://developer.berlios.de/projects/libpkg/" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Libpkg is a package management library using libarchive to
      extract the package files. It is able to download, install and get
      a list of installed packages. Work has also been started on
      implementing the package tools from the base system. Most of
      pkg_info has been implemented and pkg_add has been started.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Support for more command line options in pkg_info and
      pkg_add</task>

      <task>Creating a package</task>

      <task>Test pkg_add works as expected for all implemented command
      line options</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='net'>
    <title>Bridge STP Improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Andrew</given>

          <common>Thompson</common>
        </name>

        <email>thompsa@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <body>
      <p>Work has been started to implement the Rapid Spanning Tree
      Protocol which supersedes STP. RSTP has a much faster link failover
      time of around one second compared to 30-60 seconds for STP, this
      is very important on modern networks. Some progress has been made
      but a RSTP capable switch will be needed soon to proceed, see 
      <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/donations/wantlist.html">
      http://www.freebsd.org/donations/wantlist.html</a>

      .</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Donation of a RSTP switch</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>TMPFS (Filesystem) for FreeBSD</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Rohit</given>

          <common>Jalan</common>
        </name>

        <email>rohitj@purpe.com</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://download.purpe.com/tmpfs">Project Home</url>

      <url href="http://download.purpe.com/tmpfs/bmark.html">I/O
      Benchmarks</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Three betas have been released so far. The code is operational
      and seems to be stable but it is not MPSAFE yet.</p>

      <p>The second and third betas used different mechanisms for data
      I/O. (sfbuf vs. kernel_map+vacache) and at present I am in the
      process on selecting one mechanism over the other. Your opinion is
      solicited.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='kern'>
    <title>Sound subsystem improvements</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Multimedia</given>

          <common>Mailinglist</common>
        </name>

        <email>freebsd-multimedia@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Ariff</given>

          <common>Abdullah</common>
        </name>

        <email>ariff@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Alexander</given>

          <common>Leidinger</common>
        </name>

        <email>netchild@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.leidinger.net/FreeBSD/hdac-20060313.tbz">
      Start of Intel HDA support.</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>A lot of fixes (bugs, LORs, panics) and improvements
      (performance, compatibility, a new driver, 24/32bit samples
      support, ...) have been merged to RELENG_6. FreeBSD 6.1 is the
      first release which ships with the much improved sound system.
      Additionally there's work underway: 
      <ul>
        <li>To make the sound system API endianess clean. This should
        make it easier (for a developer) to make the sound drivers usable
        on all architectures.</li>

        <li>To rework character device allocation. This way someone can
        choose a specific channel, e.g. /dev/dsp0.r0 or /dev/dsp0.p0 to
        access the first recording or play channel respectively). With
        the "current" sound system (as in FreeBSD 6.1) this is not
        possible (accessing /dev/dsp0.0 and /dev/dsp0.1 may give you the
        first or the second channel, the number is just an enumeration,
        not a channel-chooser).</li>

        <li>To add multi-channel support/processing.</li>

        <li>To add Intel HDA support. There's already some code to look
        at (see URL referenced above), but is far from usable for an
        enduser (we need some programmers, but no testers ATM, since
        there are no user testable parts yet). Interested volunteers
        should contact the multimedia mailinglist.</li>
      </ul>

      Parts of this work may be already in 6.1, but there's still a good
      portion which isn't even in -current as of this writing.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Style(9) cleanup, survive against WARNS=2 (at least).</task>

      <task>Have a look at the sound related entries on the ideas
      list.</task>

      <task>Rewrite some parts (e.g. a new mixer subsystem with OSS
      compatibility).</task>

      <task>sndctl(1): tool to control non-mixer parts of the sound
      system (e.g. spdif switching, virtual-3D effects) by an user
      (instead of the sysctl approach in -current); pcmplay(1),
      pcmrec(1), pcmutil(1).</task>

      <task>Plugable FEEDER infrastructure. For ease of debugging various
      feeder stuff and/or as userland library and test suite.</task>

      <task>Closer compatibility with OSS, especially for the upcoming
      OSS v4.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='misc'>
    <title>Fundraising for FreeBSD security development</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Colin</given>

          <common>Percival</common>
        </name>

        <email>cperciva@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~cperciva/funding.html" />
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Since 2003, I have introduced the (now quite widely used)
      FreeBSD Update and Portsnap tools, but rarely had time to make
      improvements or add requested features. Consequently, on March
      30th, I sent email to the freebsd-hackers, freebsd-security,
      and freebsd-announce lists announcing that I was seeking funding to
      allow me to spend the summer working full-time on these and my role
      as FreeBSD Security Officer. Assuming that some cheques arrive as
      expected, I have reached my donation target and will start work at
      the beginning of May.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>The work which I'm aiming to do is listed at the URL
      above.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>FreeBSD on Xen 3.0</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Scott</given>

          <common>Long</common>
        </name>

        <email>scottl@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kip</given>

          <common>Macy</common>
        </name>

        <email>kmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>We had hoped to finish a prototype of Xen DomU and possible Dom0
      in time for FreeBSD 6.1. The primary work was focused on bringing
      Xen into the FreeBSD 'newbus' framework. Unfortunately, an
      architectural problem in FreeBSD has stopped us. Xen relies on
      message passing between to child and parent domains to communicate
      device configuration, and this message passing requires that tsleep
      and wakeup work early in boot. That doesn't seem to be the case,
      and it's unclear what it would take to make it work. Without the
      newbus work, it's hard to complete the Dom0 code, and impossible to
      support Xen 3.0 features like domain suspension.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Make tsleep and wakeup work during early boot</task>

      <task>Continue DomU newbus work</task>

      <task>Continue Dom0 work</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>TrustedBSD Audit</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <email>trustedbsd-audit@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/audit.html">TrustedBSD Audit
      Web Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>In the past three months, the TrustedBSD CAPP audit
      implementation has been merged to the FreeBSD 7-CURRENT development
      tree in CVS, and the groundwork has been laid for a merge to 6.X.
      OpenBSM, a BSD-licensed implementation of Sun's Basic Security
      Module (BSM) API and file format, as well as extensions to support
      intrusion detect applications. New features included support for
      audit pipes, a pseudo-device that provides a live audit record
      trail interface for intrusion detection applications, and an audit
      filter daemon that allows plug-in modules to monitor live
      events.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete audit coverage of non-native system call ABIs, some
      more recent base system calls.</task>

      <task>Integrate OpenBSM 1.0 alpha 6, which includes auditfilterd
      and the audit filter API.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='proj'>
    <title>TrustedBSD OpenBSM</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Robert</given>

          <common>Watson</common>
        </name>

        <email>rwatson@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <email>trustedbsd-audit@TrustedBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.OpenBSM.org/">TrustedBSD OpenBSM Web
      Page</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>OpenBSM is a BSD-licensed implementation of Sun's Basic Security
      Module (BSM) API and file format, based on Apple's Darwin
      implementation. OpenBSM 1.0 alpha 5 is now available, and includes
      significant bugfixes, documentation, and feature enhancements over
      previous releases, including 64-bit token support,
      endian-independent operation, improved memory management, and bug
      fixes resulting from the static analysis tools provided by Coverity
      and FlexeLint. Recent versions are now built and configured using
      autoconf and automake, and have been built and tested with FreeBSD,
      Mac OS X, and Linux.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Complete OpenBSM file format validation test suite.</task>

      <task>Finalize audit filter API.</task>

      <task>Complete file format documentation; record documentation for
      new record types associated with Mac OS X, FreeBSD, and Linux
      specific events not present in documented Solaris record
      format.</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>ARM Support for TS-7200</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John-Mark</given>

          <common>Gurney</common>
        </name>

        <email>jmg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://www.embeddedarm.com/epc/ts7200-spec-h.html">
      TS-7200 Board</url>

      <url
      href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/user/jmg/arm&amp;HIDEDEL=NO">
      Perforce Code Location</url>

      <url href="http://people.freebsd.org/~jmg/dmesg.ts7200">FreeBSD/arm
      TS-7200 dmesg output</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>This is just an update to note that TS-7200 is building and
      running with a recent -current.</p>

      <p>I have been working on getting FreeBSD/arm running on the
      TS-7200. So far the board boots, and has somewhat working ethernet
      (some unexplained packet loss). I can netboot from a FreeBSD/i386
      machine, and I can also mount msdosfs's on CF.</p>
    </body>

    <help>
      <task>Figuring out why some small packets transmit with error (if
      someone can get Technologic Systems to pay attention to me and this
      issue, that'd be great!)</task>

      <task>EP93xx identification information to properly attach various
      onboard devices</task>
    </help>
  </project>

  <project cat='arch'>
    <title>Ultrasparc T1 support</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Kip</given>

          <common>Macy</common>
        </name>

        <email>kmacy@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>

      <person>
        <name>
          <given>John</given>

          <common>Gurney</common>
        </name>

        <email>jmg@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
      <url href="http://opensparc-t1.sunsource.net/index.html">T1
      processor and hypervisor documentation.</url>

      <url href="http://www.fsmware.com/sun4v/todo.txt">TODO list</url>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>FreeBSD has been ported the T1, Sun's newest processor. FreeBSD
      currently runs multi-user SMP. JMG is actively working on improving
      device support.</p>

      <p>The port has taken several weeks longer than initially
      anticipated as the majority of the current sparc64 port could not
      be re-used.</p>
    </body>
  </project>

  <project cat='vendor'>
    <title>OpenBSD packet filter - pf</title>

    <contact>
      <person>
        <name>
          <given>Max</given>

          <common>Laier</common>
        </name>

        <email>mlaier@FreeBSD.org</email>
      </person>
    </contact>

    <links>
    </links>

    <body>
      <p>Work towards importing the upcoming OpenBSD 3.9 version of pf is
      starting slowly. There are a couple of infrastructural changes
      (e.g. interface groups) that need to be imported beforehand. This
      work is in the final stage of progress.</p>

      <p>A couple of bugfixes have happened since the last report and will
      be available in FreeBSD 6.1/5.5. pf users are strongly encouraged
      to upgrade to RELENG_6 as the version present in RELENG_5 is
      collecting dust.</p>
    </body>
  </project>
</report>

