<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY email 'freebsd-qa'>
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD 5.0 Open Issues">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.download">

<h1>Open Issues</h1>

<p>This is a list of open issues that need to be resolved for FreeBSD
  5.0.  If you have any updates for this list, please e-mail
  re@FreeBSD.org.</p>

<h3>Must Resolve Issues for 5.0-RELEASE</h3>

<table class="tblbasic">
  <tr><th>Issue</th><th>Status</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Description</th>
      </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>None at this time.</td>
  </tr>

</table>

<h3>Desired Features for 5.0-RELEASE</h3>

<table class="tblbasic">
  <tr><th>Issue</th><th>Status</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Description</th>
      </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>a.out toolchain port</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>A.out support in the base system was reduced; the removed build
    chain components should be made into a port.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>NETNCP and nwfs broken</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>NETNCP and nwfs appear to be as-yet unadapted for KSE, and hence
    not working.  The build needs fixing (probably not all that hard)
    and then it needs to be tested (harder: few people appear to have
    Netware servers).</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>No docs for FAST IPSEC</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>The new "fast ipsec" implementation has insufficient documentation
    (man pages, release notes), and this would be highly desirable to
    have before 5.0-RELEASE.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>Race conditions in truss</td>
  <td>Errata candidate</td>
  <td>&a.robert;</td>
  <td>Truss appears to contain a race condition during the start-up of
    debugging, which can result in truss failing to attach to the process
    before it exits.  The symptom is that truss reports that it cannot
    open the procfs node supporting the process being debugged.  A bug
    also appears to exist where in truss will hang if execve() returns
    ENOENT.  A further race appears to exist in which truss will return
    "PIOCWAIT: Input/output error" occasionally on startup.  The fix
    for this sufficiently changes process execution handling that we
    will defer the fix to post-5.0 and consider this errata.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>Documentation rottage: S/Key</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>We now use OPIE instead of S/Key.  The handbook doesn't know
    that yet.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>Documentation wanted: gdbe</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>&a.chris;</td>
  <td>5.0 includes GDBE, supporting encryption of swap and storage.
    It would be nice if that was documented in the handbook.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>iir driver fails to probe disks</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>During the install, the iir controller appears to correctly
    probe, but finds no disk devices.  The card in question is an
    Intel srcu32 RAID controller with 32Mb RAM, Firmware revision
    2.33.01.  Direct access to real iir hardware for SCSI
    developers would be very helpful in resolving this problem.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>mly driver hangs during install</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>&a.scottl;, &a.jeff;</td>
  <td>Hangs have been reported during the 5.0 snapshot install when
    installing to mly supported RAID arrays.  The same array appears
    to work fine with 4.7-RELEASE.  The card in question is a Mylex
    AcceleRAID 170, 32 Mb RAM, Firmware revision 7.01-00.  This is
    believed to be the same problem as described in PR 45383.</td>
  </tr>

</table>

<h3>Areas requiring immediate testing due to 5.0 changes</h3>

<table class="tblbasic">
  <tr><th>Issue</th><th>Status</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Description</th>
      </tr>

  <tr>
  <td>if_ie, if_le, if_wl network device drivers</td>
  <td>--</td>
  <td>&a.sam;</td>
  <td>Changes made to the ethernet driver interfaces required sweeping
    API changes across all ethernet device drivers.  While these
    changes are largely mechanical, they were not tested for three less
    frequently used interface drivers: if_ie, if_le, and if_wl.  They
    each require testing (and probably fixing) prior to 5.0-RELEASE.
    If you have access to devices that use these drivers, please perform
    local testing and provide feedback to Sam Leffler.</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>No console (term) if smbus is enable in the kernel</td>
    <td>--</td>
    <td>--</td>
    <td>There are reports that kernels build with smbus, viapm, and smb
      devices may not properly probe and support the system console
      following boot.</td>
  </tr>

</table>

<h3>Known Issues with 5.0R-RC1 / i386</h3>
<table class="tblbasic">
  <tr><th>Issue</th><th>Status</th><th>Responsible</th><th>Description</th>
      </tr>

  <tr>
    <td>KDE does not install from ISO</td>
    <td>In Progress</td>
    <td>&a.murray;</td>
    <td>The kde meta-package is not included on the ISO, but many of
      the component kde packages are, so sysinstall gets confused and
      installs kde-icontheme instead (more correct behavior would be to
      fall back to kdebase if kde package is not present).</td>
  </tr>

</table>

  </body>
</html>
