<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<foilgroup>
  <foil><title>Who uses FreeBSD?</title>

    <para>FreeBSD is used by many of the worlds largest corporations,
      and busiest Internet sites.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Yahoo!, Apache, Sony Japan, Netcraft, Weathernews,
        Supervalue.</listitem>

      <listitem>Apple chose FreeBSD over Linux as the Unix core for
        Mac OS X.</listitem>

      <listitem>According to Netcraft, nearly 2.5 million active sites
        use FreeBSD as a network server -- about one million more than Red Hat
        Linux<footnote><ulink
        url="http://www.techworld.com/opsys/news/index.cfm?newsid=1908"/>
        </footnote><footnote><ulink
        url="http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/article.php/3367381"/>
        </footnote>.</listitem>

      <listitem>In the last year alone, about one million new FreeBSD
        hosts were counted by Netcraft, an incredible growth rate
        despite more media attention for Linux.</listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </foil>

  <foil><title>FreeBSD in the Banking Industry</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>Several of the largest commercial banks in the world
        are using FreeBSD in their processing of business to business
        transactions.</listitem>

      <listitem>Combined, these systems process about 1.5 trillion
	U.S. dollars per year and growing.  They are using X11,
	Apache, jails, perl, and a lot of other free
	software.</listitem>

      <listitem>Factors that help:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>stability</listitem>

	  <listitem>source availability for helping understand and fix
	    problems that occur (sometimes having the source to the
	    system helps you understand why your application does not
	    do what you expect..)</listitem>


	  <listitem>Good performance</listitem>
	  <listitem>Easy hardware upgrade paths</listitem>
	  <listitem>PC hardware sometimes is less perfect, but at PC
	    hardware prices, hot spares are practical.</listitem>

	  <listitem>The application is spread over many servers.
	    Need more power in one part?  Add more Freebsd boxes.</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </foil>


  <foil><title>FreeBSD used for Internet Infrastructure</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>BSD has existed since the last 1970's and was the testbed
        and reference implementation for TCP/IP.</listitem>

      <listitem>The Internet Software Consortium (ISC) uses FreeBSD
        exclusively for f-root domain servers (in 21 cities now,
        usually with 3 servers per city).</listitem>

      <listitem>Modern FreeBSD is extremely refined and
        mature.</listitem>

      <listitem>FreeBSD consistently placed at the top of the "uptime"
        lists produced by Netcraft to measure the stability of the
        world's busiest websites.</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </foil>
</foilgroup>