<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<foilgroup>
  <foil><title>Who Uses FreeBSD?</title>

    <para>FreeBSD is used by many of the world's largest corporations,
      and busiest Internet sites.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Yahoo!, Apache, Sony Japan, Netcraft, Weathernews,
        Supervalue.</listitem>

      <listitem>Apple chose FreeBSD over Linux as the Unix core for
        Mac OS X.</listitem>

      <listitem>According to Netcraft, nearly 2.5 million active sites
        use FreeBSD as a network server -- about one million more than Red Hat
        Linux<footnote><ulink
        url="http://www.techworld.com/opsys/news/index.cfm?newsid=1908"/>
        </footnote><footnote><ulink
        url="http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/article.php/3367381"/>
        </footnote>.</listitem>

      <listitem>In the last year alone, about one million new FreeBSD
        hosts were counted by Netcraft, an incredible growth rate
        despite more media attention towards Linux.</listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </foil>

  <foil><title>FreeBSD in the Banking Industry</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>Several of the largest commercial banks in the world
        are using FreeBSD in their processing of business to business
        transactions.</listitem>

      <listitem>Combined, these systems process about 1.5 trillion
	U.S. dollars per year and growing.  They are using X11,
	Apache, jails, Perl, and a lot of other free
	software.</listitem>

      <listitem>Factors that help:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>Stability</listitem>

	  <listitem>Source availability for helping understand and fix
	    problems that occur (having the source to the
	    system helps you to understand why your application does not
	    do what you expect)</listitem>

	  <listitem>Good performance</listitem>

	  <listitem>Easy hardware upgrade paths</listitem>

	  <listitem>The application is spread over many servers.
	    Need more power in one part?  Add more FreeBSD boxes.</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<para>PC hardware sometimes is less than perfect, but at PC
	  hardware prices, hot spares are practical.</para>
        </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </foil>


  <foil><title>FreeBSD Used for Internet Infrastructure</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>BSD has existed since the late 1970's and was the testbed
        and reference implementation for TCP/IP.</listitem>

      <listitem>The Internet Software Consortium (ISC) uses FreeBSD
        exclusively for f-root domain servers (in 21 cities now,
        usually with 3 servers per city).</listitem>

      <listitem>Modern FreeBSD is extremely refined and
        mature.</listitem>

      <listitem>FreeBSD consistently places at the top of the "uptime"
        lists produced by Netcraft to measure the stability of the
        world's busiest websites.</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </foil>

  <foil><title>Embedded Uses of FreeBSD</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>FreeBSD is frequently used as a platform for embedded
        networking devices, including products from IBM, Inktomi,
        Juniper Networks, GTA, and Network Alchemy - a Nokia
        Company. <footnote><ulink
	url="http://www.hyperchip.com/Coverage/ICD/router_makers_speak_out.htm"/>
	</footnote></listitem>

      <listitem>The Weather Channel uses FreeBSD to do realtime
	audio/video presentation in hundreds of locations across the
	US serving content to millions of cable and satellite
	customers.</listitem>

      <listitem>The BSD license makes these commercial embedded
        applications possible.</listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </foil>
</foilgroup>
