<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->
<itemizedlist xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <listitem>
      <para>J&uuml;rgen Lock (2006 - 2015; RIP 2015)</para>
      <para>J&uuml;rgen made a number of contributions to &os;,
	including work on libvirt, the graphics stack, and QEMU.
	J&uuml;rgen's contributions and helpfulness were appreciated by
	people around the world.  That work continues to improve the
	lives of thousands every day.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.alexbl.email; (2006 - 2011; RIP 2012)</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://www.legacy.com/obituaries/sfgate/obituary.aspx?pid=159801494">Alexander</link>
	  was best known as a major contributor to &os;'s <application>Python</application> ports
	  and a founding member of &a.python; as well as his work on
	  <application>XMMS2</application>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.jb.email; (1997 - 2009; RIP 2009)</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://hub.opensolaris.org/bin/view/Community+Group+ogb/In+Memoriam">John</link>
	  made major contributions to FreeBSD, the best known of which
	  is the import of the &man.dtrace.1; code.  John's unique sense
	  of humor and plain-spokenness either ruffled feathers or
	  made him quick friends. At the end of his life, he had
	  moved to a rural area and was attempting to live with
	  as minimal impact to the planet as possible, while at
	  the same time still working in the high-tech area.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.jmz.email; (1994 - 2009; RIP 2009)</para>
      <para>
	<link xlink:href="http://www.obs-besancon.fr/article.php3?id_article=323">Jean-Marc</link>
	was an astrophysicist who made important contributions to the modeling
	of the atmospheres of both planets and comets at
	<link xlink:href="http://www.obs-besancon.fr/">l'Observatoire de Besan&ccedil;on</link>
	in Besan&ccedil;on, France.  While there, he participated in the
	conception and construction of the Vega tricanal spectrometer
	that studied Halley's Comet.  He had also been a long-time
	contributor to FreeBSD.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.itojun.email; (1997 - 2001; RIP 2008)</para>
      <para>Known to everyone as
        <link xlink:href="http://astralblue.livejournal.com/350702.html">itojun</link>,
	Jun-ichiro Hagino was a core researcher at the
	<link xlink:href="http://www.kame.net/">KAME Project</link>,
	which aimed to provide IPv6 and IPsec technology in freely
	redistributable form.   Much of this code was incorporated
	into FreeBSD.  Without his efforts, the state of IPv6 on the
	Internet would be much different.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.cg.email; (1999 - 2005; RIP 2005)</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://www.dbsi.org/cam/">Cameron</link>
	was a unique individual who contributed to the project
	despite serious physical disabilities.  He was responsible
	for a complete rewrite of our sound system during the
	late 1990s.  Many of those who corresponded with him had
	no idea of his limited mobility, due to his cheerful
	spirit and willingness to help others.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&a.alane.email; (2002 - 2003; RIP 2003)</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://freebsd.kde.org/memoriam/alane.php">Alan</link>
	was a major contributor to the KDE on FreeBSD group.  In addition,
	he maintained many other difficult and time-consuming ports such
	as <application>autoconf</application>,
	<application>CUPS</application>, and <application>python</application>.
	Alan's path was not an easy one but his passion for FreeBSD, and
	dedication to programming excellence, won him many friends.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
