<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Commercial Gallery//EN"
                         "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/gallery.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<entries>
    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">
      $FreeBSD$
    </cvs:keyword>

  <entry id="ABMX">
    <name>ABMX Servers</name>
    <url>http://www.abmx.com/</url>
    <description>
      ABMX based in California, offers custom-build Rackmount Servers
      optimized for FreeBSD.  We can custom build just about anything.
      If it can be configured, we will configure it.  Please contact our
      friendly engineers at 1-800-711-1788 or visit <a
      href="http://www.abmx.com/">http://www.abmx.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ACNODES">
    <name>Acnodes Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.acnodes.com/</url>
    <description>
      <p>Acnodes Corporation provides FreeBSD and Linux-based computer
	for customers in the industrial control, automation industries
	and the military.  Our rack mount computers, embedded systems
	and Panel PCs are fully configurable and support FreeBSD, Linux
	or any other operating system.</p>

      <p>Our product line includes <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/Rackmount-computer.htm">Rackmount
	computers</a> (1U to 4U rack-mount ready computers, standard ATX
	or SBC systems), <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/Panel-PC.htm">Panel PCs</a> (panel
	mount ready touch screen computer), <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/Fanless-embedded-microbox-system.htm">
	Embedded system boxes</a> (fan less all-in-one computer integrated
	into a rugged metal compact-size micro box), <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/Monitor-keyboard-drawer.htm">Monitor
	keyboard drawers</a> (space-saving 1U/2U control console, optional
	for Cat6, IP KVM switch) and <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/Rackmount-LCD-monitor.htm">Rackmount
	LCD monitors</a> (rack-mount ready LCD monitors up to 20-inch).</p>

      <p>Our product line configurations are illustrated on our <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com">website</a>.  However, most of the
	commercial and industrial computers are custom built to your
	exact requirements.  <a
	href="http://www.acnodes.com/zebpage_contactus.htm">Contact</a>
	us via e-mail or telephone to discover how we can provide you
	with the equipment you need for your specific needs.</p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ActiveWire">
    <name>ActiveWire Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.ActiveWireInc.com/</url>
    <description>
      ActiveWire Inc. provides an extremely flexible, USB-based I/O board
      that connects to buttons, switches, and LEDs, providing a simple API
      to read and write to the I/O pins on the board. The USB port is
      supported in <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD 4.0</a>
      or later.  An additional EZ USB chip firmware downloader is
      available in the Ports Collection.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ASA">
    <name>ASA Computers</name>
    <url>http://www.asacomputers.com/</url>
    <description>
      ASA Computers offers a wide range of performance-oriented servers,
      workstations, and networking products. We are experienced in quality
      configuration and support of FreeBSD, Linux, and other operating
      systems. Multiple-OS experience and knowledge are our strengths. We
      resell a variety of communication and networking products, including
      3COM, Cisco, Cyclades, DIGI, Livingston, and U.S. Robotics. Please
      take a look at the pre-configured systems on our web page. Contact us
      at <a href="mailto:unix@asacomputers.com">unix@asacomputers.com</a>
      to configure them your own way or if you have questions or comments.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="aspensystemsdirect">
    <name>Aspen Systems Direct</name>
    <url>http://www.aspensystemsdirect.com/</url>
    <description>
      Aspen Systems is based out of Wheat Ridge, CO and has been in
      business for over 30 years offering customizable rackmount servers
      and workstations featuring FreeBSD and other open source operating
      systems.  We also provide custom turn-key High Performance Computing
      Clusters for government, universities, and corporations throughout
      the world.  Please contact a sales engineer today at <a
      href="tel:8882271286">1-888-227-1286</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.aspensystemsdirect.com">website</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="atto">
    <name>ATTO Technology</name>
    <url>http://www.attotech.com</url>
    <description>
      For over 25 years, ATTO Technology, Inc. has been a global leader in
      storage and network connectivity and infrastructure solutions for
      data-intensive computing environments. ATTO manufactures Host Bus
      Adapters, RAID adapters, network adapters, RAID storage controllers,
      Thunderbolt-enabled Desklink devices, bridges, switches and software.
      ATTO's Celerity 16Gb Fibre Channel adapters, ExpressSAS 12Gb SAS/SATA
      HBAs and SAN Storage Controllers all support &os; 9.3 and 10.x operating
      systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="catpipe">
    <name>catpipe Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.catpipe.net/</url>
    <description>
      catpipe Systems ApS provides managed services and support contracts
      for FreeBSD, implemented on rackmountable servers preloaded with
      FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoreSystems">
    <name>Core Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.coresystemsusa.com/</url>
    <description>
      Core Systems is the market leader in <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/industrial-computers.php">rackmount
      computers</a> and <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/industrial-lcd-displays.php">rackmount
      LCD displays</a> and supports multiple versions of FreeBSD.  We
      manufacture a complete line of <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/rackmount-industrial-computer-chassis.php">
      industrial computer chassis</a>, <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/industrial-single-board-computer.php">
      single board computer</a> and <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/passive-backplanes.php">passive
      backplane</a> <a
      href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/atx-eatx-systems.php">rackmount
      systems</a>.  We design and manufacture all of our 1U and 4U
      rack mounted systems in-house to maintain strict revision control over
      our entire product line.  Our systems engineering design and
      development staff is second to none in the rackmount industry.
      Please visit our <a href="http://www.coresystemsusa.com/">website</a>
      for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoyotePointSystems">
    <name>Coyote Point Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.coyotepoint.com/</url>
    <description>
      Coyote Point Systems offers the <a
      href="http://www.coyotepoint.com/products.htm">Equalizer</a> Load
      Balancing Appliance. Equalizer distributes client UDP/TCP requests to
      multiple server machines and includes load balancing, server failure
      detection/correction, and an easy-to-use administrative interface.
      Capable of handling over 20,000 HTTP GET operations per minute,
      Equalizer enhances the Scalability, Availability and Manageability of
      any server cluster. Equalizer works with all standard protocols,
      including: HTTP, FTP, POP, SMTP, DNS, etc. Equalizer is based on the
      FreeBSD kernel.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DAVICOM">
    <name>DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.davicom.com.tw/</url>
    <description>
      DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc. designs, develops, and markets
      cost-effective integrated circuit (IC) solutions for mainstream
      networking and communications applications. DAVICOM is one of the
      leading suppliers of Local Area Network (LAN) and Wide Area Network
      (WAN) chip sets to international original equipment manufactures
      (OEMs) of networking and communications equipment. <p> The current
      products of DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc. that will support the FreeBSD
      driver are DM9102 (10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet single chip), DM9102A
      (3.3 volts Low Power10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet single chip), DM9101
      (10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet PHY chip, included into DM9102 single
      chip), DM9131 (3.3 volts Low Power10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet PHY
      chip, included into DM9102A single chip) and DM9801 (1M8 Home PNA PHY
      chip). </p> <p> Please visit <a href="http://www.davicom.com.tw">our
      web site</a> for more information about our company. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmergingTechnologies">
    <name>Emerging Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.etinc.com/</url>
    <description>
      Emerging Technologies, Inc. has high-speed serial-communications
      adapters, allowing FreeBSD systems to connect directly to leased
      lines at speeds from 56k to T1/E1. ET drivers support up to 16 T1/E1
      lines on a single FreeBSD-based PC. The adapters include a complete
      set of drivers and utilities that allow a FreeBSD machine to
      communicate directly with virtually any IP router via synchronous
      PPP, Frame Relay, X.25, and directly to Cisco brand routers with
      Cisco serial encapsulation. Full documentation and support are
      included. Hardware choices are available for both ISA and PCI buses,
      ranging from an economical single-port ISA adapter to a four T1/E1
      port PCI card with four dedicated 25MHz processors on-board. To
      contact Emerging Technologies, send E-mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@etinc.com">info@etinc.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EMT">
    <name>EMT</name>
    <url>http://www.emt.co.jp/</url>
    <description>
      Based in Japan, EMT offers tailor-made Servers and Workstations
      optimized for FreeBSD.  We provide high-quality and high-reliable
      systems by carrying out a thorough examination and offer
      Hardware Warranty Support.  Please contact us via <a
      href="mailto:sales@emt.co.jp">email</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.emt.co.jp/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EssenzConsulting">
    <name>Essenz Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.essenz.com</url>
    <description>
      Essenz Consulting is a leading provider of high-performance rackmount
      server equipment. All of our <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/servers/index.html">servers</a> feature
      dual processor capability, dual onboard networking, high-capacity
      memory support, and integrated video. From 1U Hot-Swap SCSI systems
      to 2U Hot-Swap 64-bit SCSI RAID with 2x300W Hot-Swap Power Supply,
      all Essenz Servers can be custom configured with immediate online
      pricing. For more information, visit us <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com">online</a> or call our 24/7 Sales and
      Support department at 1-800-248-1736.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FreedomTechnologies">
    <name>Freedom Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.freedomtc.com</url>
    <description>
      Freedom Technologies offers you a wide range of Premium Quality Servers
      in Rackmount and Tower configurations and, High-Performance Raid Systems.
      All our Servers will run FreeBSD out of the box (i386 and AMD/64).  We
      offer several <a
	href="http://www.freedomtc.com/nebs3.php">NEBS Level-3 1U and 2U</a>
      Rackmount Servers with standard A.C. power or with -48 Volt D.C. Power.
      We offer several <a
	href="http://www.freedomtc.com/short_depth_servers.php">short depth 1U
	and 2U Rackmount Servers</a>.  You will find a good selection of
      External Direct and Network Attached <a
	href="http://www.freedomtc.com/raid.php">RAID Enclosure Systems</a>
      from 8-Bay to 24-Bay.  Our focus is providing you with premium quality,
      trouble free Servers and RAID Storage Systems at best possible prices.
      <a href="http://www.freedomtc.com/">Visit us online</a> and get pricing
      instantly or call us toll-free 1.877.963.1900.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Gallantry">
    <name>Gallantry Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.gallantry.com/</url>
    <description>
      Gallantry Technologies Inc. offers a business broadband gateway for
      small- to medium-sized businesses. Our products are focused on
      offering an easy-to-use product that provides multiple services
      routing, firewall, e-mail, web server, DHCP, NAT, FTP, DNS, and print
      server. All these features can be accessed via an easy-to-use web
      interface. The GallantWEB-100 is an affordable and easy-to-use
      business broadband gateway that is ideal for connecting small and
      medium offices to the Internet via any broadband connection including
      xDSL, Cable, Frame Relay/T1, or ISDN. The GallantWEB-200 is the
      industry's first business broadband gateway to include a built-in
      SDSL router. This innovative one-box solution makes it easy for DSL
      service providers to deploy and manage.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GenstorSystems">
    <name>Genstor Systems, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.genstor.com/</url>
    <description>
      Genstor Systems specializes in systems customized for FreeBSD.  You
      will find Storage (like multi-TB storage using SATA disks) and
      Server options, built around quality hardware.  We also build
      clusters and provide OEM services for appliance integration.
      Genstor keeps abreast of drivers and bugs so you do not have to.
      We customize systems around Linux, and x86 Solaris as well.
      Contact us via email at
      <a href="mailto:sales@genstor.com">sales@genstor.com</a>
      or call us at (877)25-SERVERS and test our capabilities.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GND">
    <name>GND Distribution, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.gnd.com/</url>
    <description>
      GND Distribution, Ltd., a London, UK-based company, specializes in
      bespoke computer systems for FreeBSD and Linux. All GND computer
      systems are built to order, using only top-quality components. Our
      build quality is second to none. Systems are supplied configured and
      optimized to our customer's requirements. We also supply a large
      range of system components, including ASUSTeK mainboards, which are
      popular within the FreeBSD and Linux communities.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Highpoint">
    <name>HighPoint Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.highpoint-tech.com/</url>
    <description>
      HighPoint sells SATA RAID Controller products which are supported
      natively by FreeBSD 6.3 and 7.0.  Drivers for older versions of
      FreeBSD are available on their website.  HighPoint is specialized
      in providing SATA RAID solutions, including an Enterprise Series,
      Value Line Series and Upgrade Series of RAID controllers.  Their
      motto is "One Size Does Not Fit All".
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="INetU">
    <name>INetU Dedicated Managed Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.inetu.net/</url>
    <description>
      INetU Dedicated Managed Hosting are one of the top rated hosting
      firms focused on dedicated managed hosting, INetU provides managed
      dedicated FreeBSD servers, along with firewalls, load balancing,
      advanced monitoring and data backup services. They offer more free
      tech support than most other hosts and have a lucrative partner
      program for consultants and developers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IronSystems">
    <name>Iron Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.ironsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      Iron Systems, located in San Jose, California, is a provider of
      high-density rack-mount Internet systems, low cost hosting solutions
      and OEM integration services. System solutions are either
      built-to-order iServers with custom-configured hardware, OS, kernel
      and applications; or a set of pre-configured network infrastructure
      iEngines and iClusters, specially designed to deliver a dedicated
      application. Iron Systems backs all solutions with world-class
      technical support for FreeBSD and Linux. Our team at an average
      has over 10 years of experience in building BSD-based systems. We
      understand that our servers run your mission-critical applications -
      that's why we use only the highest quality components and test all
      systems in advance. We are confident that you will appreciate our
      approach. Give us an opportunity to serve you! Please send us email
      at <a href="mailto:info@ironsystems.com">info@ironsystems.com</a> or
      call 1-800-921-IRON.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ItautecPhilco">
    <name>Itautec Philco</name>
    <url>http://www.itautec.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      Itautec Philco is one of Brazil's leading IT products manufacturers
      and one the leaders in the Brazilian Market and significant market
      share in Portugal, Uruguay and Argentina. Products such as the
      Infoway and the InfoServer are fully compatible with FreeBSD, Linux,
      and other Operating Systems. Itautec Philco also manufactures Banking
      and Retail Automation products, as well as Consumer Electronics
      products. We provide complete solutions for our customers, from
      Infrastructure (such as LAN) to software applications, to Web
      development and hosting services, to call-center services.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="KYTEX">
    <name>KYTEX Computers Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.kytex.bg/</url>
    <description>
      KYTEX Computers Ltd offers K-SERVER family of pre-installed xBSD and
      Linux Internet appliances. K-SERVER product line include small
      footprint all-in-one solutions for small to middle networks and
      rackmount servers for ISP/ASP and corporate networks. All-in-one
      solutions provides Internet access via dial-up, leased lines, xDSL,
      wireless technology and offer filesharing for Windows and MacOS
      workstations across the network at no additional cost, users WEB-,
      Mail-, Firewall-, DNS-server applications started and partially
      configured for easy integration in any existing networks. K-SERVER
      setup and management is very simple - just start any browser on your
      workstation and follow the setup instructions and menus. If you have
      any questions or proposals, please e-mail us.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MOXA">
    <name>MOXA</name>
    <url>http://www.moxa.com/</url>
    <description>
      MOXA makes attractively priced multi-port serial cards which are
      compatible with FreeBSD's <em>sio</em> serial driver. The C104 / C168
      family of 2/4/8 serial port cards features custom ASIC design, speeds
      up to 921.6Kbps, surge protection, independent and
      software-configurable I/O ports and IRQs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netgate">
    <name>Netgate</name>
    <url>http://store.netgate.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netgate is a high quality communications appliance manufacturer
      that designs highly configurable computers engineered for
      low-power, high-throughput, dependable deployments.  We offer
      quick deployment with off-the-shelf systems, specialized custom
      product solutions and an end-to-end OEM service program for
      large customers.

      <p>Netgate directly supports Open Source software and Open
	Source hardware projects by providing management, engineering
	and support resources for the pfSense project.</p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetWolves">
    <name>NetWolves Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.netwolves.com</url>
    <description>
      NetWolves Corporation produces the FoxBox line of Multi-services
      Internet Communications Gateway systems. These Internet Access
      Devices offer a three stage firewall, unlimited e-mail, site hosting,
      filtered browsing, web and DNS caching, DHCP for ease of set up, file
      sharing/serving, e-mail archiving, and a series of productivity
      enhancing reports - cost effectively. The FoxBox OS is based on
      FreeBSD. Bandwidth options range from V.90 modems to T-1, cable
      modems, and DSL speeds. The FoxBox provides Internet access for
      between 8 and 1000 users on one or more LANs and is available
      internationally through our VAR reseller network. Visit <a
      href="http://www.netwolves.com/">our site</a> for more information or
      contact us by <a href="mailto:sales@netwolves.com">email</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="iXsystems">
    <name>iXsystems</name>
    <url>http://www.iXsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      iXsystems (formerly OffMyServer) provides FreeBSD and Linux-based
      Internet infrastructure-grade rackmount servers, network appliances,
      enterprise blade servers, and storage products to a global market.
      We use only the best quality components and do the required testing
      in advance - knowing that you are going to run your mission-critical
      applications on our servers.  We are confident that you will appreciate
      our approach - give us an opportunity to server you!  Send us an email
      at <a href="mailto:info@iXsystems.com">info@iXsystems.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OrbitMicro">
    <name>Orbit Micro</name>
    <url>http://www.orbitmicro.com/</url>
    <description>
      Orbit Micro is a system integrator of servers, workstations,
      industrial computers and networking products.  Our application
      design approach allows us to maximize performance for your
      computing needs.  Our products line also includes a vareity of
      computer components and peripherals as well as software.  Contact
      us at <a href="mailto:sales@orbitmicro.com">
	sales@orbitmicro.com</a> to speak to a sales engineer or if you
      have questions or comments.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PCW">
    <name>PCW Microsystems, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmount.com/</url>
    <description>
      PCW Microsystems, Inc. offers rackmount workstations and servers,
      optimized for the FreeBSD operating system. We carry full line of
      rackmount chassis, RAID, WAN, and LAN products for FreeBSD OS. Please
      <a href="http://www.rackmount.com/">visit our web site</a> for more
      information or send us an e-mail at <a
      href="mailto:sales@pcwnet.com">sales@pcwnet.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PSSCLabs">
    <name>PSSC Labs</name>
    <url>http://www.pssclabs.com/</url>
    <description>
      PSSC Labs provides custom configured computer solutions to meet any
      budget or specification. Visit our website to build your computer
      just the way you want it, including hard-drive partitioning and
      operating system setup.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="psychsoftpc">
    <name>Psychsoftpc</name>
    <url>http://www.psychsoftpc.com/</url>
    <description>
      Psychsoftpc is a manufacturer of high performance computers,
      workstations and clusters with Linux or FreeBSD preinstalled upon
      request.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RandDAssociates">
    <name>R and D Associates, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.RnDAssociates.com/</url>
    <description>
      R and D Associates, Inc. developed ServeTheWeb.com utilizing FreeBSD
      running Apache. We employed consulting services from <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">Poul-Henning Kamp</a> to develop our
      Virtual Server solution (which is now available in <a
      href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD</a> 4.0). <p> <a
      href="http://ServeTheWeb.com/">ServeTheWeb.com</a> is our System
      Admin level of Virtual Servers. Please visit <a
      href="http://www.ServeTheWeb.com/">www.ServeTheWeb.com</a> for
      additional information on this product. </p> <p> R and D Associates,
      Inc. is an application development firm, specializing in
      client/server designs. We use FreeBSD, running Apache and utilizing
      PHP's and MySQL (As well as NT with ASP's and SQL/Access). </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PerleSpecialix">
    <name>Perle Specialix</name>
    <url>http://www.perle.com/</url>
    <description>
      Perle Specialix makes a wide variety of multi-port async serial
      expansion products. The ISA, EISA, and PCI SI/XIO host cards work
      under FreeBSD, using the <em>si</em> driver.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Stallion">
    <name>Stallion Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.stallion.com/</url>
    <description>
      Stallion Technologies, Inc. offers a range of multiport serial boards
      for the ISA, EISA, MCA and PCI buses. Although Stallion does not
      officially support drivers for FreeBSD, there is an unsupported,
      freely available driver available from their <a
      href="ftp://ftp.stallion.com/drivers/unsupported/FreeBSD/stalbsd-2.0.0.tar.gz">FTP site</a>.
      This driver supports the Stallion
      <em>EasyIO</em>, <em>EasyConnection 8/32</em> and
      <em>EasyConnection 8/64</em> PCI range of multiport boards.
      For local pricing and availability information, contact Stallion
      via their <a href="http://www.stallion.com/">WWW page</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="StoreAnyWhere">
    <name>StoreAnyWhere.com</name>
    <url>http://StoreAnyWhere.com/</url>
    <description>
      StoreAnyWhere.com offers a wide range of high-performance and
      cost-effective quad- and dual-processor servers, workstations, and
      networking products with FreeBSD and Linux as their operating
      systems. Just go to our website for servers in a variety of
      configurations or custom-made systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SWTechnology">
    <name>SW Technology</name>
    <url>http://freebsd.swt.com/</url>
    <description>
      SW Technology offers quality Pentium machines with FreeBSD
      pre-installed.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Synetic">
    <name>Synetic, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.synetic.net/</url>
    <description>
      Synetic Inc. is a Canadian and North American distributor for
      IDE-to-IDE, SCSI-to-IDE and SCSI-to-SCSI RAID controllers, supporting
      the FreeBSD platform. Our products can be found at <a
      href="http://www.synetic.net/prodman.htm">www.synetic.net/prodman.htm</a>
      or <a href="http://www.synetic.net/prodspec.htm">
      www.synetic.net/prodspec.htm</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Zantech">
    <name>Zantech KVM Australia</name>
    <url>http://www.zantech.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Zantech KVM Australia is an Australian distributor of FreeBSD
      compatible KVM switches, KVM over IP products and serial console
      terminal servers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Znyx">
    <name>Znyx</name>
    <url>http://www.znyx.com/</url>
    <description>
      Znyx Corporation specializes in high-availability, high-performance,
      single and multi-channel Fast Ethernet adapters for PCI, CompactPCI,
      and PCI Mezzanine Connector (PMC). FreeBSD, Linux, QNX, NetWare,
      OS/2, and SCO Unixware are supported on virtually all products.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NCSTechnologies">
    <name>NCS Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.ncst.com/</url>
    <description>
      NCS Technologies offers "NCS Swift Appliance Partner Program
      (NCSAPP)" for Independent Software Vendors (ISVs) and other OEMs.
      Under this program, NCS develops "turn-key" server appliances for its
      ISV partners by bundling their appliance software with its own
      hardware platforms. These appliance hardware platforms are built
      using the latest industry standard chipsets and components and can
      run FreeBSD based applications.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ColoMachine">
    <name>ColoMachine</name>
    <url>http://www.colomachine.com/</url>
    <description>
      ColoMachine offers high quality sub-$500 1U rackmount servers
      optimized for the FreeBSD operating system.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="rackmountnet">
    <name>RackmountNet</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmountnet.com/</url>
    <description>
      RackmountNet offers a full line of 1U, 2U, 3U, 4U, 5U, 7U 19"
      rackmount chassis and servers for industrial mission critical
      applications.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="eracks">
    <name>eRacks Open Source Systems</name>
    <url>http://eracks.com/</url>
    <description>
      eRacks Open Source Systems is a leading provider of open source
      solutions. The company manufactures rackmount computer servers,
      specializes in custom-designed systems, and
      offers a wide array of services including open source enterprise
      migration, security, and network architecture design. eRacks
      offers a full range of open source operating systems configured
      on its systems, including FreeBSD. For more information, contact
      eRacks at <a href="mailto:info@eracks.com">info@eracks.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pyramidusa">
    <name>Pyramid computer</name>
    <url>http://www.pyramid-usa.com</url>
    <description>
      Pyramid Computer is a leading supplier of custom branded appliance
      solutions to ISVs and OEMs.  We will enable you to deliver an
      appliance solution that meets your exact needs.  We offer a
      complete range of design, manufacturing and logistics services
      that allow you to effortlessly deliver a superior product to
      customers on a world wide basis, and focus your attention on core
      business activities.  We are experts in FreeBSD, as well as Linux
      based appliances.  Most of all, Pyramid Computer is a service
      oriented supplier.  We distinguish ourselves by our ability to
      craft programs to the unique needs of your business, and to meet
      your expectations in all our endeavors.  Please contact us to
      learn more about how we can help you to achieve your business
      objectives.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="rackmountmart">
    <name>Synergy Global Inc</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmountmart.com</url>
    <description>
      We are a FreeBSD and Linux Rackmount LCD Monitor keyboard Drawer,
      Rackmount chassis, server manufacturer and distributor.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="42u">
    <name>42U</name>
    <url>http://www.42u.com/</url>
    <description>
      42U is specialized in providing remote access solutions including
      FreeBSD compatible serial console servers, KVM switches, KVM over
      IP products, remote power reboot, and environmental monitoring.
      For more information, contact <a href="mailto:info@42u.com">
	info@42u.com</a> or visit <a href="http://www.42u.com/">
	www.42u.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="kvmonline">
    <name>KVM Switches Online</name>
    <url>http://www.kvm-switches-online.com</url>
    <description>
      KVM Switches Online is a leading provider of server room
      solutions featuring server management &amp; server space
      optimization solutions utilizing FreeBSD compatible serial
      console servers and KVM switching products.  For more
      information, contact <a
	href="mailto:info@kvm-switches-online.com">
	info@kvm-switches-online.com</a> or visit <a
	href="http://www.kvm-switches-online.com">
	www.kvm-switches-online.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="serverrack">
    <name>Server Racks Online</name>
    <url>http://www.server-rack-online.com</url>
    <description>
      Server Racks Online computer rack superstore.  At Server Racks
      Online we also allow you to easily configure our computer racks,
      server cabinets, and accessories to suit your exact requirements
      and your FreeBSD needs.  Server Rack Online strives to provide a
      wide selection of server rack products and accessories for every
      solution. For more information, contact
      <a href="mailto:infor@server-rack-online.com?subject=FreeBSD Site">
        info@server-rack-online.com</a> or visit
      <a href="http://www.server-rack-online.com">
        www.server-rack-online.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ChassisPlans">
    <name>Chassis Plans Rackmount Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.chassis-plans.com</url>
    <description>
      <p>Chassis Plans is a recognized leader in manufacturing fully configured
	turn-key industrial <a
	  href="http://www.chassis-plans.com">rackmount systems</a> that support
	FreeBSD for the industrial, rugged, and military markets.  We manufacture
	1U to 6U ATX and <a
	  href="http://www.chassis-plans.com/single_board_computers.html">Single Board Computer systems</a>
	tailored exactly to customer application requirements.  We also
	manufacture a full line of industrial <a
	  href="http://www.chassis-plans.com/rackmount_keyboards.html">rackmount LCD keyboard drawers</a>
	and <a
	  href="http://www.chassis-plans.com/rackmount_keyboards.html">panel mount LCD monitors.</a></p>

      <p>Chassis Plans specializes in long-life product support offering
	unmatched in-house custom chassis design, long-life industrial
	motherboards and SBC's with strict revision control and material
	obsolescence management for trouble free program deployment.  Key
	military customers include companies such as L3, Lockheed, and Northrop
	Grumman.  Notable commercial customers include Siemens, Nikon, and
	General Electric. Chassis Plans' Systems are Engineered to
	Perform!&#8482;</p>

      <p>Our knowledgable sales engineers can be reached at 858-571-4330
	(California, United States) or at <a
	  href="mailto:saleseng@chassisplans.com">saleseng@chassis-plans.com</a>.</p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="servaris">
    <name>Servaris Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.servaris.com</url>
    <description>
      <p>Servaris builds Premium Rack Mount, <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/blade_servers.php" title="Blade
	Servers	with Fail-over and Clustering">Blade Servers</a> and <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/tower_servers.php" title="Tower
	Servers">Tower Servers</a> as well as <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/raid.php" title="RAID Storage
	Subsystems">RAID Storage</a> Subsystems.</p>

      <p>Servaris ProServ <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/1u_rack_server.php" title="FreeBSD
	1U Rack Servers">1U Rack Servers</a> and ProServ <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/2u-rack-server.php" title="FreeBSD
	2U Rack Servers"> 2U Rack Servers</a> and 4U <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/servers_4680.php" title="Quad
	Six-Core Rack Server">High Performance Computing Server</a> are
	all FreeBSD compatible.  Almost all the ProServ Servers have
	lights-out remote management via java enabled web browser.
	Servaris will pre-install FreeBSD AMD/64 or i386 with a Generic
	or fully customized FreeBSD installation.  Servaris <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/blade_servers.php" title="Blade
	Servers	by Servaris">Blade Servers</a> are an 'all in one'
	clustering and fail-over solution with complete remote management
	via any java enabled web browser and feature Intel's latest 5500
	Quad Core Xeon Processors.  <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/raid.php" title="iStor RAID Storage
	Systems"> Servaris iStor RAID Storage</a> Subsystems are 4GB/8GB
	Fibre to SAS/SATA and are available in 12-Bay, 16-Bay and 24-Bay
	Chassis.  asily expandable, simple to maintain and completely
	manageable via web browser.</p>

      <p>Servaris has friendly staff that can answer your questions.
	Please give Servaris a call at 1.877.963.1900 or <a
	href="http://www.servaris.com/contact.php">contact them from
	here</a>.  Servaris will provide you with Superior Quality
	Servers and RAID Systems with excellent Warranties at
	reasonable prices:  "Servaris, Excellence through Passion."</p>
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
