<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD FreeBSD XML Database for Commercial Gallery//EN"
                         "http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/gallery.dtd">
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<entries>
    <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">
      $FreeBSD$
    </cvs:keyword>

  <categories>
    <category id="DATABASE">Databases</category>
    <category id="DEV">Development Tools</category>
    <category id="ECOMMERCE">E-Commerce Solutions and Tools</category>
    <category id="EMAIL">Electronic Mail Software</category>
    <category id="MISC">Miscellaneous</category>
<!--
    <category id="MULTIMEDIA">Multimedia</category>
-->
    <category id="NETWORK">Network Systems and Applications</category>
    <category id="SCIENTIFIC">Scientific and Language Tools</category>
    <category id="SECURITY">Security</category>
    <category id="SYSADMIN">System Administration / ISP</category>
  </categories>

  <entry id="Aestiva" category="DEV">
    <name>Aestiva HTML/OS</name>
    <url>http://www.htmlos.com/</url>
    <description>
      Aestiva HTML/OS is a complete solution for advanced, dynamic web site
      and web software development. It eliminates the need for CGI
      programming and integration tools, includes a built-in database
      engine and tools for packaging and copy-protecting commercial web
      products, and supports over a dozen platforms. Visit <a
      href="http://www.htmlos.com">www.htmlos.com</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aker" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Aker Firewall</name>
    <url>http://www.aker.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      Aker Firewall is a firewall solution which runs on FreeBSD. The
      firewall provides a stateful filtering engine, Network Address
      Translation (NAT), cryptography (with manual key exchange and SKIP),
      automatic responses to pre-configured events, and remote
      administration by a easy-to-use graphical interface which runs on
      many different platforms. For more information, please <a
      href="http://www.aker.com.br/">visit our web site</a> or send a
      e-mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@aker.com.br">info@mail.aker.com.br</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Akopia" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>Akopia</name>
    <url>http://www.akopia.com/</url>
    <description>
      Akopia is the developer of Interchange, the leading open source
      e-commerce platform that runs on FreeBSD and other UNIX Operating
      systems. Interchange offers an extensive feature set including:
      <ul>
	<li>Intuitive content management functionality,
	  enabling business users to easily manage large, complex catalogs.</li>
	<li>Flexible merchandising, maximizing sales through product
	  presentation, cross-sells, up-sells, and promotions.</li>
	<li>Powerful transaction management functionality that handles
	  complex business rules and fully integrates with legacy systems.</li>
	<li>Comprehensive administration and reporting, which keeps business
	  and technical management informed and in control.</li>
	<li>Flexible, extensible architecture, ensuring scalability and providing
	  room to grow.</li>
      </ul>
      Akopia offers professional Interchange support and an array
      of e-commerce professional services. For more information and a free
      download, visit us at <a href="http://www.akopia.com/">www.akopia.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AMSOFT" category="DATABASE">
    <name>AM'SOFT</name>
    <url>http://www.amsoft.ru/</url>
    <description>
      AM'SOFT (Andrew Maltsev's Software) features <a
      href="http://www.amsoft.ru/easysql/">EasySQL</a>, an ODBC-like,
      database-independent C/C++ library. Full source code is available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AstroArch" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>AstroArch Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.astroarch.com/</url>
    <description>
      AstroArch Consulting, Inc. develops and licenses its <em>ISP Billing
      and Tracking System</em> (BATS) for FreeBSD as well as thirteen other
      Operating Systems. For more information, check out <a
      href="http://www.astroarch.com/">www.astroarch.com/</a>, send email
      to <a href="mailto:info@astroarch.com">info@astroarch.com</a>, or
      call +1.512.990.9711.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BSProject" category="MISC">
    <name>BS Project</name>
    <url>http://www.bsproject.net/</url>
    <description>
      BS Project is an outsourcing project. The goal of the project is
      development real-time billing system for VoIP carriers. Our
      flagship product VoIP BS is designed for medium and small sized
      VoIP carriers. VoIP BS is available for FreeBSD and Linux.  For
      further information, please see <a
        href="http://www.bsproject.net/">www.bsproject.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BSRSoft" category="SECURITY">
    <name>BSRSoft LTDA</name>
    <url>http://soft.bsrpar.com/</url>
    <description>
      BSRSoft LTDA is a brazilian open source solutions provider for
      infrastructure and FreeBSD based HPC/HA/scientific computing.  We
      offer <a
      href="http://soft.bsrpar.com/2012/01/o-serverux.html">BSRSoft ServerUX</a>,
      a FreeBSD enterprise distribution for high security and HA needs,
      AI software, securty and integrity software.  For further
      information please visit <a
      href="http://soft.bsrpar.com/">our website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Ballista" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Ballista</name>
    <url>http://www.secnet.com/ballista/</url>
    <description>
      Ballista is a network security auditing tool for evaluation of
      security postures in areas where high assurance levels are critical.
      Ballista is primarily designed to audit the remote security aspects
      of networks and runs quite well under FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BrownBear" category="MISC">
    <name>Brown Bear Software</name>
    <url>http://www.brownbearsw.com</url>
    <description>
      Brown Bear Software produces and supports <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/">Calcium</a>, an
      interactive <b>Web Calendar server</b> you use via your browser.
      Features include: dynamic calendar merging multiple views and
      formats; repeating events, email notification and reminders,
      iCalendar support, Palm Pilot synchronization, color and font
      customization, support for full HTML in event text and calendar
      headers and footers, popup text associated with any event, searching
      &amp; filtering, multi-language support, flexible security model, <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/FeaturesList.html">and
      more</a>. Calcium is very easy to use and fully supported. It runs
      anywhere that supports Perl CGIs; no non-standard Perl modules are
      necessary. A live <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsoftware.com/cgi-bin/Calcium?CalendarName=D
      emo"  >On-Line Demo</a> is available; you can download an <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/download"  >evaluation
      copy</a> (fully functional, but limited to a single calendar), or try
      your own <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/onlineTrial.html">private
      demo on our servers</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CheapBytes" category="MISC">
    <name>CheapBytes</name>
    <url>http://www.cheapbytes.com/</url>
    <description>
      CheapBytes, a company that specializes in low-cost technical
      products, now has <em>FreeBSD</em> products available on CD-ROM.
      Among our offerings, you will find FreeBSD CD-ROM sets and FreeBSD
      related books. For further information, please see <a
      href="http://www.cheapbytes.com/">www.cheapbytes.com</a> or send
      e-mail to: <a
      href="mailto:sales@cheapbytes.com">sales@cheapbytes.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoSORT" category="MISC">
    <name>CoSORT</name>
    <url>http://www.cosort.com</url>

    <description>
      CoSORT is the leading high-performance data sorting and
      manipulation package for high volumes processed on UNIX
      servers. CoSORT first shipped on UNIX in 1985 and can sort in
      parallel at rates exceeding 2GB per minute. CoSORT is most
      commonly used for: mainframe and COBOL sort and data migrations;
      speeding very large database (VLDB) reorg and loads; integrating
      and staging massive data warehouse (and data webhouse) extracts
      in ETL and ODS environments; directly replacing more than a
      dozen third-party sort engines with plug 'n' play interfaces;
      and, for writing custom reports in simple-to-complex,
      multi-format/multi-target environments. CoSORT can collate and
      convert between more than 100 data types. Most importantly,
      CoSORT allows you to combine sorting with its selection, joins,
      aggregation, type-conversion, cross-calculation, remapping, and
      formatting functions all in a single-pass through your
      data. Visit <a href="http://www.cosort.com/">www.cosort.com</a>,
      or call 1-800-333-SORT for more information and your FREE 30-day
      trial.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoolHorizon" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Cool Horizon</name>
    <url>http://www.coolhorizon.net/</url>
    <description>
      Cool Horizon provides a billing package for ISPs, called <em>Internet
      Billing</em>. This package was designed to handle all billing needs
      for Internet Service Providers. It runs under MS-Windows. One piece
      of the software is a client/server set, with a daemon that runs on a
      UNIX server (including FreeBSD), allowing the client to do all of
      their user management under a Windows front end.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CybernetSystems" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Cybernet Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.cybernet.com/</url>
    <description>
      Cybernet Systems produces the <a
      href="http://www.netmax.com/">NetMAX</a> line of Thin Servers and
      Professional Products for FreeBSD. The Thin Server Series consists of
      the FireWall (with Router), WebServer (with email and FTP), and
      FileServer (with print sharing). The NetMAX Professional contains
      these three, as well as the Discussion Group/NewsServer, dial in
      capabilities, enhanced system management and reporting functions,
      expanded support, and more. Easily install the included OS through a
      GUI and set up and manage your server through a web browser. Save
      time on mundane tasks. Access to the command line is available for
      "traditional" Unix use.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Dartware" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Dartware, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.dartware.com/</url>
    <description>
      Dartware's flagship product, InterMapper, shows active maps that
      give a visual, real-time view of traffic flows through and
      between critical network devices and links.  The status windows
      permit you to be proactive as well as reactive by displaying the
      percentage of capacity being used by any link or device.
      InterMapper uses pings, SNMP, Web, SMTP, and dozens of
      built-in server probes to keep tabs on the critical parts of your
      network, and let you know when you have problems-even before your
      customers call.  When InterMapper detects a problem, it sends a
      notification to one or more responsible individuals.  These
      sounds, emails, pages and text messages can be delayed or
      repeated to establish escalation schedules.  InterMapper's
      auto-discovery and map-arrangement tools let you install and get
      it running in an hour or two.<br />A non-expiring, full-functional
      license that lets you monitor up to five devices can be obtained
      for free.  For more information, visit
      <a href="http://www.intermapper.com/">www.intermapper.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DBMaker" category="DATABASE">
    <name>DBMaker</name>
    <url>http://www.dbmaker.com</url>
    <description>
      DBMaker provides you with a professional database system with
      multimedia capabilities, a native ODBC interface, large database
      features, and cross-platform support. The unique open architecture
      and native ODBC interface give you the freedom to build custom
      applications using a wide variety of programming tools such as Visual
      Basic or Delphi, or query your database using existing ODBC-compliant
      applications. DBMaker provides excellent multimedia-handling
      capabilities, allowing you to store, search, retrieve, and manipulate
      all types of multimedia data. Binary Large Objects (BLOBs) allow you
      to ensure the integrity of your multimedia data by taking full
      advantage of the advanced security and crash-recovery mechanisms
      included in DBMaker; File Objects (FOs) allow you to manage your
      multimedia data, while maintaining the capability to edit individual
      files in the source application. <a
      href="http://www.dbmaker.com">Download a free copy now!</a> -   This
      free copy of DBMaker includes a three-user license with no time or
      storage limitations. Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.dbmaker.com">www.dbmaker.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Devart" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Devart</name>
    <url>https://www.devart.com/unidac</url>
    <description>
      Devart Delphi Data Access Components are feature-rich and
      high-performance libraries of components that provide native
      connectivity to Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite,
      Interbase, Firebird from Delphi, C++Builder, Lazarus (and Free
      Pascal) under Windows, Mac OS X, iOS, Android, Linux, and
      FreeBSD for both 32-bit and 64-bit platforms.  These Data
      Access Components aim to assist programmers in developing of
      fast and native desktop and mobile applications.  It provides
      both possibility of connection to Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL,
      PostgeSQL, SQLite, Firebird and Interbase by means of native
      data access and directly via TCP/IP without involving Database
      Client.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Dynode" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Dynode Productions</name>
    <url>http://www.dynode.net/</url>
    <description>
      Dynode Productions, located in Perth - Western Australia, offers
      administrative services for FreeBSD and OpenBSD systems ranging
      from: default gateways; email, web and file servers; and
      workstations.  Please visit our <a href="http://www.dynode.net/">
	web site</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Easysoft" category="DEV">
    <name>Easysoft Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.easysoft.com/</url>
    <description>
      Easysoft Ltd Easysoft's ODBC-ODBC Bridge 2000 (OOB) provides full
      access to any local ODBC data source from any remote client, such as
      Unix, Linux, OpenVMS, Windows, or other systems.  For more
      information, or to download the software, please visit <a
      href="http://www.easysoft.com/">www.easysoft.com</a>. <p></p>
      Easysoft's JDBC-ODBC Bridge 2000 (JOB) provides Type 3 JDBC access
      from Java Applets or Applications on the FreeBSD platform to ODBC
      (Open Database Connectivity) data sources anywhere on the network
      where the server component of the bridge is installed.  More
      information can be found on our <a href="http://www.easysoft.com">
	web site</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EasyStat" category="MISC">
    <name>EasyStat</name>
    <url>http://www.easystat.net/</url>
    <description>
      EasyStat is a "counter"-like application. It will keep track of the
      number of visitors to your site, as well as gather information about
      your visitors such as their browser, operating system, referrer, etc.
      EasyStat will then display all it gathers in an elegant fashion, a
      demo of which is available on its site.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EfficientIP" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Efficient IP</name>
    <url>http://www.efficientip.com/</url>
    <description>
      Efficient IP is US based Solutions Provider - software editor
      focused on the development of professional tools to manage IP
      networks, wide architecture of DHCP and DNS servers.  Our
      objective is to provide you with a complete, simple and dynamic
      solution, which will allow you to carry out all administration of
      these services, whilst adapting to the technical, human or
      administrative constraints of your IT installation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EiffelSoftware" category="DEV">
    <name>Eiffel Software</name>
    <url>http://www.eiffel.com/</url>
    <description>
      Eiffel Studio is an Integrated Development Environment (IDE) designed
      for the Eiffel object-oriented application development language.
      Beside the Enterprise Edition, a Free Edition for non-commercial use
      only is freely available for download.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ElasticSoftware" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>Elastic Path Software</name>
    <url>http://www.elasticpath.com</url>
    <description>
      Elastic Path Software is the pioneer of flexible, developer
      friendly, Java ecommerce software architecture for building
      sophisticated and evolving online stores.  In a world full of
      complex software, our lightweight ecommerce framework is
      refreshingly simple, provides unlimited flexibility and minimizes
      total cost of ownership.  Companies such as Xerox, Sunoco,
      Procter &amp; Gamble, 24 Hour Fitness, JBoss and Random House
      use Elastic Path for the core ecommerce features they demand
      today and the maximum flexibility they need for tomorrow.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Elego" category="DEV">
    <name>Elego</name>
    <url>http://www.elego.de/</url>
    <description>
      Elego ComPact Configuration Management. <em>Elego ComPact</em> is a
      set of tools for configuration management, based on a very reliable
      and scalable solution for version control, integrated with a
      multi-platform language-independent build system, and the concept of
      software packages. It offers scriptable command-line-oriented
      programs, as well as an HTTP/HTML based GUI, and can be easily
      introduced in a stepwise fashion. <p> Some of its features are:
      client/server design, baseline and release branch support,
      checkin/checkout model, package-oriented change sets, integrated
      build system, support for development for/on heterogeneous platforms,
      scalable from one to hundreds of developers, default configurations
      for C, C++, Java, Modula-3, easily portable to most PC and
      workstation platforms. </p><p> Elego ComPact currently uses CVS as
      its underlying version control machine, though future versions may
      support other systems, too. Binaries are available for FreeBSD,
      Linux, Windows, and Solaris/SPARC systems. John Polstra's CVSup may
      be used for repository mirroring/replication. Like CVSup, Elego
      ComPact is completely written in Modula-3. </p><p> Fully functional
      demo CDs, including binaries for all supported platforms, and
      documentation in HTML, DVI, PDF, and PS format can be obtained by
      sending e-mail to <a href="mailto:info@elego.de">info@elego.de</a>.
      More information is also available from the <a
      href="http://www.elego.de">Elego WWW Homepage</a>. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmpressSoft" category="DEV">
    <name>Empress Software Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.empress.com</url>
    <description>
      Empress Software Inc. has developed <em>Embedded Empress Developer's
      Toolkit</em>. To learn more about the toolkit, please visit <a
      href="http://www.empress.com">www.empress.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmpressSoftware" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Empress Software</name>
    <url>http://www.empress.com</url>
    <description>
      Empress Software develops the EMPRESS RDBMS, a powerful and
      cost-effective ANSI SQL database management system designed for
      developing robust scientific and engineering, embedded, and
      e-commerce solutions. The EMPRESS RDBM engine is fast and
      compact, efficiently stores and manipulates any data, and is
      maintenance-free. Companion products include an Internet application
      development toolkit, ODBC Interface, a pure Java client, a C++
      interface, and interfaces to popular scripting languages like XML,
      PHP, Perl, and Tcl/Tk. Empress offers a <a
      href="http://www.empress.com/web-bin/ehsql/product/freetry.eht"
      >free 30 day evaluation</a>, complete with technical support.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TolisGroup" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>TOLIS Group, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tolisgroup.com/</url>
    <description>
      TOLIS Group, Inc. develops <em>BRU</em>, a very powerful and
      and reliable backup solution.  Among other features it offers
      per-file compression, an improved tape format with three
      different kinds of verification, and many safety checks to
      ensure data integrity.  BRU fully supports versions 4.2 through
      8.1 of FreeBSD.  Both as a standalone backup tool and as a client
      to the enterprise-level BRU Server product.  We offer both 32 bit
      and 64 bit Intel builds and can offer PPC, Alpha, Itanium 2, and
      SPARC versions if customers require them.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Etherpage" category="MISC">
    <name>Etherpage</name>
    <url>http://www.ppt.com/</url>
    <description>
      EtherPage provides a client/server based alphanumeric paging solution
      for Unix networks and Windows NT. Both command line and web
      interfaces are provided. Ideally suited for system and database
      administration, EtherPage allows messages to be sent automatically to
      support personnel based on database events, etc. Other features
      include links to email, integration with user-written scripts,
      multiple recipients, pagers selected by time of day/day of week,
      duplicate message suppression, long message splitting/truncation, job
      logging, and C API. Virtually all paging services are supported.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FairCom" category="DATABASE">
    <name>FairCom Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.faircom.com/</url>
    <description>
      FairCom Corporation has provided quality database development tools
      for the professional programmer since 1979. FairCom is best known for
      its extremely portable, high-performance data management product,
      <em>c-tree Plus</em>. The product is released in full source code and
      supports peer-to-peer development and client-side development for use
      with the <em>c-tree</em> database server. The FreeBSD version offers
      advanced cross-platform functionality, including industrial quality
      transaction processing, file mirroring, huge file support and
      disaster recovery. The FairCom ODBC Driver and Crystal Report(tm)
      interfaces allow end-users to access <em>c-tree</em> Plus
      applications with higher level products such as Microsoft Access and
      Crystal Reports. The FairCom toolset is completed with
      <em>r-tree</em>, a powerful report generator and the powerful FairCom
      server, with heterogeneous network support, which allows dissimilar
      clients to attach to one platform and easily migrate to over 20
      supported platforms, from FreeBSD to Windows to Mac. For more
      information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.faircom.com/">www.faircom.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GroundLabs" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Ground Labs</name>
    <url>http://www.groundlabs.com</url>
    <description>
      Ground Labs is a global leader in the development of cardholder
      data discovery software for the payment card industry. Its flagship
      products, <a
      href="http://www.groundlabs.com/products/crse">Card Recon</a> and <a
      href="http://www.groundlabs.com/products/cree">Enterprise Recon</a>,
      identify data storage risks on thousands of computer systems worldwide,
      helping companies prevent security breaches that result in the theft of
      customers' credit and debit card numbers. For more information and free
      trials of our products, visit <a
      href="http://www.groundlabs.com/">www.groundlabs.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="icon" category="DEV">
    <name>Icon Laboratories</name>
    <url>http://www.icon-labs.com/</url>
    <description>Icon Laboratories offers Envoy for FreeBSD.
      Envoy is a ported version of ISI's popular Envoy SNMP libraries.
      Each port includes SNMP libraries and header files for C development,
      a MIB compiler and source code for a sample agent,
      designed specifically for FreeBSD.
      For more information, send email to
      <a href="mailto:info@icon-labs.com">info@icon-labs.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Infinitum" category="MISC">
    <name>Infinitum Group</name>
    <url>http://www.infinitum.nl</url>
    <description>
      Infinitum Group provides several high-end solutions, based upon
      FreeBSD and other *NIX/BSD based platforms. Our
      do-maintenance-yourself website product runs on FreeBSD, in
      combination with <a href="http://www.zope.org">Zope</a>. If you would
      like an easy maintenance website or custom software development,
      please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@infinitum.nl">info@infinitum.nl</a> or by phone at
      +31 (0)70-3108950.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Inlab" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>Inlab Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.munich.net/inlab/scheme/</url>
    <description>
      Inlab Software GmbH offers binaries of <em>Inlab-Scheme</em> for
      FreeBSD and Linux (FREE for personal or educational use).
      Inlab-Scheme is a R4RS-compliant Scheme, which is capable of reading
      and writing TIFF and XBM-bitmaps to and from a special internal
      bitmap type. With built-in primitives for image processing,
      Inlab-Scheme can be a general tool for tasks like optical character
      recognition and general analysis and processing of bitmap data.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InterBase" category="DATABASE">
    <name>InterBase</name>
    <url>http://www.interbase.com</url>
    <description>
      InterBase is The Perfect Embedded Database. Behind every great
      client/server application, you will find a great database and very
      possibly an embedded database. The hallmark of a great embedded
      database is its ability to empower applications and deliver
      information while remaining virtually invisible to the end user and
      requiring little or no attention from the database administrator.
      That database is InterBase. InterBase's Japanese partner, RIOS
      Corporation, is now offering a port of InterBase 4 for FreeBSD.
      Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.interbase.com">www.interbase.com</a> or directly
      from RIOS at <a
      href="http://iblinux.rios.co.jp/intl/">http://iblinux.rios.co.jp/intl
      /</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="iPass" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>iPass</name>
    <url>http://www.ipass.com/</url>
    <description>
      i-Pass Alliance is the leading provider of global Internet-roaming
      solutions for Internet service providers. We provide a total solution
      that enables ISPs to join a global network and provide convenient,
      low-cost worldwide access to their traveling Internet subscribers. We
      are an independent organization, handling the financial settlement
      between you and other Internet service providers and enabling you to
      bill their subscribers for this service. There is no cost to join and
      no cost for the i-Pass software. The i-Pass cross-authorization and
      settlement software is compatible with all common authentication
      protocols and servers, including FreeBSD. For more information,
      please visit <a href="http://www.ipass.com/">www.ipass.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="irie" category="DEV">
    <name>Irie Tools</name>
    <url>http://www.irietools.com/</url>
    <description>Irie Tools develops Irie Pascal, a multi-platform
      compiler and interpreter that creates console programs and web
      server programs using the Common Gateway Interface.  Features
      include strong support for Standard Pascal (ideal for learning
      Pascal), MySQL database programming, and creating programs to
      process large datasets (no 64K limit on code or data).  Irie
      Pascal supports five different operating systems (FreeBSD,
      Windows, Linux, Solaris/x86, and Solaris/Sparc).  There is a
      separate edition of Irie Pascal for each supported operating
      system, and programs created with the compiler in any edition
      can be executed (without being recompiled) by the interpreters
      in all editions.  A free evaluation copy is available at the <a
      href="http://www.irietools.com">Irie Tools website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="journyx" category="MISC">
    <name>journyx WebTime</name>
    <url>http://journyx.com/products.html</url>
    <description>
      journyx WebTime is a web-based time and attendance tracking product
      for engineering departments and technical consultancies or
      contracting firms with people on the go. It was developed on FreeBSD.
       Since it is web-based, it allows for worldwide collection of data.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Kaspersky" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Kaspersky Lab</name>
    <url>http://www.kaspersky.com/</url>
    <description>
      Kaspersky Lab offers KasperskyT Anti-Virus (AVP) - a unique
      anti-virus solution for FreeBSD. The product provides comprehensive
      protection for your file and application servers and gateways running
      FreeBSD. Kaspersky Anti-Virus for FreeBSD includes the most complete
      set of anti-virus tools that will help you to build a multi-level
      defense system against attacks of malicious code of any type,
      including computer viruses, Internet worms and Trojan horses. The
      package includes an anti-virus scanner for on-demand check for
      viruses on data storage devices (local and network); an anti-virus daemon
      that filters data from viruses in real-time mode. Kaspersky
      Anti-Virus for FreeBSD offers an interactive configuration program
      and a utility for automatic anti-virus database updates download. The
      product also includes a ready-made solution to integrate the product
      into popular Sendmail and Qmail gateways. This is a perfect solution
      to create your own centralized filtering system for e-mail traffic
      and cleanse it of viruses. The client part of Kaspersky Anti-Virus
      for FreeBSD/BSDi is supplied in open source code. This enables you to
      easily integrate the product into your own applications to perform
      specific tasks, e.g., into other e-mail or application servers.
      Kaspersky Lab also develops anti-virus solutions for DOS, Windows
      95/98, Windows 2000/NT Workstation/Server, Novell NetWare, Linux,
      OS/2, BSDi, MS Exchange Server, Lotus Notes, and MS Office 2000.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LoneStar" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Lone Star Software Corp</name>
    <url>http://www.LONE-TAR.com/</url>
    <description>
      For over 15 years,
      LONE-TAR has been the de facto standard backup solution
      for the UNIX Systems Administrator.
      LONE-TAR is a fully menu-driven data-archiving and -recovery utility.
      It employs high compression,
      allowing it to double the capacity of your archive device,
      as well as Bit-level Verification of archived data against the hard disk.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Lugaru" category="DEV">
    <name>Lugaru Software Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.lugaru.com</url>
    <description>
      Lugaru's Epsilon Programmer's Editor features EMACS-style &amp;
      Brief-style key bindings, C/C++/Java, Perl, HTML, and TeX modes,
      concurrent compiler control with typescript journaling, syntax
      highlighting, asynchronous Internet support, smart indenting &amp;
      tags, and multi-file, multi-directory search &amp; replace. Plus full
      undo/redo, directory-spanning file patterns, command/filename
      completion, convenient keyboard macros, interactive customizability,
      and much more. Executables for FreeBSD, Linux, Windows
      95/98/NT/2000/3.1, OS/2, and DOS are included. Visit <a
      href="http://www.lugaru.com">www.lugaru.com</a> for details and a
      free evaluation copy.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MainStreet" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>MainStreet</name>
    <url>http://www.mainstreetsoftworks.com/</url>
    <description>
      MainStreet Softworks develops and markets critical financial
      transaction software to the retail, mail/phone order, and eCommerce
      industries. Their primary software offering, the MainStreet Credit
      Verification Engine, provides direct credit card
      authorization/settlement services on many POSIX-compliant Host
      Operating Systems such as FreeBSD. MCVE provides all the required
      functionality to authorize and settle Major Credit Cards and is
      certified with Established Clearing Houses (processors) to ensure the
      lowest possible merchant rates. To find out more, visit our <a
      href="http://www.mainstreetsoftworks.com/">web site</a> or contact us
      at <a
      href="mailto:info@mainstreetsoftworks.com">info@mainstreetsoftworks.c
      om</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Mercantec" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Mercantec, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.mercantec.com/</url>
    <description>
      Mercantec, Inc. develops <em>SoftCart</em>(tm), a complete retail
      electronic commerce solution for marketing and selling goods and
      services on the World Wide Web. Mercantec sells its products through
      a worldwide network of Internet Service Providers (ISPs) and Web
      hosting service providers, Web consultants, software developers,
      integrators, and OEMs. Visit us at <a
      href="http://www.mercantec.com/">www.mercantec.com</a>, contact us
      through email at <a
      href="mailto:info@mercantec.com">info@mercantec.com</a>, or call us
      at +1.630.305.3200.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="motifdeveloper.com" category="DEV">
    <name>motifdeveloper.com</name>
    <url>http://www.motifdeveloper.com/</url>
    <description>
      motifdeveloper.com provides both the Open Motif toolkit for FreeBSD
      via download and also a range of technical information, resources,
      and in-depth hints and tips for X/Motif developers. To download Open
      Motif for FreeBSD, please visit <a
      href="http://www.motifdeveloper.com/"  >www.motifdeveloper.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Muonics" category="DEV">
    <name>Muonics</name>
    <url>http://www.muonics.com/Products/MIBSmithy/</url>
    <description>
       Muonics' MIB Smithy  is a software product for Simple Network
      Management Protocol (SNMP) developers, Management Information Base
      (MIB) designers and internet-draft authors providing a Visual
      GUI-based environment for designing, editing and compiling MIB
      modules according to the SMIv1 and SMIv2 (Structure of Management
      Information) standards. MIB Smithy is supported on several platforms,
      including FreeBSD. More information and a 15-day limited evaluation
      version can be obtained from <a
      href="http://www.muonics.com/">www.muonics.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NAG" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>NAG, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.nag.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      NAG, Ltd. produces a Fortran-90 Compiler for most flavors of Unix
      (including FreeBSD), VMS, and the PC. The <em>NAGWare f90</em>
      Compiler is a full implementation of Fortran 90 (which, by
      definition, includes Fortran 77) plus a single-processor
      implementation of HPF. For further information, in North America,
      email <a href="mailto:naginfo@nag.com">naginfo@nag.com</a>, and
      elsewhere, email <a
      href="mailto:infodesk@nag.co.uk">infodesk@nag.co.uk</a>. Or, visit <a
      href="http://www.nag.co.uk/">www.nag.co.uk/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NameSurfer" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>NameSurfer, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.namesurfer.com/</url>
    <description>
      NameSurfer, Ltd. NameSurfer is a distributed administration tool for
      DNS data, with a WWW-based graphical user interface for remote
      Internet and Intranet DNS administration. A fully functional
      evaluation version is available for FreeBSD. For more information,
      please visit <a
      href="http://www.namesurfer.com/">www.namesurfer.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetBeans" category="DEV" >
    <name>NetBeans, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.netbeans.org/</url>
    <description>
      NetBeans, Inc. make Java IDEs, written in Java, that run on FreeBSD.
      A complete set of Open APIs is available for extending the
      environment.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetBoz" category="NETWORK">
    <name>NetBoz Firewall</name>
    <url>http://www.netboz.net/</url>
    <description>
      NetBoz Firewall Free CD-ROM bootable firewall. No hard disk required.
      Web administration interface, real time traffic monitoring and more.
      Visit our web site <a
      href="http://www.netboz.net/">www.netboz.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netsville" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Netsville, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.netsville.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netsville, Inc. sells an Internet merchandising system called <a
      href="http://hazel.netsville.com/">Hazel</a> which allows webmasters,
      web consultants, or regular shopkeeps to create a web storefront on
      the Internet. Hazel interfaces with web servers, using SSL for
      security and various transaction processors for credit card
      authorization. The developers actually wrote Hazel using FreeBSD as
      their operating system. If you need a flexible shopping cart solution
      for the Internet, Hazel is your best bet.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NettixPeru" category="MISC">
    <name>Nettix Peru</name>
    <url>http://www.nettix.com.pe/</url>
    <description>
      Nettix Peru provides value added solutions based on opensource
      software for today's Peruvian and Latin-American small and mid-range
      companies.  Our main skills are in Linux, Unix, Networking, and
      Security related subjects.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Openmake" category="DEV">
    <name>Openmake</name>
    <url>http://www.openmake.com/</url>
    <description>
      Openmake is a GUI- and shell-based build manager that goes beyond
      beloved GNU make. Used at some of the world's largest companies for
      simple apps and complex multi-language/multi-OS applications,
      Openmake allows complete standardization and automation of the build
      process. Coupled with any version control tool (e.g. RCS), Openmake
      absolutely ensures matching source and executables. Submit your
      client build to Windows and your server build to FreeBSD at the same
      time (or AIX, HP, Sun, Sequent, OS/2). For more information, visit <a
      href="http://www.openmake.com">www.openmake.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OSATech" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>OSATech, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.osatech.com/</url>
    <description>
      OSATech, Inc. is a Massachusetts-based corporation. We specialize in
      e-commerce software development, using Perl, C++ and Java. We perform
      all of our project management activities from the US, whereas our
      development activities are performed in our offshore center in India.
      Using this approach, we are able to provide quality service at a low
      cost. Please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:gprakash@osatech.com">gprakash@osatech.com</a> or at
      617-306-6578. Please refer to <a
      href="http://www.osatech.com">www.osatech.com</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PacificTimesheet" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>Pacific Timesheet</name>
    <url>http://www.pacifictimesheet.com/</url>
    <description>
      Pacific Timesheet is a web-based timesheet software that provides
      payroll, project, job costing, time and attendance features in one
      system.  Other modules include automated approvals, billing and
      pay rates, time-off scheduling, custom reporting, iPhone timesheet,
      IVR integration, time clock integration and payroll integration.
      We support all major operating systems and browsers.  Our software
      is available as a licensed or as a ASP/online version.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Parabase" category="MISC">
    <name>Parabase Technology Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.parabase.com</url>
    <description>
      Parabase Technology Inc. offers the Parabase Web-Order-System, an
      integrated set of web-based business applications that incorporate
      web-based order entry, catalog generation, shopping cart, and
      administration. It automatically calculates shipping and handling
      charges and sales tax [depending on location] and has a full invoice
      preview and email order confirmation. The system currently interfaces
      to QuickBooks and Excel; other accounting packages are available on
      request. The system is based on a highly reliable journalizing
      database concept. Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.parabase.com">www.parabase.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Perforce" category="MISC">
    <name>Perforce Software</name>
    <url>http://www.perforce.com/</url>
    <description>
      Perforce Software produces <a
	href="http://www.perforce.com/product/perforce"
      >PERFORCE</a> -- the FAST Software Configuration
      Management System. Perforce SCM streamlines the
      software development process for organizations working with multiple
      operating systems and in multiple physical locations. This
      high-powered SCM system runs on more than 50 operating systems
      including Windows, and nearly every UNIX variation, from Linux to Mac
      OS X to AS/400, providing software developers with an easy-to-use
      tool for version control, workspace management and atomic change
      transactions. Free, fully functional evaluation versions are
      available from the <a href="http://www.perforce.com">Perforce Web
      site</a>. Organizations developing software that is licensed or
      otherwise distributed exclusively under an Open Source license may be
      eligible to obtain Perforce licenses gratis. Perforce Software can be
      reached at <a href="mailto:info@perforce.com">info@perforce.com</a>
      or +1-510-864-7400.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pfSense" category="SECURITY">
    <name>pfSense</name>
    <url>https://www.pfsense.org/</url>
    <description>
      The <a href="https://www.pfsense.org">pfSense project</a> is a
      free network firewall distribution based on the FreeBSD
      operating system with a custom kernel and including third party
      free software packages for additional functionality.  pfSense
      software, with the help of the package system, is able to
      provide the same or more functionality as more common commercial
      firewalls, without any of the artificial limitations.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PixInsight" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>PixInsight</name>
    <url>http://pixinsight.com/</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://pixinsight.com/features/index.html">PixInsight</a>
      is an advanced, modular image processing software platform designed
      specifically for the demanding requirements of astrophotography and
      other technical imaging fields.  PixInsight is available natively
      on &os;, Linux, Mac OS X and Windows operating systems (both in
      32-bit and 64-bit versions).  For more information please visit our
      <a href="http://pixinsight.com/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Polyhedra" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Polyhedra</name>
    <url>http://www.polyhedra.com</url>
    <description>
      Polyhedra is a main-memory, object-relational database that is
      ideally suited for mission-critical applications requiring
      event-driven, real-time responses to data changes, complex database
      designs, distributed applications, and fault tolerance for high
      availability and continuous operation. <p> The Object-relational
      database can contain objects that handle IP-based protocols, with
      object methods running in the database process itself and accessible
      to other objects/information stored in the database. Our own web
      site, <a href="http://www.polyhedra.com">www.polyhedra.com</a>,
      provides an example of Polyhedra, acting as both the web server and
      the information store, including free downloads available for trying
      Polyhedra on FreeBSD in Linux mode. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="quadstor" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>QUADStor Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.quadstor.com</url>
    <description>
      QUADStor Systems provides storage virtualization and data
      deduplication products for FreeBSD and Linux.  Benefits of QUADStor
      storage virtualization include data deduplication, data compression,
      easy management etc.  The best thing is that QUADStor products are
      free for non-commercial use.  For more information please visit our
      <a href="http://www.quadstor.com">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="REBOL" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>REBOL</name>
    <url>http://www.rebol.com/</url>
    <description>
      REBOL is a new, network-based messaging language that increases
      productivity, cuts application size, and reduces application
      time-to-market. The language is human-centric, instead of
      computer-centric, and offers a new alternative to anachronistic
      programming languages like Java and C++ and scripting languages like
      PERL and Tcl. REBOL is compact, platform independent, and functions
      over a network or on a single system. It is ideally suited for
      webmasters, technicians, hobbyists, educators, experimenters, and any
      one who requires a simple, customizable, robust, easy-to-understand
      language. Download <em>The Language of the Free</em>(tm) now at <a
      href="http://www.rebol.com/downloads.html"
      >www.rebol.com/downloads.html</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Relex" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Relex US, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.relexus.com/</url>
    <description>
      Relex US, Inc. present:
      <ul>
	<li>RDBMS Linter(tm) SQL has a
	  client-server architecture  and supports SQL-92, ODBC, and JDBC
	  interfaces.  User access is available through PHP, Perl, TCL/TK, and
	  a C/C++ language call interface.Linter includes search engine and
	  replication server capabilities, is well designed for embedded
	  systems, and is currently ported to more than 20 operating systems.</li>
	<li>Our Ticket Tracking System  is suitable for resolving
	  problems ranging from software bugs  to consumer product complaints.</li>
	<li>Nevod is a system for data warehousing &amp; mining.</li>
	<li>Lakuna  is a program for rapid database application
	  development.</li>
      </ul>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Revolution" category="DEV">
    <name>Revolution</name>
    <url>http://www.runrev.com/</url>
    <description>
      Revolution is a multi-platform software development tool that enables
      developers to easily and quickly create powerful applications for OS
      X, classic Mac OS, Windows, Linux, and popular Unix systems
      (including FreeBSD)... with native look and feel on all platforms.
      For more information or to download a free 30-day trial evaluation
      edition, visit <a href="http://www.runrev.com/">www.runrev.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Sage" category="MISC">
    <name>Sage Electronic Engineering</name>
    <url>https://www.se-eng.com</url>
    <description>
      Sage Electronic supports booting FreeBSD on x86 embedded
      computers with Intel and AMD processors.  SageBIOS, a commercial
      distribution of <a href="http://coreboot.org">coreboot</a> and
      other open source firmware resources, is the leading open source
      BIOS alternative to UEFI BIOS on x86 hardware.  Sage Electronic
      is a top contributor to coreboot, the only open source firmware
      compatible with Intel and AMD processors.  Each SageBIOS Board
      Support Package supports booting to FreeBSD, Windows, Linux,
      RTOS, and legacy operating systems.  Eliminate royalties, obtain
      source code, and request custom features such as security and
      fast booting.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Sendmail" category="EMAIL">
    <name>Sendmail Inc</name>
    <url>http://www.sendmail.com/</url>
    <description>
      Sendmail Inc. develop the commercial (Sendmail Pro) and free versions
      of sendmail, the ubiquitous mail transport agent. It supports
      FreeBSD, as well as many other Unix implementations.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SerengetiSystems" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Serengeti Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.serengeti.com/</url>
    <description>
      Serengeti Systems provides PC to mainframe communication packages
      over Bisync and SDLC lines. We support FreeBSD, as well as DOS,
      Windows, SCO, AIX, and OS/2. For more information, please <a
      href="http://www.serengeti.com/">visit our web site</a>, e-mail us at
      <a href="mailto:sales@serengeti.com">sales@serengeti.com</a>, or call
      +1.800.634.3122.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SiamScan" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>SiamScan.NET</name>
    <url>http://www.siamscan.net/</url>
    <description>
      SiamScan.NET, a Bangkok based company offers commercial web
      application software, CPA - Collaborative Portable Accounting. CPA is
      web accounting software designed to be easy enough for non
      accountants to use. Also, we offer service on maintenance and
      implementation of FreeBSD systems. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:sale@siamscan.net">sale@siamscan.net</a>, visit <a
      href="http://www.siamscan.net/">SiamScan.NET</a> Website, call +66
      2532 9068-70, or fax +66 2533 4167.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Oracle" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Oracle</name>
    <url>http://www.oracle.com</url>
    <description>
      Oracle distributes Berkeley DB, an embeddable database system with
      full source.  Oracle Berkeley DB is tested and certified
      to compile and run on all modern operating systems including Solaris,
      Windows, Linux, Android, Mac OS/X, BSD, iPhone OS, VxWorks, and QNX
      to name a few. It offers high-end data management
      services, including full transaction support, disaster recovery, hot
      backup, very large databases, and the ability to handle large numbers
      of users concurrently. Keys and records can be arbitrarily long, and
      of arbitrary data types. Berkeley DB can store data in B+trees, hash
      tables, or sequential stores. The programmatic interfaces are simple,
      and can be called from C, C++, Java, or Perl. Berkeley DB is easy to
      install and manage, so your customers can use your application
      without learning how to be database administrators. For more
      information visit the <a
      href="http://www.oracle.com/us/products/database/berkeley-db/index.html">
      Berkeley DB website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SlickEdit" category="DEV">
    <name>SlickEdit</name>
    <url>http://www.slickedit.com/</url>
    <description>
      SlickEdit develops and markets Visual SlickEdit, a programmer's
      editor that allows developers to increase their productivity. Visual
      SlickEdit v6.0 for FreeBSD allows developers to streamline workflow,
      simplify processes, manage large files, and reduce keystrokes.
      Developers can customize Visual SlickEdit, based on individual
      preferences and preferred coding styles. Visit <a
      href="http://www.slickedit.com/">www.slickedit.com</a> for more
      information or to download a demo.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SoftIntegration" category="DEV">
    <name>SoftIntegration, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.softintegration.com/</url>
    <description>
      Ch is an embeddable C/C++ interpreter for cross-platform scripting,
      2D/3D plotting, numerical computing, shell programming and embedded
      scripting.  Ch supports the ISO 1990 C Standard (C90), major features
      in C99 (complex numbers, variable length arrays or VLAs, type generic
      functions, long data type, etc), and C++ class.  Ch has extensions to
      C language with built-in string type etc for easy scripting.  Ch also
      has extensions with computational array for easy numerical computing
      and 2D/3D plotting.  In addition to Ch, we also have a free C CGI
      toolkit which is similar to ASP and JSP for web development.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SoftMaker" category="MISC">
    <name>SoftMaker Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.softmaker.de/tml_en.htm</url>
    <description>
      TextMaker is the fast, efficient Microsoft Word-compatible word processor for FreeBSD.
      It provides all the features of a modern high-end word processor, reads and
      writes Microsoft Word documents seamlessly, and is available on <a
      href="http://www.softmaker.de/tm_en.htm">multiple platforms</a> (FreeBSD,
      Linux, Windows, Pocket PCs, Handheld PCs).
      <a href="http://www.softmaker.de/tmldemo_en.htm">Free trial</a> available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Solid" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Solid Information Technology Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.solidtech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Solid Information Technology Ltd is the maker of a unique data
      management product, <a
      href="http://www.solidtech.com/market/products/index.htm">SOLID
      Server</a>. It is designed for robust operation in demanding
      environments. Its small size and ease-of-use make it ideal for
      deployment to web sites, various embedded systems, and other
      environments where databases need to operate unattended. Free
      evaluation copies maybe downloaded from <a
      href="http://www.solidtech.com/market/eval/index.htm">here</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Sophos" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Sophos Anti-Virus</name>
    <url>http://www.sophos.com</url>
    <description>
      Sophos Plc offers <em>Sophos Anti-Virus</em> for FreeBSD. Sophos
      Anti-Virus is a unique solution to the virus problem, providing true
      cross-platform protection in a single, fully integrated product. The
      network-centric design provides a host of benefits for the protection
      of servers, workstations, and portables. Sophos's ground-breaking
      architecture maximizes protection, while minimizing performance and
      administrative overheads. Sophos Anti-Virus is fully scalable,
      equally at home protecting a single PC, a local network, or the
      entire enterprise. Sophos Anti-Virus is available for all popular
      desktop and network operating systems, including DOS, Windows
      3.x/95/98/NT/2000, Unix (including FreeBSD), OS/2, Netware, and
      OpenVMS. Sophos Anti-Virus monitors all virus entry points, including
      disks, programs, documents, network drives, CD-ROMs, Internet
      downloads, email attachments, and compressed files. Over 65 per cent
      of The Times Top 100 Companies use Sophos Anti-Virus to protect their
      networks from viruses. This endorsement of Sophos Anti-Virus
      protection is shared around the world. FREE evaluation copies may be
      <a href="http://www.sophos.com/en-us/products/free-trials.aspx">downloaded</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="StalkerSoftware" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Stalker Software, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.stalker.com/</url>
    <description>
      Stalker Software, Inc. offers <a
      href="http://www.stalker.com/CommuniGatePro/">CommuniGate Pro</a>,
      The Internet Messaging Server. Based on the Stalker Foundation
      framework, it employs the native services of all major operating
      systems, including FreeBSD, Windows 95/98, Windows NT, Apple
      Rhapsody, Linux, Solaris, and others. The CommuniGate Pro server
      takes full advantage of modern multi-threaded and multi-processor
      environments, and includes anti-spam protection, administration via
      the Web, extensive multi-domain support, dial-up capabilities, unique
      IMAP multi-mailbox features and designed to provide access to
      hundreds of thousands of accounts, and to relay mail on the most
      heavily loaded sites. Download the FREE Trial version from <a
      href="http://www.stalker.com/">www.stalker.com</a> or e-mail <a
      href="mailto:sales@stalker.com">Stalker Software Sales</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="StarQuest" category="DATABASE">
    <name>StarQuest Ventures</name>
    <url>http://www.starquest.com/</url>
    <description>
      StarQuest Ventures provides connectivity products that allow
      Windows, UNIX, and Java applications to access IBM host resources
      on mainframe and midrange systems.  StarQuest offers StarSQL (an
      ODBC-compliant driver for connectivity to IBM's DB2 relational
      databases) and StarSQL for Java (a type 4 JDBC-compliant driver
      for DB2 access) for use with FreeBSD.  These drivers implement
      native DRDA protocol over direct TCP/IP connections to a wide range
      of IBM DB2 platforms with no additional host software required.
      They include support for LOB (large object) data, encrypted
      passwords, connection pooling, and global Two-Phase Commit (2PC)
      transactions.  Please visit <a href="http://www.starquest.com">
      www.starquest.com</a> for additional information or a trial
      version.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Tonec" category="MISC">
    <name>Tonec, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tonec.com</url>
    <description>
      Tonec, Inc. provides award-winning products and solutions for web
      development, Java applets, and Perl modules. Tonec is a developer of
      Adgen - a BMP to PFR dynamic font converter for Linux and FreeBSD. In
      addition, Tonec provides custom programming, cost-effective offshore
      software development, web design, and custom ASP and Java development
      services in its development centers located in Russia, Poland, and
      Latvia. <a href="http://www.tonec.com">Visit our site</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Vembu" category="MISC">
    <name>Vembu StoreGrid</name>
    <url>http://www.vembu.com/</url>
    <description>
      Vembu StoreGrid is an extremely flexible Desktop Backup Software.
      StoreGrid's innovative, trusted intranet peer-to-peer backup
      solution helps backup desktop and laptop data with no need for
      additional storage hardware.  With backup servers, StoreGrid can
      also be deployed for conventional client-server and remote backup
      purposes.  StoreGrid works on FreeBSD, Linux, Windows and Mac OS X
      operating systems.  Check out <a href="http://www.vembu.com">http://www.vembu.com</a>
      for a free trial download of Vembu StoreGrid Desktop Backup
      Software.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Vital" category="DEV">
    <name>Vital, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.vital.com/</url>
    <description>
      Vital, Inc. is the maker of the CRiSP visual text editor. CRiSP is a
      development tool for FreeBSD and most other Windows, UNIX, and Linux
      platforms. CRiSP is 100% BRIEF-compatible and also emulates other
      popular editors such as vi, emacs, EDT, CUA, and Wordstar. This makes
      CRiSP a very powerful yet easy-to-use editing package with features
      like cut &amp; paste, syntax coloring, code beautifying, code
      folding, searching, and much more.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebCrossing" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Web Crossing</name>
    <url>http://webcrossing.com/</url>
    <description>
      Web Crossing, by Lundeen &amp; Associates, is a conferencing server
      for the intranet/extranet and World Wide Web providing discussion
      forums and chat rooms. Web Crossing is a groupware application
      server, accessible with any Web browser, via most Web servers. It
      makes communication more efficient and productive than newsgroups or
      email mailing lists. Contact L &amp; A at <a
      href="mailto:sales@lundeen.com">sales@lundeen.com</a>,
      +1.510.521.5855 (Voice), or +1.510.522.6647 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebHostWorks.net" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>WebHostWorks.net</name>
    <url>http://www.webhostworks.net/</url>
    <description>
      WebHostWorks.net is a small and thriving web development firm
      specializing in e-commerce integration for small and medium sized
      businesses. Our proprietary E-Cart commerce package supports
      extraordinarily usable shopping cart services with backend product
      list management, order processing, executive summary reports,
      customer review processing, and inventory projections. See <a
      href="http://www.webhostworks.net">webhostworks.net</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebEvent" category="NETWORK">
    <name>WebEvent</name>
    <url>http://www.matadordesign.com/</url>
    <description>
      Matador Design produces WebEvent, a web-based calendar and scheduling
      solution that is available for FreeBSD-based web servers. It is a
      perfect addition to any Internet or Intranet web site that needs to
      display event information, manage schedules, rooms, or other
      resources.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XDesigner" category="DEV">
    <name>X-Designer</name>
    <url>http://www.ist-inc.com/xd/</url>
    <description>
      X-Designer from <a href="http://www.ist-inc.com/">Imperial Software Technology</a>
      is an advanced GUI Builder for FreeBSD.
      X-Designer makes it easy to build and test graphical user interfaces.
      Use X-Designer to quickly create a working X/Motif, Windows, or Java GUI
      from a single design.
      Includes automated GUI testing and technology
      to re-engineer legacy Motif interfaces with XD/Capture.
      Visit our <a href="http://www.ist-inc.com/xd">web site</a>
      for more information or send an e-mail
      to <a href="mailto:sales@ist-inc.com">sales@ist-inc.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XAT" category="NETWORK">
    <name>XAT.com</name>
    <url>http://www.xat.com/</url>
    <description>
      XAT.com offers commercial web-acceleration software for FreeBSD. <a
      href="http://www.xat.com/jdo/">JPEG Disk Optimizer</a> is designed to
      run on a web server and either run in the background to compress all
      JPG images on a disk or to compress them as they arrive. Users have
      reported a 40% saving in file size and corresponding savings in
      bandwidth, disk space, and server load, all of which contributes to
      faster web sites. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:sales@xat.com">sales@xat.com</a>, visit the <a
      href="http://www.xat.com/jdo/">XAT.com website</a>, or call +44 1752
      872181.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XGForce" category="NETWORK">
    <name>XGForce.COM</name>
    <url>http://www.xgforce.com/</url>
    <description>
      XGForce.COM announces <a href="http://www.xgforce.com/eCluster.html">
        eCluster(tm)</a> software. New Internet Clustering Technology is
      designed to cluster Intranet/Internet Servers into virtual groups,
      where server load balancing and fail safe is made possible.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="YARD" category="DATABASE">
    <name>YARD Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.yard.de/</url>
    <description>
      YARD Software GmbH provides its relational ANSI-SQL database for
      FreeBSD systems.	<em>YARD-SQL</em> is available on most UNIX systems
      and has interfaces for C, ODBC (MS Windows) and JDBC (Java). A
      Private Edition for private, non-commercial use can be downloaded
      from <a
      href="ftp://ftp.yard.de/pub/private/">ftp://ftp.yard.de/pub/private/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SippySoftwareInc" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Sippy Software, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.sippysoft.com</url>
    <description>
      Sippy Software, Inc. is a VoIP solutions company. We enable Internet
      Telephony Service Providers (ITSP's) and the operators of voice
      networks to quickly and efficiently implement, manage, and deliver a
      wide range of IP telephony services. Our flagship product
      <a href="http://www.sippysoft.com/?page=products&amp;m_l2=0&amp;m_l3=0">
      Sippy Softswitch</a> is a carrier-grade SIP session controller and
      rating/billing solution as well as an extremely flexible customer
      management platform that enables the providers of IP Telephony
      services to launch, price, and provision an array of VoIP services.
      For further information, please see <a href="http://www.sippysoft.com">
      www.sippysoft.com</a>. We use FreeBSD as a platform for running our
      software on and actively support it along with several other free
      software projects, such as <a href="http://www.iptel.org/ser">SER</a>
      and <a href="http://www.b2bua.org">Sippy B2BUA</a>, by contributing
      back our fixes and enhancements.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ClickTime" category="NETWORK">
    <name>ClickTime</name>
    <url>http://www.clicktime.com/</url>
    <description>
      ClickTime is an easy-to-use web timesheet for billing, cost accounting,
      and payroll. User-friendly and superfast, employees can easily enter
      time on any computer (Mac or PC) with an Internet connection. And if
      they forget, ClickTime will remind them.  Now, employees don't have
      to wait to get back to the office to submit their expenses; with
      ClickTime they can be approved from anywhere without paperwork hassles.
      Managers are also saved those hassles with powerful reports, simple
      timesheet approval, 24-hour customer support, and data-export to Excel,
      QuickBooks, PDF, and other popular software. Cost effective and time
      saving, ClickTime requires no contract, no installation, and minimal
      training. Try our 30-day free trial and see for yourself that ClickTime
      is the simplest way to track employee time.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ConnectDaily" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Connect Daily Web Calendar</name>
    <url>http://www.mhsoftware.com/connectdaily.htm</url>
    <description>
      Connect Daily is a Java based web calendar.  It provides advanced
      capabilities for scheduling resources including Gantt Chart views
      and approvals.  Users can subscribe to notifications and reminders
      to receive Email messages about events as they are added.  Event export
      to iCal is supported, as well as a synchronization program to export
      events to Palm and MS Outlook.  Users can be authenticated against LDAP
      directories or MS Active Directory.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="dbstar" category="DATABASE">
    <name>dbstar</name>
    <url>http://www.ittia.com/dbstar/dbstar.html</url>
    <description>
      db.* is a free, small-footprint (less than 150K) open-source
      database management system (DBMS) designed to provide powerful,
      flexible, high-performance capabilities for developing
      applications using an embedded database.
      By combining the network and relational model technologies
      in a single system, db.* lets you organize and access
      information efficiently, regardless of the complexity of the
      data. It is well-documented and absolutely free to use,
      modify and distribute on Open Source operating systems.
      db.* is very reliable and stable, and as all embedded
      databases, requires no DBA.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ieasoftware" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>IEA Software, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.iea-software.com</url>
    <description>
      <a href="http://www.iea-software.com/emerald">
        Emerald Management Suite</a><br />
      Emerald offers automated billing, reporting, account management,
      integrated AAA/RADIUS, CRM, customer self sign-up and management,
      usage billing, network accounting, automatic scheduling,
      provisioning and powerful security features enabling Virtual ISP
      and roaming scenarios.  For more information information on
      Emerald please see the <a
      	href="http://www.iea-software.com/emerald">Emerald product
      	page</a>.  A free evaluation license including full product
      support is available form the <a
      	href="http://www.iea-software.com/download">IEA download
      	center</a>.  For an on-line look at the product, a web-based
      demonstration is <a
      	href="http://www.iea-software.com/products/emerald4_demo.cfm"> available
      	here</a>. Emerald runs natively on FreeBSD 5.0 or later.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="wisdomforce" category="DATABASE">
    <name>WisdomForce Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.wisdomforce.com</url>
    <description>
      WisdomForce Technologies delivers software products that help
      data-intensive businesses and governmental entities to improve
      the quality, availability and continuity of the data within their
      IT systems, leading to better business decision-making, increased
      productivity, and an improved bottom line.  WisdomForce's products
      focused on the real-time database data movement and data
      integration market.  WisdomForce is offering solutions for
      real-time moving data across heterogeneous systems.  WisdomForce
      is providing customers with software infrastructure for data
      replication, extract, capture, transformation, movement and
      management of data from one/many database to one/many database.
      WisdomForce FastReader for Oracle data transfer is capable to
      extract data from large production tables into flate files on
      average rate 100,000 rows per second.
    </description>
  </entry>
  <entry id="TrackSite" category="NETWORK">
    <name>TrackSite, Websolutions Software</name>
    <url>http://Tracksite.ru</url>
    <description>
      TrackSite is real-time, private, invisible, automated,
      comprehensive visitor tracking and traffic analytics system for
      websites.  Features include: real-time reporting, comprehensive
      analytics with 57 reports, downloads &amp; robots, referrals,
      searchwords, conversion rates &amp; visitors segmentation,
      webserver &amp; bandwidth stats, automated install &amp; use,
      cross-platform, multi-host, multi-user, data security, very
      compact database, easy ISP switching, scalability, flexible
      deployment, free edition. For more information visit
      <a href="http://TrackSite.ru/">www.TrackSite.ru</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="anthemion" category="MISC">
    <name>Anthemion Software Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.anthemion.co.uk</url>
    <description>
      Anthemion Software Ltd. is a small independent software company
      based in Edinburgh, Scotland, specialising in tools to help
      writers and users of the wxWidgets application development
      framework.  We provide you with the following products:

      <p><a href="http://www.dialogblocks.com/">DialogBlocks</a>
	is a sizer-based GUI resource editor that allows you to
	quickly create professional-looking dialogs, wizards and
	frames for deployment on Windows, Linux, Mac or any other
	supported wxWidgets platform.</p>

      <p><a href="http://www.jutoh.com/">Jutoh</a> makes it easy
	to create ebooks in popular formats that you can sell on
	many ebook sites.  Create your project in seconds from
	existing files using the New Project Wizard; or create
	your book from scratch using the built-in styled text
	editor.  Select a book cover design from Jutoh's template,
	or create your own cover design with the built-in cover
	editor.  Jutoh lets you start creating your ebooks quickly,
	but has plenty of features and configuration for more
	advanced use, including support for contents, index and
	endnotes pages.</p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="supportex" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Supportex.Net</name>
    <url>http://www.supportex.net</url>
    <description>
      Supportex.Net is an outsourced server administration company, based in
      Moscow, Russia.  Offers a tailored FreeBSD configuration, optimization
      and tuning services.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ahsay" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Ahsay Online Backup Software</name>
    <url>http://www.ahsay.com</url>
    <description>
      Ahsay Online Backup Software is a commercial solution for ISPs and
      online backup service providers.  Besides its robust backup features
      and multi-platform support, AhsayOBS is the only fully brandable
      solution on the market.  AhsayOBS is user-friendly, yet feature-rich.
      Not only does it support common features like incremental file backup
      and scheduled backup, it also supports brick-level Exchange backup
      (including Outlook mails, calendar, etc).  AhsayOBS is specially
      designed to backup databases such as MS SQL Server, MySQL Server,
      Oracle, MS Exchange Server, Lotus Domino Server and more.  AhsayOBS
      offers high level of security. Data from multiple AhsayOBS can be
      further replicated to Ahsay Replication Server as an additional level
      of protection.  Besides, data can be restored to a particular snapshot
      across different platforms.  Moreover, extensive APIs and comprehensive
      reports facilitate account management.  Being the global leader with
      over 150,000 installations, AhsayOBS is multilingual in 18 languages,
      and the number is growing.  For more information and a free download,
      visit us at <a href="http://www.ahsay.com">www.ahsay.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="anoigo" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Anoigo</name>
    <url>http://www.anoigo.co.uk</url>
    <description>
      Anoigo is an open source solutions provider, focusing mainly on the SME
      market.  With more than 25 years IT and technology experience we offer a
      full range of services from web development to systems integration.  Our
      main area of expertise includes turnkey systems, system administration,
      penetration testing, Apache, MySQL, PHP and Perl.  We can be reached at
      <a href="mailto:sales@anoigo.co.uk">sales@anoigo.co.uk</a> or at
      <a href="http://www.anoigo.co.uk">http://www.anoigo.co.uk</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="binarysec" category="SECURITY">
    <name>BinarySEC</name>
    <url>http://www.binarysec.com/</url>
    <description>
      BinarySEC is an intelligent web application firewall.  It runs on
      FreeBSD as an Apache module either on i386 and amd64 architectures.
      Its artificial intelligence engine learns normal traffic received on a
      website or any web application (provided it uses Apache) and is then
      able to stop suspicious HTTP requests.  It has two modes: alert
      (suspicious traffic is just reported, not stopped) and blocking mode.
      The webmaster (or the admin) has the ability to make the AI engine learn
      normal traffic so that the profiles of these requests generate no more
      false positives.  After a few days, no more false alerts will appear,
      only suspicious traffic will have been blocked.  BinarySEC is a relevant
      tool to harden a web application.<br/>
      A free trial is available on our website.  It can be installed in a few
      minutes.  <a href="http://www.binarysec.com/page-eng-freetrial.html">Grab
      it from here</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="kernun" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Kernun Firewall</name>
    <url>http://www.kernun.com/</url>
    <description>
      Kernun firewall is a commercial software package consisting of a set
      of application proxies, configuration tools and other utilities,
      delivered with their source code.  It relies on FreeBSD operating
      system and a piece of hardware (currently, i386 PC and amd64 Hammer
      architectures are supported).  Kernun firewall is extremely effective
      in controlling data communication on all network layers.<br/>
      Kernun firewall is designed to mediate legitimate communication between
      hosts on different networks, if it is allowed by firewall policy, while
      stopping both illegitimate communication and network attacks launched
      on one network and aiming at a different network protected by Kernun.
      It can also be used to cease misuse of network resources, detect and
      block viruses, spyware, spam and other unwanted content.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="chartdirector" category="DEV">
    <name>ChartDirector</name>
    <url>http://www.advsofteng.com/</url>
    <description>
      ChartDirector is a powerful chart component for creating professional and
      interactive charts for both web and standalone applications.  Its unique
      layering architecture enables you to synthesize the charts you want using
      standard chart layers.  ChartDirector's comprehensive chart styles
      include pie, donut, bar, line, spline, step line, trend line,
      curve-fitting, inter-line coloring, area, scatter, bubble, floating box,
      box-whisker, waterfall, finance (numerous indicators support), gantt,
      vector, radar, polar, rose, and angular and linear meters and gauges.
      ChartDirector charts are interactive with full suite of mouse events,
      tool tips and are AJAX enabled.<br/><br/>
      ChartDirector includes with the following editions:<br/><br/>
      <ul>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdphp.html'>ChartDirector PHP
	  Charts and Graphs</a></li>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdperl.html'>ChartDirector Perl
	  Charts and Graphs</a></li>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdpython.html'>ChartDirector
	  Python Charts and Graphs</a></li>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdruby.html'>ChartDirector Ruby
	  Charts and Graphs</a></li>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdcpp.html'>ChartDirector C++
	  Charts and Graphs</a></li>
	<li><a href='http://www.advsofteng.com/cdjava.html'>ChartDirector
	  JSP/Java Charts and Graphs</a></li>
      </ul>
      Free trial (no expiration!) available from <a
	href='http://www.advsofteng.com/download.html'>http://www.advsofteng.com/download.html</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="linguasystems" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>Lingua-Systems Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.lingua-systems.com</url>
    <description>
      Lingua-Systems is dedicated to providing high-quality, Unix-based
      software solutions for natural language processing that fulfill
      the principles of simplicity and efficiency and are developed with
      passion founded on solid research.  All our
      <a href="http://www.lingua-systems.com/products.html">products</a>,
      including the
      <a href="http://www.lingua-systems.com/language-identifier/lid-library/">"lid" language identifier</a>,
      are available for FreeBSD.  For more information, visit our website:
      <a href="http://www.lingua-systems.com/">http://www.lingua-systems.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="isoftplus" category="DEV">
    <name>iSoftPlus</name>
    <url>http://www.isoftplus.com</url>
    <description>
      We are software company specialized in developing Internet
      applications.  We are providing entirely open source solutions based
      on FreeBSD, PHP, Apache and MySQL.  Other Linux and FreeBSD based
      services are available as well, including system and network
      administration as well as consulting.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
