<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title 'Resources for Newbies'>
<!ENTITY url.articles "&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles">
<!ENTITY url.books "&base;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.docs">

    <h2><a>Getting &os;</a></h2>

    <p>The latest &os; releases are available <a
	href="&enbase;/where.html">here</a>.  Before you begin,
	please carefully read the <a
	href="&url.books;/handbook/bsdinstall.html">installation
	instructions</a>.</p>

    <h2><a>Learning about &os;</a></h2>

    <ul>
      <li><p>The <a href="&url.books;/handbook/index.html">&os;
	Handbook</a> and <a
	href="&url.books;/faq/index.html">Frequently Asked Questions
	(FAQ)</a> are the main documents for &os;. Essential reading,
	they contain a lot of material for newbies as well as advanced
	users.  For users interested in installing a GUI, see the <a
	href="&url.books;/handbook/x11.html">X Windows</a> chapter.
	</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="&cgibase;/man.cgi">Manual pages</a> are good for
	reference but not always the best introduction for a novice.
	They generally provide information on a specific command,
	driver or service.</p></li>

    </ul>

    <h2><a>Questions and Support</a></h2>

    <ul>
      <li><p>Join the &os;-Questions mailing list to see the questions
	you were too afraid to ask, and their answers. Subscribe by
	filling out the following form: <a
	href="http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-questions">http://lists.FreeBSD.org/mailman/listinfo/freebsd-questions</a>.
	You can look up old questions and answers via the <a
	href="&base;/search/search.html#mailinglists">search</a>
	page.</p></li>

      <li><p>The &os; <a href="https://forums.freebsd.org">Forums</a>
	offer another support channel.  Many users have written various
	tutorials and lots of new users receive help there.</p></li>

      <li><p>You can <a href="&base;/search/search.html">search</a> the
	Handbook and FAQ, the whole web site, or the &os; mailing list
	archives.</p></li>

      <li><p>The <a href="&base;/support.html">Support</a> page
	contains a wealth of information about &os;, including mailing
	lists, user groups, web and FTP sites, release information,
	and links to some sources of &unix; information.</p></li>
    </ul>

    <h2><a>Learning about &os;-derived projects</a></h2>

    <p>&os; is widely used as a building block for other commercial
      and open-source operating systems.  Some of the most widely used
      and publicly available systems are listed below.</p>

    <ul>
      <li><p><a href="http://www.freenas.org">FreeNAS</a> is a storage
	solution that can be installed on virtually any hardware
	platform to share data over a network.  It uses ZFS to protect,
	store, backup, all of your data.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="https://ghostbsd.org">GhostBSD</a> is derived
	from &os;, GhostBSD uses the GTK environment to provide a
	beautiful looks and comfortable experience on the modern BSD
	platform offering a natural and native &unix; work
	environment.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="https://www.midnightbsd.org">MidnightBSD</a> is
	a BSD-derived operating system developed with desktop users
	in mind.  It includes all the software you'd expect for your
	daily tasks: mail, web browsing, word processing, gaming,
	and much more.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="https://nomadbsd.org/">NomadBSD</a> is a
      persistent live system for USB flash drives, based on &os;.
      Together with automatic hardware detection and setup, it is
      configured to be used as a desktop system that works out
      of the box, but can also be used for data recovery, for
      educational purposes, or to test &os;'s hardware
      compatibility.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.pfsense.org">pfSense</a> is a &os;
	based network security solution.  pfSense
	software, with the help of the package system, is able to
	provide the same functionality or more of common commercial
	firewalls, without any of the artificial limitations.  It has
	successfully replaced every big name commercial firewall you can
	imagine in numerous installations around the world.</p></li>
    </ul>

    <h2><a>How to Contribute</a></h2>

    <p>Everyone has something to contribute to the &os; community,
      even newbies! Some are busy working with the new advocacy group
      and some have become involved with the <a
	href="&base;/docproj/docproj.html">Documentation Project</a> as
      reviewers.  Other &os; newbies might have particular skills and
      experiences to share, either computer related or not, or just
      want to meet new newbies and make them feel welcome. There are
      always people around who help others simply because they like
      to.</p>

    <p>Friends who run &os; are a great resource. No book can replace
      chatting on the phone or across a pizza with someone who has the
      same interests, enjoys similar accomplishments, and faces the
      same challenges. If you do not have many friends who use &os;,
      consider using your old &os; CDs to create some more.</p>

    <p><a href="&base;/usergroups.html">User groups</a> are good
      places to meet other &os; users. If there is no one nearby, you
      might consider starting one!</p>

    <p>For more information on getting involved in the community, see
      the <a
	href="&enbase;/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/contributing/index.html">Contributing
	to &os;</a> article.</p>
  </body>
</html>
