<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Development Projects">

<!ENTITY url.articles "../doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles">
<!ENTITY url.books "../doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

<a name="development"></a>

<p>In addition to the mainstream development path of FreeBSD, a number
of developer groups are working on the cutting edge to expand
FreeBSD's range of applications in new directions.  Follow the links
below to learn more about these exciting projects.</p>

If you feel that a project is missing, please send the URL and a short
description (3-10 lines) to
<a href="../mailto.html">www@FreeBSD.org</a>.

<p>In addition, some of these projects regularly submit status reports,
which can be viewed on the <a href="../news/status/status.html">status
reports page</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#documentation">Documentation</a></li>
  <li><a href="../advocacy/index.html">Advocacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="#applications">Applications</a></li>
  <li><a href="#storage">Storage</a></li>
  <li><a href="#kernelandsecurity">Kernel and Security</a></li>
  <li><a href="#devicedrivers">Device drivers</a></li>
  <li><a href="#architecture">Architecture</a></li>
  <li><a href="#misc">Misc</a></li>
  <li><a href="summerofcode.html">Google Summer of Code</a></li>
</ul>

<a name="documentation"></a>
<h3>Documentation</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="../docproj/docproj.html">FreeBSD Documentation Project</a>:
The FreeBSD Documentation Project is a group of people who maintain
and write the documentation (such as the Handbook and FAQ) for the
FreeBSD	project.  If you want to help with the documentation project,
subscribe to the freebsd-doc@FreeBSD.org
mailing list and participate.</li>

<li><a name="newbies" href="newbies.html">FreeBSD Resources for Newbies</a>:
A list of resources to help those new to FreeBSD and &unix; in
general.</li>

<li><a name="diary" href="http://www.freebsddiary.org/">The FreeBSD
Diary</a>: A collection of how-to entries aimed at UNIX
novices.  The aim is to provide a set of step-by-step guides to
installing and configuring various ports.</li>

<li><a href="&url.books;/developers-handbook/index.html">
The FreeBSD Developers' Handbook</a></li>

<li><a href="&url.articles;/contributing/index.html">
Contributing to FreeBSD</a></li>

</ul>

<a name="applications"></a>
<h3>Applications</h3>
<ul>
<li><a name="java" href="../java/index.html">&java; on FreeBSD</a>:
This contains information on where to obtain the latest &jdk; for
FreeBSD, how to install and run it, and a list of &java; software that
you may find interesting.</li>

<li><a name="gnome" href="../gnome/index.html">GNOME on FreeBSD</a>:
This contains information on where to obtain the latest GNOME for
FreeBSD, how to install and run it, latest project news and
updates, FAQ covering FreeBSD-specific GNOME issues, application
porting guidelines and much more.</li>

<li><a name="kde" href="https://freebsd.kde.org">KDE on FreeBSD</a>:
This contains links to the latest KDE releases for FreeBSD, as well as
documentation and tutorials about how to install and run KDE on
FreeBSD.  Project news and a FreeBSD-specific FAQ are also
available.</li>

<li>
<a name="mono" href="http://www.mono-project.com/docs/about-mono/supported-platforms/bsd/">Mono on FreeBSD</a>:
Here you can find information about the state of Mono and C# for FreeBSD.</li>

<li><a name="openoffice" href="https://porting.openoffice.org/freebsd/">
OpenOffice.org on FreeBSD</a>:
Information about the various OpenOffice.org ports.</li>

<li><a href="../ports/index.html">FreeBSD Ports Collection</a>:
The FreeBSD Ports Collection provides an easy way to compile and
install a wide range of applications with a minimum amount of effort.
A list of current ports is available along with a search mechanism
to see if a specific application exists in the Ports Collection.</li>

<li><a href="https://portscout.FreeBSD.org/">FreeBSD Ports distfiles scanner</a>:
A list which checks the Ports Collection for unfetchable distfiles
and provides a summary for each port.</li>

<li><a href="https://FreshPorts.org/">FreshPorts</a>: Provides the most up-to-date list of
ports and port changes.  Add your favourite ports to your watch list and receive email
notification of any changes.</li>

<li><a href="https://portsmon.FreeBSD.org/">PortsMon</a>: Is a server which
  checks the Ports Collection and keeps package building logs and error
  logs for each port.</li>
</ul>

<a name="storage"></a>
<h3>Storage</h3>
<ul>
<li><a name="coda" href="http://www.coda.cs.cmu.edu/">Coda</a>:
A distributed filesystem.  Among its features are disconnected
operation, good security model, server replication and persistent
client side caching.</li>

<li><a name="journaling" href="http://www.ece.cmu.edu/~ganger/papers/">
Journaling versus Soft Updates</a>: Asynchronous Meta-data Protection in File Systems.</li>
</ul>

<a name="kernelandsecurity"></a>
<h3>Kernel, security</h3>
<ul>

<li><a name="trustedbsd" href="http://www.TrustedBSD.org/">TrustedBSD</a>:
Provides a set of trusted operating system extensions to the FreeBSD operating
system.  This includes features such as fine-grained privileges (capabilities),
Access Control Lists, and Mandatory Access Control.  These features are
being integrated back into the base FreeBSD distribution, as well as being
ported to other BSD-derived systems.</li>

<li><a name="kernelstresstest"
  href="https://people.freebsd.org/~pho/stress/index.html">Kernel
  Stress Test Suite</a>:  The purpose of this stress test is to crash
  the system.  The stress test is composed of small test programs and
  scripts. Each test targets a specific area of the kernel.  The key
  concept of this test suite is chaos. Each test sleeps for a random
  number of seconds before it starts up in a random number of
  invocations.</li>

</ul>

<a name="devicedrivers"></a>
<h3>Device drivers</h3>
<ul>

<li><a name="homeauto" href="https://people.FreeBSD.org/~fsmp/HomeAuto/HomeAuto.html">Home Automation</a>:
Using FreeBSD to run appliance controllers, infra-red controllers,
automated telephone systems, and more.</li>
</ul>

<a name="architecture"></a>
<h3>Architecture</h3>
<ul>
<li><a name="ppc" href="../platforms/ppc.html">Porting FreeBSD to PowerPC&reg; systems</a>:
Contains information on the FreeBSD PPC port, such as mailing list
information and so on.</li>

<li><a name="sparc" href="../platforms/sparc.html">Porting FreeBSD to SPARC&reg; systems</a>:
Contains information on the FreeBSD SPARC port including a FAQ,
some early boot code, information on SPARC processors and motherboards,
and other SPARC projects.</li>

<li><a name="sysvr4" href="http://slash.dotat.org/~newton/freebsd-svr4/">
SysVR4 Emulation</a>: This page describes an SysVR4 emulator for
FreeBSD. It is currently capable of running (or walking, in some
cases) a wide-ish variety of SysV executables taken from Solaris&trade;/x86
2.5.1 and 2.6 systems. I have reason to believe that it will also run
SCO UnixWare and SCO OpenServer binaries.</li>

<li><a name="oskit" href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/flux/oskit/">The OSKit</a>:
The OSKit is a framework and a set of 31 component libraries oriented
to operating systems, together with extensive documentation. By
providing in a modular way not only most of the infrastructure
"grunge" needed by an OS, but also many higher-level components, the
OSKit's goal is to lower the barrier to entry to OS R&amp;D and to
lower its costs. The OSKit makes it vastly easier to create a new OS,
port an existing OS to the x86 (or in the future, to other
architectures supported by the OSkit), or enhance an OS to support a
wider range of devices, filesystem formats, executable formats, or
network services. The OSKit also works well for constructing OS-related
programs, such as boot loaders or OS-level servers atop a
microkernel.</li>
</ul>

<a name="misc"></a>
<h3>Misc</h3>
    <ul>
      <li><a name="nanobsd" href="&url.articles;/nanobsd/index.html">NanoBSD</a>:
	NanoBSD is a tool designed to create a possibly reduced FreeBSD
	system image, which is suited to fit on a Compact Flash card
	(or other mass storage medium) in a way which is suitable for
	use in appliance like applications.  The FreeBSD documentation
	collection includes an introductory
	<a href="&url.articles;/nanobsd/index.html">article about NanoBSD</a>,
	which includes useful tips about setting up, running and
	using NanoBSD.</li>

      <li><a name="global" href="http://www.gnu.org/software/global/global.html">GLOBAL</a>:
	A common source code tag system that works the same way across
	diverse environments.  Currently, it supports the shell command line,
	the nvi editor, web browser, the emacs editor, and the elvis editor,
	and the supported languages are C, Yacc, and Java.</li>

      <li><a name="acpi"
	href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/ACPI">ACPI on FreeBSD</a>:
	A Project created to get ACPI working smoothly on FreeBSD.</li>

      <li><a name="testsuite" href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/TestSuite">
	  TestSuite</a>: This project aims to equip FreeBSD with a
	comprehensive test suite that is easy to run out of the box
	and during the development of the system. The goal of the test
	suite is to assist both developers and users in assessing the
	quality of FreeBSD.</li>

    </ul>

</body>
</html>
