<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Summer of Code 2007">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

<p>The FreeBSD Project is proud to have taken part in the Google <a
  href="http://code.google.com/soc">Summer of Code
  2007</a>.  We received more high quality applications this year than
  ever before.  In the end it was a very tough decision to narrow it
  down to the 25 students selected for funding by Google.
  These student projects included security research,
  improved installation tools, new utilities, and more.  Many of the
  students have continued working on their FreeBSD projects even after
  the official close of the program.</p>

<p>We are happy to report that all students made some progress towards
  their goals for the summer, and the 22 students listed below
  completed the program successfully.</p>

<p>Information about the student projects is available from our <a
  href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2007">Summer of Code
  wiki</a> and all of the code is checked into <a
  href="http://perforce.freebsd.org/depotTreeBrowser.cgi?FSPC=//depot/projects/soc2007/">Perforce</a>.
  The summaries below were submitted by the individual students and
  their mentors with minor editing for consistency.</p>

<a name="students"></a>
<h2>2007 Student Projects</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Project:</strong> GNOME front-end to freebsd-update(8)<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Andrew Turner<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.marcus;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>The FreeBSD update front-end is a GTK+ interface to
        freebsd-update. It is split into a GUI to allow system
        administrators to select the binary patches to update or
        rollback and a back-end that communicates with
        freebsd-update. Development of both parts has moved to Berlios
        at <a href="http://developer.berlios.de/projects/facund/">http://developer.berlios.de/projects/facund/</a>.</p>

      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> The back-end is not yet
      ready to enter CVS, but a port is being made for the front-end<br/><br/>
      </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Multicast DNS responder (BSD-licensed)<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Fredrik Lindberg<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.bms;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>Multicast DNS (mDNS) is a part of Zero Configuration
        Networking (Zeroconf) and provides the ability to address
        hosts using DNS-like names without the need of an existing
        (unicast), managed DNS server.</p>

      <p>The Multicast DNS responder (mdnsd), is more or less feature
        complete and is currently in a bug fixing and testing phase.
        A few more features are planned, most notably mdns proxy
        support.  The daemon performs multicast dns queries on behalf
        of clients and acts as a unified cache to all clients.
        Provides the ability to announce its own mdns records onto the
        network.</p>

      <p>The daemons abilities are exposed to clients through libmdns,
        it provides an API to do mDNS queries and to add/remove/list
        records and view/flush cache.  Two consumers exists, one
        console based basic debugging and administrative utility
        (mdns) which simply provides whatever libmdns provides and a
        NSS module (nss_mdns) which integrates mDNS lookups with the
        systems name lookup routines.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> after testing and reviewing<br/><br/>
      </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Unified ports / package system database backend<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Garrett Cooper<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.krion;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This project revised FreeBSD's package tools
        (/usr/src/usr.sbin/pkg_install) to use Berkeley DB files for
        storing information held in /var/db/pkg/*, and use Hash table
        structures.  It also aims to devise a frontend for dealing
        with package and ports installation and management and insert
        virtuals into ports infrastructure to support modular
        components functionality, for dealing with ports installed
        components vs base installed components (OpenSSL, OpenSSH,
        Kerberos).</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Super Tunnel Daemon<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Matus Harvan<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.mlaier;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>The project implements the Super Tunnel Daemon, a tunneling
        daemon using plugins for different encapsulations and
        automagically selecting the best encapsulation in each
        environment.  When the environment changes, the user should not
        notice the transition to a different encapsulation except for
        a small delay.  Connections established within the tunnel
        shall seamlessly migrate to a different encapsulation. In this
        way, mobility is supported as well, even to the extent of
        changing between different physical network interfaces,
        e.g. disabling the wireless interface and plugging in an
        ethernet cable. New encapsulations can easily be added in the
        future using the plugin interface.</p>

      <p>The daemon and several plugins have been written. The daemon
        now has multi-user support, i.e., one server supports multiple
        clients. Plugins implemented so far are UDP, TCP, ICMP,
        DNS. There are also sys patches allowing it to listen on all
        unused UDP and TCP ports as well as processing ICMP echo
        requests in the user space.</p>

      <p>Missing features:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>more plugins (HTTP, SSH,...)</li>
        <li>config file format and parsing</li>
        <li>and some more...</li>
      </ul>

      <p>More details are available at
      <a href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/mtund">http://wiki.freebsd.org/mtund</a></p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> after some additional features
        as part of the Ports Collection<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Rewriting lockmgr(9)<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Attilio Rao<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.jeff;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This project involved rewriting the lockmgr synchronization
        primitive since recent efforts (in particular sun4v porting)
        evicted that this is a strong bottleneck for fs workloads (due
        to its spreadness in VFS land). One of the main goals of the
        rewriting was offering a more customized interface, trimming all
        unused (and possibly bugged) features of lockmgr and offering
        a more intelligent interface (that would help a lot in
        debugging and lock assertions).</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Apple's MacBook on FreeBSD<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Rui Paulo<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.andre;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>Apple's MacBook computers are nicely designed and have neat
        features that other laptops don't. While Mac OS X is a nice
        operating system, UNIX folks (like me) would prefer to run
        other operating systems like FreeBSD. This project
        brings bug fixes and new drivers to FreeBSD that help
        running this OS on this platform.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> some parts committed already<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Security regression tests<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Zhouyi ZHOU<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.rwatson;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>This project involved testing the correctness of FreeBSD
        Mandatory Access Control Framework including correctly passing
        the security label from userland to kernel and
        non-bypassibility of Mandatory Access Control Hooks.
	Specific contributions include:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>A pair of pseudo ethernet drivers used for
          testing network related hooks. To avoid the packet go
          through the lo interface, the IP address in the packet is
          twisted in the driver.</li>

        <li>A framework for logging Mandatory Access Control
 hooks which is called during a period of time.
          <ul>

            <li>In kernel, every non-null label is got externalized
              into human readable string and recorded in a tail queue
              together with the name of hook that got called and
              possible flags or modes (etc. VREAD/VWRITE for
              mac_check_vnode_open hook). There is a thread much like
              audit subsystem's audit_worker logging the queue into a
              userspace file. The userland program use open, ioctl and
              close the /dev/mactest node to trigger and stop the
              logging. The logging file is truncated to zero every
              time the logging mechanism is triggered.</li>

	    <li>In userland, a bison based parsing tool is used to
              parse the logged file and reconstruct the record chain
              which will be compared with testsuite supplied
              configuration file to examine if expected hooks is got
              called and the label/flags/modes are correct. The
              testsuite mainly follows src/tools/regression/fstest,
              modified to adapt to test Mandatory Access Control
              Framework and include tests for signals</li>
          </ul>
        </li>

        <li>The test cases about mandatory access control hooks for
          fifo, link, mdconfig, netinet, open, pipe, rename, rmdir,
          signal, symlink, sysvshm and truncate are written. Two
          security vulnerabilities where found during the test case
          writing.</li>
      </ol>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> GVinum Enhancements<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Ulf Lilleengen<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.le;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>The project schedule was a bit changed in the start, because
        there were some rewriting of some internal parts of
        gvinum. Much of the time went to adapt the rest of gvinum to
        this new event-based system. This rewrite made gvinum less
        vulnerable to race bugs, and made it much easier for a
        developer to reason about the code.</p>

      <p>Improvements were made to the rebuild and syncing process of
        volumes, so that one could still use the volume (e.g. have it
        mounted) while rebuilding or syncing gvinum plexes.</p>

      <p>The growing of striped volumes (includes RAID-5) in the
        background was also implemented.  Perhaps most important, is
        that most important gvinum features were implemented, and many
        bugs were fixed. A lot of testing has been done to make gvinum
        more robust.</p>

      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> yes<br/><br/>
  </li>

<!--
  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Parallelization of the Ports Collection<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Wade Wesolowsky<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.pav;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong> <p>      </p></li>
-->

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> TCP/IP regression test suite<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Nanjun Li<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.gnn;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>The project was about a testing suite for any host's
        perform-ability in TCP/IP networks. N. Li implemented it on a
        FreeBSD machine using libpcap (a library of BSD Packet Filter)
        to sniff frames on MAC layer, decode them into human-readable
        format, and send crafted ones to examinate if the target host
        follows RFC793's requirements.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> no<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Avoiding syscall overhead<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Jesper Brix Rosenkilde<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.scottl;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>In FreeBSD the setproctitle call is implemented with a
        sysctl, this has the unfortunate side effect that this simple
        call locks the Giant-lock. As this call is a simple matter of
        setting a value, it could be better implemented with shared
        memory between the kernel and user-space.</p>

      <p>This project proposes a scheme to securely share process
        specific data between the kernel and a user-space
        process. This is done by having each process allocate a
        special memory page, in which the kernel and user-space
        process can share data. This will give the security needed, as
        the VM-system will make sure that no outside processes can
        fiddle with a process' data. As everything is going on in
        user-space, there is no concern about a rogue process could
        write inside the kernel memory. There is still a locking
        concern, which will be addressed either by locking the entire
        page, or micro-locking each data field on the page.</p>

<!--      <p><strong>XXX: if this is tested/implemented, we need to say it, if it is
        not implemented/tested, we can remove this
        paragraph. XXX</strong> -->

      <p>A suggestion by Howard Su is a multi page scheme, where a
        read/write page is used for things like get/setproctitle and a
        read-only page for things like getpid. And maybe a system wide
        read-only page for things like getdomain, gethostname
        etc.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>
<!--
  <li><strong>Project:</strong> msdosfs Infrastructure<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Brian Chu<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.kib;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong> <p>      </p></li>
-->

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Port OpenBSD's sysctl Hardware Sensors framework<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Constantine A. Murenin<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.syrinx;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>The GSoC2007/cnst-sensors project was about porting the
        sysctl hw.sensors framework from OpenBSD to FreeBSD.  The
        project was successfully completed, and is pending final
        <a href="http://lists.freebsd.org/pipermail/freebsd-hackers/2007-September/021722.html">review
        and integration</a> into the CVS tree.</p>

      <p>The sensors framework provides a unified interface for
        storing, registering and accessing information about hardware
        monitoring sensors.  Sensor types include, but are not limited
        to, temperature, voltage, fan RPM, time offset and logical
        drive status.  In the OpenBSD base system, the framework spans
        sensor_attach(9), sysctl(3), sysctl(8), systat(1),
        sensorsd(8), ntpd(8), and more than 50 drivers, ranging from
        I2C temperature sensors and Super I/O hardware monitors to
        ipmi(4) and RAID controllers.  Several third-party tools are
        also available, for example, a plug-in for Nagios and
        ports/sysutils/symon.</p>

      <p>As a part of this project, all major parts of the framework
        were ported, including sysctl, systat and sensorsd.  Some
        drivers for most popular Super I/O Hardware Monitors were
        ported, too: it(4), supporting most contemporary ITE Tech
        Super I/O, and lm(4), supporting most contemporary Winbond
        Super I/O.  Moreover, some existing FreeBSD drivers were
        modified to use the new framework, for example,
        coretemp(4).</p>

      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> after more testing and review<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Distributed audit daemon<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Alexey Mikhailov<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.bz;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>The basic idea of this project was to implement secure and
        reliable log file shipping to remote hosts. While the
        implementation focuses on audit logs, the goal was to build
        tools that will make it possible to perform distributed
        logging for any application by using a simple API and linking
        with a shared library. The audit logs served as a testbed,
        other logs can be adopted.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not yet, needs further work<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Generic input device layer<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Maxim Zhuravlev<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.philip;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>Originally selected to design and implement a common way to
        retrieve and process data from input devices, the project
        resulted in a code base of a bigger and more generic project --
        <b>Enhanced NewBus</b>. The following features are introduced by
        now: basic functional devices support, filter drivers and
        NewBus input/output subsystem. Functional devices
        (ex. demuxing, muxing, terminals) are supposed to coordinate
        real devices. Each device is handled by a stack of drivers
        (low-level and filters). Filter drivers are to simplify code
        reuse. The NewBus input/output subsystem is designed to push
        io requests through the NewBus graph.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> bus_alloc_resources() Code Update<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Christopher Davis<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.imp;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>Currently, many devices in FreeBSD's source tree use the
        excessively verbose methods of resource allocation and
        deallocation. Numerous calls to bus_alloc_resource() or
        bus_alloc_resource_any() are used to allocate resources, and
        subsequently, multiple calls to bus_release_resource() are
        used to free the resources after an error in allocation or
        when the device is detached.</p>

      <p>Recently, however, the bus_alloc_resources() and
        bus_release_resources() functions have been added. These
        simple wrappers around bus_alloc_resource_any() and
        bus_release_resource() both operate on the same resource
        description, so that much of the repetition once needed to
        allocate and free resources can be mitigated.</p>

      <p>This project updated driver source code where necessary using
        the new functions to make the code related to allocation and
        deallocation simpler and clearer, while making other
        refinements as needed.  Approximately 40 drivers were updated
        during SoC, although testing is still needed. There are likely
        25 or more other drivers that could be updated as well, and
        these are listed on the wiki.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> BSD bintools project (Part I)<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Kai Wang<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.jkoshy;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This project re-implemented part of the GNU binutils
        based on the libelf and libarchive libraries. It will bring
        FreeBSD a BSD Licensed toolchain for processing ELF binary
        files. The project mainly concentrated on
        re-implementing the tools ar(1), ranlib(1), objcopy(1),
        strip(1) and composing corresponding manual pages.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> soon<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Update of Linuxulator for Linux 2.6<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Roman Divacky<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.kib;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This is a continuation of the same project of the last GSoC. While
        the last year the focus was to bring basic 2.6 compatibility to
        FreeBSD, this year was focused on bug fixing and implementing epoll()
        and *at().</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> after a final review<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> FreeBSD 'safety net' IO logging utility<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Sonja Milicic<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.le;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>

      <p>Some administrative operations like filesystem or partition
        table debugging/repair would benefit from an "Undo" function,
        so they can be performed without putting vital data at risk.
        This project's goal was to implement a module which plugs into
        the GEOM framework and allows copy-on-write style logging of
        I/O requests to one or more snapshot files, including the
        possibility to rollback, replay or analyze their
        effects.</p>

      <p>The core functionality of this module and a userland tool was
        finished, but will need more testing/bug fixing.</p>

      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Provide an audit log analysis tool<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Liu Dongmei<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.rwatson;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>A GUI audit log analysis tool which can display audit log in tree view
      and list view and analyze audit log lively. It is important to
      provide a intuitionistic and visualize audit log to
      administrator. This program's intention is to provide a totally
      GUI audit log display, filter and statistic, in addition provide
      expandability when a new type of token added. The Glib library
      is used as a basic platform abstraction library and GTK are used
      to build AuditAnalyzer's GUI.</p>

      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Improve the FreeBSD Ports Collection Infrastructure<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> &a.gabor;<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> &a.sat;<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This project reimplemented the DESTDIR support from the last GSoC
        by the same student in a technically better way. Additionally, the PERL
        support was refactored from bsd.port.mk into its own file and
        enhanced to provide more features.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> already committed<br/><br/>
  </li>

<!--
  <li><strong>Project:</strong> PMC GUI<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Mathieu Prevot<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> Joseph Koshy<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong> <p>      </p></li>
-->

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> http support for PXE<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Alexey Tarasov<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> Ed Maste<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>The goal of this project was to write extendable code wrappers
        (as much as possible in C) to provided by PXE and UNDI
        APIs to support downloading of files via TCP-based protocols
        in the preboot environment. This allows to
        download and prepare the booting of a FreeBSD kernel from a remote
        server via a direct connection or a http proxy.</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> not determined yet<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Graphical installer for FreeBSD (finstall)<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Ivan Voras<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> Murray Stokely<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>This project aims to create a user-friendly graphical
        installer for FreeBSD &amp; FreeBSD-derived systems. The project
        should yield something usable for 7.x-RELEASE, but the
        intention is to keep it as a "second" installer system during
        7.x, alongside sysinstall. In any case, sysinstall will be
        kept for architectures not supported by finstall (e.g. currently
        all except i386 and amd64).</p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> ready to enter the Ports Collection
        after some src patches<br/><br/>
  </li>

  <li><strong>Project:</strong> Porting Linux KVM to FreeBSD<br/>
      <strong>Student:</strong> Fabio Checconi<br/>
      <strong>Mentor:</strong> Luigi Rizzo<br/>
      <strong>Summary:</strong>
      <p>Linux KVM is a Virtual Machine Monitor, part of the Linux
        kernel, that uses Intel VT-x or AMD-V extensions for x86
        processors to create a full virtualization environment.  This
        project consists in porting Linux KVM to the FreeBSD
        kernel.</p>

      <p>Since Linux KVM has a structure similar to that of a device
        driver (actually, it is a device driver, from many points of
        view) core kernel changes are not required to support it, so
        it is an external loadable kernel module, exporting an
        interface based on ioctl() calls to a device descriptor.  Part
        of the project was also the porting of the userspace client for
        that interface, a modified qemu that uses KVM to execute its
        guests.</p>

      <p>A project snapshot at the end of the Summer of Code is
        available.  It supports only AMD-V (SVM) on amd64, as this was
        the hardware used during the development (adding support for
        other platforms is in progress); it is still highly
        experimental code, but it can boot FreeBSD guests.</p>

      <p>For code, further details, and future developments, please refer to:
	<a href="http://feanor.sssup.it/~fabio/soc07/">http://feanor.sssup.it/~fabio/soc07/</a></p>
      <strong>Ready to enter CVS:</strong> no<br/><br/>
  </li>
</ul>

<a name="press"></a>
<h2>FreeBSD Summer of Code Links</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://wiki.freebsd.org/moin.cgi/SummerOfCode2007">FreeBSD Summer of Code 2007 Wiki</a> - with links to student project pages.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</html>
