<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Project Launches FreeBSD 6.0">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<h3>FreeBSD raises the bar for open source operating systems.</h3>

  <p>FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE<br/>
    Berkeley, CA November 4, 2005</p>

  <p>The FreeBSD Project announces the availability of FreeBSD 6.0, an open
    source operating system derived from BSD UNIX, which offers a powerful
    alternative to Linux, Solaris, and Windows. FreeBSD enables enterprise
    organizations to utilize open source technologies that focus on
    reliability, security, and scalability.</p>

  <p>"Yahoo! is impressed with the performance and stability of FreeBSD 6.0,"
    says David Filo, Yahoo! co-founder. Yahoo! is one of many enterprise
    companies that rely on the world-renowned stability and performance of the
    FreeBSD operating system.</p>

  <p>One of the new features in FreeBSD 6.0 is a multithreaded filesystem,
    which greatly improves data access times for local disks, RAID
    configurations, network filesystems, and SANs. Recent performance
    benchmarks show that FreeBSD 6.0 outperforms Linux in raw data
    throughput.</p>

  <p>Additionally, FreeBSD 6.0 extends support for wireless devices such as
    Intel Centrino and adds support for the popular new WPA wireless security
    protocol. Several improvements are incorporated into NDISulator, a
    component of the operating system that allows Windows network drivers to
    run natively under FreeBSD.</p>

  <p>FreeBSD now scales much more efficiently across multiple processor
    systems. Support for 8 or more processors, such as the new dual core AMD
    Opteron configurations, gives consumers a viable alternative against more
    expensive, proprietary hardware platforms and operating systems from IBM,
    HP, and Sun.</p>

<h3>About the FreeBSD Project</h3>

  <p>The FreeBSD Project provides a free, open source operating system for
    several platforms, including Intel x86 and AMD64. FreeBSD is derived from
    BSD, the version of UNIX developed at UC Berkeley. The unencumbered BSD
    license permits modification and redistribution of the software while
    allowing an individual or company to retain intellectual property.</p>

  <p>For more information, please visit
    <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/">www.FreeBSD.org</a>.</p>

<h3>Press Contact</h3>

  <p>For interviews or further information, contact: <a
    href="mailto:marketing@FreeBSD.org">marketing@FreeBSD.org</a>,
    +1-408-943-4100 ext 113; or The FreeBSD Foundation, +1-720-207-5142</p>

</body>
</html>


