<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Press Release: October 31, 2002">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<p></p>

<h3>The Daemon of the Opera: Opera Software Releases Version for FreeBSD</h3>

<p><b>Oslo, Norway, October 31, 2002:</b> Opera Software is proud to
announce the first golden release of its new port to the UNIX variance
FreeBSD. With FreeBSD joining the Opera family, Opera is now available on
eight different operating systems.</p>

<p>The BSD (Berkeley Software Distribution) operating system has its origins
at the University of California, Berkeley. It started out as a supplement to
UNIX, but over time it evolved into several operating systems. Of the
different BSD flavors available, the most widely distributed is FreeBSD,
popular among high-end users like system administrators who are looking for a
fast, reliable operating system.</p>

<p><cite>"Opera and FreeBSD´s users are alike in that they emphasize and
expect stability and reliability. The match between FreeBSD and Opera should
strike a cord with many enterprise customers,"</cite> says Jon S. von
Tetzchner, CEO, Opera Software ASA. <cite>"On a personal level, I'm also happy
to welcome FreeBSD users into the Opera family. FreeBSD is strictly not only
an operating system, but also a community and a philosophy with values I know
resonate well with our own."</cite></p>

<p>The FreeBSD community is enthusiastic to finally be able to surf with
Opera.</p>

<p><cite>"With the release of Opera for FreeBSD, FreeBSD users who download
Opera for FreeBSD can browse the Web with one of the fastest browsers
available on the market,"</cite> says Robert Watson, FreeBSD Core Team member.
<cite>"FreeBSD´s reputation as a reliable and fast desktop operating system is
becoming widely known, and we are glad to see that Opera Software is helping
us create a more complete desktop environment."</cite></p>

<p>Opera 6.1 for FreeBSD can be downloaded from
<a href="http://www.opera.com/">www.opera.com</a>.</p>

<h3>About Opera Software</h3>

<p>Opera Software ASA is an industry leader in the development of Web
browsers for the desktop and embedded markets, partnering with companies
such as IBM, AMD, Symbian, Canal+ Technologies, Ericsson, Sharp and Lineo
(now a division of Embedix). The Opera browser has received international
recognition from end users and the industry press for being faster,
smaller and more standards-compliant than other browsers. Opera is
available on Windows, Mac, Linux, Solaris, FreeBSD, OS/2, Symbian OS and
QNX. Opera Software ASA is a privately held company headquartered in Oslo,
Norway. Learn more about Opera at
<a href="http://www.opera.com/">www.opera.com</a>.</p>

<h3>About the Berkeley Software Distribution Operating System</h3>

<p>Berkeley Software Distribution operating system technologies were
originally developed from 1979 to 1992 by the Computer Systems Research
Group (CSRG) at the University of California at Berkeley. Berkeley-derived
operating system and networking technologies are at the heart of most modern
Unix and Unix-like operating systems. Today, virtually every major Internet
infrastructure provider uses BSD operating systems. BSD operating system
technologies are used by leading mission- critical network computing
environments and are embedded in Internet appliance platforms that require
advanced Internet functionality, reliability and security.</p>

<h3>About the FreeBSD Project</h3>

<p>FreeBSD is a popular open source operating system developed by the FreeBSD
Project and its worldwide team, consisting of more than 5,000 developers
funneling their work to 185 "committer" developers. It is available free of
charge from <a href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/">ftp.FreeBSD.org</a> and also
distributed as a shrink-wrap software product through CompUSA, Fry's, Borders,
Ingram, FreeBSDmall.com and others. FreeBSD includes thousands of ported
applications, including office automation, groupware and multimedia
applications, and is widely used in companies all over the world as a web
server, file server, firewall and router. FreeBSD is distributed under the
Berkeley Software Distribution license, which means that it can be copied and
modified freely or commercially. For more information about the FreeBSD
Project, visit <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org/">www.FreeBSD.org</a>.</p>

<h3>Press Contact</h3>

<p>Opera Software<br/>
Pal A. Hvistendahl<br/>
Marcom Director<br/>
Tel: +47 99 72 43 31<br/>
Fax: +47 24 16 40 01<br/>
<a href="mailto:pal@opera.com">pal@opera.com</a><br/>
US Toll Free: 1-888-624-4846, press only please</p>

<p>The FreeBSD Project<br/>
<a href="mailto:press@FreeBSD.org">press@FreeBSD.org</a></p>

</body>
</html>
