<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Netperf Cluster">
<!ENTITY email 'mux'>


]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.developers">

    <h2>Contents</h2>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
      <li><a href="#donors">Donors</a></li>
      <li><a href="#admins">Netperf Cluster Admins</a></li>
      <li><a href="#resources">Netperf Cluster Resources</a></li>
      <li><a href="#procedures">Netperf Cluster Procedures</a></li>
      <li><a href="#notes">Current Configuration Notes and News</a></li>
    </ul>

    <a name="introduction"></a>
    <h2>Introduction</h2>

    <p>The netperf cluster provides a multi-node, SMP-capable, network
      functionality and performance test capability for the <a
      href="../../">FreeBSD Project</a>, supporting a variety of on-going
      sub-projects including the <a href="./index.html">netperf project</a>,
      and on-going work on
      high performance threading.  The cluster is available on a check out
      basis for developers, who must request accounts be created by
      contacting one of the <a href="#admins">netperf cluster admins</a>.
      The cluster includes both 1gbps and 10gbps test segments, with
      network hardware from a number of vendors.</p>

    <a name="donors"></a>
    <h2>Donors</h2>

    <p>The netperf cluster was made possible through the generous donation
      of a number of organizations, including:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><p><a href="http://www.sentex.ca/">Sentex Data Communications</a>,
	who not only host the complete cluster, provide front-end build
	system, several test systems, and the management infrastructure
	(remote power, serial console, network switch, etc), but also appear
	to be endlessly willing to help configure, reconfigure, and
	troubleshoot at almost any time of day or night.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.freebsdsystems.com/">FreeBSD Systems</a>,
	who through a generous matching grant with the FreeBSD Foundation,
	provide the majority of testing hardware used in the cluster,
	including three dual-Xeon test systems.</p></li>

      <li><p>The <a href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/">FreeBSD
	Foundation</a>, who provided a matching grant for the purposes of
	purchasing testing hardware, as well as taking ownership of hardware,
	offering tax receipts to donors in its role as a non-profit, and
	participating in cluster planning.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.ironport.com">IronPort Systems</a>, who have
	donated a test server.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.ixsystems.com/">iXsystems</a>, who have
	donated several test servers.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.google.com/">Google, Inc.</a>, who have
	donated two test servers.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.cisco.com/">Cisco, Inc.</a>, who have
	donated a 10gbps switch.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.chelsio.com/">Chelsio Communications</a>,
	who have donated two 10gbps network cards.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.myricom.com/">Myricom, Inc.</a>, who have
	donated two 10gbps network cards.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.intel.com/">Intel Corporation</a>, who
	have donated two 10gbps network cards.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="http://www.meinberg-usa.com/">Meinberg</a>, who
	have donated a LANTIME M600 IEEE 1588 Grandmaster Clock.</p></li>

      <li><p>&a.gnn;, who has donated a quad-core AMD test
	system.</p></li>

      <li><p>&a.rwatson;, who has donated a dual-CPU PIII system and a
	Portmaster terminal server.</p></li>
    </ul>

    <p>Donations to support the netperf cluster have an immediate and
      substantial impact on the success of a number of on-going performance
      projects, providing access to high-end hardware to a large number of
      developers.  If you or your company are interested in helping to
      support continued development of the netperf cluster as a resource for
      FreeBSD development, please contact the <a href="#admins">netperf
      cluster admins</a>.</p>

    <a name="admins"></a>
    <h2>Netperf Cluster Admins</h2>

    <p>The FreeBSD netperf cluster is managed by a small team of
      developer/administrators to support SMP development and performance
      testing on high-end hardware.  If you have any questions, including
      questions about access to the cluster as a developer, or about possible
      future donations of testing hardware, please feel free to contact them
      via netperf-admin at FreeBSD.org.</p>

    <a name="resources"></a>
    <h2>Netperf Cluster Resources</h2>

    <p>The Netperf cluster consists of several systems interconnected using a
      management network, as well as individual back-to-back gigabit ethernet
      links for a test network.  Please refer to the <a
	href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/TestClusterOneReservations">Test
	Cluster One Reservations</a> page on the &os; wiki for the
      current allocations.</p>

    <a name="procedures"></a>
    <h2>Netperf Cluster Procedures</h2>

    <p>As the netperf cluster is a centrally managed and shared resource,
      understanding and consistent following of its procedures is important.
      In particular, following of the procedures makes it easier for
      developers to have reasonable expectations about the configuration of
      systems in the cluster, as well as to avoid treading on each others
      toes.</p>

    <p>Pointers and documentation on Netperf Cluster procedures can be found
      on the <a href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/TestClusterOnePointers">Test
      Cluster One Pointers</a> page on the FreeBSD wiki.</p>
  </body>
</html>
