<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "About &os;'s Technological Advances">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

    <h1>&os; offers many unique features.</h1>

    <p>No matter what the application, an operating system should take
    advantage of every resource available.  &os;'s focus on
    performance, networking, and storage combines with ease of system
    administration and comprehensive documentation to realize the full
    potential of any computer.</p>

    <h2>A complete operating system based on 4.4BSD.</h2>

      <p>&os;'s distinguished roots derive from the <b>BSD</b>
	software releases from the Computer Systems Research Group at
	the University of California, Berkeley.  Over twenty years of
	work have been put into enhancing &os;, adding
	industry-leading scalability, network performance, management
	tools, file systems, and security features.  As a result,
	&os; may be found across the Internet, in the operating system
	of core router products, running root name servers, hosting
	major web sites, and as the foundation for widely used desktop
	operating systems.  This is only possible because of the
	diverse and worldwide membership of the
	volunteer &os; Project.</p>

      <p><b>&os;&nbsp;10.X</b> introduces many new features
	and replaces many legacy tools with updated versions.</p>

      <ul>
	<li><b>bhyve</b>:
	  A new BSD licensed, legacy-free hypervisor has been imported
	  to the &os; base system.  It is currently able to run all
	  supported versions of &os;, and with the help of the
	  grub-bhyve port, OpenBSD and Linux.</li>

	<li><b>KMS And New drm2 Video Drivers</b>:
	  The new drm2 driver provides support for AMD GPUs up to the
	  Radeon HD 6000 series and provides partial support for
	  the Radeon HD 7000 family.  &os; now also supports
	  Kernel Mode Setting for AMD and Intel GPUs.</li>

	<li><b>Capsicum Enabled By Default</b>:
	  Capsicum has been enabled in the kernel by default, allowing
	  sandboxing of several programs that work within the
	  "capabilities mode", such as:
	  <ul>
	    <li>tcpdump</li>
	    <li>dhclient</li>
	    <li>hast</li>
	    <li>rwhod</li>
	    <li>kdump</li>
	  </ul>
	</li>

	<li><b>New Binary Packaging System</b>:
	  &os; now uses pkg, a vastly improved package management
	  system that supports multiple repositories, signed packages,
	  and safe upgrades.  The improved system is combined with
	  more frequent official package builds for all supported
	  platforms and a new stable branch of the ports tree for
	  better long term support.</li>

	<li><b>Unmapped I/O</b>:
	  The newly implemented concept of unmapped VMIO buffers
	  eliminates the need to perform costly TLB shootdowns for
	  buffer creation and reuse, reducing system CPU time by up to
	  25-30% on large SMP machines under heavy I/O load.</li>
      </ul>

      <p><b>&os;&nbsp;9.X</b> brought many new features
	and performance enhancements with a special focus on desktop
	support and security.</p>

      <ul>
	<li><b>OpenZFS</b>:
	  &os; 9.2 includes OpenZFS v5000 (Feature Flags), including
	  the feature flags:
	  <ul>
	    <li>async_destroy</li>
	    <li>empty_bpobj</li>
	    <li>lz4_compress</li>
	  </ul>
	  which allow ZFS destroy operations to happen in the
	  background, make snapshots consume less disk space, and
	  offers a better compression algorithm for compressed
	  datasets.</li>

	<li><b>Capsicum Capability Mode</b>:
	  Capsicum is a set of features for sandboxing support, using
	  a capability model in which the capabilities are file
	  descriptors.  Two new kernel options CAPABILITIES and
	  CAPABILITY_MODE have been added to the GENERIC kernel.</li>

	<li><b>Hhook</b>:  (Helper Hook) and khelp(9) (Kernel Helpers)
	  KPIs have been implemented.  These are a superset of the
	  pfil(9) framework for more general use in the kernel.  The
	  hhook(9) KPI provides a way for kernel subsystems to export
	  hook points that khelp(9) modules can hook into to provide
	  enhanced or new functionality to the kernel.  The khelp(9)
	  KPI provides a framework for managing khelp(9) modules,
	  which indirectly use the hhook(9) KPI to register their hook
	  functions with hook points of interest within the kernel.
	  Together, they allow a structured way to dynamically extend the
	  kernel at runtime in an ABI-preserving manner.</li>

	<li><b>Accounting API</b> has been implemented.  It can keep
	  per-process, per-jail, and per-login class resource
	  accounting information.  Note that this is neither built nor
	  installed by default.  To build and install this, specify
	  the option RACCT in the kernel configuration file and rebuild
	  the base system as described in the &os; Handbook.</li>

	<li><b>Resource-limiting API</b> has been implemented.
	  It works in conjunction with the RACCT resource accounting
	  implementation and takes user-configurable actions based on
	  the set of rules it maintains and the current resource
	  usage.  The rctl(8) utility has been added to manage the
	  rules in userland.  Note that this is neither built nor
	  installed by default.</li>

	<li><b>USB</b> subsystem now supports USB packet filter.
	  This allows capturing packets which go through each USB
	  host.  The architecture of the packet filter is similar to that of
	  bpf.  The userland program usbdump(8) has been
	  added.</li>

	<li><b>Infiniband support</b>: OFED (OpenFabrics Enterprise
	  Distribution) version 1.5.3 has been imported into the
	  base system.</li>

	<li><b>TCP/IP network</b> stack now supports the mod_cc(9)
	  pluggable congestion control framework.  This allows TCP
	  congestion control algorithms to be implemented as
	  dynamically loadable kernel modules.  Many kernel
	  modules are available: cc_chd(4) for the CAIA-Hamilton-Delay
	  algorithm, cc_cubic(4) for the CUBIC algorithm, cc_hd(4)
	  for the Hamilton-Delay algorithm, cc_htcp(4) for the H-TCP
	  algorithm, cc_newreno(4) for the NewReno algorithm, and
	  cc_vegas(4) for the Vegas algorithm.  The default algorithm
	  can be set by a new sysctl(8) variable
	  net.inet.tcp.cc.algorithm.</li>

	<li><b>SU+J</b>: &os;'s Fast File System now supports soft
	  updates with journaling.  It introduces an intent log into
	  a softupdates-enabled file system which eliminates the need
	  for background fsck(8) even on unclean shutdowns.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>&os; includes a number of other great features:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><b>Firewalls:</b>
	  The base system includes IPFW and IPFilter, as well as a
	  modified version of the popular pf with improved SMP
	  performance.  IPFW also includes the dummynet feature,
	  allowing network administrators to simular adverse network
	  conditions, including latency, jitter, packet loss and
	  limited bandwidth.</li>

	<li><b>Jails</b>
	  are a light-weight alternative to virtualization.
	  Allowing processes to be restricted to a namespace with
	  access only to the file systems and network addresses
	  assigned to that namespace.  Jails are also Hierarchical,
	  allowing jails-within-jails.</li>

	<li><b>Linux emulation</b>
	  provides a system call translation layer that allows
	  unmodified Linux binaries to be run on &os; systems.</li>

	<li><b>DTrace</b>
	  provides a comprehensive framework for tracing and
	  troubleshooting kernel and application performance issues
	  while under live load.</li>

	<li><b>The Ports Collection</b> is a set of more than 23,000 third
	  party applications that can be easily installed and run on
	  &os;.  The ports architecture also allows for easy
	  customization of the compile time options of many of the
	  applications.</li>

	<li><b>Network Virtualization:</b> A container ("vimage") has
	  been implemented, extending the &os; kernel to maintain
	  multiple independent instances of networking state.	  Vimage facilities can be used independently to create fully
	  virtualized network topologies, and jail(8) can directly
	  take advantage of a fully virtualized network stack.</li>
      </ul>
  </body>
</html>
