<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD 2.2.7 Errata Notes">
]>
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.download">

<pre>
The file <a href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/2.2.7-RELEASE/ERRATA.TXT">
ERRATA.TXT</a> contains post-release ERRATA for 2.2.7 and should always
be considered the definitive place to look *first* before reporting
a problem with this release.  This file will also be periodically
updated as new issues are reported so even if you've checked this
file recently, check it again before filing a bug report.  Any
changes to this file are also automatically emailed to:

	freebsd-stable@FreeBSD.org

For 2.2.7 security advisories, see:

<a href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/CERT/">ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/CERT/</a>

For the latest information.

---- Security Advisories:

Current active security advisories for 2.2.7:   None

---- System Update Information:
<strong>o XFree86:  The XF86Setup utility sometimes fails with an XIO
  error (visible on the 2nd VTY) rather than starting properly if you
  run it during system installation time.  This is not a new bug and
  has been seen in previous releases of FreeBSD, but it seems to happen
  far more reliably with 2.2.7 now (for some as yet unknown reason).</strong>

Fix: Should this happen to you, run /usr/X11R6/bin/XF86Setup by hand
     after the system comes up off the hard disk for the first time.
     For some reason, when not run off the boot floppy or CD, it works
     perfectly (making this one somewhat more difficult to debug).

<strong>
o Release notes state that Texas Instruments ThunderLAN PCI NICs are
  supported in 2.2.7.</strong>

Fix: This was an embarrassing mis-merge from the 3.0 release notes and,
     indeed, those cards are only supported in 3.0-current.  Please ignore
     this section of the release notes and any other docs which claim that
     the ThunderLAN NICs are supported in 2.2.7.

<strong>
o rshd was broken during -Wall cleanup, as noted in PR#7500</strong>

Fix: This was fixed in the 2.2-stable branch as of 1998/07/24 04:32:21
     in revision 1.9.2.9 of /usr/src/libexec/rshd/rshd.c.  Obtain the
     fixed version via CVSup (see instructions in handbook or simply
     ``pkg_add ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/development/CVSup/cvsupit.tgz''
     and follow the instructions) or get it from FTP at:
     <a href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/FreeBSD-stable/src/libexec/rshd/rshd.c">ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD/FreeBSD-stable/src/libexec/rshd/rshd.c</a>

</pre>

<p></p><a href="../index.html">Release Home</a>
</body>
</html>
