<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "Trademark Legend">
]>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.about">

<p>FreeBSD is a registered trademark of The FreeBSD Foundation.</p>

<p>The FreeBSD Logo is a trademark of The FreeBSD Foundation.</p>

<p>See <a href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/">The FreeBSD
  Foundation's</a> <a
    href="https://www.freebsdfoundation.org/legal/trademark-usage-terms-and-conditions/">Trademark
  Usage Terms and Conditions</a> page for information on use of the
  FreeBSD marks.</p>

<p>Adobe, Acrobat, Acrobat Reader, and PostScript are either
  registered trademarks or trademarks of Adobe Systems Incorporated in
  the United States and/or other countries.</p>

<p>AMD, Am486, Am5X86, AMD Athlon, AMD Duron, AMD Opteron, AMD-K6,
  Athlon, &Eacute;lan, Opteron, and PCnet are trademarks of Advanced Micro Devices,
  Inc.</p>

<p>Apple, FireWire, Mac, Macintosh, Mac OS, Quicktime, and TrueType
  are trademarks of Apple Computer, Inc., registered in the United
  States and other countries.</p>

<p>CVSup is a registered trademark of John D. Polstra.</p>

<p>IBM and PowerPC are trademarks of International Business Machines
  Corporation in the United States, other countries, or both.</p>

<p>IEEE, POSIX, and 802 are registered trademarks of The Institute of
  Electrical and Electronics Engineers, Inc.</p>

<p>Intel, Celeron, EtherExpress, i386, i486, Itanium, Pentium, and
  Xeon are trademarks or registered trademarks of Intel Corporation or
  its subsidiaries in the United States and other countries.</p>

<p>Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds in the United
  States.</p>

<p>Motif, OSF/1, and UNIX are registered trademarks and IT DialTone
  and The Open Group are trademarks of The Open Group in the United
  States and other countries.</p>

<p>MySQL is a registered trademark of MySQL AB in the United States,
  the European Union and other countries.</p>

<p>Silicon Graphics, SGI, and OpenGL are registered trademarks of
  Silicon Graphics, Inc., in the United States and/or other countries
  worldwide.</p>

<p>Sparc, Sparc64, SPARCEngine, and UltraSPARC are trademarks of SPARC
  International, Inc in the United States and other countries.
  Products bearing SPARC trademarks are based upon architecture
  developed by Sun Microsystems, Inc.</p>

<p>Sun, Sun Microsystems, SunOS, Solaris, and Java are trademarks or
  registered trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. in the United States
  and other countries.</p>

<p>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to
  distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks.  Where those
  designations appear on this website, and the FreeBSD Project was aware
  of the trademark claim, the designations have been followed by the
  '&trade;' or the '&reg;' symbol.</p>

</body>
</html>
