<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries SYSTEM "entries.dtd">
<!--
  Available continents: < africa | asia | australia | europe
  | nzealand | namerica | samerica >
-->

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/en/commercial/consult.xml,v 1.2 2004/05/05 07:41:04 josef Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="tech" continent="namerica">
    <name>757 Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.757tech.net</url>
    <description>
      757 Technologies offer installation and integration of FreeBSD, as
      well as FreeBSD co-location and maintenance. Serving the Hampton
      Roads area of Virginia. Please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@757tech.net">info@757tech.net</a> for more
      information. We can also be reached by telephone at (757) 233-9460.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aaronsen" continent="namerica">
    <name>Aaronsen Group, Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.aaronsen.com/freebsd/</url>
    <description>
      Aaronsen Group, Ltd. advises on and implements a wide range of
      internetworking technologies, including remote access, wide area
      networks, international telecommunications, Intranetworking, web
      applications and local area services. Many of our custom web-enabled
      solutions are engineered using FreeBSD, Apache, mod_perl, and
      MySQL/Oracle. Please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@aaronsen.com">info@aaronsen.com</a>. Our web site
      is at <a href="http://www.aaronsen.com">http://www.aaronsen.com</a>
      and we can be reached via telephone at +1.412.391.6000.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Achean" continent="europe">
    <name>Achean</name>
    <url>http://www.achean.com/</url>
    <description>
      Achean is a consultancy dedicated to helping our customers achieve
      better use of organisational information and real cost savings
      through the use of open source software. The <a
      href="http://www.achean.com/HardwareSoftware/AcheanFramework/">Achean
      Framework</a> explains our holistic approach to implementing
      solutions. We work with several open source operating systems, and
      many desktop and server based <a
      href="http://www.achean.com/HardwareSoftware/Applications/">applicati
      ons</a>. Where necessary, we can provide custom built servers,
      workstations and diskless clients. We also provide support and
      training services for our customers. Based in the UK, Achean can be
      contacted through our <a
      href="http://www.achean.com/Contact/">contact page</a>. If you are
      looking for a new job, please take a look at our <a
      href="http://www.achean.com/Careers/">careers</a> section.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Adimus" continent="europe">
    <name>Adimus GmbH &amp; Co. KG</name>
    <url>http://www.adimus.de/</url>
    <description>
      Adimus GmbH &amp; Co. KG is a company based in Bochum, Germany. As a
      consulting partner we provide services in system administration for
      all flavors of Unix and Microsoft Windows, design and maintenance of
      LANs and WANs, IT security auditing and database management.
      Solutions for intra- and internet servers as well as our firewall
      toolkit are based on FreeBSD and third-party products from Compaq,
      Peacock, Cisco and Ascend. For more information please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@adimus.de">info@adimus.de</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.adimus.de/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Advance" continent="namerica">
    <name>Advance Systems Group</name>
    <url>http://www.advansys.net/</url>
    <description>
      Advance Systems Group builds, administrates, and maintains
      Intranet/Internet networks using FreeBSD and other UNIX operating
      systems. ASG also provides a variety of other services including
      domain name hosting, web site construction, and software training.
      For more information, please phone us at +1.317.507.4229, e-mail <a
      href="mailto:sales@advansys.net">sales@advansys.net</a>, or <a
      href="http://www.advansys.net/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ASG" continent="namerica">
    <name>ASG Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.asgtechnologies.com/</url>
    <description>
      ASG Technologies' Professional Services division offers network
      security management products and services. Staffed by experienced
      information technology and systems professionals, ASG Professional
      Services has in-depth experience in network systems design,
      integration and management across diverse computing platforms. For
      more information, please phone us at +1.506.460.5400, e-mail <a href=
      "mailto:consulting@asgtechnologies.com">consulting@asgtechnologies.co
      m</a>, or <a href="http://www.asgtechnologies.com/">visit our web
      site</a> and follow the Professional Services Links.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AlphaZed" continent="europe">
    <name>AlphaZed, Ltd</name>
    <url>http://uk.AlphaZed.COM/</url>
    <description>
      AlphaZed, Ltd offers UNIX consulting, system administration and
      programming, with primary focus on FreeBSD. We have over a decade of
      UNIX and networking experience. Available for anything from C
      programming to system administration, and networking to web site
      building and hosting. We are located in SE London. For more
      information, please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@uk.AlphaZed.COM">info@uk.AlphaZed.COM</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Atlas" continent="namerica">
    <name>Atlas Software Engineering</name>
    <url>http://www.atlase.com</url>
    <description>
      Atlas Software Engineering offers custom programming for FreeBSD and
      other flavors of Unix. Atlas specializes in applications using PHP,
      C++, Perl, PostgreSQL, and LDAP. Usage on our applications ranges
      from 1 to 20,000,000 hits per day. For more information, email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@atlase.com">info@atlase.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AYN" continent="namerica">
    <name>AYN &amp; Associates</name>
    <url>http://www.aynassociates.com</url>
    <description>
      AYN &amp; Associates, based in Austin, TX, is a software and internet
      consulting company specializing in FreeBSD. We provide a full range
      of services including setting up FreeBSD servers, LAN setups, setting
      up internet services such as mail and news servers, proxies, web
      servers. We also provide custom programming solutions in most
      operating systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BITNETS" continent="namerica">
    <name>BITNETS Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.bitnets.ca</url>
    <description>
      BITNETS Inc. specializes in BIND, Apache, Postfix, Courier-IMAP and a
      variety of server components running on FreeBSD with emphasis on
      security and stability. Services include <a
      href="http://www.netguru.ca">consulting</a> on server evaluation,
      installation and configuration and FreeBSD-based managed <a
      href="http://www.mailhosting.ca">secure e-mail hosting</a>. BITNETS
      sells commercial <a href="http://www.mailservers.ca">mail
      servers</a>, retail boxed computer peripherals and <a
      href="http://www.pcx.bitnets.ca">platform-independent network
      appliances</a> at discounted prices. We are located at <a
      href="http://www.cityplaza.ca">City Plaza</a> in St. Albert, serving
      the Edmonton area of Alberta, Canada. Call us at +1 (780) 418-5151,
      toll-free in North America at 1-877-BITNETS (1-877-248-6387) for
      general enquiries or 1-877-NETGURU (1-877-638-4878) for tech support,
      or <a href="https://secure.bitnets.com/message/">e-mail us</a>.
      Winners of the chamber of commerce InfoTech Award of Distinction.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Brevik" continent="europe">
    <name>Brevik, Peter</name>
    <url>http://users.lindesign.se/~pb/</url>
    <description>
      Brevik, Peter Provides custom programming in C, Pascal, Sh/Csh, Perl,
      X-window, Assembler. Digital electronics construction. HTML
      documentation. Network and internet protocols applications. Specific
      application experience in RDS, Teletext, I2C, ISO9660. For enquiries
      email <a href="mailto:pb@ludd.luth.se">pb@ludd.luth.se</a> or have a
      look at <a href="http://users.lindesign.se/~pb/">the website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BMK" continent="australia">
    <name>B.M.K. Industries</name>
    <url>http://www.bmk.com.au</url>
    <description>
      B.M.K. Industries is located in Melbourne Australia and specializes
      in setting up low cost routers and servers (Web, E-Mail, FTP, DNS and
      Secure Web Servers ) all using FreeBSD. Setting up Permanent Modem &amp;
      ISDN Internet Connections is also a specialty. <a
      href="http://www.bmk.com.au">Please visit our web page.</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Boulder" continent="namerica">
    <name>Boulder Labs</name>
    <url>http://www.boulderlabs.com/</url>
    <description>
      Boulder Labs (Colorado) is a software consulting company specializing
      in FreeBSD, embedded systems, digital processing, security and system
      administration. We have built products requiring numerous device
      drivers, disk optimization up through elaborate GUIs and specialized
      applications. Bi-monthly we publish Source Code Unix articles in
      ";login:" magazine and on our web server. Please contact us at
      +1.303.530.2056 or <a
      href="mailto:info@boulderlabs.com">info@boulderlabs.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BSDConsulting" continent="europe">
    <name>BSD Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.bsdconsulting.no/</url>
    <description>
      BSD Consulting provides consulting services related to Internet
      servers/infrastructure, programming, FreeBSD &amp; BSD operating
      systems, security auditing/firewalls, system administration, etc.
      Based in Oslo, Norway.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="catpipe" continent="europe">
    <name>catpipe Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.catpipe.net/</url>
    <description>
      catpipe Systems ApS provide managed services and support contracts
      for FreeBSD implemented on rackmountable servers preloaded with
      FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Clue" continent="namerica">
    <name>Clue Computing, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.clue.com/</url>
    <description>
      Clue Computing, Inc. has over 10 years of UNIX experience,
      specializing in system administration, networking, and security.
      Custom application development and testing available, including
      device drivers, kernel work, etc. We offer sales, assembly, and
      installation of FreeBSD systems for any application. For more
      information, email <a href="mailto:info@clue.com">info@clue.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Codeangels" continent="europe">
    <name>Codeangels Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.codeangels.com</url>
    <description>
      Codeangels Solutions GmbH based in Switzerland, region Zuerich.
      Offers its customers a range of IT Security, Network and UNIX
      Services. We utilize and support FreeBSD in our services and
      solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CodeGen" continent="namerica">
    <name>CodeGen Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.codegen.com/</url>
    <description>
      CodeGen, Inc. provide consulting and programming services,
      specializing in embedded systems. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:info@codegen.com">info@codegen.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Collective" continent="namerica">
    <name>Collective Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.colltech.com</url>
    <description>
      Collective Technologies is the recognized leader in systems
      management services for distributed enterprise computing
      environments. Collective Technologies highly skilled consultants
      combine technical expertise with solid business sense to develop
      world-class IT solutions. Collective Technologies specializes in
      keeping complex computer systems running reliably offering a full
      range of support services including UNIX, NT, Linux, FreeBSD, OpenBSD
      and NetBSD to address the needs of a client.s systems management
      lifecycle. The company is headquartered in Austin, Texas, with 19
      offices nationwide. For more information, visit <a
      href="http://www.colltech.com">our website</a> or e-mail us at <a
      href="mailto:contact@colltech.com">contact@colltech.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ComputerMavericks" continent="namerica">
    <name>Computer Mavericks</name>
    <url>http://mavericks.critesclan.com</url>
    <description>
      Computer Mavericks is a full-spectrum UNIX consulting company, since
      1987, serving the entire Texas Panhandle from our office in Canyon,
      Texas. We feature FreeBSD as our operating system of choice. We can
      provide you with a complete enterprise solution tailored to your
      needs. We do hardware, software solutions, web development,
      firewalls, security, and more. We convert the world to FreeBSD, one
      happy client at a time! Email <a
      href="mailto:mavericks@critesclan.com">Lee Crites</a> or call
      806-655-2250 and discover what it is like to be a satisfied client.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ConnectionsUSA" continent="namerica">
    <name>Connections USA</name>
    <url>http://www.connectionsusa.com/</url>
    <description>
      Connections, USA is a FreeBSD-based Internet Service provider. We
      provide hosting and co-location services and web site development.
      Other FreeBSD-based services are available as well, including system
      and network administration as well as consulting. Check out our <a
      href="http://www.connectionsusa.com/">corporate Web page</a> and <a
      href="http://www.iserve.com/">http://www.iserve.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoreDigital" continent="australia">
    <name>Core Digital</name>
    <url>http://www.core-digital.com</url>
    <description>
      Core Digital is based in Perth, Western Australia. We are a
      consulting company specializing in OpenBSD, FreeBSD, Linux and
      Windows. We work with firewalls, Virtual Private Networks, Database
      Servers, Email and Web Servers, Security, WAN/LAN implementations,
      Multi OS networks. For more information please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@core-digital.com">info@core-digital.com</a> or
      visit our <a href="http://www.core-digital.com">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DaemonTechnologies" continent="namerica">
    <name>Daemon Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.daemontech.com</url>
    <description>
      Daemon Technologies is located in the heart of Silicon Valley,
      California and provides a full range of systems and network
      consulting specializing in the needs of ISP's and those building a
      web presence. We can provide UNIX support and administration
      contracts and on-site training. We also offer custom built, high
      performance, fault tolerant, X86 based workstations and servers
      tailored to your needs or choose a pre-configured package ready with
      FreeBSD pre-installed to your specifications. Please <a
      href="http://www.daemontech.com">visit our webpage</a> or call us at
      408-719-0263
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DaemonWare" continent="samerica">
    <name>DaemonWare</name>
    <url>http://www.daemonware.com.ar/</url>
    <description>
      DaemonWare offers UNIX consulting, system administration, network
      solution, programming and security; with several UNIX systems:
      FreeBSD, OpenBSD, Linux and others. We have over 5 years of UNIX and
      networking experience and programming experience. Specialized for
      Internet services. For further information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.daemonware.com.ar/"> ower web </a>site or email us
      at <a
      href="mailto:info@daemonware.com.ar">info@daemonware.com.ar</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DatapipeCommunications" continent="namerica">
    <name>Datapipe Communications</name>
    <url>http://www.datapipecomm.com/</url>
    <description>
      Datapipe Communications, based out of Wilmington, Delaware,
      specializes in all flavors of Unix and Microsoft Windows. We offer
      service in network design of LAN's and also WAN's. Solutions for
      intranet and internet servers as well as firewall solutions using
      FreeBSD. The Web Hosting division of Datapipe Communications only
      uses FreeBSD, and we are confident in the reliability of this
      operating system. For more information please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@datapipecomm.com">info@datapipecomm.com</a> or
      visit our website at <a
      href="http://www.datapipecomm.com/">www.datapipecomm.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Dextra" continent="samerica">
    <name>Dextra Solu&#231;&#245;es em Inform&#225;tica</name>
    <url>http://www.dextra.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      Dextra Solu&#231;&#245;es em Inform&#225;tica. Specialized
      consulting in TCP/IP networks, capacity and contingency planning,
      UNIX systems and network administration, system security and
      firewalls, VPNs implementation, Internet/Intranets projects. For more
      information, please phone us at +55.19.251.3644 (Brazil), e-mail <a
      href="mailto:staff@dextra.com.br">staff@dextra.com.br</a>, or <a
      href="http://www.dextra.com.br/">visit our web site</a> (in
      Portuguese).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DieWebmaster" continent="europe">
    <name>Die Webmaster Gmbh</name>
    <url>http://www.diewebmaster.at</url>
    <description>
      Die Webmaster Gmbh - We are a consulting company from Linz, Austria
      and offer a wide range of FreeBSD based services: FreeBSD
      installation, integration, troubleshooting, maintenance, FreeBSD
      based hosting (for example jail servers), serverhousing, hardware
      selection, configuration and support. e-mail: <a
      href="mailto:info@diewebmaster.at">info@diewebmaster.at</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EssenzConsulting" continent="namerica">
    <name>Essenz Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.essenz.com</url>
    <description>
      Essenz Consulting is a web services and products provider. We offer
      custom built High-Performance Intel based <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/open.html">Workstations</a> and <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/server.html">Servers</a>. These systems
      are 100% FreeBSD compatible. Our systems feature Ultra2-LVD SCSI,
      high speed networking, Dual Pentium III and Dual Pentium III XEON
      processors, and many other fault tolerant and backup features. For
      more information contact <a
      href="mailto:sales@essenz.com">sales@essenz.com</a> or visit us at <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com">http://www.essenz.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TheFreeBSDMall" continent="namerica">
    <name>The FreeBSD Mall</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsdmall.com/</url>
    <description>
      The FreeBSD Mall offers several different levels of support contracts
      for FreeBSD. Support is available on a per-incident basis, or as a
      convenient, extensible annual contract. Our highly trained technical
      support staff will handle your requests in a professional and
      efficient manner and will provide detailed responses to your needs by
      phone, fax, or email. The FreeBSD Mall staff has over 8 years of
      experience supporting FreeBSD.
  For more information, please see <a
      href="http://www.freebsdmall.com/support/">our support page</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FarNorthNetworks" continent="australia">
    <name>Far North Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.networks.nq.nu/</url>
    <description>
      Far North Networks, Based in Innisfail, North Queensland (About 100Km
      South of Cairns). Focus is on business network support providing low
      cost file/print servers based on FreeBSD. We also specialize in
      setting up internet gateways/firewalls. For more information send us
      an email to <a
      href="mailto:info@networks.nq.nu">info@networks.nq.nu</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FrigateNetworks" continent="namerica">
    <name>Frigate Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.frigate.com/</url>
    <description>
      frigate networks provides network troubleshooting, system
      administration, kernel development and ports of BSD software to
      commercial products such as routers and firewalls. Our Email, DNS,
      and WWW servers run FreeBSD. We also provide network management
      solutions based on HTTP and tcl. For more information please <a
      href="http://www.frigate.com/">visit our web site</a>, call us at
      +1.650.903.2266, or send email to <a
      href="mailto:info@frigate.com">info@frigate.com></a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FSCInternet" continent="namerica">
    <name>FSC Internet</name>
    <url>http://www.fscinternet.com/</url>
    <description>
      FSC Internet is Canada's largest FreeBSD consulting firm. FSC's
      clients include numerous top-tier corporations (e.g. Mazda, Heinz),
      as well as mid-sized companies (e.g. the Vermont Telephone Company)
      and the public sector. FSC provides full consulting, implementation,
      support, and training services for all FreeBSD applications,
      including a special focus on security, high-performance Web
      applications, and Intranets. Please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@fscinternet.com">info@fscinternet.com</a> or call
      us at +1.416.921.4280 for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FasterRasterSystems" continent="namerica">
    <name>Faster Raster Systems</name>
    <url>http://cessna.tippecanoe.com/fastrr.htm</url>
    <description>
      Faster Raster Systems is a FreeBSD, X11, Graphics, Hardware drivers
      consulting company. For further details, please <a
      href="http://cessna.tippecanoe.com/fastrr.htm">visit our web
      site</a>, or email us at <a
      href="mailto:jay@tippecanoe.com">jay@tippecanoe.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GurixWebProfessionals" continent="namerica">
    <name>Gurix Web Professionals</name>
    <url>http://www.gurix.com</url>
    <description>
      Gurix Web Professionals Web Development, design, and custom
      application programming using both open source and proprietary
      environments. Services also include private consulting, emergency
      response coordination and various IT solutions to maximize the
      effectiveness of your business.
    </description>
  </entry>
  <entry id="BackWatcher" continent="namerica">
    <name>BackWatcher, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.backwatcher.com/</url>
    <description>
      BackWatcher, Inc., while specializing in security (firewalls, VPNs,
      security audits, intrusion detection systems, etc.), handles
      installation and configuration, systems integration, performance
      tuning, disaster recovery, network architecture and programming on
      FreeBSD, NetBSD, OpenBSD, Linux and many commercial UNIX systems. For
      additional information, visit our website at <a
      href="http://www.backwatcher.com/">www.backwatcher.com</a>, email <a
      href="mailto:info@backwatcher.com">info@backwatcher.com</a> or call
      813-979-1633.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HCS" continent="europe">
    <name>HCS Hanseatischer Computerservice GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.hcs.de/</url>
    <description>
      HCS Hanseatischer Computerservice GmbH. Located in Hamburg, Germany,
      we offer professional FreeBSD support, consulting and programming, as
      well as system setup, administration and maintenance. For more
      information, please contact us at +49.40.55974770, e-mail <a
      href="mailto:support@hcs.de">support@hcs.de</a> , or <a
      href="http://www.freebsd-support.de/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HerrinSoftware" continent="namerica">
    <name>Herrin Software Development</name>
    <url>http://www.hsdi.com/</url>
    <description>
      Herrin Software Development, Inc., creator of <em>Qddb</em>, provides
      custom software development, internet consulting, general computer
      consulting, and training services. For more information email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@hsdi.com">info@hsdi.com</a> or <a
      href="http://www.hsdi.com/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GregLehey" continent="australia">
    <name>Greg Lehey</name>
    <url>http://www.lemis.com/~grog/</url>
    <description>
      Greg Lehey has over 20 years industry experience in all system
      programming and systems administration disciplines, including device
      drivers, kernel debugging, compilers, libraries, performance
      analysis, and site planning. He is the author of <a
      href="http://www.lemis.com/vinum.html">
	The Vinum Volume Manager</a>, a virtual disk driver which includes
      software RAID, and also the books
      <a href="http://www.ora.com/catalog/port/noframes.html">
	Porting UNIX Software</a> and <a
      href="http://www.cdrom.com/titles/freebsd/bsdbook.phtml">
	The Complete FreeBSD</a>. Contact him <a
      href="mailto:grog@FreeBSD.org">
	via Email</a>,
      or visit his <a href= "http://www.lemis.com/~grog">web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IKTech" continent="europe">
    <name>IKTech</name>
    <url>http://www.iktech.net</url>
    <description>
      IKTech Dipl.-Ing. Gernot Schmied is a high-end systems integrator and
      UNIX competence center located in Vienna, Austria. We especially
      focus on telecommunications, networking and security aspects for NPO,
      corporate and Service Provider/Carrier customers. We use selected
      commercial products as well as FreeBSD, OpenBSD, NetBSD, Linux and
      Solaris and are the premier competence center with regards to
      advanced routing gateways. For inquiries please contact <a
      href="mailto:office@iktech.net?subject=IKTech%20inquiry%20with%20rega
      rds%20to%20www.freebsd.org%20listing">office@iktech.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InformSystem" continent="asia">
    <name>Inform System Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.inform.co.jp/</url>
    <description>
      Inform System Inc. is a FreeBSD/Internet/DataBase consulting company.
      Located in Osaka Japan, we offer a wide range of services to school
      and small businesses. For further details, please <a
      href="http://www.inform.co.jp/">visit our web site</a>, or send email
      to <a href="mailto:info@inform.co.jp">info@inform.co.jp</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="innominate" continent="europe">
    <name>innominate AG</name>
    <url>http://innominate.de/</url>
    <description>
      innominate AGis a Linux, *BSD and Open Source service provider based
      in Berlin, Germany. Not only as consulting partner but also as system
      administrator, programmer, supporter and trainer we offer the full
      range of services with a heavy focus on Open Source products. Many of
      our tailor-made products are engineered using apache, Perl, Zope,
      MySQL and Oracle running on Linux and *BSD. For further information
      please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@innominate.de">info@innominate.de</a> or visit our
      <a href="http://innominate.de/">website</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InterACT" continent="europe">
    <name>InterACT</name>
    <url>http://www.interact.se</url>
    <description>
      InterACT is a Sweden based provider of Consultancy and Custom
      Development Services. Principal consultant <a
      href="mailto:cl@interact.se">Chris Lindbergh</a> has over10 years
      system software development experience on BSD based platforms. Areas
      of expertise include Firewall and Networking System setup, custom
      development in C and C++, and supply of turnkey solutions. For
      further information, contact us by email at: <a
      href="mailto:info@interact.se">info@interact.se</a>, or phone Sweden
      on +46 (0)920-888 03
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="inTEXT" continent="namerica">
    <name>inTEXT Communications</name>
    <url>http://www.networkinformation.com</url>
    <description>
      inTEXT Communications was founded in 1994 as a Unix Management
      Provider. We support FreeBSD, BSDi, Solaris and other Unix variants.
      Services include co-location, tele-commuting, and on-site service
      anywhere in North America. We support Government and Industry as well
      as the private sector. <a
      href="http://www.networkinformation.com/contact_info.php">Email</a>
      or call us for more information (toll free within USA on 800.309.8996
      or internationally on 604.484.2426).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Schweikhardt" continent="europe">
    <name>Jens Schweikhardt</name>
    <url>http://www.schweikhardt.net/</url>
    <description>
      Jens Schweikhardt, located near <b>Stuttgart/Germany</b>, is a
      FreeBSD committer with 20 years of Unix experience who won several
      national and international programming contests. If you have a
      problem that can be solved using the Unix toolbox (preferably C,
      perl, shell) he is the one to make it happen. With his background in
      Unix Standardization he will make sure your investment runs portably
      and efficiently on all the Unices you care for. Contact him via <a
      href="mailto:schweikh@FreeBSD.org">schweikh@FreeBSD.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Polstra" continent="namerica">
    <name>John Polstra</name>
    <url>http://www.polstra.com/</url>
    <description>
      John Polstra, of Polstra &amp; Co., Inc., has been a UNIX developer
      since 1978, and was a FreeBSD Core Team member from 1997-2000.
      Developer of the <em>CVSup</em> network software update package and
      the <em>ElfKit</em> ELF tool set, his specialties include network
      protocols, language tools, UNIX internals, and UNIX applications. For
      more information, please send email to <a
      href="mailto:jdp@polstra.com">jdp@polstra.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Stacey" continent="europe">
    <name>Julian Stacey</name>
    <url>http://www.berklix.com/~jhs/</url>
    <description>
      Julian Stacey maintains a <a
      href="http://www.berklix.com/~jhs/consultants.html">FreeBSD
      Commercial Consultants Index</a>. Be sure to visit his page!
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MediaCenter" continent="europe">
    <name>MediaCenter</name>
    <url>http://www.umc.se/</url>
    <description>
      MediaCenter, Ume&#230;, Sweden. Located in northern Sweden we offer
      professional consulting and programming for secure inter/intranet
      solutions using FreeBSD and UNIX(-like) operating systems. We also
      work high performance database programming, primarily using
      PostgreSQL. For more information, please send email to <a
      href="mailto:info@umc.se">info@umc.se</a>, or visit our website (<a
      href="http://www.umc.se/">http://www.umc.se/</a>)
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MindStep" continent="namerica">
    <name>MindStep Corp.</name>
    <url>http://www.mindstep.com/</url>
    <description>
      MindStep Corp. configure and maintain Intranet/Internet networks
      using FreeBSD and other Unix operating systems. MindStep also offers
      products and provides software development services customized to fit
      the needs of corporations of any size.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MidwestSystems" continent="namerica">
    <name>Midwest Systems Solutions, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.midwestsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      Midwest Systems Solutions Inc. , based in Winnipeg Canada, provides
      hardware, software and consulting services including LAN, WAN, remote
      access, file and printer servers, Internet solutions and support and
      administration of FreeBSD and Linux systems. Midwest Systems
      specializes in Web, FTP, Internet Gateways, firewall solutions based
      on FreeBSD and Linux. Midwest Systems Solutions also offers both
      virtual and dedicated webhosting solutions. For more information,
      please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@midwestsystems.com">mailto:info@midwestsystems.com</a>
	or visit our website at <a
      href="http://www.midwestsystems.com/">www.midwestsystems.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Neturn" continent="namerica">
    <name>Neturn Corp.</name>
    <url>http://neturn.sinacity.com/netserv/</url>
    <description>
      Neturn Corp., based in Vancouver, Canada, provides complete solutions
      on selective and fine-tuned hardware and software (BSDs as primary
      server OSs) platforms to meet the <b>demand from e-commerce,
      telecom, manufacturing, industrial, aerospace, medical applications
      where stability and reliability are mandatory</b>. For detailed
      information, please visit <a
      href="http://neturn.sinacity.com/netserv/">http://neturn.sinacity.com
      /netserv</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netgraft" continent="namerica">
    <name>Netgraft Corp.</name>
    <url>http://netgraft.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netgraft Corp. is a technology consulting firm that specializes in
      open source technologies like Linux, FreeBSD, MySQL, Apache,
      Sendmail, BIND, etc. We're New York City based and can provide
      on-site support and customized business solutions based on these
      technologies.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netizen" continent="australia">
    <name>Netizen</name>
    <url>http://netizen.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Netizen, based in Melbourne, Australia, provide Internet and Open
      Source consultancy services, including FreeBSD installation,
      configuration, support contracts, applications development,
      E-Commerce solutions, etc. See <a
      href="http://netizen.com.au/">http://netizen.com.au/</a> or email <a
      href="mailto:info@netizen.com.au">info@netizen.com.au</a> for more
      information.</description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OmarSiddique" continent="namerica">
    <name>Omar Siddique</name>
    <url>http://www.heedme.com/resume</url>
    <description>
      Omar Siddique is a Washington, D.C. area consultant with a broad
      array of experience in FreeBSD, Linux, Solaris, and IRIX. His
      specialties include systems integration, network security, and set-up
      of internet services. Custom application design is also available.
      Contact him <a href="mailto:omar@heedme.com">via email</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Omniscient" continent="namerica">
    <name>Omniscient Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.omniscient.com/</url>
    <description>
      Omniscient Technologies is a Washington D.C. based consulting group
      with a broad array of experience in *BSD, Solaris, Linux and many
      other varieties of UNIX specializing in highly scalable systems,
      systems integration and network security. Custom application design
      also available. Contact via <a
      href="mailto:info@omniscient.com">info@omniscient.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenWorld" continent="namerica">
    <name>OpenWorld</name>
    <url>http://www.stdio.com/</url>
    <description>
      OpenWorld has been providing computer, network, and security
      consulting since 1994. Our clients? range from Fortune 500 companies
      to regional small businesses. Our engineers each have at least 10
      years of experience in Unix systems and networks. We provide full
      service consulting, implementation, installation, security, and
      support for FreeBSD, SUN Solaris, SCO Unixware, SCO OpenServer, SGI
      Irix, IBM AIX, Compaq Digital Unix, and Cisco IOS. Please email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@stdio.com">info@stdio.com</a> or call us at
      606-514-1800 for further information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Puryear" continent="namerica">
    <name>Puryear Information Technology, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.puryear-it.com</url>
    <description>
      Puryear Information Technology, LLC provides open source application
      support, integration services, and technology management expertise to
      the Southeastern United States. Our company plays a pivotal role in
      the design and deployment of open source solutions--we have worked
      with companies to design and manage FreeBSD and Linux web farms;
      deployed open source-based clustering software to ensure high
      availability of critical network services; performed critical
      performance tuning and software integration for a popular spam filter
      appliance; and integrated Samba into Internet-accessible, VPN-based
      file services. Phone: +1-225-343-3056.
    </description>

    </entry>
  <entry id="PeterDufault" continent="namerica">
    <name>Peter Dufault</name>
    <url>mailto:dufault@hda.com</url>
    <description>
      Peter Dufault, of HD Associates. Peter has over 15 years experience
      in medical device control, high performance simulation systems,
      digital closed-loop feedback systems, realtime UNIX-like systems, and
      UNIX device drivers. For more information, please send email to <a
      href= "mailto:dufault@hda.com">dufault@hda.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PHBSolutions" continent="europe">
    <name>PHB Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.phbsolutions.com</url>
    <description>
      PHB Solutions, based in Belgium, provides *BSD installation,
      maintenance, support and consulting services (file servers, web
      servers, mail servers, database servers, routers). For more
      information, please contact <a
      href="mailto:philippe.bresoux@phbsolutions.com">philippe.bresoux@phbs
      olutions.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PhilBudne" continent="namerica">
    <name>Phil Budne</name>
    <url>http://www.ultimate.com/phil/resume.html</url>
    <description>
      Phil Budne is a Boston area consultant who has worked professionally
      with BSD and other Unix systems since 1985. Services include
      development and porting of kernel extensions, device drivers, network
      protocol implementation, and applications, as well as network and
      system administration. For more information contact <a href=
      "mailto:phil+fbsd@ultimate.com">phil+fbsd@ultimate.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PineInternet" continent="europe">
    <name>Pine Internet</name>
    <url>http://www.pine.nl/</url>
    <description>
      Pine Internet implements LAN, WAN and remote access solutions, offers
      Unix support and administration contracts and advises ISP's and other
      corporate customers concerning their network and server setup. Pine
      specializes in <a href="http://security.pine.nl/">Internet
      security</a>, performs security auditing services on demand, and
      offers firewall solutions based on FreeBSD. Other products we offer
      are webhosting, facility management and leased lines. Among the
      products we use are FreeBSD, Cisco routers, PHP, Apache, Perl,
      Solaris and MySQL. Pine has 8+ years of Unix and Internet experience.
      We feature some of the largest ISP's in the Netherlands as our
      customers. For more information, please contact <a
      href="mailto:info@pine.nl">info@pine.nl</a> or visit our website at
      <a href="http://www.pine.nl/">www.pine.nl</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PotentialTechnology" continent="namerica">
    <name>Potential Technology</name>
    <url>http://www.potentialtech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Potential Technology is based in Ohio and western Pennsylvania. We
      specialize in FreeBSD-based solutions and have experience integrating
      FreeBSD with Apple, Microsoft and other Unix environments in file,
      print, mail, web, database and proxy server applications. For more
      information, please email <a
      href="mailto:moreinfo@potentialtech.com">moreinfo@potentialtech.com</a>,
      visit our <a href="http://www.potentialtech.com/">website</a> or
      call 1-412-793-4257.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PotterSystems" continent="namerica">
    <name>Potter Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.pottersystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      Matthew R. Potter has over 8 years in UNIX IP Networks, specializes
      in BSD, OS X and Network Consulting and is located in Northern
      Virginia. You can reach him via email at <a
      href="mailto:mpotter@pottersystems.net">Matthew R. Potter</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PoulHenningKamp" continent="europe">
    <name>Poul-Henning Kamp</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsd.org/~phk/</url>
    <description>
      Poul-Henning Kamp has over 12 years in UNIX &amp; Networks, and is a
      former FreeBSD Core Team member. Poul developed <em>phkmalloc</em>,
      <em>tcl_nm</em>, <em>tcl_db</em>, <em>tcl_snmp</em> and more, and was
      the Release Engineer for several FreeBSD releases. Poul resides in
      Denmark, and can be reached via email at <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">phk@FreeBSD.org</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RandDAssociates" continent="europe">
    <name>R and D Associates, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.RnDAssociates.com/</url>
    <description>
      R &amp; D Associates, Inc. developed ServeTheWeb.com utilizing FreeBSD
      running Apache. We employed consulting services from <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">Poul-Henning Kamp</a> to develop our
      Virtual Server solution (which is now available in <a
      href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD</a> 4.0). <p> <a
      href="http://ServeTheWeb.com/">ServeTheWeb.com</a> is our System
      Admin level of Virtual Servers. Please visit <a
      href="http://www.ServeTheWeb.com/"> http://www.ServeTheWeb.com</a>
      for additional information on this product. </p> <p> R &amp; D
      Associates, Inc. is an application development firm specializing in
      client/server app. dev. We use FreeBSD running Apache and utilizing
      PHP and MySQL (As well as NT with ASP and SQL/Access). </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Secnetix" continent="europe">
    <name>Secnetix GmbH and Co KG</name>
    <url>http://www.secnetix.de/</url>
    <description>
      Secnetix GmbH &amp; Co KG -- located in Munich, Germany -- has a
      strong focus on BSD systems and offers professional consulting
      services, ranging from basic administration, programming and
      security-related tasks to sophisticated projects involving design,
      implementation and maintenance of complex network setups. For more
      information, please <a href="http://www.secnetix.de/">visit our web
      site</a> or send a message to <a
      href="mailto:info@secnetix.de">info@secnetix.de</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BrianSomers" continent="europe">
    <name>Brian Somers</name>
    <url>http://www.Awfulhak.org/brian/</url>
    <description>
      Brian Somers has over 10 years in UNIX, Networks, C &amp; C++. Brian is
      responsible for the <em>PPP</em> code in FreeBSD, and located in NW
      London. You can reach him via email at <a
      href="mailto:brian@Awfulhak.org">brian@Awfulhak.org</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SouthernGazer" continent="australia">
    <name>Southern Gazer</name>
    <url>http://www.southerngazer.com</url>
    <description>
      Southern Gazer is a consulting company with 20 years PC technical
      support experience based in Sydney's idyllic Sutherland Shire. Our
      focus is helping businesses get their computers working right while
      spending as little as possible on IT. We're passionate supporters of
      Open Source products and can help the average business save money and
      gain reliability by using systems such as FreeBSD on their file
      servers, print servers, e-mail systems plus lots more. We also supply
      a complete range of Linux and BSD CD's at ultra low prices. Please
      drop by our <a href="http://www.southerngazer.com">website</a>, email
      us at <a
      href="mailto:info@southerngazer.com">info@southerngazer.com</a>, or
      call us on 02 9532 1217 to have a chat.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Syntonet" continent="europe">
    <name>Syntonet Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.syntonet.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      Syntonet Ltd is UK based provider of Consultancy and Custom
      Development Services. Principal consultant <a
      href="mailto:rob@syntonet.co.uk">Rob Pickering</a> has over 10 years
      system software development experience on BSD based platforms. Areas
      of expertise include firewall and networking system setup, custom
      development in C and C++, and supply of turnkey solutions. For
      further information, contact us by email at <a
      href="mailto:info@syntonet.co.uk">info@syntonet.co.uk</a>, call
      +44.870.166.4400 (Voice) or +44.870.166.4411 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SysConfigConsulting" continent="namerica">
    <name>SysConfig Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.sysconfig.com/</url>
    <description>
      SysConfig Consulting designs, configures, and installs FreeBSD based
      email gateway solutions, Dial-on-Demand ISDN, and T-1 Network to
      Network, Network to Internet Connections for businesses in the
      Southeastern United States. For more information, please send e-mail
      to <a href="mailto:info@sysconfig.com">info@sysconfig.com</a>, or <a
      href="http://www.sysconfig.com/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ThinkSec" continent="europe">
    <name>ThinkSec AS</name>
    <url>http://www.thinksec.no/</url>
    <description>
      ThinkSec AS offers security-related consulting and software
      development services, primarily on FreeBSD but also on other POSIX
      platforms. Experience ranges from programming embedded
      microcontrollers, through writing and deploying security
      infrastructure software, to developing web applications. Based in
      Oslo, Norway.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TundraWare" continent="namerica">
    <name>TundraWare Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tundraware.com/</url>
    <description>
      TundraWare Inc. provides FreeBSD related consultancy in all contexts,
      from Embedded to large Transaction Processing systems. We have
      extensive International experience and can provide services in
      network design, systems architecture, development, deployment and
      operations. Contact us via telephone on 847/827-1706, via email to <a
      href="mailto:info@tundraware.com"> info@tundraware.com</a> or write
      to us at TundraWare Inc., 817 Fairmont Court, Des Plaines, IL 60018,
      USA.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="UnixPorting" continent="namerica">
    <name>UnixPorting</name>
    <url>http://www.UnixPorting.com/</url>
    <description>
      UnixPorting.com specializes in the porting of existing software to
      new operating systems or hardware. In addition to porting, we
      specialize in C and Perl programming, Unix system administration and
      security, and open source
      technologies (FreeBSD, Perl, Apache,
      mod_perl, MySQL, etc.). For more information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.UnixPorting.com/">our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CSRCorporation" continent="namerica">
    <name>CSR Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.comsys.com/</url>
    <description>
      CSR Corporation is a Portland, OR, based consulting company with
      offices in Portland, OR; San Jose, CA; and Vero Beach, FL. CSR
      specializes in network applications for IPSs and CLECs, applying open
      network technologies for complete customer solutions. CSR has been in
      business since 1986. Telephone: 503-708-4330.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Camtech" continent="australia">
    <name>Camtech Pty Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.camtech.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Camtech Pty Ltd The Consulting Services Division of Camtech provides
      a broad range of technical and professional services to assist
      businesses to achieve higher levels of productivity through efficient
      use of Information Technology. Services available encompass all
      aspects of information systems scoping and analysis, design,
      implementation, integration, administration, testing, training and
      maintenance. Camtech is a provider of FreeBSD-based solutions,
      including Internet gateway servers, firewalls, and Intranet servers.
      Phone +61 8 8303 3300.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WilliamRichard" continent="namerica">
    <name>William Richard &amp; Associates</name>
    <url>http://www.tdl.com/~wdr/consulting.html</url>
    <description>
      William Richard &amp; Associates offers FreeBSD, Internet, and e-commerce
      consulting, implementation, and support options for clients
      throughout the San Francisco Bay Area. Visit our website or <a
      href="mailto:wdr@tdl.com">e-mail us</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WorkgroupTechnology" continent="namerica">
    <name>Workgroup Technology Partners, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.wgtech.com</url>
    <description>
      Workgroup Technology Partners, Inc.We sell and support Unix systems
      including Solaris, HP/UX, AIX, Linux and FreeBSD. For comments refer
      to <a href="http://www.wgtech.com">our site</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WorldServe" continent="namerica">
    <name>WorldServe Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.worldserve.net</url>
    <description>
      WorldServe Consulting offers FreeBSD installation, configuration and
      maintenance consulting services to businesses in Northern Virginia.
      We also offer web site development and custom web solutions. Over
      four years of experience. Check out our <a
      href="http://www.worldserve.net">web site</a> or e-mail us at <a
      href="mailto:info@worldserve.net">info@worldserve.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SecurityAudit" continent="africa">
    <name>Security Audit and Control Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.sacs.co.za/</url>
    <description>
      Security Audit and Control Solutions (SACS) provides information
      security consultation and IT auditing services and offers
      professional FreeBSD support. SACS has developed a complete range of
      Technological Risk Management solutions using FreeBSD as an anchor
      for data analysis. Firewalls deployed using FreeBSD makes a cost
      effective solution in any organization and SACS can implement a
      secure FreeBSD firewall with caching engines, Network Address
      Translation (NAT) and proxies. For additional information please
      contact <a href="mailto:pearcem@sacs.co.za">Mervin Pearce</a> or
      visit <a href="http://www.sacs.co.za">http://www.sacs.co.za</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Paladin" continent="australia">
    <name>Paladin Corporation Pty, Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.paladincorp.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Paladin Corporation Pty, Ltd Providing Software engineering, Systems
      Integration and multi-tier Commercial support for all aspects of
      FreeBSD networking and Security. We also have an E-Cart solution and
      a Dispatch system for FreeBSD. Visit <a
      href="http://www.paladincorp.com.au/">
      http://www.paladincorp.com.au/</a> for details.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EDILtd" continent="namerica">
    <name>EDI Ltd Consulting Engineers</name>
    <url>http://www.ediltd.com</url>
    <description>
      EDI Ltd Consulting Engineers. We provide consulting services for
      FreeBSD as well as local and wide area network design. Our
      diversified staff allows us to help you in all the areas your project
      requires, from cabling to encryption, network security audits,
      network design and network health studies. We have successfully
      completed several FreeBSD installations for mission critical
      operations, using it as a firewall, web server or mail server. If you
      would like to discuss your project with us, please contact us as
      (770) 956-7000, or <a
      href="mailto:info@ediltd.com">info@ediltd.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Bellamy" continent="nzealand">
    <name>Bellamy Consulting Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.bellamy.co.nz</url>
    <description>
      Bellamy Consulting Ltd, based in
	 Auckland, New Zealand, is a
      consulting company specializing in Linux, FreeBSD, NetBSD and
      OpenBSD. Our main focus is on Internet servers (Web Servers &amp;
      Caches, Email, DNS, FTP, Databases, etc.), software and security
      (Firewalls, VPNs, Proxies). See our web site for more information, or
      contact us directly at <a
      href="mailto:info@bellamy.co.nz">info@bellamy.co.nz</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CrepidoSystems" continent="europe">
    <name>Crepido Systems AB</name>
    <url>http://www.crepido.com</url>
    <description>
      Crepido Systems AB provides services for custom software development
      and system design under BSD and other Unixes. We have 10+ years
      experience in Unix programming and system design using Unix as
      building block.
	  Crepido System AB operates mainly in Sweden but
      requests outside Sweden are welcome.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MarkTinguely" continent="namerica">
    <name>Mark Tinguely</name>
    <url>http://www.cs.ndsu.NoDak.edu/~tinguely/</url>
    <description>
      Mark Tinguely has provided Network and Unix solutions for over ten
      years. These solutions include work with Unix kernels and Unix
      applications, TCP/IP applications, Local Area Network protocol
      debugging, and BSD device drivers. Mark has authored BSD device
      drivers for 3 video capture boards, an Asynchronous Transfer Mode
      (ATM) network card, and a Watchdog card.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AnansiInnovations" continent="namerica">
    <name>Anansi Innovations</name>
    <url>http://www.ainnovations.com/</url>
    <description>
      Anansi Innovations provides comprehensive, cutting-edge system and
      software design for your business. From hardware selection and
      configuration to interface design and release management, we can
      build an enterprise that takes best advantage of the expanding
      Internet market. Our experience includes computer system design
      and integration, interactive software, interface design, release
      management, cross-platform coordination, e-commerce, and
      business-to-business applications. For more information email <a
      href="MAILTO:info@ainnovations.com">info@ainnovations.com</a> or
      phone (617) 995-2590.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ITworksConsulting" continent="australia">
    <name>ITworks Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.itworks.com.au</url>
    <description>
      ITworks Consulting is a privately owned information technology
      consultancy, situated in the central business district of
      Melbourne, Australia. The business consists of a specialized team
      of consultants who aim to provide information technology solutions
      to meet the needs of the business community. We provide a range of
      FreeBSD based web hosting, web database development and e-commerce
      services as well as professional FreeBSD consulting services and
      support contracts. For more information please visit our <a
      href="http://www.itworks.com.au">web site</a> or contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@itworks.com.au">info@itworks.com.au</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BlackHatNetworks" continent="namerica">
    <name>Black Hat Networks</name>
    <url>http://blackhatnetworks.com</url>
    <description>
      Black Hat Networks offers premium IT consulting and FreeBSD based
      hosting services for the sophisticated customer: administration,
      management, web hosting, web design, FreeBSD shells, nationwide
      Internet access, co-location, programming, hardware and computers,
      data warehousing and more, all with the emphasis on security.
      Because We believe that <i>security is not a convenience, it is a
      necessity.</i>
      </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Raditex" continent="europe">
    <name>Raditex AB</name>
    <url>http://raditex.se/</url>
    <description>
      Raditex AB are a firm of consultants and also do education in Unix.
      We have long experience with all kinds of Unix systems not only
      FreeBSD or Linux. For more information phone us at +46.8.6949270 or
      give us an email at <a
      href="mailto:info@raditex.se">info@raditex.se</a> or <a
      href="http://raditex.se/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Metadesign" continent="australia">
    <name>Metadesign</name>
    <url>http://www.metadesign.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Metadesign located in Hobart, Tasmania, Australia is a FreeBSD
      consultancy, providing configuration, installation and system
      maintenance of FreeBSD hosted Internet services and applications.
      Email <a href="mailto:info@metadesign.com.au">us</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Mike_Meyer" continent="namerica">
    <name>Mike_Meyer</name>
    <url>http://www.mired.org/home/mwm/</url>
    <description>
      Mike Meyer of Meyer Consulting has been providing Unix-based
      solutions since 1976, and web-based applications since 1992. These
      solutions range from chemical systems modeling to device drivers, and
      the web applications have ranged from community-building applications
      to web based software release systems. For more information, please
      contact <a href="mailto:mwm@mired.org">mwm@mired.org</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TheLinuxBox" continent="namerica">
    <name>The Linux Box</name>
    <url>http://www.linuxbox.nu/</url>
    <description>
      The Linux Box, located in Ann Arbor, Michigan, provides consulting
      and training services for open source operating systems and products,
      including FreeBSD and Linux. For more information, contact <a
      href="mailto:info@linuxbox.nu">info@linuxbox.nu</a> or view our
      website at <a href="http://www.linuxbox.nu">www.linuxbox.nu</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BillWells" continent="namerica">
    <name>Bill Wells</name>
    <url>mailto:bill@twwells.com</url>
    <description>
      Bill Wells does C programming, FreeBSD administration, network
      administration, and Web development. He's been programming for over
      25 years, developing for the Internet (largely on FreeBSD), 10 years,
      ISP work, 6, and Web development, 4. Check out his <a
      href="http://www.twwells.com/">home page</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Tetrapod" continent="europe">
    <name>Tetrapod Communications Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tetrapod.com</url>
    <description>
      Tetrapod Communications Inc. is a technical consultancy based in
      Harlow, Essex in the United Kingdom offering custom programming and
      administration services. Our services include Custom Programming
      (Java, C++, perl) CIFS (Samba), E-Commerce, Internet (Web)
      Programming, Network Administration, System Administration (FreeBSD,
      OpenBSD, Linux, Solaris). Contact us at <a
      href="mailto:sales@tetrapod.com">sales@tetrapod.com</a> or <a
      href="http://www.tetrapod.com/">www.tetrapod.com</a> or by phone on
      +44(0)8451 275272.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LANCO" continent="asia">
    <name>LANCO Global Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.lancoglobal.com/</url>
    <description>
      LANCO Global Systems (LGSL), based in India, Hyderabad, with offices
      in USA and UK, provides and specializes in <i>Application
      Development, Shell Scripting, PHP, C, C++ and Perl Programming,
      Networking Solutions, Unix device driver development, Web page
      Designing and Hosting, Web Server Solutions and configurations, ISP
      Services especially on Linux, FreeBSD and Solaris</i>. For more
      information, please email us at <a
      href="mailto:services@lancoglobal.com">services@lancoglobal.com</a>
      or call us at 0091-9849043975 or FAX us at 0091-040-3755413.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NS3G" continent="namerica">
    <name>NS3G.COM</name>
    <url>http://www.ns3g.com/</url>
    <description>
      NS3G.COM, based out of Toronto, Ontario, Canada, offers a variety of
      services and products. We specialize in products that run under
      FreeBSD and other *NIX systems but also support other platforms.
      Solutions for firewalls, LAN's, WAN'S and web presence are just a few
      that we offer. Please visit us at <a
      href="http://www.ns3g.com/">www.ns3g.com</a> or contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@ns3g.com">info@ns3g.com</a> for more information or
      to get a quote.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Linast" continent="europe">
    <name>Linast-Systemtechnik GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.linast.de</url>
    <description>
      Linast-Systemtechnik GmbH is located in Sankt Augustin, Germany (near
      Bonn/Cologne) and provides consulting, support and training for
      FreeBSD, Linux, MacOS X and other Unix Systems. For more information,
      please call +49.2241.209467, e-mail us at <a
      href="mailto:info@linast.de">info@linast.de</a> or visit our <a
      href="http://www.linast.de/">website</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Cybersource" continent="australia">
    <name>Cybersource Pty. Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.cyber.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      Cybersource is Australia's leading IT Professional Services Company
      in the areas of Unix/FreeBSD/Linux, TCP/IP Datanetworking and Open
      Platform application development using these technologies. With
      around 40 staff, are based in Melbourne and have been successfully
      providing IT Professional Services for 10 years.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="KMJ" continent="europe">
    <name>KMJ Consulting Austria</name>
    <url>http://www.kmj.at</url>
    <description>
      KMJ Consulting Austria is a full service Consultant and Supplier for
      pre installed <a href="http://www.proline.at">FreeBSD Servers</a> as
      a replacement for Windows NT/2000 Servers. We ship Firewalls,
      Internet Gateways, File and Print Servers. Network planing and
      implementation of Wans with IPSEC tunneling, Mail Servers with
      IMAP/LDAP as an replacement for MS Exchange, Samba and Hylafax
      installations. Our newest pre installed System is a FreeBSD
      Workstation running on a P733 with 512MB Ram, <b>Matrox G400 Dual VGA
      and 2 Monitors</b>. If sometimes Windows is needed a Demo of Vmware
      is preinstalled to run Windows in a Window of the FreeBSD System.
      Founded 1985 with Unix and Mainframe experience since 1978. We are
      based in Salzburg and Vienna / Austria and operate mostly in the
      german language territory of the EC. For non-commercial information
      please visit <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.at">FreeBSD.AT</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="APriori" continent="namerica">
    <name>A Priori Consulting</name>
    <url>http://apriori.cnchost.com/</url>
    <description>
      A Priori Consulting is a Boston-based company providing high-quality
      system and software development and consulting services to the
      computer, networking and software industry -- specializing in UNIX
      and BSD system and application development, including embedded
      systems, networking, driver, kernel, porting, realtime, and systems
      integration.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NationalInformatics" continent="namerica">
    <name>National Informatics Company</name>
    <url>http://www.nationalinformatics.com</url>
    <description>
      National Informatics Company provides research and development
      services for information technology. We work with FreeBSD to support
      or manage research projects for high performance computing,
      bioinformatics, enterprise software technologies and artificial
      intelligence. We also help companies make the transition from
      proprietary software products to Open Source products. Our phone
      number is (425) 740-0139.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Bilch" continent="europe">
    <name>Bilch International Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.bilch.com/</url>
    <description>
      Bilch International Consulting, Hamburg is based in Germany. We are
      building fire walled servers and connect them to your ISDN, POTS, ATM
      or E1/T1 Line. BILCH Com is an ASP and application software
      developer. Please mail us at <a
      href="mailto:info@bilch.com">info@bilch.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ParcProductions" continent="europe">
    <name>Parc Productions</name>
    <url>http://www.parcproductions.com/</url>
    <description>
      Parc Productions. Located in the Netherlands. Started in 1997. We
      deliver professional system engineering services for FreeBSD, OpenBSD
      and MacOS X. Our services include 24/7 support, consultancy,
      maintenance of both hardware and software, assembly and installation
      of hardware, remote and on-site support, development of scripts and
      software for the machines we maintain etcetera. Of course we deliver
      hosting facilities and space for your servers at low costs as well.
      Visit our websites at <a
      href="http://www.parcproductions.com/">www.parcproductions.com</a> or
      <a href="http://www.bsdengineering.com/">www.bsdengineering.com</a>.
      Please contact us by <a
      href="mailto:info@parcproductions.com">email</a> or by telephone:
      +31-204892456.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Worria" continent="asia">
    <name>Worria Affordable Web Hosting</name>
    <url>http://worria.com/en/hosting.shtml</url>
    <description>
      Worria Affordable Web Hosting is a privately owned company in Hong
      Kong. We offer FreeBSD web hosting related consulting services, such
      as server administration and website management. For more details,
      please email <a href="mailto:sales@worria.com">our sales team</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Xensia" continent="europe">
    <name>Xensia LLP</name>
    <url>http://www.xensia.com/</url>
    <description>
      Xensia LLP provide UNIX systems/admin/security/networking consultancy
      services within London, UK. Specializing in Open Source software on
      Solaris/*BSD systems. Over 7.5 years experience with UNIX systems,
      administration, security/firewalls and networking. Contact <a
      href="mailto:paul.civati@xensia.com">paul.civati@xensia.com</a> for
      more details.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ZYTRAX" continent="namerica">
    <name>ZYTRAX, Inc</name>
    <url>http://www.zytrax.com/</url>
    <description>
      Zytrax, Inc. is based in Montreal, Canada and provides consulting,
      development, implementation, hosting and maintenance services
      specialising in the BSD platforms. Our skill base includes Apache,
      PHP, Ruby, DNS, Mail, LDAP, Samba, PostgeSQL/MySQL and embedded
      systems. Please email us at <a
      href="MAILTO:consulting@zytrax.com">consulting@zytrax.com</a>. We can
      be reached via telephone at +1.514.285.9088.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OpenTrend" continent="namerica">
    <name>OpenTrend Solutions Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.opentrend.net</url>
    <description>
      OpenTrend Solutions Ltd provides consulting and facilities management
      services through Canada. We specialize in supporting FreeBSD, NetBSD,
      OpenBSD and Linux, and have specialist skills in system
      administration, security and network design &amp; management. We donate
      2% of gross profits to the support of open source software and have
      partnered with organisations in the United States and Australia to
      better support multi-national clients.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DaemonizedNetworking" continent="namerica">
    <name>Daemonized Networking Services</name>
    <url>http://www.daemonized.com</url>
    <description>
      Daemonized Networking Services. Our staff have been supporting
      software and hardware development, brokerages, banks, hospitals,
      publishers, e-commerce, legal and medical research,
      telecommunications, and other environments since 1986, in the San
      Francisco Bay Area and Northern California. We build industrial
      strength web servers, running the latest release of Apache, OpenSSH,
      and OpenSSL, with all source, and firewall, based on FreeBSD, in less
      than one hour.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Linux4biz" continent="asia">
    <name>Linux4biz</name>
    <url>http://www.linux4biz.net/</url>
    <description>
      Linux4biz is an independent provider of comprehensive Internet
      solutions, specialising in the Solaris, LINUX, FreeBSD, OpenBSD,
      NetBSD operating systems and Open Source Software. Linux4biz
      Consultants are able to advise on all aspects of implementing and
      administrating Unix/Linux servers, SAMBA solutions, E-mail servers,
      Mailing list servers, Web servers, DNS, Internet Security, Security
      Audits, Intrusion detection, Stress testing, Intranet setup, High
      Availability server solutions, Network solutions, Remote
      administration solutions. We also provide onsite as well as offsite
      support and consultancy. For more information about our services,
      please visit our website.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="INFOMATIK" continent="samerica">
    <name>INFOMATIK</name>
    <url>http://info.matik.com.br</url>
    <description>
      INFOMATIK Tecnologia e Desenvolvimento - Brazilian Company is
      offering total site support for FreeBSD Servers. We have high
      performance solutions for Intranet and Internet. We are specialized
      in UNIX systems since 92. Please visit our Interactive Website or
      contact us per e-mail: <a
      href="mailto:info@matik.com.br">info@matik.com.br</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LOGIOS" continent="europe">
    <name>LOGIOS</name>
    <url>http://www.logios.cz/</url>
    <description>
      LOGIOS NETWORK SYSTEMS, located in the Czech Republic, provides
      system maintenance, consulting and other services on various
      platforms, including FreeBSD and Linux. We also offer information
      security services, firewalls and IDS systems, system integration,
      software applications etc.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Xetpoint" continent="europe">
    <name>Xetpoint</name>
    <url>http://www.xetpoint.fi/</url>
    <description>
      Xetpoint Oy is located in Pirkkala, Finland. We offer professional
      FreeBSD support, consulting, programming, maintenance and monitoring
      services. For more information, please visit our website.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RackmountNet" continent="namerica">
    <name>RackmountNet</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmountnet.com</url>
    <description>
      RackmountNet is a One-stop shop for rackmount Linux, FreeBSD systems.
      Our products include Rackmount chassis, server rack cabinet,
      Rackmount LCD Monitor, and related accessories. For more information,
      contact <a
      href="mailto:sales@rackmountnet.com">sales@rackmountnet.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="siliconlandmark" continent="namerica">
    <name>Silicon Landmark LLC</name>
    <url>http://siliconlandmark.com/</url>
    <description>
      Silicon Landmark's mission is to supply our customers with
      fully customized, scalable, turn-key Information Technology
      solutions at competitive prices. We specialize in designing
      package products that will meet and your business' needs
      and budget.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="pythonbyte" continent="namerica">
    <name>Python Byte Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.pythonbyte.com/</url>
    <description>
      Python Byte Solutions is an independant IT
      consulting company based in Southwestern Ontario, Canada.
      We provide services pertaining to software
      &amp; web development, hosting, support, installation,
      and training. We specialize in Python, Zope, Apache,
      MySQL, *BSD, and Linux. You can
      check out our web site or contact us directly at <a
      href='mailto:info@pythonbyte.com'>info@pythonbyte.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
