<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries SYSTEM "entries.dtd">

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/en/commercial/hardware.xml,v 1.1 2004/05/02 21:53:07 josef Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="ActiveWire">
    <name>ActiveWire Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.ActiveWireInc.com/</url>
    <description>
      ActiveWire Inc. provides an extremely flexible, USB-based I/O board
      that connects to buttons, switches, and LEDs, providing a simple API
      to read and write to the I/O pins on the board. The USB port is
      supported in <a href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD 4.0</a>, with
      native <a href="http://www.etla.net/~n_hibma/usb/usb.pl">USB
      support</a>. An additional EZ USB chip firmware downloader is
      available in the Ports Collection.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ADCOMTEC">
    <name>ADCOMTEC</name>
    <url>http://www.adcomtec.com</url>
    <description>
      ADCOMTEC specializes in providing high-performance, advanced
      communications and networking solutions. FreeBSD driver support is
      provided for a range of high-performance WAN adapters for ADSL, T1,
      E1, and Synchronous Serial (RS-232/V.35/X.21/EIA530) connectivity
      that support a number of downloadable protocol modules including ATM,
      Frame Relay, X.25, HDLC, SDLC, PPP, and SS7. For more information,
      contact <a href="mailto:info@adcomtec.com">info@adcomtec.com</a> or
      visit <a href="http://www.adcomtec.com">http://www.adcomtec.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AdvancedComputer">
    <name>Advanced Computer and Network Management Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.acnc.com/</url>
    <description>
      Advanced Computer and Network Corporation Our site, dedicated to RAID
      (Redundant Array of Independent Disks) technology, features, an
      excellent, easy-to-understand, graphical RAID tutorial. We are a
      one-stop source for cost-effective, high-performance RAID arrays,
      SCSI switches, boosters, cables, fiber-optic extenders, and
      high-availability solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ASA">
    <name>ASA Computers</name>
    <url>http://www.asacomputers.com/</url>
    <description>
      ASA Computers offers a wide range of performance-oriented servers,
      workstations, and networking products. We are experienced in quality
      configuration and support of FreeBSD, Linux, and other operating
      systems. Multiple-OS experience and knowledge are our strengths. We
      resell a variety of communication and networking products, including
      3COM, Cisco, Cyclades, DIGI, Livingston, and U.S. Robotics. Please
      take a look at the pre-configured systems on our web page. Contact us
      at <a href="mailto:unix@asacomputers.com">unix@asacomputers.com</a>
      to configure them your own way or if you have questions or comments.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BISInc">
    <name>BIS, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.bisworld.com/</url>
    <description>
      BIS, Inc. specializes in Internet- and Intranet-networking servers,
      running FreeBSD. We custom design and construct high-performance
      servers to fill any need. BIS also provides IS Support, network
      administration and management, training, Internet connectivity,
      corporate-wide e-mail gateways, domain name registration and hosting,
      web site development, and more. Please send e-mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@bisworld.com">info@bisworld.com</a> or visit <a
      href="http://www.bisworld.com/">http://www.bisworld.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="catpipe">
    <name>catpipe Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.catpipe.net/</url>
    <description>
      catpipe Systems ApS provides managed services and support contracts
      for FreeBSD, implemented on rackmountable servers preloaded with
      FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ComputerAccess">
    <name>Computer Access Technology Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.catc.com/</url>
    <description>
      CATC - Computer Access Technology Corporation, popularly called CATC
      ("cat-see"), is the world's leading supplier of development and test
      tools for the Universal Serial Bus (USB) and IEEE 1394 (FireWire[tm])
      serial communication standards. The company also offers a variety of
      peripheral devices, including a USB-to-Ethernet interface and the
      industry's first USB hub.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoyotePointSystems">
    <name>Coyote Point Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.coyotepoint.com/</url>
    <description>
      Coyote Point Systems offers the <a
      href="http://www.coyotepoint.com/equalizer.shtml">Equalizer</a> Load
      Balancing Appliance. Equalizer distributes client UDP/TCP requests to
      multiple server machines and includes load balancing, server failure
      detection/correction, and an easy-to-use administrative interface.
      Capable of handling over 20,000 HTTP GET operations per minute,
      Equalizer enhances the Scalability, Availability and Manageability of
      any server cluster. Equalizer works with all standard protocols,
      including: HTTP, FTP, POP, SMTP, DNS, etc. Equalizer is based on the
      FreeBSD kernel.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CycladesCorporation">
    <name>Cyclades Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.cyclades.com/</url>
    <description>
      Cyclades Corporation sells a variety of high performance, multiport
      serial cards which FreeBSD supports directly in its standard
      releases.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DAVICOM">
    <name>DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.davicom.com.tw/</url>
    <description>
      DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc. designs, develops, and markets
      cost-effective integrated circuit (IC) solutions for mainstream
      networking and communications applications. DAVICOM is one of the
      leading suppliers of Local Area Network (LAN) and Wide Area Network
      (WAN) chip sets to international original equipment manufactures
      (OEMs) of networking and communications equipment. <p> The current
      products of DAVICOM Semiconductor, Inc. that will support the FreeBSD
      driver are DM9102 (10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet single chip), DM9102A
      (3.3 volts Low Power10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet single chip), DM9101
      (10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet PHY chip, included into DM9102 single
      chip), DM9131 (3.3 volts Low Power10M/100M PCI Fast Ethernet PHY
      chip, included into DM9102A single chip) and DM9801 (1M8 Home PNA PHY
      chip). </p> <p> Please visit <a href="http://www.davicom.com.tw">our
      web site</a> for more information about our company. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DigitalNetworks">
    <name>Digital Networks United Kingdom</name>
    <url>http://www.dnuk.com</url>
    <description>
      Digital Networks is one of the UK's leading supplier of desktops,
      workstations, and servers designed and optimized for the FreeBSD and
      Linux operating systems. From scientific to e-commerce applications,
      our products can be used as building blocks to create complete
      solutions. All products are built to order and can be purchased
      online from the company's web site at <a
      href="http://www.dnuk.com">www.dnuk.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmergingTechnologies">
    <name>Emerging Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.etinc.com/</url>
    <description>
      Emerging Technologies, Inc. has high-speed serial-communications
      adapters, allowing FreeBSD systems to connect directly to leased
      lines at speeds from 56k to T1/E1. ET drivers support up to 16 T1/E1
      lines on a single FreeBSD-based PC. The adapters include a complete
      set of drivers and utilities that allow a FreeBSD machine to
      communicate directly with virtually any IP router via synchronous
      PPP, Frame Relay, X.25, and directly to Cisco brand routers with
      Cisco serial encapsulation. Full documentation and support are
      included. Hardware choices are available for both ISA and PCI buses,
      ranging from an economical single-port ISA adapter to a four T1/E1
      port PCI card with four dedicated 25MHz processors on-board. To
      contact Emerging Technologies, send E-mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@etinc.com">info@etinc.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EnterpriseSystems">
    <name>Enterprise Systems and Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.enterprisess.com/</url>
    <description>
      Enterprise Systems and Solutions builds high quality, customized
      systems, fully loaded and configured with FreeBSD for
      intranet/internet server and workstation use, at a competitive price.
      We also sell LAN/WAN products (from CISCO, 3COM, Livingston, SDL
      Comm, Digi, and more) and provide service. Please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@enterprisess.com">info@enterprisess.com</a> or <a
      href="http://www.enterprisess.com/">visit our web site</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EssenzConsulting">
    <name>Essenz Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.essenz.com</url>
    <description>
      Essenz Consulting is a leading provider of high-performance rackmount
      server equipment. All of our <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com/servers/index.html">servers</a> feature
      dual processor capability, dual onboard networking, high-capacity
      memory support, and integrated video. From 1U Hot-Swap SCSI systems
      to 2U Hot-Swap 64-bit SCSI RAID with 2x300W Hot-Swap Power Supply,
      all Essenz Servers can be custom configured with immediate online
      pricing. For more information, visit us <a
      href="http://www.essenz.com">online</a> or call our 24/7 Sales and
      Support department at 1-800-248-1736.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FreeBSDSystems">
    <name>FreeBSD Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsdsystems.com</url>
    <description>
      FreeBSD Systems - The Power To Serve&#8482; is so true with an
      iNET Server. We manufacture and <em>customize</em> 1U to 7U
      Rackmount Servers utilizing Intel Processors ranging from Xeon MP to
      Celeron, from single processing to quad and 8-Way Systems. Every
      Server is fully customized to our clients requirements including the
      installation of FreeBSD. iNET Servers are available in ATA and SCSI
      configurations. Looking for Direct Attached Storage? Check out the
      iSTOR6000, with data capacity of up to 7 Tera Bytes. Since 1999,
      FreeBSD Systems has been providing high performance Rackmount Servers
      and Storage Systems to clients ranging from start-up Web Hosting
      Companies to Fortune 500 Companies to Federal Government Departments.
      We offer On-Site hardware warranty support to all of North America,
      Mexico and, Puerto Rico. Visit our web site <a
      href="http://www.FreeBSDsystems.com">http://www.FreeBSDsystems.com</a>
      or call us toll free at 1.877.963.1900.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FreedomTechnologies">
    <name>Freedom Technologies Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.FreeBSDsystems.COM/</url>
    <description>
      Freedom Technologies Corporation offers businesses a total solution
      to Server systems. All our servers are based on the business needs of
      our customers. Each server is custom designed, both in terms of the
      hardware and the operating system, as well as the applications to be
      run. FreedomTC delivers to its customers, server(s) that will do
      the task(s) at the highest level of performance. FreedomTC only uses
      the highest quality of hardware for any system we design. FreedomTC
      also includes its Net@dmin [TM] service for 1 year. Our servers
      work extremely well with customer's workstations, using Windows or
      Macintosh for file and print sharing. Please call us at our toll
      free telephone number, 1-877-963-1900.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Gallantry">
    <name>Gallantry Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.gallantry.com/</url>
    <description>
      Gallantry Technologies Inc. offers a business broadband gateway for
      small- to medium-sized businesses. Our products are focused on
      offering an easy-to-use product that provides multiple services
      routing, firewall, e-mail, web server, DHCP, NAT, FTP, DNS, and print
      server. All these features can be accessed via an easy-to-use web
      interface. The GallantWEB-100 is an affordable and easy-to-use
      business broadband gateway that is ideal for connecting small and
      medium offices to the Internet via any broadband connection including
      xDSL, Cable, Frame Relay/T1, or ISDN. The GallantWEB-200 is the
      industry's first business broadband gateway to include a built-in
      SDSL router. This innovative one-box solution makes it easy for DSL
      service providers to deploy and manage.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GND">
    <name>GND Distribution, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.gnd.com/</url>
    <description>
      GND Distribution, Ltd., a London, UK-based company, specializes in
      bespoke computer systems for FreeBSD and Linux. All GND computer
      systems are built to order, using only top-quality components. Our
      build quality is second to none. Systems are supplied configured and
      optimized to our customer's requirements. We also supply a large
      range of system components, including ASUSTeK mainboards, which are
      popular within the FreeBSD and Linux communities.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Hewlett_Packard">
    <name>Hewlett_Packard</name>
    <url>http://www.hp.com/</url>
    <description>
      Hewlett-Packard sells Proliant BL10e blade servers that are
      compatible with FreeBSD. 280 blades can fit within in a 42U rack,
      offering superior density, computing power and management for all
      front-end and cluster applications.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="iMimicNetworking">
    <name>iMimic Networking, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.imimic.com/</url>
    <description>
      iMimic Networking, Inc. offers the <a
      href="http://www.imimic.com/">DataReactor</a> family of Web-cache
      appliances. The DataReactor family leads the caching industry in
      price/performance, from an aggressively priced entry-level caching
      appliance to a high-end caching appliance at mid-level prices.
      The FreeBSD-based <a
      href="http://www.imimic.com/indexd746.html">DataReactor Core
      software</a> includes management features such as SNMP monitoring
      support, Common Logfile Format logging, and Web-based or
      console-based configuration. Please send mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@imimic.com">info@imimic.com</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="INetU">
    <name>INetU Dedicated Managed Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.inetu.net/</url>
    <description>
      INetU Dedicated Managed Hosting are one of the top rated hosting
      firms focused on dedicated managed hosting, INetU provides managed
      dedicated FreeBSD servers, along with firewalls, load balancing,
      advanced monitoring and data backup services. They offer more free
      tech support than most other hosts and have a lucrative partner
      program for consultants and developers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IntrospectiveTechnologies">
    <name>Introspective Technologies USA</name>
    <url>http://www.itechusa.net/</url>
    <description>
      Introspective Technologies USA delivers networking solutions with
      high powered servers and workstations pre-installed with choice of
      operating systems, including FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IronSystems">
    <name>Iron Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.ironsystems.com/</url>
    <description>
      Iron Systems, located in San Jose, California, is a provider of
      high-density rack-mount Internet systems, low cost hosting solutions
      and OEM integration services. System solutions are either
      built-to-order iServers with custom-configured hardware, OS, kernel
      and applications; or a set of pre-configured network infrastructure
      iEngines and iClusters, specially designed to deliver a dedicated
      application. Iron Systems backs all solutions with world-class
      technical support for FreeBSD and Linux. Our team at an average
      has over 10 years of experience in building BSD-based systems. We
      understand that our servers run your mission-critical applications -
      that's why we use only the highest quality components and test all
      systems in advance. We are confident that you will appreciate our
      approach. Give us an opportunity to serve you! Please send us email
      at <a href="mailto:info@ironsystems.com">info@ironsystems.com</a> or
      call 1-800-921-IRON.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ItautecPhilco">
    <name>Itautec Philco</name>
    <url>http://itautecamerica.com/</url>
    <description>
      Itautec Philco is one of Brazil's leading IT products manufacturers
      and one the leaders in the Brazilian Market and significant market
      share in Portugal, Uruguay and Argentina. Products such as the
      Infoway and the InfoServer are fully compatible with FreeBSD, Linux,
      and other Operating Systems. Itautec Philco also manufactures Banking
      and Retail Automation products, as well as Consumer Electronics
      products. We provide complete solutions for our customers, from
      Infrastructure (such as LAN) to software applications, to Web
      development and hosting services, to call-center services.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="KYTEX">
    <name>KYTEX Computers Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.kytex.bg/</url>
    <description>
      KYTEX Computers Ltd offers K-SERVER family of pre-installed xBSD and
      Linux Internet appliances. K-SERVER product line include small
      footprint all-in-one solutions for small to middle networks and
      rackmount servers for ISP/ASP and corporate networks. All-in-one
      solutions provides Internet access via dial-up, leased lines, xDSL,
      wireless technology and offer filesharing for Windows and MacOS
      workstations across the network at no additional cost, users WEB-,
      Mail-, Firewall-, DNS-server applications started and partially
      configured for easy integration in any existing networks. K-SERVER
      setup and management is very simple - just start any browser on your
      workstation and follow the setup instructions and menus. If you have
      any questions or proposals, please e-mail us.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MOXA">
    <name>MOXA</name>
    <url>http://www.moxa.com/</url>
    <description>
      MOXA makes attractively priced multi-port serial cards which are
      compatible with FreeBSD's <em>sio</em> serial driver. The C104 / C168
      family of 2/4/8 serial port cards features custom ASIC design, speeds
      up to 921.6Kbps, surge protection, independent and
      software-configurable I/O ports and IRQs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Neturn">
    <name>Neturn Corp.</name>
    <url>http://neturn.sinacity.com/netserv/</url>
    <description>
      Neturn Corp., based in Vancouver, Canada, provides complete solutions
      on selective and fine-tuned hardware and software (BSDs as primary
      server OSs) platforms to meet the demand from e-commerce, telecom,
      manufacturing, industrial, aerospace, medical applications where
      stability and reliability are mandatory. For detailed information,
      please visit <a href="http://neturn.sinacity.com/netserv/">
        http://neturn.sinacity.com/netserv</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetWolves">
    <name>NetWolves Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.netwolves.com</url>
    <description>
      NetWolves Corporation produces the FoxBox line of Multi-services
      Internet Communications Gateway systems. These Internet Access
      Devices offer a three stage firewall, unlimited e-mail, site hosting,
      filtered browsing, web and DNS caching, DHCP for ease of set up, file
      sharing/serving, e-mail archiving, and a series of productivity
      enhancing reports - cost effectively. The FoxBox OS is based on
      FreeBSD. Bandwidth options range from V.90 modems to T-1, cable
      modems, and DSL speeds. The FoxBox provides Internet access for
      between 8 and 1000 users on one or more LANs and is available
      internationally through our VAR reseller network. Visit <a
      href="http://www.netwolves.com/">our site</a> for more information or
      contact us by <a href="mailto:sales@netwolves.com">email</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Offmyserver">
    <name>Offmyserver</name>
    <url>http://www.offmyserver.com/</url>
    <description>
      Offmyserver offers state-of-the-art Internet Server Systems, Internet
      Appliance Platforms, RAID solutions, Multi-boot Workstations, LAN/WAN
      products, and peripherals at competitive prices. We&#39;ll help you
      find the right system hardware - configure, price, build, AND test it
      with BSD operating systems. If that&#39;s not enough, we&#39;ll even
      bend sheet metal to suit your identity. That&#39;s what you get when
      the company that sells you the complete system is also the one that
      custom builds it for you. We use only the best quality components and
      do the required testing in advance - knowing that you are going to
      run your mission-critical applications on our servers. We are
      confident that you will appreciate our approach - give us an
      opportunity to serve you! Send us an email at <a
      href="mailto:info@offmyserver.com">info@offmyserver.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PCW">
    <name>PCW Microsystems, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.rackmount.com/</url>
    <description>
      PCW Microsystems, Inc. offers rackmount workstations and servers,
      optimized for the FreeBSD operating system. We carry full line of
      rackmount chassis, RAID, WAN, and LAN products for FreeBSD OS. Please
      <a href="http://www.rackmount.com/">visit our web site</a> for more
      information or send us an e-mail at <a
      href="mailto:sales@pcwnet.com">sales@pcwnet.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PSSCLabs">
    <name>PSSC Labs</name>
    <url>http://www.pssclabs.com/</url>
    <description>
      PSSC Labs provides custom configured computer solutions to meet any
      budget or specification. Visit our website to build your computer
      just the way you want it, including hard-drive partitioning and
      operating system setup.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RandDAssociates">
    <name>R and D Associates, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.RnDAssociates.com/</url>
    <description>
      R and D Associates, Inc. developed ServeTheWeb.com utilizing FreeBSD
      running Apache. We employed consulting services from <a
      href="mailto:phk@FreeBSD.org">Poul-Henning Kamp</a> to develop our
      Virtual Server solution (which is now available in <a
      href="http://www.FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD</a> 4.0). <p> <a
      href="http://ServeTheWeb.com/">ServeTheWeb.com</a> is our System
      Admin level of Virtual Servers. Please visit <a
      href="http://www.ServeTheWeb.com/">www.ServeTheWeb.com</a> for
      additional information on this product. </p> <p> R and D Associates,
      Inc. is an application development firm, specializing in
      client/server designs. We use FreeBSD, running Apache and utilizing
      PHP's and MySQL (As well as NT with ASP's and SQL/Access). </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SangomaTechnologies">
    <name>Sangoma Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.sangoma.com/</url>
    <description>
      Sangoma Technologies Inc. offers the WANPIPE&#153; range of high
      speed intelligent communication adapters that support a number of
      downloadable protocol modules including PPP, Frame Relay and X.25.
      The cards are available with RS-232/V.35/X.21/EIA530 interfaces or an
      on board T1 or Fractional T-1 CSU/DSU. All of our FreeBSD and Linux
      code is distributed under the GNU Public License (GPL) in source code
      form. The FreeBSD PPP driver and utilities for Sangoma WANPIPE&#153;
      kits are available for download at <a
      href="ftp://ftp.sangoma.com/FreeBSD">ftp.sangoma.com/FreeBSD</a>.
      Frame Relay and X.25 support will follow shortly.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SBE">
    <name>SBE</name>
    <url>http://www.sbei.com/</url>
    <description>
      SBE specializes in providing high-performance, advanced
      communications and networking solutions for CompactPCI-, PCI-, and
      PMC-based applications. FreeBSD driver support is provided for a
      range of high-performance WAN adapters, providing connectivity for
      Synchronous Serial, T1/E1, DS3/T3, and HSSI. For more information,
      contact <a href="mailto:info@sbei.com">info@sbei.com</a> or visit <a
      href="http://www.sbei.com/">http://www.sbei.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SeraSystems">
    <name>Sera Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.serasystems.com</url>
    <description>
      Sera Systems is a manufacturer of xBSD-based servers and
      workstations. Sera Systems was formed to address the security needs
      of Internet-connected businesses by helping develop, setup, and
      support network infrastructure computers with reliable,
      proactively-secure free software. Sera Systems products include the
      SeraBox, a low-cost, multi-function server, the SeraVPN, a dedicated
      virtual private network server, and a line of customizable servers
      based on choice of xBSD. Sera Systems offers with all products a
      value-added preconfiguration service which is designed to help
      customers implement specific network applications using xBSD and be
      up and running as quickly as possible. For more information please <a
      href="http://www.serasystems.com">visit our web site</a> or e-mail <a
      href="mailto:sales@serasystems.com">sales@serasystems.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PerleSpecialix">
    <name>Perle Specialix</name>
    <url>http://www.perle.com/</url>
    <description>
      Perle Specialix makes a wide variety of multi-port async serial
      expansion products. The ISA, EISA, and PCI SI/XIO host cards work
      under FreeBSD, using the <em>si</em> driver.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Stallion">
    <name>Stallion Technologies, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.stallion.com/</url>
    <description>
      Stallion Technologies, Inc. offers a range of multiport serial boards
      for the ISA, EISA, MCA and PCI buses. Although Stallion does not
      officially support drivers for FreeBSD, there is an unsupported,
      freely available driver available from their <a
      href="ftp://ftp.stallion.com/drivers/unsupported/freebsd/stalbsd-0.0.
      5.tar.gz">FTP site</a>. This driver supports the Stallion
      <em>EasyIO</em> and <em>EasyConnection 8/32</em> multiport boards.
      For local pricing and availability information, contact Stallion via
      their <a href="http://www.stallion.com/">WWW page</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="StoreAnyWhere">
    <name>StoreAnyWhere.com</name>
    <url>http://StoreAnyWhere.com/</url>
    <description>
      StoreAnyWhere.com offers a wide range of high-performance and
      cost-effective quad- and dual-processor servers, workstations, and
      networking products with FreeBSD and Linux as their operating
      systems. Just go to our website for servers in a variety of
      configurations or custom-made systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SWTechnology">
    <name>SW Technology</name>
    <url>http://freebsd.swt.com/</url>
    <description>
      SW Technology offers quality Pentium machines with FreeBSD
      pre-installed.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Synetic">
    <name>Synetic, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.synetic.net/</url>
    <description>
      Synetic Inc. is a Canadian and North American distributor for
      IDE-to-IDE, SCSI-to-IDE and SCSI-to-SCSI RAID controllers, supporting
      the FreeBSD platform. Our products can be found at <a
      href="http://www.synetic.net/prodman.htm">www.synetic.net/prodman.htm</a>
      or <a href="http://www.synetic.net/prodspec.htm">
      www.synetic.net/prodspec.htm</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TegataiSystems">
    <name>Tegatai Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.tegatai.com/</url>
    <description>
      Tegatai Systems develops software and networking products and
      services using FreeBSD and Linux-based open-source software.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Ten26">
    <name>Ten 26</name>
    <url>http://www.ten26.com/</url>
    <description>
      Ten 26 Enterprises is your source for high performance, fault
      tolerant FreeBSD workstations and servers. Choose a pre-configured
      package or create your own custom machine from our list of
      well-tested components. All machines carry a 2 year warranty. For
      more information, visit <a href="http://www.ten26.com/">Ten 26</a> or
      e-mail <a href="mailto:info@ten26.com">info@ten26.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TeraSolutions">
    <name>TeraSolutions, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.terasolutions.com/</url>
    <description>
      TeraSolutions, Inc. is a manufacturer of high-reliability,
      high-performance rack-mount Internet server and RAID storage systems
      which are specifically designed and built for the best operation with
      FreeBSD. Our servers come with FreeBSD pre-installed and tuned for
      high-traffic Internet server applications. TeraSolutions was founded
      by FreeBSD co-founder David Greenman and has built some of the
      highest-traffic Internet servers in the world. Please <a
      href="http://www.terasolutions.com/">visit our web site</a> or
      contact us directly at +1 503 288 9544 for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TPC">
    <name>TPC IT Pty, Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.tpcit.com.au/</url>
    <description>
      TPC IT Pty, Ltd is Authorized Australian Cyclades Distributor. We
      have just set up an online discussion group for Cyclades customers
      and anyone wishing to know about the product. Visit our <a
      href="http://www.tpcit.com.au/">web site</a> for details.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Znyx">
    <name>Znyx</name>
    <url>http://www.znyx.com/</url>
    <description>
      Znyx Corporation specializes in high-availability, high-performance,
      single and multi-channel Fast Ethernet adapters for PCI, CompactPCI,
      and PCI Mezzanine Connector (PMC). FreeBSD, Linux, QNX, NetWare,
      OS/2, and SCO Unixware are supported on virtually all products.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NCSTechnologies">
    <name>NCS Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.ncsapp.com/</url>
    <description>
      NCS Technologies offers "NCS Swift Appliance Partner Program
      (NCSAPP)" for Independent Software Vendors (ISVs) and other OEMs.
      Under this program, NCS develops "turn-key" server appliances for its
      ISV partners by bundling their appliance software with its own
      hardware platforms. These appliance hardware platforms are built
      using the latest industry standard chipsets and components and can
      run FreeBSD based applications.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ColoMachine">
    <name>ColoMachine</name>
    <url>http://www.colomachine.com/</url>
    <description>
      ColoMachine offers high quality sub-$500 1U rackmount servers
      optimized for the FreeBSD operating system.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
