<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries SYSTEM "entries.dtd">

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/en/commercial/isp.xml,v 1.3 2004/05/14 12:01:30 josef Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="ipglobal">
    <name>IP Global.net</name>
    <url>http://www.ipglobal.net/</url>
    <description>
      IP Global is the leading Texas Internet Service Provider offering
      data transport services to all major cities as well as hosting and
      colocation solutions to businesses and groups around the globe.
      We specialize in carrier grade transport circuits for Houston,
      Austin, Dallas / Fort Worth, and San Antonio ranging in
      connections from Fractional T1, Integrated T1,
      Full Unmetered T1 Service, and bundled T1's up to Burstable
      and Full T3 packages. IP Global also delivers Highspeed DSL
      and Local 56K Dialup Internet to the Houston area.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="757tech">
    <name>757 Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.757tech.net/</url>
    <description>
      BSD friendly hosting and colocation solutions for small
      and medium sized businesses. Willing to meet 
      customer needs, a smaller operation that values
      support over size.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oberon">
    <name>Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.oberon.net/</url>
    <description>
      Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH is one of the biggest Internet
      Service Provider for japanese customers in Germany. We
      deliver services like WWW-housing, E-Mail gates, Highspeed
      DSL and PPP Dialup. With our germany-wide dialin-infrastructure
      we try to satisfy all of our customers needs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="emuadmin">
    <name>EmuAdmin</name>
    <url>http://www.emuadmin.com/</url>
    <description>
      Emuadmin is offering a full range of services supporting the FreeBSD
      operating system. Security, customized firewalls, full server management,
      custom programming, performance tuning, network management solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
