<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries SYSTEM "entries.dtd">

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD: www/en/commercial/isp.xml,v 1.34 2005/11/08 10:04:51 jcamou Exp $
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="ipglobal">
    <name>IP Global.net</name>
    <url>http://www.ipglobal.net/</url>
    <description>
      IP Global is the leading Texas Internet Service Provider offering
      data transport services to all major cities as well as hosting and
      colocation solutions to businesses and groups around the globe.
      We specialize in carrier grade transport circuits for Houston,
      Austin, Dallas / Fort Worth, and San Antonio ranging in
      connections from Fractional T1, Integrated T1,
      Full Unmetered T1 Service, and bundled T1's up to Burstable
      and Full T3 packages. IP Global also delivers Highspeed DSL
      and Local 56K Dialup Internet to the Houston area.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="757tech">
    <name>757 Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.757tech.net/</url>
    <description>
      BSD friendly hosting and colocation solutions for small
      and medium sized businesses. Willing to meet
      customer needs, a smaller operation that values
      support over size.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="oberon">
    <name>Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.oberon.net/</url>
    <description>
      Oberon.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH is one of the biggest Internet
      Service Provider for japanese customers in Germany. We
      deliver services like WWW-housing, E-Mail gates, Highspeed
      DSL and PPP Dialup. With our Germany-wide dialin-infrastructure
      we try to satisfy all of our customers needs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bayhosting">
    <name>Bay Hosting</name>
    <url>http://www.bayhosting.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      UK based FreeBSD hosting in secure, resilient facilities.
      Customised firewalls, managed servers, website hosting,
      e-mail hosting with virus/spam-scanning.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bewide">
    <name>Bewide Internet Service Provider</name>
    <url>http://www.bewide.com</url>
    <description>
      Bewide is an Internet Service Provider focussing on all forms
      of hosting, domain registration and development of internet
      applications.  We are a company demanding a high level of
      quality, using high quality hardware.  FreeBSD is the operating
      system of our choice, powering our systems with a high quality
      operating system, perfectly suited for our company.  For more
      information about Bewide, please visit our website <a
	href="http://www.bewide.com">http://www.bewide.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="bpa">
    <name>Black Point Arts Internet Solutions GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.bpanet.de/</url>
    <description>
      We offer flexible solutions and serve our customers needs with
      compentent and fast support.  Our services include website hosting,
      virtual Servers (VPS) and server homing (e.g. managed
      servers)/colocation for all kinds of companies.  We are located in
      Germany.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="emuadmin">
    <name>EmuAdmin</name>
    <url>http://www.emuadmin.com/</url>
    <description>
      Emuadmin is offering a full range of services supporting the FreeBSD
      operating system. Security, customized firewalls, full server management,
      custom programming, performance tuning, network management solutions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="escapebox">
    <name>EscapeBox</name>
    <url>http://www.escapebox.net/</url>
    <description>
      The ISP-in-a-Box: Managed On-Demand UNIX Servers.  Time efficient and
      affordable! Relevant Internet software is pre-installed and maintained
      centrally.  User benefit: the convenience of a homepage account, combined
      with the flexibility of a dedicated server.  No hassle with security
      updates etc. Resellers are welcome, too.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="lf">
    <name>LF.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.LF.net/</url>
    <description>
      LF.net Netzwerksysteme GmbH is an Internet Service Provider and
      specialist in network integration services and solutions.
      Founded in 1992, with an assembled team of 25 specialists,
      LF.net is located in one of Germany's largest industrial regions
      in Baden-Wuerttemberg.  We deliver german-wide Highspeed DSL, 64K
      ISDN Dialup and leased line Internet access.  We also specialize
      in domain services, webserver hosting and housing, System
      integration services, network management, security and VPN
      solutions, virus and spam checking, screen design and
      programming as well as consulting and training.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="macomnet">
    <name>MAcomnet telecommunications company, Moscow, Russia</name>
    <url>http://www.macomnet.com/</url>
    <description>
      CJSC MAcomnet is one of the biggest Moscow telecommunication
      companies founded in 1991 by the Moscow Metropoliten and
      Andrew Corporation (USA).  Numerous customers do justice to
      MAcomnet service high quality and level, among them are large
      communications operators, Internet providers, telephone companies,
      banks, hotels, exhibition centers, embassies, well known trading
      companies, government organizations, institutions, industrial
      enterprises, scientific-research institutes, mass media.
      A lot of MAcomnet ISP servers are FreeBSD based.  MAcomnet
      hosts cvsup4.ru.FreeBSD.org and cvsup5.ru.FreeBSD.org cvsup
      mirrors.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="sublimesp">
    <name>Sublime Service Provider</name>
    <url>http://sublimesp.com/</url>
    <description>
      Sublimesp.com is an internet services provider like web
      hosting, shell providing, game servers and streaming
      services running FreeBSD in all servers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="improware">
    <name>ImproWare AG</name>
    <url>http://www.imp.ch/</url>
    <description>
      ImproWare AG focuses on Internet and Networking Services
      as well as System Integration and Consulting.
      ImproWare runs its own swiss-wide Multiservice-Backbones.
      It offers internet access via cable and leased lines.
      Serverhousing with 24/7 access to the server-room is
      also a service ImproWare offers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="fastzone">
    <name>FastZone.at</name>
    <url>http://www.fastzone.at</url>
    <description>
      FastZone.at is a branch of DataMax GesmbH, 
      which provides internet access for private 
      and business customers in Austria. They 
      also run a housingcenter in the middle of 
      Vienna for colocation / managed housing 
      with 24/7 access. FastZone.at offers 
      domainservices, webhosting and also 
      dedicated serverhousing with FreeBSD as 
      the OS of choice.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="gradwell">
    <name>gradwell dot com Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.gradwell.com/</url>
    <description>
      gradwell dot com Ltd is a UK Internet Email and Webhosting
      provider offering UNIX shell accounts, web hosting, mailman
      and ezmlm, pop3, imap, webmail (squirrelmail), mysql, php,
      fastcgi and mod_perl hosting on FreeBSD servers in London.
      Our site is <a href="http://www.gradwell.com/">
      http://www.gradwell.com</a>. Phone: 0870 787 9129.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="celeritystorm">
    <name>CelerityStorm</name>
    <url>http://www.celeritystorm.com/</url>
    <description>
      We run 100% on FreeBSD and Intel Dual Xeons/AMD Dual Opteron
      64 bit servers.  We are a company in the business of shell
      providing, webhosting, gameservers and virtual servers;
      We aim to provide the lowest price for the most resources.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="keyway">
    <name>Keyway Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.keyway.net/</url>
    <description>
      Keyway Internet Services has provided premium business
      and residential solutions since 1995.  Nationwide services
      include business-class hosting and dialup access.  Southern
      California services include T1, Fiber, DSL, and Wireless.
      We feature our own colocation facility in Ontario, CA, and
      are proud to feature FreeBSD as a recommended platform.
      All clients receive live no-hold support, and T1/Colocation
      clients receive 24/7/365 support.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="claryss">
    <name>Claryss Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.claryss.com/</url>
    <description>
      Claryss Networks provides secure and dependable technologies
      backed with years of experience.  Based in France, we provide
      shared and dedicated hosting, housing, consulting and
      outsourcing.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="easyspeedy">
    <name>EasySpeedy</name>
    <url>http://www.easyspeedy.com</url>
    <description>
      EasySpeedy provides dedicated servers with colocation benefits,
      and a flexible self-service environment.  We're dedicated to
      bringing our customers a wide range of automatically installed
      Linux and BSD-systems, all available at the click of a button.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="virtualhosting">
    <name>Virtualhosting.com</name>
    <url>http://www.virtualhosting.com/</url>
    <description>
      Virtualhosting.com offers high speed website hosting with free
      domain names, no data transfer charges, no setup fees and spam
      solutions.  Virtual Host accounts and Virtual Servers with FreeBSD
      as the operating system.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="eserver">
    <name>eServer.ru</name>
    <url>http://www.eServer.ru</url>
    <description>
      We probvide high quality web-hosting and VIP-hosting services in
      Russia and CIS based only on FreeBSD systems customized for
      hosting needs, dedicated servers with support of all currently
      available FreeBSD distributions.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="k2">
    <name>K2 Colocation</name>
    <url>http://www.k2colocation.com/</url>
    <description>
      K2 Colocation is a BSD friendly colocation company.  Our
      infrastructure resides on IBM xSeries servers running FreeBSD.
      We can provide colocation solutions for small, medium and
      enterprise level businesses.  We believe by focusing our efforts
      to the colocation arena we can better serve our customers.
     </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Quonix">
    <name>Quonix Networks</name>
    <url>http://www.quonix.net/</url>
    <description>
      Quonix Networks provides a variety of personal and enterprise
      hosting solutions powered by FreeBSD, including web, mail, secure
      shell hosting, dedicated servers and colocation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="velocity">
    <name>Velocity Servers</name>
    <url>http://velocity-servers.net/</url>
    <description>
      Velocity Servers provides game server hosting and webhosting on
      FreeBSD.  We can host any specific games that are designed to run
      on Linux.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LayeredTech">
    <name>Layered Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.layeredtech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Layered Technologies provides enterprise level, dedicated self
      managed hosting solutions to our clients at the best, very
      affordable prices.  The self-managed dedicated servers are hosted
      on tier-1 bandwidth.  FreeBSD is our no. 1 supported OS.  We have
      a local FreeBSD/CVSup mirror for customers.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PantherTech">
    <name>PanterTech Media Solutions</name>
    <url>http://www.pantertech.de/</url>
    <description>PantherTech offers low-cost CMS Hosting on FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MultaCom">
    <name>MultaCom Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.multacom.com/</url>
    <description>
      MultaCom Offers a full line of internet services including
      Colocation, Dedicated Servers, Web development, Bandwidth and IP
      services, Virtual Private Networks and Shared hosting based on
      FreeBSD and on site 24/7 FreeBSD System Engineers.  FreeBSD is
      widely used in our organization and our shared hosting is FreeBSD
      based.  We provide FreeBSD servers as dedicated and also install
      for free on servers we sell to others.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aplus">
    <name>Aplus.Net</name>
    <url>http://www.aplus.net/</url>
    <description>
      Aplus.Net is a facilities based provider located in San Diego, CA
      since 1995.  We provide Web Hosting, Dedicated Servers, Domain
      Names, Web Design, and E-Commerce solutions.  We offer to our
      customers the power and stability of the FreeBSD Operating System
      with our Web Hosting and Dedicated Servers.  Aplus.Net, everything
      for your online business.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IntegrityHost">
    <name>Integrity Host</name>
    <url>http://www.integrityhost.com</url>
    <description>
      Integrity Host provides shared hosting, VPS (Virtual Private
      Servers), and fully managed dedicated servers that run on
      multiple versions of FreeBSD.  cPanel and Fnastastico are
      available and bandwidth allocation is generous.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="inetassociation">
    <name>Internet Engineering Association, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.inetassociation.com/</url>
    <description>
      Internet Engineering Association, LLC specializes in providing
      extremely secure, private and reliable Internet services.  Our
      complete website and email services provide clients a reliable,
      worry free environment.  Every server we use to provide service
      runs on FreeBSD.  Our technical infrastructure is housed within
      state-of-the-art Internet Data Center facilities located in
      Tokyo and San Francisco.  Our systems are designed to be extremely
      secure and reliable.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Venigo">
    <name>Venigo Internet Services</name>
    <url>http://www.venigo.fr/</url>
    <description>
      Venigo Internet Services is a French based company, which provides
      hosting solutions like shared, dedicated, colocation hostings, and
      VPN solutions based on FreeBSD.  Venigo Internet Services is also
      able to provide management and support for variety of BSD &amp;
      Linux systems.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HostDepartment">
    <name>Host Department</name>
    <url>http://www.hostdepartment.com/</url>
    <description>
      Host Department provides FreeBSD-based web hosting, eseller
      hosting, domain name registration, and free web hosting services
      for personal, small=medium enterprise businesses, government,
      and also non-profit organizations.
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
