<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE entries SYSTEM "entries.dtd">
<!--
  Available categories: < DATABASE | DEV | ECOMMERCE | EMAIL
  | MISC | MULTIMEDIA | NETWORK | SCIENTIFIC | SECURITY | SYSADMIN >
-->

<entries>
  <cvs:keywords xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS" version="1.0">
    <cvs:keyword name="freebsd">
      $FreeBSD$
    </cvs:keyword>
  </cvs:keywords>

  <entry id="Acadix" category="DEV">
    <name>Another Programmer's Editor (APE)</name>
    <url>http://www.execpc.com/~acadix</url>
    <description>
      Another Programmer's Editor is a terminal-independent integrated
      development environment which runs on a variety of Unix platforms.
      APE offers syntax highlighting and full error-message processing
      and works with <strong>any</strong> compiled or interpreted language.
      For more information,
      please visit our <a href="http://www.execpc.com/~acadix">web site</a>
      or send email to <a href="mailto:acadix@execpc.com">acadix@execpc.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aestiva" category="DEV">
    <name>Aestiva HTML/OS</name>
    <url>http://www.htmlos.com/</url>
    <description>
      Aestiva HTML/OS is a complete solution for advanced, dynamic web site
      and web software development. It eliminates the need for CGI
      programming and integration tools, includes a built-in database
      engine and tools for packaging and copy-protecting commercial web
      products, and supports over a dozen platforms. Visit <a
      href="http://www.htmlos.com">www.htmlos.com</a> for more information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Aker" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Aker Firewall</name>
    <url>http://www.aker.com.br/</url>
    <description>
      Aker Firewall is a firewall solution which runs on FreeBSD. The
      firewall provides a stateful filtering engine, Network Address
      Translation (NAT), cryptography (with manual key exchange and SKIP),
      automatic responses to pre-configured events, and remote
      administration by a easy-to-use graphical interface which runs on
      many different platforms. For more information, please <a
      href="http://www.aker.com.br/">visit our web site</a> or send a
      e-mail to <a
      href="mailto:info@aker.com.br">info@mail.aker.com.br</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Akopia" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>Akopia</name>
    <url>http://www.akopia.com/</url>
    <description>
      Akopia is the developer of Interchange, the leading open source
      e-commerce platform that runs on FreeBSD and other UNIX Operating
      systems. Interchange offers an extensive feature set including:
      <ul>
	<li>Intuitive content management functionality,
	  enabling business users to easily manage large, complex catalogs.</li>
	<li>Flexible merchandising, maximizing sales through product
	  presentation, cross-sells, up-sells, and promotions.</li>
	<li>Powerful transaction management functionality that handles
	  complex business rules and fully integrates with legacy systems.</li>
	<li>Comprehensive administration and reporting, which keeps business
	  and technical management informed and in control.</li>
	<li>Flexible, extensible architecture, ensuring scalability and providing
	  room to grow.</li>
      </ul>
      Akopia offers professional Interchange support and an array
      of e-commerce professional services. For more information and a free
      download, visit us at <a href="http://www.akopia.com/">www.akopia.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Altera" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Altera SQL Server</name>
    <url>http://www.altera.gr/</url>
    <description>
      Altera SQLServer is a multi-user, relational database with ODBC and
      JDBC options, demanding very few resources. Altera's client-server
      architecture allows numerous concurrent users. Altera SQL server
      supports CGI and is ideal for Web applications since it transfers
      MIME-typed BLOBS directly to the web browser via HTTP protocol
      (acting as a web server). For more information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.altera.gr/">www.altera.gr</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AMSOFT" category="DATABASE">
    <name>AM'SOFT</name>
    <url>http://www.amsoft.ru/</url>
    <description>
      AM'SOFT (Andrew Maltsev's Software) features <a
      href="http://www.amsoft.ru/easysql/">EasySQL</a>, an ODBC-like,
      database-independent C/C++ library. Full source code is available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="AstroArch" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>AstroArch Consulting</name>
    <url>http://www.astroarch.com/</url>
    <description>
      AstroArch Consulting, Inc. develops and licenses its <em>ISP Billing
      and Tracking System</em> (BATS) for FreeBSD as well as thirteen other
      Operating Systems. For more information, check out <a
      href="http://www.astroarch.com/">www.astroarch.com/</a>, send email
      to <a href="mailto:info@astroarch.com">info@astroarch.com</a>, or
      call +1.512.990.9711.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Ballista" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Ballista</name>
    <url>http://www.secnet.com/ballista/</url>
    <description>
      Ballista is a network security auditing tool for evaluation of
      security postures in areas where high assurance levels are critical.
      Ballista is primarily designed to audit the remote security aspects
      of networks and runs quite well under FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="BrownBear" category="MISC">
    <name>Brown Bear Software</name>
    <url>http://www.brownbearsw.com</url>
    <description>
      Brown Bear Software produces and supports <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/">Calcium</a>, an
      interactive <b>Web Calendar server</b> you use via your browser.
      Features include: dynamic calendar merging multiple views and
      formats; repeating events, email notification and reminders,
      iCalendar support, Palm Pilot synchronization, color and font
      customization, support for full HTML in event text and calendar
      headers and footers, popup text associated with any event, searching
      &amp; filtering, multi-language support, flexible security model, <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/FeaturesList.html">and
      more</a>. Calcium is very easy to use and fully supported. It runs
      anywhere that supports Perl CGIs; no non-standard Perl modules are
      necessary. A live <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsoftware.com/cgi-bin/Calcium?CalendarName=D
      emo"  >On-Line Demo</a> is available; you can download an <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/download"  >evaluation
      copy</a> (fully functional, but limited to a single calendar), or try
      your own <a
      href="http://www.brownbearsw.com/calcium/onlineTrial.html">private
      demo on our servers</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CForge" category="DEV">
    <name>C-Forge</name>
    <url>http://www.codeforge.com/</url>
    <description>
      C-Forge (pronounced Code Forge) is a multi-user integrated
      development environment that provides full project management and
      complete edit/compile/debug cycle support. Features include complete
      abstraction of the "makefile" concept, a Project Manager for visual
      presentation of project structure and component status using a
      dependency tree and a separate "desktop" area showing work in
      progress, support for C/C++, Perl, Oracle ProC/C++, Tcl, PHP, Java,
      JavaScript, Python, Qt, Pascal, Free Pascal, FORTRAN, TeX/LaTeX,
      SGML, Modula-2, and Assembler, integrated revision control, fully
      configurable programmer's editor, and much more. An evaluation
      version is available for download.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CactusInternational" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Cactus International Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.cactus.com/</url>
    <description>
      Cactus International Inc. <p> <a
      href="http://www.cactus.com/bp/bp.html">Backup Professional
      Enterprise Wide Network Backup </a></p> The Enterprise Wide Backup
      and Recovery System, which provides high-performance backup and
      recovery for a wide variety of systems across your intranet.     The
      Backup Professional utilizes a Client/Server architecture to provide
      enterprise-wide services via TCP/IP. Master and Incremental backups
      for each client or group of clients can be scheduled as often as
      desired. The Backup Professional's internal database maintains every
      backup on the tape and every file in that backup. System
      Administration of the Backup Library is only a few keystrokes away.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CheapBytes" category="MISC">
    <name>CheapBytes</name>
    <url>http://www.cheapbytes.com/</url>
    <description>
      CheapBytes, a company that specializes in low-cost technical
      products, now has <em>FreeBSD</em> products available on CD-ROM.
      Among our offerings, you will find FreeBSD CD-ROM sets and FreeBSD
      related books. For further information, please see <a
      href="http://www.cheapbytes.com/">www.cheapbytes.com</a> or send
      e-mail to: <a
      href="mailto:sales@cheapbytes.com">sales@cheapbytes.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CobolScript" category="DEV">
    <name>CobolScript</name>
    <url>http://www.deskware.com/</url>
    <description>
      Deskware, Inc. is a revolutionary, cross-platform Internet
      programming language, designed for anyone who wants to do web
      development. If you don't yet know an Internet development language,
      learning CobolScript is the fastest and easiest way for you to
      acquire web application development skills. Deskware's own <a
      href="https://www.cobolscript.com/cgi-bin/cobolscript.exe?catalog.cbl
      "  >e-commerce-enabled catalog</a> is powered by the CobolScript
      engine.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ConeticSoftware" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Conetic Software</name>
    <url>http://www.conetic.com/</url>
    <description>
      Conetic Software is offering a FREE copy of <a
      href="http://www.conetic.com/css_freebsdinst.html">C/BASE 4GL</a> for
      the FreeBSD operating system. C/BASE 4GL features a powerful and
      fully portable application-development tool and database engine. It
      featuring an easy-to-use visual development environment, a scripting
      language, and application libraries with a C language (API)
      interface.  Your FREE copy of C/BASE 4GL is set to run for a maximum
      of 2 concurrent users and 1,000 records. Please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@conetic.com">info@conetic.com</a> if you would like
      a taste of even more power and programming fun.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CoolHorizon" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Cool Horizon</name>
    <url>http://www.coolhorizon.net/</url>
    <description>
      Cool Horizon provides a billing package for ISPs, called <em>Internet
      Billing</em>. This package was designed to handle all billing needs
      for Internet Service Providers. It runs under MS-Windows. One piece
      of the software is a client/server set, with a daemon that runs on a
      UNIX server (including FreeBSD), allowing the client to do all of
      their user management under a Windows front end.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CovalentTechnologies" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Covalent Technologies</name>
    <url>http://raven.covalent.net/</url>
    <description>
      Covalent Technologies presents the <em>Raven SSL Module</em> for the
      ever-popular <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Web Server</a>.
      Raven offers the ability to add secure server functionality to your
      Apache installation, using the RSA encryption algorithms available to
      residents of North America. For more information, please email <a
      href="mailto:info@raven.covalent.net">info@raven.covalent.net</a> or
      call +1.402.441.5710 (Voice) or +1.402.441.5720 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CybernetSystems" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Cybernet Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.cybernet.com/</url>
    <description>
      Cybernet Systems produces the <a
      href="http://www.netmax.com/">NetMAX</a> line of Thin Servers and
      Professional Products for FreeBSD. The Thin Server Series consists of
      the FireWall (with Router), WebServer (with email and FTP), and
      FileServer (with print sharing). The NetMAX Professional contains
      these three, as well as the Discussion Group/NewsServer, dial in
      capabilities, enhanced system management and reporting functions,
      expanded support, and more. Easily install the included OS through a
      GUI and set up and manage your server through a web browser. Save
      time on mundane tasks. Access to the command line is available for
      "traditional" Unix use.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DBMaker" category="DATABASE">
    <name>DBMaker</name>
    <url>http://www.dbmaker.com</url>
    <description>
      DBMaker provides you with a professional database system with
      multimedia capabilities, a native ODBC interface, large database
      features, and cross-platform support. The unique open architecture
      and native ODBC interface give you the freedom to build custom
      applications using a wide variety of programming tools such as Visual
      Basic or Delphi, or query your database using existing ODBC-compliant
      applications. DBMaker provides excellent multimedia-handling
      capabilities, allowing you to store, search, retrieve, and manipulate
      all types of multimedia data. Binary Large Objects (BLOBs) allow you
      to ensure the integrity of your multimedia data by taking full
      advantage of the advanced security and crash-recovery mechanisms
      included in DBMaker; File Objects (FOs) allow you to manage your
      multimedia data, while maintaining the capability to edit individual
      files in the source application. <a
      href="http://www.dbmaker.com">Download a free copy now!</a> -   This
      free copy of DBMaker includes a three-user license with no time or
      storage limitations. Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.dbmaker.com">www.dbmaker.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Differential" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Differential, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.differential.com/</url>
    <description>
      Differential, Inc. develops <em>FileDrive</em>, a suite of secure and
      extensible high-performance FTP file transfer client/server software.
      FileDrive provides the industry's most secure file transfer solution
      through the use of SSL encryption, extensive access controls,
      comprehensive logging, and an optional security auditing system.
      Differential's <em>FileDrive EX</em> extranet server also provides
      extensible FTP access to dynamically generated content and
      server-based data processing.  FileDrive servers are easy to
      configure, manage, and maintain through their integrated Web-based
      remote administration systems. FileDrive servers are available for
      FreeBSD, Linux, and Solaris, with IRIX and HP/UX version available
      soon. 15-day evaluation versions of FileDrive and FileDrive EX are
      available at <a
      href="http://www.differential.com/">www.differential.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Easysoft" category="DEV">
    <name>Easysoft Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.easysoft.com/</url>
    <description>
      Easysoft Ltd Easysoft's ODBC-ODBC Bridge 2000 (OOB) provides full
      access to any local ODBC data source from any remote client, such as
      Unix, Linux, OpenVMS, Windows, or other systems. A free version of
      the Easysoft ODBC-ODBC Bridge is available on the FreeBSD platform.
      For further information, or to download the software, please visit <a
      href="http://www.easysoft.com/">www.easysoft.com</a>. <p></p>
      Easysoft's JDBC-ODBC Bridge 2000 (JOB) provides Type 3 JDBC access
      from Java Applets or Applications on the FreeBSD platform to ODBC
      (Open Database Connectivity) data sources anywhere on the network
      where the server component of the bridge is installed. A free version
      is available to download from <a
      href="http://www.easysoft.com/">www.easysoft.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EasyStat" category="MISC">
    <name>EasyStat</name>
    <url>http://www.easystat.net/</url>
    <description>
      EasyStat is a "counter"-like application. It will keep track of the
      number of visitors to your site, as well as gather information about
      your visitors such as their browser, operating system, referrer, etc.
      EasyStat will then display all it gathers in an elegant fashion, a
      demo of which is available on its site.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EiffelSoftware" category="DEV">
    <name>Eiffel Software</name>
    <url>http://www.eiffel.com/</url>
    <description>
      Eiffel Studio is an Integrated Development Environment (IDE) designed
      for the Eiffel object-oriented application development language.
      Beside the Enterprise Edition, a Free Edition for non-commercial use
      only is freely available for download.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Elego" category="DEV">
    <name>Elego</name>
    <url>http://www.elego.de/</url>
    <description>
      Elego ComPact Configuration Management. <em>Elego ComPact</em> is a
      set of tools for configuration management, based on a very reliable
      and scalable solution for version control, integrated with a
      multi-platform language-independent build system, and the concept of
      software packages. It offers scriptable command-line-oriented
      programs, as well as an HTTP/HTML based GUI, and can be easily
      introduced in a stepwise fashion. <p> Some of its features are:
      client/server design, baseline and release branch support,
      checkin/checkout model, package-oriented change sets, integrated
      build system, support for development for/on heterogeneous platforms,
      scalable from one to hundreds of developers, default configurations
      for C, C++, Java, Modula-3, easily portable to most PC and
      workstation platforms. </p><p> Elego ComPact currently uses CVS as
      its underlying version control machine, though future versions may
      support other systems, too. Binaries are available for FreeBSD,
      Linux, Windows, and Solaris/SPARC systems. John Polstra's CVSup may
      be used for repository mirroring/replication. Like CVSup, Elego
      ComPact is completely written in Modula-3. </p><p> Fully functional
      demo CDs, including binaries for all supported platforms, and
      documentation in HTML, DVI, PDF, and PS format can be obtained by
      sending e-mail to <a href="mailto:info@elego.de">info@elego.de</a>.
      More information is also available from the <a
      href="http://www.elego.de">Elego WWW Homepage</a>. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmpressSoft" category="DEV">
    <name>Empress Software Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.empress.com</url>
    <description>
      Empress Software Inc. has developed <em>Embedded Empress Developer's
      Toolkit</em>. To learn more about the toolkit, please visit <a
      href="http://www.empress.com">www.empress.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EmpressSoftware" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Empress Software</name>
    <url>http://www.empress.com</url>
    <description>
      Empress Software develops the EMPRESS RDBMS, a powerful and
      cost-effective ANSI SQL database management system designed for
      developing robust scientific and engineering, embedded, and
      e-commerce solutions. The EMPRESS RDBM engine is fast and
      compact, efficiently stores and manipulates any data, and is
      maintenance-free. Companion products include an Internet application
      development toolkit, ODBC Interface, a pure Java client, a C++
      interface, and interfaces to popular scripting languages like XML,
      PHP, Perl, and Tcl/Tk. Empress offers a <a
      href="http://www.empress.com/web-bin/ehsql/product/freetry.eht"
      >free 30 day evaluation</a>, complete with technical support.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="EnhancedSoftware" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Enhanced Software Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.estinc.com/</url>
    <description>
      Enhanced Software Technologies develops <em>BRU</em>, a very powerful
      and reliable tape backup system. It offers per-file compression, an
      improved tape format with three different kinds of verification, and
      many safety checks to insure data integrity. A Fully ELF-based
      version is available for FreeBSD 3.1/3.2.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Etherpage" category="MISC">
    <name>Etherpage</name>
    <url>http://www.ppt.com/</url>
    <description>
      EtherPage provides a client/server based alphanumeric paging solution
      for Unix networks and Windows NT. Both command line and web
      interfaces are provided. Ideally suited for system and database
      administration, EtherPage allows messages to be sent automatically to
      support personnel based on database events, etc. Other features
      include links to email, integration with user-written scripts,
      multiple recipients, pagers selected by time of day/day of week,
      duplicate message suppression, long message splitting/truncation, job
      logging, and C API. Virtually all paging services are supported.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="FairCom" category="DATABASE">
    <name>FairCom Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.faircom.com/</url>
    <description>
      FairCom Corporation has provided quality database development tools
      for the professional programmer since 1979. FairCom is best known for
      its extremely portable, high-performance data management product,
      <em>c-tree Plus</em>. The product is released in full source code and
      supports peer-to-peer development and client-side development for use
      with the <em>c-tree</em> database server. The FreeBSD version offers
      advanced cross-platform functionality, including industrial quality
      transaction processing, file mirroring, huge file support and
      disaster recovery. The FairCom ODBC Driver and Crystal Report(tm)
      interfaces allow end-users to access <em>c-tree</em> Plus
      applications with higher level products such as Microsoft Access and
      Crystal Reports. The FairCom toolset is completed with
      <em>r-tree</em>, a powerful report generator and the powerful FairCom
      server, with heterogenous network support, which allows dissimilar
      clients to attach to one platform and easily migrate to over 20
      supported platforms, from FreeBSD to Windows to Mac. For more
      information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.faircom.com/">www.faircom.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Firehunter" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Firehunter</name>
    <url>http://www.firehunter.com/</url>
    <description>
      Firehunter from <a href="http://www.hp.com/">Hewlett-Packard</a>. The
      HP Firehunter family of intelligent, out-of-the box software
      solutions delivers the information you need to proactively monitor
      and manage your Internet services, including mail, news and Web
      functions. Its powerful operational capabilities and service level
      reports are your keys to delivering consistently high levels of
      service quality, improving customer satisfaction, decreasing churn
      and expanding revenue.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Gaussian" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>Gaussian Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.gaussian.com/</url>
    <description>
      Gaussian Inc. produces <em>Gaussian 94</em>, the latest in the
      Gaussian series of electronic structure programs. It is being used in
      chemistry and physics research in several universities and research
      and supercomputer centers around the world. Gaussian 94 is designed
      to model a broad range of molecular systems under a variety of
      conditions, performing its computations starting from the basic laws
      of quantum mechanics. Gaussian 94 can predict energies, molecular
      structures, vibrational frequencies, and numerous molecular
      properties for systems in the gas phase and in solution, and can
      model both their ground state and excited states.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HerrinSoftware" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Herrin Software Development</name>
    <url>http://www.hsdi.com/</url>
    <description>
      Herrin Software Development, Inc. offers <em>Qddb</em> database
      software, <em>Gustar</em> site search engines, <em>Qbib</em>
      bibliography-management software, and other products that run on
      FreeBSD and other UNIX platforms. To download these packages or to
      learn more, please visit <a
      href="http://www.hsdi.com/">www.hsdi.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HighWind" category="NETWORK">
    <name>HighWind Software</name>
    <url>http://www.highwind.com/</url>
    <description>
      HighWind Software develops <em>Cyclone</em>, <em>Typhoon</em>, and
      <em>Breeze</em>. USENET server products are available for FreeBSD 3.0
      and later. HighWind products are carrier-class Internet News Servers
      and are in wide-spread use at almost every major ISP involved in
      USENET. Free trials are available at <a
      href="http://www.highwind.com/">www.highwind.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="HKS" category="MISC">
    <name>HKS, Incorporated</name>
    <url>http://www.hks.net/</url>
    <description>
      HKS, Incorporated offers <em>CCVS</em> for FreeBSD. CCVS allows Unix
      systems to act as a POS terminal. Our APIs let people build credit
      card processing capabilities into just about any system that runs on
      any Unix we support.  Please visit our <a
      href="http://www.hks.net/products.html">web site</a> for more
      details.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="icon" category="DEV">
    <name>Icon Laboratories</name>
    <url>http://www.icon-labs.com/</url>
    <description>Icon Laboratories offers Envoy for FreeBSD.
      Envoy is a ported version of ISI's popular Envoy SNMP libraries.
      Each port includes SNMP libraries and header files for C development,
      a MIB compiler and source code for a sample agent,
      designed specifically for FreeBSD.
      For more information, send email to
      <a href="mailto:info@icon-labs.com">info@icon-labs.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Infinitum" category="MISC">
    <name>Infinitum Group</name>
    <url>http://www.infinitum.nl</url>
    <description>
      Infinitum Group provides several high-end solutions, based upon
      FreeBSD and other *NIX/BSD based platforms. Our
      do-maintenance-yourself website product runs on FreeBSD, in
      combination with <a href="http://www.zope.org">Zope</a>. If you would
      like an easy maintenance website or custom software development,
      please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:info@infinitum.nl">info@infinitum.nl</a> or by phone at
      +31 (0)70-3108950.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Infoflex" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Infoflex, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.infoflex.com/</url>
    <description>
      Infoflex, Inc. products include: 1) <a
      href="http://www.infoflex.com/sqlinfo.htm">SQLflex</a>, an SQL
      client/server clone of Informix ESQL/C and Informix Standard
      engine, 2) <a
      href="http://www.infoflex.com/infoinfo.htm">Infoflex-4GL</a>, a 4GL
      language syntactically similar to Informix and database
      compatible, 3) <a
      href="http://www.infoflex.com/qryinfo.htm">Queryflex</a>, a point and
      shoot report writer enabling novice users to develop their own
      reports.4) <a
      href="http://www.infoflex.com/accountflex.htm">AccountFlex</a>, a
      full featured accounting system for Order Entry, Inventory, Job Cost,
      Bill of Materials, Purchasing, A/R, A/P, G/L, and Payroll. All
      Infoflex products are supported on UNIX, DOS, NT, and VMS. For more
      information on Infoflex products, please <a
      href="http://www.infoflex.com/">visit our web site</a> or email us at
      <a href="mailto:info@infoflex.com">info@infoflex.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Inlab" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>Inlab Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.munich.net/inlab/scheme/</url>
    <description>
      Inlab Software GmbH offers binaries of <em>Inlab-Scheme</em> for
      FreeBSD and Linux (FREE for personal or educational use).
      Inlab-Scheme is a R4RS-compliant Scheme, which is capable of reading
      and writing TIFF and XBM-bitmaps to and from a special internal
      bitmap type. With built-in primitives for image processing,
      Inlab-Scheme can be a general tool for tasks like optical character
      recognition and general analysis and processing of bitmap data.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="InterBase" category="DATABASE">
    <name>InterBase</name>
    <url>http://www.interbase.com</url>
    <description>
      InterBase is The Perfect Embedded Database. Behind every great
      client/server application, you will find a great database and very
      possibly an embedded database. The hallmark of a great embedded
      database is its ability to empower applications and deliver
      information while remaining virtually invisible to the end user and
      requiring little or no attention from the database administrator.
      That database is InterBase. InterBase's Japanese partner, RIOS
      Corporation, is now offering a port of InterBase 4 for FreeBSD.
      Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.interbase.com">www.interbase.com</a> or directly
      from RIOS at <a
      href="http://iblinux.rios.co.jp/intl/">http://iblinux.rios.co.jp/intl
      /</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="IP23" category="NETWORK">
    <name>IP23 GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.ip23.net/</url>
    <description>
      IP23 GmbH offers IPmeter, an IP mediation and accounting system. <p>
      Product Description </p><p> IPmeter is Open Source software for IP
      mediation, accounting, and billing. It evaluates costs and charges
      customers for network use and service value, based on detailed
      information about IP sessions and flows. IPmeter will let you
      identify traffic flows in your network, summarize and consolidate
      usage metrics, apply tariffs to flows and prepare bills online,
      analyze network usage patterns, plan new service offerings and
      strategies, and evaluate your network infrastructure. </p><p>
      Licensing </p><p> IPmeter is GPL'ed and available for download on <a
      href="http://www.ipmeter.com">www.ipmeter.com</a>. A self-installing
      IPmeter 1.0 beta CD-ROM (including FreeBSD 3.4) is available
      commercially from <a href="http://www.ip23.net/">IP23 GmbH</a>.</p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="iPass" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>iPass</name>
    <url>http://www.ipass.com/</url>
    <description>
      i-Pass Alliance is the leading provider of global Internet-roaming
      solutions for Internet service providers. We provide a total solution
      that enables ISPs to join a global network and provide convenient,
      low-cost worldwide access to their traveling Internet subscribers. We
      are an independent organization, handling the financial settlement
      between you and other Internet service providers and enabling you to
      bill their subscribers for this service. There is no cost to join and
      no cost for the i-Pass software. The i-Pass cross-authorization and
      settlement software is compatible with all common authentication
      protocols and servers, including FreeBSD. For more information,
      please visit <a href="http://www.ipass.com/">www.ipass.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="journyx" category="MISC">
    <name>journyx WebTime</name>
    <url>http://journyx.com/products.html</url>
    <description>
      journyx WebTime is a web-based time and attendance tracking product
      for engineering departments and technical consultancies or
      contracting firms with people on the go. It was developed on FreeBSD.
       Since it is web-based, it allows for worldwide collection of data.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Joydesk" category="MISC">
    <name>Joydesk</name>
    <url>http://joydesk.com</url>
    <description>
      Joydesk is a Web-based Groupware package from VirtualTek Corporation,
      an ISV based in Seattle, WA. VirtualTek has developed a
      state-of-the-art, web-based Groupware server that runs on FreeBSD and
      allows an ISP, Portal, or virtually any website running on FreeBSD to
      integrate web-based email, calendar, address book, message board and
      other features. It's fully customizable, so you maintain your own
      name and brand, installs in about 15 minutes and is offered at a low,
      one-time cost. <a href="http://joydesk.com/download.htm">Download</a>
      a copy today and don't forget to <a
      href="http://joydesk.com/signup.htm">create your free account</a> if
      you would like to experience Joydesk's features firsthand.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Kaspersky" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Kaspersky Lab</name>
    <url>http://www.kaspersky.com/</url>
    <description>
      Kaspersky Lab offers KasperskyT Anti-Virus (AVP) - a unique
      anti-virus solution for FreeBSD. The product provides comprehensive
      protection for your file and application servers and gateways running
      FreeBSD. Kaspersky Anti-Virus for FreeBSD includes the most complete
      set of anti-virus tools that will help you to build a multi-level
      defence system against attacks of malicious code of any type,
      including computer viruses, Internet worms and Trojan horses. The
      package includes an anti-virus scanner for on-demand check for
      viruses on data storages (local and network); an anti-virus daemon
      that filters data from viruses in real-time mode. Kaspersky
      Anti-Virus for FreeBSD offers an interactive configuration program
      and a utility for automatic anti-virus database updates download. The
      product also includes a ready-made solution to integrate the product
      into popular Sendmail and Qmail gateways. This is a perfect solution
      to create your own centralized filtering system for e-mail traffic
      and cleanse it of viruses. The client part of Kaspersky Anti-Virus
      for FreeBSD/BSDi is supplied in open source code. This enables you to
      easily integrate the product into your own applications to perform
      specific tasks, e.g., into other e-mail or application servers.
      Kaspersky Lab also develops anti-virus solutions for DOS, Windows
      95/98, Windows 2000/NT Workstation/Server, Novell NetWare, Linux,
      OS/2, BSDi, MS Exchange Server, Lotus Notes, and MS Office 2000.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="KXSystems" category="DATABASE">
    <name>KX Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.kx.com/</url>
    <description>
      KX Systems presents Kdb, an RDBMS that provides both transaction
      processing and decision support capabilities for large amounts of
      data. Kdb extracts data from ODBC, flat files, ASCII, and binary
      storage formats. Kdb connects with Excel, Visual Basic, C, Java and
      HTML, enabling users with Web browsers to access and analyze data
      from any location. Data formats include relational, multidimensional,
      time series, and object. Queries are written in SQL and KSQL, an
      extended, more powerful query language. Application deployment is
      client/server. High-end processing is parallel. Kdb supports FreeBSD,
      Linux, UNIX, and NT. For more information, call Kx Systems at +1 305
      642 5242 or visit <a href="http://www.kx.com/">www.kx.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Lilikoi" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Lilikoi Software</name>
    <url>http://www.lilikoi.com/</url>
    <description>
      Ceilidh, from Lilikoi Software, Inc., is a bulletin board package for
      the World Wide Web, intra-, and extra-nets. It adds discussion forum
      capability to Web servers, including Apache. Ceilidh's forums are
      accessible through all browsers; its users can also opt for
      notification of new messages by e-mail. The forums are threaded and
      self-maintaining, with old messages being automatically deleted
      according to a schedule chosen by the administrator and author.
      Contact Lilikoi Software at <a
      href="mailto:sales@lilikoi.com">sales@lilikoi.com</a>,
      +1.619.405.4247 (Voice) or +1.619.487.0451 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="LoneStar" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Lone Star Software Corp</name>
    <url>http://www.LONE-TAR.com/</url>
    <description>
      For over 15 years,
      LONE-TAR has been the de facto standard backup solution
      for the UNIX Systems Administrator.
      LONE-TAR is a fully menu-driven data-archiving and -recovery utility.
      It employs high compression,
      allowing it to double the capacity of your archive device,
      as well as Bit-level Verification of archived data against the hard disk.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Lugaru" category="DEV">
    <name>Lugaru Software Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.lugaru.com</url>
    <description>
      Lugaru's Epsilon Programmer's Editor features EMACS-style &amp;
      Brief-style key bindings, C/C++/Java, Perl, HTML, and TeX modes,
      concurrent compiler control with typescript journaling, syntax
      highlighting, asynchronous Internet support, smart indenting &amp;
      tags, and multi-file, multi-directory search &amp; replace. Plus full
      undo/redo, directory-spanning file patterns, command/filename
      completion, convenient keyboard macros, interactive customizability,
      and much more. Executables for FreeBSD, Linux, Windows
      95/98/NT/2000/3.1, OS/2, and DOS are included. Visit <a
      href="http://www.lugaru.com">www.lugaru.com</a> for details and a
      free evaluation copy.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MainStreet" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>MainStreet</name>
    <url>http://www.mainstreetsoftworks.com/</url>
    <description>
      MainStreet Softworks develops and markets critical financial
      transaction software to the retail, mail/phone order, and eCommerce
      industries. Their primary software offering, the MainStreet Credit
      Verification Engine, provides direct credit card
      authorization/settlement services on many POSIX-compliant Host
      Operating Systems such as FreeBSD. MCVE provides all the required
      functionality to authorize and settle Major Credit Cards and is
      certified with Established Clearing Houses (processors) to ensure the
      lowest possible merchant rates. To find out more, visit our <a
      href="http://www.mainstreetsoftworks.com/">web site</a> or contact us
      at <a
      href="mailto:info@mainstreetsoftworks.com">info@mainstreetsoftworks.c
      om</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="MathTools" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>MathTools, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://mathtools.com/</url>
    <description>
      MathTools, Ltd. is offering solutions for scientists and engineers.
      Take a look at our <a
      href="http://www.mathtools.com/matcom.html">MATCOM</a>, a Matlab to
      C++ Compiler, and <a
      href="http://www.mathtools.com/matlib.html">Matrix&lt;LIB&gt;</a>,
      our C++ Matrix Class Library. Both are available for download from
      our <a href="http://www.mathtools.com/">home page</a> for a 30-day
      evaluation period. To receive more information about our products,
      please email us at <a
      href="mailto:info@mathtools.com">info@mathtools.com</a> or call us at
      +1.212.208.4476 (Voice) or +1.212.208.4477 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Mercantec" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Mercantec, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.mercantec.com/</url>
    <description>
      Mercantec, Inc. develops <em>SoftCart</em>(tm), a complete retail
      electronic commerce solution for marketing and selling goods and
      services on the World Wide Web. Mercantec sells its products through
      a worldwide network of Internet Service Providers (ISPs) and Web
      hosting service providers, Web consultants, software developers,
      integrators, and OEMs. Visit us at <a
      href="http://www.mercantec.com/">www.mercantec.com</a>, contact us
      through email at <a
      href="mailto:info@mercantec.com">info@mercantec.com</a>, or call us
      at +1.630.305.3200.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Metro" category="MULTIMEDIA">
    <name>Metro Link</name>
    <url>http://www.metrolink.com/</url>
    <description>
      Metro Link produces the <a
      href="http://www.metrolink.com/metroxindex.html"	>Metro-X Enhanced
      Server Set</a>, an accelerated and enhanced replacement X server. The
      set includes an easy-to-use graphical configuration tool and supports
      touch screens and multi-headed systems. In addition, Metro Link is
      now shipping <a href="http://www.metrolink.com/motif/index.html"
      >Metro Link Motif Complete!</a>, containing full distributions of
      Motif 1.2, 2.0, and 2.1 on one CD-ROM. FreeBSD x86 (both a.out and
      ELF), Linux/x86 (glibc and libc5), and Linux/Alpha are supported on
      the same CD-ROM! More FreeBSD products on the way! For more
      information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.metrolink.com/">www.metrolink.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="motifdeveloper.com" category="DEV">
    <name>motifdeveloper.com</name>
    <url>http://www.motifdeveloper.com/</url>
    <description>
      motifdeveloper.com provides both the Open Motif toolkit for FreeBSD
      via download and also a range of technical information, resources,
      and in-depth hints and tips for X/Motif developers. To download Open
      Motif for FreeBSD, please visit <a
      href="http://www.motifdeveloper.com/"  >www.motifdeveloper.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Muonics" category="DEV">
    <name>Muonics</name>
    <url>http://www.muonics.com/Products/MIBSmithy/</url>
    <description>
       Muonics' MIB Smithy  is a software product for Simple Network
      Management Protocol (SNMP) developers, Management Information Base
      (MIB) designers and internet-draft authors providing a Visual
      GUI-based environment for designing, editing and compiling MIB
      modules according to the SMIv1 and SMIv2 (Structure of Management
      Information) standards. MIB Smithy is supported on several platforms,
      including FreeBSD. More information and a 15-day limited evaluation
      version can be obtained from <a
      href="http://www.muonics.com/">www.muonics.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NAG" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>NAG, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.nag.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      NAG, Ltd. produces a Fortran-90 Compiler for most flavors of Unix
      (including FreeBSD), VMS, and the PC. The <em>NAGWare f90</em>
      Compiler is a full implementation of Fortran 90 (which, by
      definition, includes Fortran 77) plus a single-processor
      implementation of HPF. For further information, in North America,
      email <a href="mailto:naginfo@nag.com">naginfo@nag.com</a>, and
      elsewhere, email <a
      href="mailto:infodesk@nag.co.uk">infodesk@nag.co.uk</a>. Or, visit <a
      href="http://www.nag.co.uk/">www.nag.co.uk/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NameSurfer" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>NameSurfer, Ltd.</name>
    <url>http://www.namesurfer.com/</url>
    <description>
      NameSurfer, Ltd. NameSurfer is a distributed administration tool for
      DNS data, with a WWW-based graphical user interface for remote
      Internet and Intranet DNS administration. A fully functional
      evaluation version is available for FreeBSD. For more information,
      please visit <a
      href="http://www.namesurfer.com/">www.namesurfer.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetBeans" category="DEV" >
    <name>NetBeans, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.netbeans.com/</url>
    <description>
      NetBeans, Inc. make Java IDEs, written in Java, that run on FreeBSD.
      A complete set of Open APIs is available for extending the
      environment.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetBoz" category="NETWORK">
    <name>NetBoz Firewall</name>
    <url>http://www.netboz.net/</url>
    <description>
      NetBoz Firewall Free CD-ROM bootable firewall. No hard disk required.
      Web administration interface, real time traffic monitoring and more.
      Visit our web site <a
      href="http://www.netboz.net/">www.netboz.net</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetCon" category="NETWORK">
    <name>NetCon Corporation</name>
    <url>http://www.netcon.com/</url>
    <description>
      NetCon Corporation, established in 1985 and with over 10,000
      installed servers, is the leading supplier of NetWare-compatible
      operating systems and Internet Gateways for standard UNIX platforms.
      NetCon offers a complete line of systems for FreeBSD, SUN Solaris,
      SCO UNIX/ODT and IBM AIX RS6000, serving from 5 to 1000 users.
      Services include: Full Internet access from NetWare/WIN95/Windows
      workstations over IPX/SPX, X Windows over IPX/SPX, NetWare file and
      print services, NetWare Client services for UNIX, High-performance,
      DOS/Windows Terminal Emulation.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Netsville" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Netsville, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.netsville.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netsville, Inc. sells an Internet merchandising system called <a
      href="http://hazel.netsville.com/">Hazel</a> which allows webmasters,
      web consultants, or regular shopkeeps to create a web storefront on
      the Internet. Hazel interfaces with web servers, using SSL for
      security and various transaction processors for credit card
      authorization. The developers actually wrote Hazel using FreeBSD as
      their operating system. If you need a flexible shopping cart solution
      for the Internet, Hazel is your best bet.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetZuno" category="NETWORK">
    <name>NetZuno</name>
    <url>http://www.netzuno.com</url>
    <description>
      netZuno Technologies designs and develops <a
      href="http://www.netzuno.com/content/en/html/zbserver.html">ZunoBox</a>,
      FreeBSD-based network server software for growing enterprises.
      ZunoBox provides a comprehensive set of networking tools that are
      easy enough for the novice, yet sophisticated enough for the needs of
      experienced sysadmins. ZunoBox systems include cross-platform file
      and print sharing, email service, an Internet gateway, and more --
      all set up and configured through an innovative, browser-based GUI.
      For more information, contact us by <a
      href="mailto:info@netzuno.com">email</a> or visit <a
      href="http://www.netzuno.com">www.netzuno.com</a> where you can <a
      href="http://www.netzuno.com/content/en/html/downloads.html">download
      </a> an evaluation copy or <a
      href="http://www.netzuno.com/content/en/html/order.html">order</a>
      ZunoBox from one of our vendors.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="NetworkSecurityWizard" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Network Security Wizard</name>
    <url>http://www.securitywizards.com</url>
    <description>
      Network Security Wizards, Inc Dragon is a real-time, packet-based,
      intrusion-detection system. Dragon sensors collect events, based on
      user configurable data driven attack signatures and protocol
      violations. When events occur, Dragon collects the response from the
      target server, along with any other traffic that an attacker may try.
      Event data is logged to a database that can be analyzed with a
      variety of command line forensic tools that summarize events, replay
      suspicious network sessions, and perform statistical analysis. Dragon
      sensors can send real-time data via SNMP traps, Syslog messages, and
      a Blowfish-encrypted, ICMP-based network pipe to a central
      Dragon-Master server. Up to one hundred sensors can be handled by one
      Dragon-Master server. Dragon correctly reconstructs IP fragments and
      UDP/TCP network traffic. It can also operate at 100base-T speeds and
      some customers have placed Dragon onto Gigabit networks with success.
      Please visit <a
      href="http://www.securitywizards.com">www.securitywizards.com</a> for
      more information and to receive a 30-day test license.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Openmake" category="DEV">
    <name>Openmake</name>
    <url>http://www.openmake.com/</url>
    <description>
      Openmake is a GUI- and shell-based build manager that goes beyond
      beloved GNU make. Used at some of the world's largest companies for
      simple apps and complex multi-language/multi-OS applications,
      Openmake allows complete standardization and automation of the build
      process. Coupled with any version control tool (e.g. RCS), Openmake
      absolutely ensures matching source and executables. Submit your
      client build to Windows and your server build to FreeBSD at the same
      time (or AIX, HP, Sun, Sequent, OS/2). For more information, visit <a
      href="http://www.openmake.com">www.openmake.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OracleVideoServer" category="MULTIMEDIA">
    <name>Oracle Video Server</name>
    <url>http://www.netscape.com/</url>
    <description>
      Netscape-compatible browsers, <a
      href="http://www.javasoft.com/">Java</a> applets, <a
      href="http://www.macromedia.com/index.html">Macromedia Director or
      Authorware</a>, <a
      href="http://www.asymetrix.com/products/iconauthor/"  >Asymetrix
      IconAuthor</a>, or user-written applications. Integration with the <a
      href="http://www.oracle.com/st/">Oracle8</a> database (optional)
      allows for a complete, enterprise-wide information management
      solution. The <a
      href="http://www.nc.com/download/svrsuit.pdf">FreeBSD (NCOS)</a>
      version is completely compatible with versions for other platforms.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="OSATech" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>OSATech, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.osatech.com/</url>
    <description>
      OSATech, Inc. is a Massachusetts-based corporation. We specialize in
      e-commerce software development, using Perl, C++ and Java. We perform
      all of our project management activities from the US, whereas our
      development activities are performed in our offshore center in India.
      Using this approach, we are able to provide quality service at a low
      cost. Please contact us at <a
      href="mailto:gprakash@osatech.com">gprakash@osatech.com</a> or at
      617-306-6578. Please refer to <a
      href="http://www.osatech.com">www.osatech.com</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PACT" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>PACT</name>
    <url>http://pact.insider.org/</url>
    <description>
      PACT Port Accounting and Collection Tool - is a set of programs and
      PHP-scripts that allows for complete accounting of SNMP-queryable
      ports, and includes detailed overview of ports and their bandwidth
      usage. Multiple ports can be assigned to single customers. Free for
      non-commercial use.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Parabase" category="MISC">
    <name>Parabase Technology Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.parabase.com</url>
    <description>
      Parabase Technology Inc. offers the Parabase Web-Order-System, an
      integrated set of web-based business applications that incorporate
      web-based order entry, catalog generation, shopping cart, and
      administration. It automatically calculates shipping and handling
      charges and sales tax [depending on location] and has a full invoice
      preview and email order confirmation. The system currently interfaces
      to QuickBooks and Excel; other accounting packages are available on
      request. The system is based on a highly reliable journalizing
      database concept. Additional information is available at <a
      href="http://www.parabase.com">www.parabase.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Perforce" category="MISC">
    <name>Perforce Software</name>
    <url>http://www.perforce.com/</url>
    <description>
      Perforce Software produces <a
      href="http://www.perforce.com/perforce.html"
      >PERFORCE</a> -- the FAST Software Configuration
      Management System. Perforce SCM streamlines the
      software development process for organizations working with multiple
      operating systems and in multiple physical locations. This
      high-powered SCM system runs on more than 50 operating systems
      including Windows, and nearly every UNIX variation, from Linux to Mac
      OS X to AS/400, providing software developers with an easy-to-use
      tool for version control, workspace management and atomic change
      transactions. Free, fully functional evaluation versions are
      available from the <a href="http://www.perforce.com">Perforce Web
      site</a>. Organizations developing software that is licensed or
      otherwise distributed exclusively under an Open Source license may be
      eligible to obtain Perforce licenses gratis. Perforce Software can be
      reached at <a href="mailto:info@perforce.com">info@perforce.com</a>
      or +1-510-864-7400.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Polyhedra" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Polyhedra</name>
    <url>http://www.polyhedra.com</url>
    <description>
      Polyhedra is a main-memory, object-relational database that is
      ideally suited for mission-critical applications requiring
      event-driven, real-time responses to data changes, complex database
      designs, distributed applications, and fault tolerance for high
      availability and continuous operation. <p> The Object-relational
      database can contain objects that handle IP-based protocols, with
      object methods running in the database process itself and accessible
      to other objects/information stored in the database. Our own web
      site, <a href="http://www.polyhedra.com">www.polyhedra.com</a>,
      provides an example of Polyhedra, acting as both the web server and
      the information store, including free downloads available for trying
      Polyhedra on FreeBSD in Linux mode. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PolyServe" category="NETWORK">
    <name>PolyServe</name>
    <url>http://www.polyserve.com/</url>
    <description>
      PolyServe is a vendor of Understudy, a high-availability webserver
      monitoring and failover utility for FreeBSD. Understudy resides on
      two or more webservers and monitors the health and responsiveness of
      websites. In the event that Understudy detects a failure, it
      fails-over requests for the failed website to a backup server. Thus,
      people browsing the website see no interruption or delay; from their
      standpoint the website keeps right on working. <p> Understudy
      monitors IP services including HTTP, SMTP, TCP and FTP. Upon
      detection of a failure, Understudy removes the failed server from the
      cluster and fails-over to the secondary backup host. Understudy then
      generates a network-administrator notification via email and/or page
      so that whatever problem caused the failover can be remedied. </p><p>
      For more information, visit <a
      href="http://www.polyserve.com/">www.polyserve.com</a>. </p>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Quantified" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Quantified Systems, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.urchin.com/</url>
    <description>
      Urchin 5 About Urchin Web Analytics Software: Urchin 5 is a web
      analytics software solution that provides detailed metrics and
      marketing intelligence about how visitors interact with your website.
      Urchin provides detailed conversion metrics for online marketing
      initiatives in colorful and easy to read graphs. It is essential for
      anyone interested in the marketing, design or success of a website.
      Urchin for FreeBSD and all platforms can be downloaded from <a
      href="http://www.urchin.com/">www.urchin.com/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RealNetworks" category="MULTIMEDIA">
    <name>RealNetworks, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.real.com/</url>
    <description>
      RealNetworks, Inc. offers its <a
      href="http://www.real.com/products/player/index.html">RealPlayer</a>,
      <a href="http://www.real.com/products/index.html">RealServer</a>, and
      <a href="http://www.real.com/products/index.html">RealEncoder</a>
      software for FreeBSD.  The FREE RealPlayer allows you to play live
      and on-demand audio over 14.4Kbps and faster connections. All you
      have to do is click on a RealAudio link from your Web browser and
      audio begins playing instantly.  Check out <a
      href="http://www.timecast.com/">The RealMedia Guide</a> to access
      thousands of sites, offering music, news, live radio stations, live
      events, etc. The RealServer allows your web site to deliver live and
      on-demand audio, video, and animation over the Internet or your
      company network. A FREE version of the RealServer, called the <a
      href="http://www.real.com/server/basic/index.html"	>Basic
      Server</a>, is available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="REBOL" category="SCIENTIFIC">
    <name>REBOL</name>
    <url>http://www.rebol.com/</url>
    <description>
      REBOL is a new, network-based messaging language that increases
      productivity, cuts application size, and reduces application
      time-to-market. The language is human-centric, instead of
      computer-centric, and offers a new alternative to anachronistic
      programming languages like Java and C++ and scripting languages like
      PERL and Tcl. REBOL is compact, platform independent, and functions
      over a network or on a single system. It is ideally suited for
      webmasters, technicians, hobbyists, educators, experimenters, and any
      one who requires a simple, customizable, robust, easy-to-understand
      language. Download <em>The Language of the Free</em>(tm) now at <a
      href="http://www.rebol.com/downloads.html"
      >www.rebol.com/downloads.html</a>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Relex" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Relex US, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.relexus.com/</url>
    <description>
      Relex US, Inc. present:
      <ul>
	<li>RDBMS Linter(tm) SQL has a
	  client-server architecture  and supports SQL-92, ODBC, and JDBC
	  interfaces.  User access is available through PHP, Perl, TCL/TK, and
	  a C/C++ language call interface.Linter includes search engine and
	  replication server capabilities, is well designed for embedded
	  systems, and is currently ported to more than 20 operating systems.</li>
	<li>Our Ticket Tracking System  is suitable for resolving
	  problems ranging from software bugs  to consumer product complaints.</li>
	<li>Nevod is a system for data warehousing &amp; mining.</li>
	<li>Lakuna  is a program for rapid database application
	  development.</li>
      </ul>
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Revolution" category="DEV">
    <name>Revolution</name>
    <url>http://www.runrev.com/</url>
    <description>
      Revolution is a multi-platform software development tool that enables
      developers to easily and quickly create powerful applications for OS
      X, classic Mac OS, Windows, Linux, and popular Unix systems
      (including FreeBSD)... with native look and feel on all platforms.
      For more information or to download a free 30-day trial evaluation
      edition, visit <a href="http://www.runrev.com/">www.runrev.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="RTD" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>RTD</name>
    <url>http://www.rtd.com/</url>
    <description>
      RTD provides <a href="http://www.rtd.com/software/uta.html">UTA</a>,
      an ISP billing package for FreeBSD-based ISPs.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SaneSolutions" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>Sane Solutions, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.sane.com/</url>
    <description>
      Sane Solutions, LLC offers <a
      href="http://www.sane.com/products/NetTracker">NetTracker</a>, one of
      the most powerful, yet easy to use Internet usage tracking programs
      on the market today. NetTracker allows marketing professionals,
      webmasters, and ISPs to get the essential information they need to
      make informed decisions regarding their web sites. A demonstration of
      NetTracker can be seen at <a
      href="http://www.sane.com/demo/">www.sane.com/demo/</a> and a FREE,
      30-day evaluation copy can be downloaded from <a
      href="http://www.sane.com/eval/">www.sane.com/eval</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Sendmail" category="EMAIL">
    <name>Sendmail Inc</name>
    <url>http://www.sendmail.com/</url>
    <description>
      Sendmail Inc. develop the commercial (Sendmail Pro) and free versions
      of sendmail, the ubiquitous mail transport agent. It supports
      FreeBSD, as well as many other Unix implementations.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SerengetiSystems" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Serengeti Systems</name>
    <url>http://www.serengeti.com/</url>
    <description>
      Serengeti Systems provides PC to mainframe communication packages
      over Bisync and SDLC lines. We support FreeBSD, as well as DOS,
      Windows, SCO, AIX, and OS/2. For more information, please <a
      href="http://www.serengeti.com/">visit our web site</a>, e-mail us at
      <a href="mailto:sales@serengeti.com">sales@serengeti.com</a>, or call
      +1.800.634.3122.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ShpinkSoftware" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Shpink Software</name>
    <url>http://www.shpink.com/</url>
    <description>
      Shpink Software offers The Network Shell. The Network Shell provides
      for a Perl and Shell environment to allow you to perform secure
      automated and/or interactive remote administration of UNIX and
      Windows 95/NT hosts from the local host without the need for telnet,
      ftp, or .rhosts. You get access to remote files, processes, commands,
      and other data easily and securely from your local Shell and Perl
      environment. To download a fully functional evaluation copy, or to
      get more information, please <a href="http://www.shpink.com/">visit
      our web site</a>. For more information, send email to <a
      href="mailto:info@shpink.com">info@shpink.com</a> or call us at
      +1.888.I.WANT.NSH (Toll Free) or +1.650.525.1537.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SiamScan" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>SiamScan.NET</name>
    <url>http://www.siamscan.net/</url>
    <description>
      SiamScan.NET, a Bangkok based company offers commercial web
      application software, CPA - Collaborative Portable Accounting. CPA is
      web accounting software designed to be easy enough for non
      accountants to use. Also, we offer service on maintenance and
      implementation of FreeBSD systems. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:sale@siamscan.net">sale@siamscan.net</a>, visit <a
      href="http://www.siamscan.net/">SiamScan.NET</a> Website, call +66
      2532 9068-70, or fax +66 2533 4167.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SleepycatSoftware" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Sleepycat Software</name>
    <url>http://www.sleepycat.com</url>
    <description>
      Sleepycat Software distributes Berkeley DB, an embeddable database
      system with full source. Berkeley DB runs on a wide variety of Unix
      systems and on Windows 95 and NT. It offers high-end data management
      services, including full transaction support, disaster recovery, hot
      backup, very large databases, and the ability to handle large numbers
      of users concurrently. Keys and records can be arbitrarily long, and
      of arbitrary data types. Berkeley DB can store data in B+trees, hash
      tables, or sequential stores. The programmatic interfaces are simple,
      and can be called from C, C++, Java, or Perl. Berkeley DB is easy to
      install and manage, so your customers can use your application
      without learning how to be database administrators. For more
      information, please visit <a
      href="http://www.sleepycat.com">www.sleepycat.com</a> or send us
      email at <a href="mailto:db@sleepycat.com">db@sleepycat.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SlickEdit" category="DEV">
    <name>SlickEdit</name>
    <url>http://www.slickedit.com/</url>
    <description>
      SlickEdit develops and markets Visual SlickEdit, a programmer's
      editor that allows developers to increase their productivity. Visual
      SlickEdit v6.0 for FreeBSD allows developers to streamline workflow,
      simplify processes, manage large files, and reduce keystrokes.
      Developers can customize Visual SlickEdit, based on individual
      preferences and preferred coding styles. Visit <a
      href="http://www.slickedit.com/">www.slickedit.com</a> for more
      information or to download a demo.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="SoftMaker" category="MISC">
    <name>SoftMaker Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.softmaker.de/tml_en.htm</url>
    <description>
      TextMaker is the fast, efficient Microsoft Word-compatible word processor for FreeBSD.
      It provides all the features of a modern high-end word processor, reads and
      writes Microsoft Word documents seamlessly, and is available on <a
      href="http://www.softmaker.de/tm_en.htm">multiple platforms</a> (FreeBSD,
      Linux, Windows, Pocket PCs, Handheld PCs).
      <a href="http://www.softmaker.de/tmldemo_en.htm">Free trial</a> available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Software2Go" category="MULTIMEDIA">
    <name>Software2Go, LLC</name>
    <url>http://www.apps2go.com</url>
    <description>
      Software2Go, LLC is proud to announce the availability of <a
      href="http://www.opengroup.org/motif">Motif 2.1.10</a> for FreeBSD
      versions 2.2.x (a.out) and 3.0 (ELF). Motif 2.1.10, <em>Development
      Edition</em>, is available for immediate purchase and download from
      <a href="http://www.apps2go.com">www.apps2go.com</a>. Native ports to
      other Free UNIX's are also available.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Solid" category="DATABASE">
    <name>Solid Information Technology Ltd</name>
    <url>http://www.solidtech.com/</url>
    <description>
      Solid Information Technology Ltd is the maker of a unique data
      management product, <a
      href="http://www.solidtech.com/market/products/index.htm">SOLID
      Server</a>. It is designed for robust operation in demanding
      environments. Its small size and ease-of-use make it ideal for
      deployment to web sites, various embedded systems, and other
      environments where databases need to operate unattended. Free
      evaluation copies maybe downloaded from <a
      href="http://www.solidtech.com/market/eval/index.htm">here</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Sophos" category="SECURITY">
    <name>Sophos Anti-Virus</name>
    <url>http://www.sophos.com</url>
    <description>
      Sophos Plc offers <em>Sophos Anti-Virus</em> for FreeBSD. Sophos
      Anti-Virus is a unique solution to the virus problem, providing true
      cross-platform protection in a single, fully integrated product. The
      network-centric design provides a host of benefits for the protection
      of servers, workstations, and portables. Sophos's ground-breaking
      architecture maximizes protection, while minimizing performance and
      administrative overheads. Sophos Anti-Virus is fully scalable,
      equally at home protecting a single PC, a local network, or the
      entire enterprise. Sophos Anti-Virus is available for all popular
      desktop and network operating systems, including DOS, Windows
      3.x/95/98/NT/2000, Unix (including FreeBSD), OS/2, Netware, and
      OpenVMS. Sophos Anti-Virus monitors all virus entry points, including
      disks, programs, documents, network drives, CD-ROMs, Internet
      downloads, email attachments, and compressed files. Over 65 per cent
      of The Times Top 100 Companies use Sophos Anti-Virus to protect their
      networks from viruses. This endorsement of Sophos Anti-Virus
      protection is shared around the world. FREE evaluation copies may be
      <a href="http://www.sophos.com/downloads/full/">downloaded</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="StalkerSoftware" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Stalker Software, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.stalker.com/</url>
    <description>
      Stalker Software, Inc. offers <a
      href="http://www.stalker.com/CommuniGatePro/">CommuniGate Pro</a>,
      The Internet Messaging Server. Based on the Stalker Foundation
      framework, it employs the native services of all major operating
      systems, including FreeBSD, Windows 95/98, Windows NT, Apple
      Rhapsody, Linux, Solaris, and others. The CommuniGate Pro server
      takes full advantage of modern multi-threaded and multi-processor
      environments, and includes anti-spam protection, administration via
      the Web, extensive multi-domain support, dial-up capabilities, unique
      IMAP multi-mailbox features and designed to provide access to
      hundreds of thousands of accounts, and to relay mail on the most
      heavily loaded sites. Download the FREE Trial version from <a
      href="http://www.stalker.com/">www.stalker.com</a> or e-mail <a
      href="mailto:sales@stalker.com">Stalker Software Sales</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Tonec" category="MISC">
    <name>Tonec, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.tonec.com</url>
    <description>
      Tonec, Inc. provides award-winning products and solutions for web
      development, Java applets, and Perl modules. Tonec is a developer of
      Adgen - a BMP to PFR dynamic font converter for Linux and FreeBSD. In
      addition, Tonec provides custom programming, cost-effective offshore
      software development, web design, and custom ASP and Java development
      services in its development centers located in Russia, Poland, and
      Latvia. <a href="http://www.tonec.com">Visit our site</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="TriPolar" category="NETWORK">
    <name>TriPolar Technologies</name>
    <url>http://www.tri-polar.com/</url>
    <description>
      TriPolar Technologies offers LynkStation,
      website software designed to increase the number of visitors
      to a website without all the usual work.  With LynkStation,
      website owners automatically run a database-driven Links Page
      and at the same time spread the word about their products and/or services
      to thousands of Internet users weekly.
      Detailed additional information and free online demos are available
      at <a href="http://www.tri-polar.com/ls/">www.tri-polar.com/ls/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="VectorSystems" category="MISC">
    <name>Vector Systems Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.freebsd.org/~jhs/vsl/products/med/med.html</url>
    <description>
      Vector Systems Limited
      sells the <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/~jhs/vsl/products/med/med.html">
        MED</a> Screen Editor for FreeBSD &amp; HP-UX.
      This editor is particularly familiar to PCS Cadmus users,
      in the German CAD industry.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="VirtuFlexSoftware" category="MISC">
    <name>VirtuFlex Software</name>
    <url>http://www.virtuflex.com/</url>
    <description>
      VirtuFlex Software produces a versatile tool called
      <em>VirtuFlex</em>, which allows web developers to build dynamic web
      pages without CGI programming. It integrates databases, email,
      faxing, and telephony with the web. VirtuFlex is available for most
      Unix platforms, including FreeBSD.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="Vital" category="DEV">
    <name>Vital, Inc.</name>
    <url>http://www.vital.com/</url>
    <description>
      Vital, Inc. is the maker of the CRiSP visual text editor. CRiSP is a
      development tool for FreeBSD and most other Windows, UNIX, and Linux
      platforms. CRiSP is 100% BRIEF-compatible and also emulates other
      popular editors such as vi, emacs, EDT, CUA, and Wordstar. This makes
      CRiSP a very powerful yet easy-to-use editing package with features
      like cut &amp; paste, syntax coloring, code beautifying, code
      folding, searching, and much more.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebCrossing" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Web Crossing</name>
    <url>http://webcrossing.com/</url>
    <description>
      Web Crossing, by Lundeen &amp; Associates, is a conferencing server
      for the intranet/extranet and World Wide Web providing discussion
      forums and chat rooms. Web Crossing is a groupware application
      server, accessible with any Web browser, via most Web servers. It
      makes communication more efficient and productive than newsgroups or
      email mailing lists. Contact L &amp; A at <a
      href="mailto:sales@lundeen.com">sales@lundeen.com</a>,
      +1.510.521.5855 (Voice), or +1.510.522.6647 (Fax).
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebHostWorks.net" category="ECOMMERCE">
    <name>WebHostWorks.net</name>
    <url>http://www.webhostworks.net/</url>
    <description>
      WebHostWorks.net is a small and thriving web development firm
      specializing in e-commerce integration for small and medium sized
      businesses. Our proprietary E-Cart commerce package supports
      extraordinarily usable shopping cart services with backend product
      list management, order processing, executive summary reports,
      customer review processing, and inventory projections. See <a
      href="http://www.webhostworks.net">webhostworks.net</a> for more
      information.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="WebEvent" category="NETWORK">
    <name>WebEvent</name>
    <url>http://www.matadordesign.com/</url>
    <description>
      Matador Design produces WebEvent, a web-based calendar and scheduling
      solution that is available for FreeBSD-based web servers. It is a
      perfect addition to any Internet or Intranet web site that needs to
      display event information, manage schedules, rooms, or other
      resources.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XDesigner" category="DEV">
    <name>X-Designer</name>
    <url>"http://www.ist-inc.com/xd/</url>
    <description>
      X-Designer from <a href="http://www.ist-inc.com/">Imperial Software Technology</a>
      is an advanced GUI Builder for FreeBSD.
      X-Designer makes it easy to build and test graphical user interfaces.
      Use X-Designer to quickly create a working X/Motif, Windows, or Java GUI
      from a single design.
      Includes automated GUI testing and technology
      to re-engineer legacy Motif interfaces with XD/Capture.
      Visit our <a href="http://www.ist-inc.com/xd">web site</a>
      for more information or send an e-mail
      to <a href="mailto:sales@ist-inc.com">sales@ist-inc.com</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XAT" category="NETWORK">
    <name>XAT.com</name>
    <url>http://www.xat.com/</url>
    <description>
      XAT.com offers commercial web-acceleration software for FreeBSD. <a
      href="http://www.xat.com/jdo/">JPEG Disk Optimizer</a> is designed to
      run on a web server and either run in the background to compress all
      JPG images on a disk or to compress them as they arrive. Users have
      reported a 40% saving in file size and corresponding savings in
      bandwidth, disk space, and server load, all of which contributes to
      faster web sites. For more information, email <a
      href="mailto:sales@xat.com">sales@xat.com</a>, visit the <a
      href="http://www.xat.com/jdo/">XAT.com website</a>, or call +44 1752
      872181.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XGForce" category="NETWORK">
    <name>XGForce.COM</name>
    <url>http://www.xgforce.com/</url>
    <description>
      XGForce.COM announces <a href="http://www.xgforce.com/eCluster.html">
        eCluster(tm)</a> software. New Internet Clustering Technology is
      designed to cluster Intranet/Internet Servers into virtual groups,
      where server load balancing and fail safe is made possible.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XiGraphics" category="MULTIMEDIA">
    <name>Xi Graphics</name>
    <url>http://www.xig.com/</url>
    <description>
      Xi Graphics offers commercial-grade graphical software enhancements
      for FreeBSD.  <em>AcceleratedX Server</em> completely supports over
      400 different graphics adapters from over 40 vendors, including many
      that are partially supported or not included with XFree86. Download a
      FREE demonstration copy from <a
      href="ftp://ftp.xig.com/">ftp.xig.com</a>. Also utilize Motif v2.0
      runtime + development environment with <em>AcceleratedX Motif</em>
      and 3D graphics with <em>AcceleratedX OpenGL</em>. For more
      information, email <a href="mailto:sales@xig.com">sales@xig.com</a>
      or call +1.303.298.7478.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="XVScan" category="SYSADMIN">
    <name>XVScan</name>
    <url>http://www.tummy.com/xvscan/</url>
    <description>
      XVScan allows you to use your HP ScanJet scanner under FreeBSD. It is
      a commercial product based on John Bradley's xv.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="YARD" category="DATABASE">
    <name>YARD Software GmbH</name>
    <url>http://www.yard.de/</url>
    <description>
      YARD Software GmbH provides its relational ANSI-SQL database for
      FreeBSD systems.	<em>YARD-SQL</em> is available on most UNIX systems
      and has interfaces for C, ODBC (MS Windows) and JDBC (Java). A
      Private Edition for private, non-commercial use can be downloaded
      from <a
      href="ftp://ftp.yard.de/pub/private/">ftp://ftp.yard.de/pub/private/</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="ZeusTechnology" category="NETWORK">
    <name>Zeus Technology Limited</name>
    <url>http://www.zeus.co.uk/</url>
    <description>
      Zeus Technology Limited offers <em>Zeus Server</em> for FreeBSD. Zeus
      Server is an advanced, powerful, full-featured, commercial grade web
      server designed with exceptional performance, minimal machine
      resource requirements, and ease of administration in mind. FREE
      evaluation copies may be <a
      href="http://www.zeus.co.uk/">downloaded</a>.
    </description>
  </entry>

  <entry id="PortaOne" category="NETWORK">
    <name>PortaOne</name>
    <url>http://www.portaone.com</url>
    <description>
      PortaOne is a VoIP billing solutions company. We enable Internet
      Telephony Service Providers (ITSP's) and the operators of voice
      networks to quickly and efficiently implement, manage, and deliver a
      wide range of billing solutions for IP telephony. Our flagship
      product <a
      href="http://www.portaone.com/solutions/">PortaBilling100</a> is an
      extremely flexible customer management and billing platform that
      enables the providers of IP Telephony services to launch, price, and
      provision an array of VoIP services. For further information,
      please see <a href="http://www.portaone.com">www.portaone.com</a>
    </description>
  </entry>
</entries>
