<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD Security Vulnerability Reporting Information">
]>
<!-- $FreeBSD$ -->

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.support">

      <h2>Table of contents</h2>

      <ul>
	<li><a href="#how">How and where to report a FreeBSD security issue</a></li>
 	<li><a href="#sec">Information about the FreeBSD Security Officer</a></li>
 	<li><a href="#pol">Information handling policies</a></li>
 	<li><a href="security.html#sup">Supported FreeBSD Releases</a></li>
 	<li><a href="unsupported.html">Unsupported FreeBSD Releases</a></li>
      </ul>

      <a name="how"></a>
      <h2>How and where to report a FreeBSD security issue</h2>

      <p>FreeBSD security issues specific to the operating system
	should be reported to the <a
	  href="mailto:secteam@FreeBSD.org">FreeBSD Security Team</a>
	or, if a higher level of confidentiality is required, PGP
	encrypted to the <a
          href="mailto:security-officer@FreeBSD.org">Security Officer
	  Team</a> using the <a href="so_public_key.asc">Security
	  Officer PGP key</a>.</p>

      <p>FreeBSD security issues specific to the Ports Collection should
	be reported to the <a href="mailto:ports-secteam@FreeBSD.org">
	  FreeBSD Ports Security Team</a>.</p>

      <p>All reports should contain at least:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>A description of the vulnerability.</li>
	<li>What versions of FreeBSD seem to be affected if possible.</li>
	<li>Any plausible workaround.</li>
	<li>Example code if possible.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Whenever possible, including the background, problem
	description, impact, and workaround (if applicable) using the
	templates for <a
	  href="advisory-template.txt">security advisories</a> and <a
	  href="errata-template.txt">errata notices</a> as appropriate
	would also be helpful.</p>

      <p>After this information has been reported the Security Officer
	or a Security Team delegate will get back to you.</p>

      <h3>Spam filters</h3>

      <p>Due to high volume of spam the main security contact mail
	addresses are subject to spam filtering.  If you cannot contact
	the FreeBSD Security Officers or Security Team due to spam filters
	(or suspect your mail has been filtered), please send mail to
	<tt>security-officer-<em>XXXX</em>@FreeBSD.org</tt> with
	<em>XXXX</em> replaced with <tt>3432</tt> instead of the normal
	addresses.  Note that this address will be changed periodically so
	check back here for the latest address.  Mails to this address
	will go to the FreeBSD Security Officer Team.</p>

      <a name="sec"></a>
      <h2>The FreeBSD Security Officer Team and the FreeBSD Security Team</h2>

      <p>In order that the FreeBSD Project may respond to vulnerability
	reports in a timely manner, emails sent to the <a
	  href="mailto:security-officer@FreeBSD.org">&lt;security-officer@FreeBSD.org&gt;</a>
	mail alias are currently delivered to the following people:</p>

      <table>
	<tr valign="top">
	  <td>&a.gordon.email;</td>
	  <td>Security Officer</td>
	</tr>
	<tr valign="top">
	  <td>&a.emaste.email;</td>
	  <td>Deputy Security Officer</td>
	</tr>
	<tr valign="top">
	  <td>&a.delphij.email;</td>
	  <td>Security Officer Emeritus</td>
	</tr>
	<tr valign="top">
	  <td>&a.des.email;</td>
	  <td>Security Officer Emeritus</td>
	</tr>
      </table>

      <p>The Security Officer is supported by the <a
	  href="&base;/administration.html#t-secteam">FreeBSD Security
	  Team</a>, <a
	  href="mailto:secteam@FreeBSD.org">&lt;secteam@FreeBSD.org&gt;</a>,
	a small group of committers vetted by the Security Officer.</p>

      <a name="pol"></a>
      <h2>Information handling policies</h2>

      <p>As a general policy, the FreeBSD Security Officer favors full
	disclosure of vulnerability information after a reasonable delay
	to permit safe analysis and correction of a vulnerability, as well
	as appropriate testing of the correction, and appropriate
	coordination with other affected parties.</p>

      <p>The Security Officer <em>will</em> notify one or more of the
	FreeBSD Cluster Admins of
	vulnerabilities that put the FreeBSD Project's resources under
	immediate danger.</p>

      <p>The Security Officer may bring additional FreeBSD developers or
	outside developers into discussion of a submitted security
	vulnerability if their expertise is required to fully understand
	or correct the problem.  Appropriate discretion will be exercised
	to minimize unnecessary distribution of information about the
	submitted vulnerability, and any experts brought in will act in
	accordance of Security Officer policies.  In the past, experts
	have been brought in based on extensive experience with highly
	complex components of the operating system, including FFS, the VM
	system, and the network stack.</p>

      <p>If a FreeBSD release process is underway, the FreeBSD Release
	Engineer may also be notified that a vulnerability exists, and its
	severity, so that informed decisions may be made regarding the
	release cycle and any serious security bugs present in software
	associated with an up-coming release.  If requested, the Security
	Officer will not share information regarding the nature of the
	vulnerability with the Release Engineer, limiting information flow
	to existence and severity.</p>

      <p>The FreeBSD Security Officer has close working relationships with
        a number of other organizations, including third-party vendors
        that share code with FreeBSD (the OpenBSD, NetBSD and DragonFlyBSD
        projects, Apple, and other vendors deriving software from FreeBSD,
        as well as the Linux vendor security list), as well as
        organizations that track vulnerabilities and security incidents,
        such as CERT.  Frequently vulnerabilities may extend beyond the
        scope of the FreeBSD implementation, and (perhaps less frequently)
        may have broad implications for the global networking community.
        Under such circumstances, the Security Officer may wish to
        disclose vulnerability information to these other organizations:
        if you do not wish the Security Officer to do this, please
        indicate so explicitly in any submissions.</p>

      <p>Submitters should be careful to explicitly document any special
        information handling requirements.</p>

      <p>If the submitter of a vulnerability is interested in a
        coordinated disclosure process with the submitter and/or other
        vendors, this should be indicated explicitly in any submissions.
        In the absence of explicit requests, the FreeBSD Security Officer
        will select a disclosure schedule that reflects both a desire for
        timely disclosure and appropriate testing of any solutions.
        Submitters should be aware that if the vulnerability is being
        actively discussed in public forums (such as bugtraq), and
        actively exploited, the Security Officer may choose not to follow
        a proposed disclosure timeline in order to provide maximum
        protection for the user community.</p>

      <p>Submissions may be protected using PGP.  If desired, responses
        will also be protected using PGP.</p>

    </body>
</html>
