<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//FreeBSD//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional-Based Extension//EN"
"http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/share/xml/xhtml10-freebsd.dtd" [
<!ENTITY title "FreeBSD 3.1 Announcement">
]>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
      <title>&title;</title>

      <cvs:keyword xmlns:cvs="http://www.FreeBSD.org/XML/CVS">$FreeBSD$</cvs:keyword>
    </head>

    <body class="navinclude.download">

<p><b>Date:</b> Mon, 15 Feb 1999 12:00:03 -0700<br/>
<b>From:</b> "Jordan K. Hubbard" &lt;jkh@freebsd.org&gt;<br/>
<b>Subject:</b>FreeBSD 3.1 is now released!</p>

<p>We are pleased, as always, to announce the availability
of 3.1-RELEASE, the much anticipated follow-on release to
FreeBSD 3.0 (released November, 1998).  Many hundreds of bug
fixes and general enhancements have been made to the system
so please see the <a href="notes.html">release notes</a> for
more information.</p>

<p>FreeBSD 3.1-RELEASE is available on <a
href="ftp://ftp.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD">ftp.freebsd.org</a> and
various <a href="&base;/handbook/mirrors.html">FTP mirror sites</a>
throughout the world.  It can also be ordered on CD from
<a href="http://www.cdrom.com/">Walnut Creek CDROM</a>, from where it
will be shipping shortly as a 4 CD set containing a lot of extra stuff
of interest to programmers and general users alike.</p>

<p><b>IMPORTANT NOTE</b>: All of the profits from the sales of this CD set
go to support the FreeBSD Project!</p>

<p>Like many businesses in the field of high-tech, Walnut Creek CDROM has
realized that in order to make any product for an emerging market
grow, you have to make a significant investment in such growth, even
if it means abandoning short-term profits.  Walnut Creek CDROM is the
only CDROM vendor who currently does anything like this and it's
certainly my hope that you will help support the project by buying (or
getting someone else to buy :) one of their CDs.  Thanks!</p>

<p>The official FTP distribution site for FreeBSD is:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><a href="ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD">ftp://ftp.FreeBSD.org/pub/FreeBSD</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Or via the WEB page at:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.cdrom.com">http://www.cdrom.com</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>And on CD-ROM from Walnut Creek CDROM:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Walnut Creek CDROM<br/>
4041 Pike Lane, #F<br/>
Concord CA, 94520 USA<br/>
Phone: +1 925 674-0783<br/>
Fax: +1 925 674-0821<br/>
Tech Support: +1 925 603-1234<br/>
Email: <a href="mailto:info@cdrom.com">info@cdrom.com</a><br/>
WWW: <a href="http://www.cdrom.com/">http://www.cdrom.com/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you are in Japan, please refer to <a href="http://www.pht.co.jp/">
Pacific HiTech</a> for information on ordering a localized (or the english)
version of the 3.1 product when it becomes available.  Pacific HiTech is
now an affiliate of Walnut Creek CDROM for Japanese sales of FreeBSD.</p>

<p>Additionally, FreeBSD is available via anonymous FTP from <a
href="&base;/handbook/mirrors.html">mirror sites</a>
in the following countries: Argentina, Australia, Brazil, Bulgaria,
Canada, the Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France,
Germany, Hong Kong, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Israel, Japan, Korea,
Latvia, Malaysia, the Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Russia,
Slovenia, South Africa, Spain, Sweden, Taiwan, Thailand, the Ukraine
and the United Kingdom (and quite possibly several others which I've
never even heard of :).</p>

<p>Before trying the central FTP site, please check your regional
mirror(s) first by going to:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>ftp://ftp.&lt;yourdomain>.freebsd.org/pub/FreeBSD</p>
</blockquote>

Any additional mirror sites will be labeled ftp2, ftp3 and so on.

<p>The latest versions of export-restricted code for FreeBSD (2.0C or
later) (eBones and secure) are also being made available at the
following locations. If you are outside the U.S. or Canada, please get
secure (DES) and eBones (Kerberos) from one of the following foreign
distribution sites:</p>

<dl>
<dt>South Africa</dt>
<dd><p><a href="ftp://ftp.internat.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD">ftp://ftp.internat.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD</a><br/>
<a href="ftp://ftp2.internat.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD">ftp://ftp2.internat.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD</a></p></dd>

<dt>Brazil</dt>

<dd><p><a href="ftp://ftp.br.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD">ftp://ftp.br.FreeBSD.ORG/pub/FreeBSD</a></p></dd>

<dt>Finland</dt>

<dd><p><a href="ftp://nic.funet.fi/pub/unix/FreeBSD/eurocrypt">ftp://nic.funet.fi/pub/unix/FreeBSD/eurocrypt</a></p></dd>
</dl>

<p></p><a href="../index.html">Release Home</a>
</body>
</html>
